<chapter id="modconcepts-20809"><title>Managing Terminals
and Modems (Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides overview information for managing terminals and
modems. </para><itemizedlist><para>This is a list of the overview information in this chapter:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="fqvaj" remap="internal">What's New in Managing Terminals
and Modems?</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="modconcepts-20134" remap="internal">Terminals, Modems, Ports,
and Services</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="modconcepts-31870" remap="internal">Tools for Managing Terminals
and Modems</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="modconcepts-17758" remap="internal">Serial Ports Tool</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="modconcepts-24083" remap="internal">Service Access Facility</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For step-by-step instructions on how to set up terminals and modems
with the Serial Ports tool, see <olink targetptr="modsetup-43877" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2,
Setting Up Terminals and Modems (Tasks)</olink>.</para><para>For step-by-step instructions on how to set up terminals and modems
with the Service Access Facility (SAF), see <olink targetptr="modsafapp-84569" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3,
Managing Serial Ports With the Service Access Facility (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="fqvaj"><title>What's New in Managing Terminals and Modems?</title><para>This section describes new or changed features for managing terminals
and modems in the Solaris release. </para><sect2 id="gdhfy" arch="sparc"><title>Coherent Console</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 8/07:</emphasis> The coherent console subsystem feature
implements a part of the kernel console subsystem to facilitate rendering
console output, The coherent console uses the Solaris kernel mechanisms to
render console output rather than Programmable Read-Only Memory (PROM) interfaces.
This reduces the console rendering dependence on the OpenBoot PROM (OBP).
The coherent console uses a kernel-resident framebuffer driver to generate
console output. The generated console output is more efficient than using
OBP rendering. The coherent console also avoids idling CPUs during the SPARC
console output and enhances the user experience.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="gdfpb" arch="sparc"><title>Changes to How $TERM Value for Console
Is Set</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 8/07:</emphasis> The <literal>$TERM</literal> value is now dynamically derived and depends on the terminal
emulator that the console is using. On x86 based systems, the <literal>$TERM</literal> value
is <literal>sun-color</literal> because the kernel's terminal emulator is
always used.</para><para>On SPARC based systems the <literal>$TERM</literal> value is as follows:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term><literal>sun-color</literal></term><listitem><para>This value is used for <literal>$TERM</literal> if the system
uses the kernel's terminal emulator.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><literal>sun</literal></term><listitem><para>This value is used for <literal>$TERM</literal> if the system
uses the PROM's terminal emulator.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>This change does not impact how the terminal type is set for the serial
port. You can still  use the <command>svccfg</command> command to modify the <literal>$TERM</literal> value, as  shown in the following example:</para><screen># <userinput>svccfg</userinput>
svc:> <userinput>select system/console-login</userinput>
svc:/system/console-login> <userinput>setprop ttymon/terminal_type = "xterm"</userinput>
svc:/system/console-login> <userinput>exit</userinput></screen>
</sect2><sect2 id="fdkzx"><title><command>ttymon</command> Invocations on the System
Console Managed by SMF</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10:</emphasis> <command>ttymon</command> invocations
on the system console are managed by SMF. The addition of properties to the <literal>svc:/system/console-login:default</literal> service enables you to specify <command>ttymon</command> command arguments with the <command>svccfg</command> command.
Note that these properties are specific to <command>ttymon</command>, not
generic SMF properties.</para><note><para>You can no longer customize the <command>ttymon</command> invocation
in the <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> file.</para>
</note><para>For step-by-step instructions on how to specify <command>ttymon</command> command
arguments with SMF, see <olink targetptr="fdzue" remap="internal">How to Set the ttymon Console
Terminal Type</olink>.</para><para>For a complete overview of SMF, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="hbrunlevels-25516" remap="external">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Services (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink>. For information on the step-by-step
procedures that are associated with SMF, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="faauf" remap="external">Chapter 17, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Services (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="modconcepts-20134"><title>Terminals, Modems, Ports, and Services</title><para>Terminals and modems provide both local and remote access to system
and network resources. Setting up terminals and modem access is an important
responsibility of a system administrator. This section explains some of the
concepts behind modem and terminal management in the Solaris Operating System.</para><sect2 id="modconcepts-71466"><title>Terminal Description</title><para>Your system's bitmapped graphics
display is not the same as an alphanumeric terminal. An alphanumeric terminal
connects to a serial port and displays only text. You don't have to perform
any special steps to administer the graphics display.   </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="modconcepts-66642"><title>Modem Description</title><itemizedlist><para>Modems can be set up in three basic configurations:</para><listitem><para>Dial-out</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Dial-in</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Bidirectional</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>A modem connected
to your home computer might be set up to provide <emphasis>dial-out</emphasis> service.
With dial-out service, you can access other computers from your own home.
However, nobody outside can gain access to your machine.   </para><para><emphasis>Dial-in</emphasis> service
is just the opposite. Dial-in service allows people to access a system from
remote sites. However, it does not permit calls to the outside world.  </para><para><emphasis>Bidirectional</emphasis> access,
as the name implies, provides both dial-in and dial-out capabilities.  </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="modconcepts-22732"><title>Ports Description</title><para>A <emphasis>port</emphasis> is a channel through which
a device communicates with the operating system. From a hardware perspective,
a port is a &ldquo;receptacle&rdquo; into which a terminal or modem cable
might be physically connected. </para><para>However, a port is not strictly a physical receptacle, but an entity
with hardware (pins and connectors) and software (a device driver) components.
A single physical receptacle often provides multiple ports, allowing connection
of two or more devices.</para><para>Common types of ports include serial, parallel, small computer systems
interface (SCSI), and Ethernet.</para><para>A <emphasis>serial port</emphasis>,
using a standard communications protocol, transmits a byte of information
bit-by-bit over a single line. </para><para>Devices that have been designed according to RS-232-C
or RS-423 standards, this include most modems, alphanumeric terminals, plotters,
and some printers. These devices can be connected  interchangeably, using
standard cables, into serial ports of computers that have been similarly designed. </para><para>When many serial port devices
must be connected to a single computer, you might need to add an <emphasis>adapter
board</emphasis> to the system. The adapter board, with its driver software,
provides additional serial ports for connecting more devices than could otherwise
be accommodated.  </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="modconcepts-22377"><title>Services Description</title><para>Modems and terminals gain access to computing resources by using serial
port software. Serial port software must be set up to provide a particular &ldquo;service&rdquo;
for the device attached to the port. For example, you can set up a serial
port to provide bidirectional service for a modem. </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="modconcepts-1"><title>Port Monitors</title><para>The main mechanism for gaining
access to a service is through a <emphasis>port monitor</emphasis>. A port
monitor is a program that continuously monitors for requests to log in or
access printers or files. </para><para>When a port monitor detects a request, it sets whatever parameters are
required to establish communication between the operating system and the device
requesting service. Then, the port monitor transfers control to other processes
that provide the services needed.</para><para>The following table describes the two types of port monitors included
in the Solaris Operating System.</para><table frame="topbot" id="modconcepts-31658"><title>Port Monitor Types</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="131.00*"/><colspec colname="column1" colwidth="131*"/><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="223*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Man Page</para>
</entry><entry><para>Port Monitor</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry><para><olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="listen-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>listen</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><command>listen</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Controls access to network services, such as handling remote print
requests prior to the Solaris 2.6 release. The default Solaris Operating System no longer
uses this port monitor type. </para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="ttymon-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ttymon</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><command>ttymon</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Provides access to the login services needed by modems and alphanumeric
terminals. The Serial Ports tool automatically sets up a <literal>ttymon</literal> port
monitor to process login requests from these devices. </para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>You
might be familiar with an older port monitor called <literal>getty</literal>.
The new <literal>ttymon</literal> port monitor is more powerful. A single <literal>ttymon</literal> port monitor can replace multiple occurrences of <command>getty</command>.
Otherwise, these two programs serve the same function. For more information,
see the <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="getty-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>getty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="modconcepts-31870"><title>Tools for Managing Terminals and Modems</title><para>The following table lists the tools for managing
terminals and modems.</para><table frame="topbot" id="modconcepts-tbl-2"><title>Tools For Managing Terminals
and Modems</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="108*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="141*"/><colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="110*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Managing Terminals and Modems Method</para>
</entry><entry><para>Tool</para>
</entry><entry><para>For More Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>The most comprehensive</para>
</entry><entry><para>Service Access Facility (SAF) commands</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="modconcepts-24083" remap="internal">Service Access Facility</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>The quickest setup</para>
</entry><entry><para>Solaris Management Console's Serial Ports tool</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="modsetup-43877" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Setting Up Terminals
and Modems (Tasks)</olink> and Solaris Management Console online help</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><sect2 id="modconcepts-17758"><title>Serial Ports Tool</title><para>The Serial Ports tool sets up the serial port software to work with
terminals and modems by calling the <command>pmadm</command> command with
the appropriate information. </para><itemizedlist><para>The tool also provides the following:</para><listitem><para>Templates for common terminal and modem configurations</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Multiple port setup, modification, or deletion</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Quick visual status of each port</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="modconcepts-24083"><title>Service Access Facility</title><para>The SAF is the tool used for administering terminals, modems,
and other network devices. </para><itemizedlist><para>In particular, the SAF enables you to set up the following:</para><listitem><para><literal>ttymon</literal> and <literal>listen</literal> port
monitors by using the <command>sacadm</command> command</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>ttymon</literal> port monitor services by using the <command>pmadm</command> and <command>ttyadm</command> commands</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>listen</literal> port monitor services by using the <command>pmadm</command> and <command>nlsadmin</command> commands</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Troubleshoot <literal>tty</literal> devices</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Troubleshoot incoming network requests for printing service</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Troubleshoot the Service Access Controller by using the <command>sacadm</command> command</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The SAF is an open-systems solution that
controls access to system and network resources through <literal>tty</literal> devices
and local-area networks (LANs). The SAF is not a program, but a hierarchy
of background processes and administrative commands. </para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>