<chapter id="tsswmgr-40462"><title>Troubleshooting
Software Package Problems (Tasks)</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes problems you might encounter
when installing or removing software packages. The Specific Software Package
Installation Errors section describes package installation and administration
errors you might encounter. The General Software Package Installation Problems
section describes behavioral problems that might not display an error message.</para><itemizedlist><para>This is a list of information in this chapter:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="tsswmgr-38960" remap="internal">Specific Software
Package Installation Errors</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="tsswmgr-42066" remap="internal">General Software Package
Installation Problems</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information about managing software packages, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="swmgrpkgsconcepts-52619" remap="external">Chapter 18, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Software (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="tsswmgr-3"><title>Troubleshooting Software Package Symbolic Link
Problems</title><para>In previous Solaris releases, there was no way to specify a symbolic
link target in the <filename>pkgmap</filename> file when creating a software
package. This meant a package or patch-related  symbolic link was always followed
to the source of the symbolic link rather than to the target of the symbolic
link when a package was added with the <command>pkgadd</command> command.
This created problems when upgrading a package or a patch package that needed
to change a symbolic link target destination to something else.</para><para>Now, the default behavior is that if a package needs to change the target
of a symbolic link to something else, the target of the symbolic link and
not the source of the symbolic link is inspected by the <command>pkgadd</command> command.</para><para>Unfortunately, this means that some packages may or may not conform
to the new <command>pkgadd</command> behavior.</para><para>The <literal>PKG_NONABI_SYMLINKS</literal> environment variable might
help you transition between the old and new <command>pkgadd</command> symbolic
link behaviors. If this environment variable is set to true, <command>pkgadd</command> follows
the source of the symbolic link.</para><para>Setting this variable enables a non-conforming package to revert to
the old behavior if set by the administrator before adding a package with
the <command>pkgadd</command> command.</para><para>The new <command>pkgadd</command> symbolic link behavior might cause
an existing package to fail when added with the <command>pkgadd</command> command.
You might see the following error message in this situation:</para><screen>unable to create symbolic link to &lt;path></screen><para>If a package doesn't install due to this problem, do the following:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>If this is a Sun-supplied package, call the Resolution Center
and report the non-conforming package name.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Set the <literal>PKG_NONABI_SYMLINKS</literal> environment
variable and try adding the package with the <command>pkgadd</command> command
again.</para><screen># <userinput>PKG_NONABI_SYMLINKS=true</userinput>
# <userinput>export PKG_NONABI_SYMLINKS</userinput>
# <userinput>pkgadd</userinput> <replaceable>pkg-name</replaceable></screen>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="tsswmgr-38960"><title>Specific Software Package Installation Errors</title><screen>WARNING: filename &lt;not present on Read Only file system></screen><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><colspec colname="column1" colwidth="180*"/><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="180*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Reason Error Occurred</para>
</entry><entry><para>How to Fix the Problem</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>This error message indicates that not all of a package's files could
be installed. This usually occurs when you are using <command>pkgadd</command> to
install a package on a client. In this case, <command>pkgadd</command> attempts
to install a package on a file system that is mounted from a server, but <command>pkgadd</command> doesn't have permission to do so.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you see this warning message during a package installation, you must
also install the package on the server. See <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="swmgrpkgsconcepts-52619" remap="external">Chapter 18, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Software (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink> for details.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="tsswmgr-42066"><title>General Software Package Installation Problems</title><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><colspec colname="column1" colwidth="180*"/><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="180*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Reason Error Occurred</para>
</entry><entry><para>How to Fix the Problem</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>There is a known problem with adding or removing some packages developed
prior to the Solaris 2.5 release and compatible versions. Sometimes, when adding
or removing these packages, the installation fails during user interaction
or you are prompted for user interaction and your responses are ignored. </para>
</entry><entry><para>Set the following environment variable and try to add the package again.</para><para><envar>NONABI_SCRIPTS=TRUE</envar></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
</chapter>