<preface id="vol2preface-11"><title>About
This Book</title><highlights><para><citetitle>System Administration Guide: Advanced Administration</citetitle> is
part of a set that covers a significant part of the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> system
administration information. This guide includes information for both <trademark class="registered">SPARC</trademark> and x86 based systems.</para><para>This book assumes that you have installed the <trademark>SunOS</trademark>  Solaris Operating
System. It also assumes that you have set up any networking software that
you plan to use. The SunOS  Solaris Operating
System is part of the  Solaris product
family, which also includes many features, including the GNOME Desktop Environment.
The SunOS  Solaris Operating System is
compliant with AT&amp;T's System V, Release 4 operating system.</para><para>For the  Solaris release,
new features that are interesting to system administrators are covered in
sections called <citetitle>What's New in ... ?</citetitle> in the appropriate
chapters.</para>&platform;
</highlights><sect1 id="vol2preface-1"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is intended for anyone responsible for administering one or
more systems that are running the  Solaris release.
To use this book, you should have 1-2 years of <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> system administration experience. Attending UNIX system administration
training courses might be helpful.</para>
</sect1>&sagset;<sect1 id="eteso"><title>Related Third-Party Web Site References</title><note><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party web
sites mentioned in this document.  Sun does not endorse and is not responsible
or liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials that
are available on or through such sites or resources.  Sun will not be responsible
or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused by or in connection
with the use of or reliance on any such content, goods, or services that are
available on or through such sites or resources.</para>
</note>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;<sect1 id="vol2preface-9"><title>General Conventions</title><para>Be aware of the following conventions that are used in this book.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>When following steps or using examples, be sure to type double-quotes
(<filename>"</filename>), left single-quotes (<filename>`</filename>), and
right single-quotes (<filename>'</filename>) exactly as shown.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The key referred to as Return is labeled Enter on some keyboards.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>It is assumed that the root path includes the <filename>/sbin</filename>, <filename>/usr/sbin</filename>, <filename>/usr/bin</filename>, and <filename>/etc</filename> directories,
so the steps in this book show the commands in these directories without absolute
path names. Steps that use commands in other, less common, directories show
the absolute path in the example.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The examples in this book are for a basic SunOS  Solaris software
installation without the Binary Compatibility Package installed and without <filename>/usr/ucb</filename> in the path.</para><caution><para>If <filename>/usr/ucb</filename> is included in a search path,
it should always be at the end of the search path. Commands like <command>ps</command> or <command>df</command> are duplicated in <filename>/usr/ucb</filename> with different
formats and different options from the SunOS  Solaris commands.</para>
</caution>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</preface>