<chapter id="intro-1"><title>Where to Find Solaris Installation Planning
Information</title><highlights><para>This book provides information on how to use the Solaris Live Upgrade
program to upgrade the Solaris operating system. This book provides all you
need to know about using Solaris Live Upgrade, but a planning book in our
collection of installation documentation might be useful to read before you
begin. The following references provide useful information before you upgrade
your system.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="gdlyq"><title>Where to Find Planning and System Requirement Information</title><para>The <olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink> provides system requirements and high-level planning information,
such as planning guidelines for file systems, and upgrade planning and much
more. The following list describes the chapters in the planning book and provides
links to those chapters.</para><informaltable frame="topbot" pgwide="100"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="61.61*"/><colspec colwidth="38.39*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Chapter Descriptions From the Planning Guide</para>
</entry><entry><para>Reference</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>This chapter describes new features in the Solaris installation programs.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="gaufd" remap="external">Chapter 2, <citetitle remap="chapter">What&rsquo;s New in Solaris Installation,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter provides you with information about decisions you need
to make before you install or upgrade the Solaris OS. Examples are deciding
when to use a network installation image or DVD media and descriptions of
all the Solaris installation programs.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="planning-8" remap="external">Chapter 3, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Installation and Upgrade (Roadmap),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter describes system requirements to install or upgrade to
the Solaris OS. General guidelines for planning the disk space and default
swap space allocation are also provided. Upgrade limitations are also described.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="diskspace-1" remap="external">Chapter 4, <citetitle remap="chapter">System Requirements, Guidelines, and Upgrade (Planning),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter contains checklists to help you gather all of the information
that you need to install or upgrade your system. This information is useful,
for example, if you are performing an interactive installation. You'll have
all the information in the checklist that you'll need to do an interactive
installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="gatherinfo-1" remap="external">Chapter 5, <citetitle remap="chapter">Gathering Information Before Installation or Upgrade (Planning),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>These chapters provide overviews of several technologies that relate
to a Solaris OS installation or upgrade. Guidelines and requirements related
to these technologies are also included. These chapters include information
about GRUB based booting, Solaris Zones partitioning technology, and RAID-1
volumes that can be created at installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="epucs" remap="external">Part&nbsp;II, <citetitle remap="chapter">Understanding Installations That Relate to GRUB, Solaris Zones, and RAID-1 Volumes,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
</chapter>