<chapter id="gdzlc"><title>Upgrading the Solaris OS on a System With
Non-Global  Zones Installed</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes using Solaris Live Upgrade to upgrade a system
that has non-global zones installed. This chapter contains the following sections:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For a summary of changes when you upgrade a system that contains
non-global zones with Solaris Live Upgrade, see <olink targetptr="gdxkz" remap="internal">Upgrading
With Solaris Live Upgrade and Installed Non-Global Zones (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For step-by-step instructions for creating a new boot environment
and upgrading a system with Solaris Live Upgrade, see <olink targetptr="gdxla" remap="internal">Creating
and Upgrading a Boot Environment When Non-Global Zones Are Installed (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For an example with brief instructions for creating a new
boot environment and upgrading a system with Solaris Live Upgrade, see <olink targetptr="gdzlg" remap="internal">Upgrading a System With Non-Global  Zones Installed (Example)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For general information about creating non-global zones, see <olink targetdoc="sysadrm" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="gdxkz"><title>Upgrading With Solaris Live Upgrade and Installed
Non-Global Zones (Overview)</title><para>Starting with the Solaris Express
2/07 release, you can upgrade or patch
a system that contains non-global zones with Solaris Live Upgrade. If you
have a system that contains non-global zones, Solaris Live Upgrade is the
recommended program to upgrade and to add patches.  Other upgrade programs
might require extensive upgrade time, because the time required to complete
the upgrade increases linearly with the number of installed non-global zones.
 If you are patching a system with Solaris Live Upgrade, you do not have 
to take the system to single-user mode and you can maximize your system's
uptime. The following list summarizes changes to accommodate systems that
have non-global zones installed.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>A new package, <literal>SUNWlucfg</literal>, is required to
be installed with the  other Solaris Live Upgrade packages, <literal>SUNWlur</literal> and <literal>SUNWluu</literal>. This package is required for any system, not just a system
with non-global zones installed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Creating a new boot environment from the currently running
boot environment remains the same as in previous releases with one exception.
You can specify a destination disk slice for a shared file system within a
non-global zone. For more information, see <olink targetptr="gdxla" remap="internal">Creating
and Upgrading a Boot Environment When Non-Global Zones Are Installed (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <command>lumount</command> command now provides non-global
zones with access to their corresponding file systems that exist on inactive
boot environments.  When the global zone administrator uses the <command>lumount</command> command
to mount an inactive boot environment, the boot environment is mounted for
non-global zones as well. See <olink targetptr="gebjo" remap="internal">Using the lumount Command
on a System That Contains Non-Global Zones</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Comparing boot environments is enhanced. The <command>lucompare</command> command
now generates a comparison of boot environments that includes the contents
of any non-global zone. See <olink targetptr="gedjg" remap="internal">To Compare Boot Environments
for a System With Non-Global Zones Installed</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Listing file systems with the <command>lufslist</command> command
is enhanced to list file systems for both the global zone and the non-global
zones. See <olink targetptr="gebjm" remap="internal">To View the Configuration of a Boot Environment's
Non-Global Zone File Systems</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="gdxkc"><title>Understanding Solaris Zones and Solaris Live Upgrade</title><para>The Solaris Zones
partitioning technology is used to virtualize operating system services and
provide an isolated and secure environment for running applications.  A non-global
zone is a virtualized operating system environment created within a single
instance of the Solaris OS, the global zone. When you create a non-global
zone, you produce an application execution environment in which processes
are isolated from the rest of the system.</para><para>Solaris Live Upgrade is a mechanism to copy the currently running system
onto new slices. When non-global zones are installed, they can be copied to
the inactive boot environment along with the global zone's file systems.</para><para><olink targetptr="gedht" remap="internal">Figure 9&ndash;1</olink> shows a non-global
zone that is copied to the inactive boot environment along with the global
zone's file system.</para><figure id="gedht"><title>Creating a Boot Environment &ndash; Copying
Non-Global Zones</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="lu-create-zone1"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The context describes the illustration.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><itemizedlist><listitem><para>In this example of a system with a single disk, the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system is copied to <literal>c0t0d0s4</literal>. All non-global
zones that are associated with the file system are also copied to <literal>s4</literal>.
The <filename>/export</filename> and <literal>/swap</literal> file systems
are shared between the current boot environment, <literal>bootenv1</literal>,
and the inactive boot environment, <literal>bootenv2</literal>. The <command>lucreate</command> command is the following:</para><screen># <userinput>lucreate -c bootenv1 -m /:/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s4:ufs</userinput> <userinput>-n bootenv2</userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>In this example of a system with two disks, the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system is copied to <literal>c0t1d0s0</literal>. All non-global
zones that are associated with the file system are also copied to <literal>s0</literal>.
The <filename>/export</filename> and <literal>/swap</literal> file systems
are shared between the current boot environment, <literal>bootenv1</literal>,
and the inactive boot environment, <literal>bootenv2</literal>. The <command>lucreate</command> command is the following:</para><screen># <userinput>lucreate -c bootenv1 -m /:/dev/dsk/c0t1d0s0:ufs</userinput> <userinput>-n bootenv2</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><olink targetptr="gedip" remap="internal">Figure 9&ndash;2</olink> shows that a non-global
zone is copied to the inactive boot environment.</para><figure id="gedip"><title>Creating a Boot Environment  &ndash; 
Copying a Shared File System From a Non-Global Zone</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="lu-create-zone2"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The context describes the illustration.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><itemizedlist><listitem><para>In this example of a system with a single disk, the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system is copied to <literal>c0t0d0s4</literal>. All non-global
zones that are associated with the file system are also copied to <literal>s4</literal>.
The non-global zone, <literal>zone1</literal>, has a separate file system
that was created by the <command>zonecfg add fs</command> command. The zone
path is <filename>/zone1/root/export</filename>. To prevent this file system
from being shared by the inactive boot environment, the file system is placed
on a separate slice, <literal>c0t0d0s6</literal>. The <filename>/export</filename> and <literal>/swap</literal> file systems are shared between the current boot environment, <literal>bootenv1</literal>, and the inactive boot environment, <literal>bootenv2</literal>.
The <command>lucreate</command> command is the following:</para><screen># <userinput>lucreate -c bootenv1 -m /:/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s4:ufs</userinput> \
<userinput>-m /export:/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s6:ufs:zone1 -n bootenv2</userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>In this example of a system with two disks, the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system is copied to <literal>c0t1d0s0</literal>. All non-global
zones that are associated with the file system are also copied to <literal>s0</literal>.
The non-global zone, <literal>zone1</literal>, has a separate file system
that was created by the <command>zonecfg add fs</command> command. The zone
path is <filename>/zone1/root/export</filename>. To prevent this file system
from being shared by the inactive boot environment, the file system is placed
on a separate slice, <literal>c0t1d0s4</literal>. The <filename>/export</filename> and <literal>/swap</literal> file systems are shared between the current boot environment, <literal>bootenv1</literal>, and the inactive boot environment, <literal>bootenv2</literal>.
The <command>lucreate</command> command is the following:</para><screen># <userinput>lucreate -c bootenv1 -m /:/dev/dsk/c0t1d0s0:ufs</userinput> \
<userinput>-m /export:/dev/desk/c0t1d0s4:ufs:zone1  -n bootenv2</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdxla"><title>Creating and Upgrading a Boot Environment When Non-Global
Zones Are Installed (Tasks)</title><para>The
following sections provide information about creating a boot environment when
non-global zones are installed and a procedure for upgrading when non-global
zones are installed.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gdxla" remap="internal">Creating and Upgrading a Boot Environment
When Non-Global Zones Are Installed (Tasks)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gdzpq" remap="internal">Upgrading With Solaris Live Upgrade
When Non-Global Zones Are Installed on a System (Tasks)</olink></para><para>For
an example with abbreviated steps, see <olink targetptr="gdzlg" remap="internal">Upgrading
a System With Non-Global  Zones Installed (Example)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="geptq"><title>Creating a Boot Environment When a Non-Global Zone
Is on a Separate File System</title><para>Creating
a new boot environment from the currently running boot environment remains
the same as in previous releases with one exception. You can specify a destination
disk slice for a shared file system within a non-global zone. This exception
occurs under the following conditions:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If on the current boot environment the <command>zonecfg add
fs</command> command was used to create a separate file system for a non-global
zone</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If this separate file system resides on a shared file system,
such as <filename>/zone/root/export</filename></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>To prevent this separate file system from being shared in the new boot
environment, the <command>lucreate</command> command enables specifying a
destination slice for a separate file system for a non-global zone. The argument
to the <option>m</option> option has a new optional field, <replaceable>zonename</replaceable>.
This new field places the non-global zone's separate file system on a separate
slice in the new boot environment. For more information about setting up a
non-global zone with a separate file system, see <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="zonecfg-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>zonecfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.</para><note><para>By default, any file system other than the critical file systems
(root (<filename>/</filename>), <filename>/usr</filename>, and <filename>/opt</filename> file
systems) is shared between the current and new boot environments. Updating
shared files in the active boot environment also updates data in the inactive
boot environment. For example, the <filename>/export</filename> file system
is a shared file system. If you use the <option>m</option> option and the <replaceable>zonename</replaceable> option, the non-global zone's file system is copied
to a separate slice and data is not shared. This option prevents non-global
zone file systems that were created with the <command>zonecfg add fs</command> command
from being shared between the boot environments. </para>
</note>
</sect2><task id="gdzpq"><title>Upgrading With Solaris Live Upgrade When Non-Global
Zones Are Installed on a System (Tasks)</title><tasksummary><para>The following procedure provides detailed instructions for upgrading
with Solaris Live Upgrade for a system with non-global zones installed.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Remove existing Solaris Live Upgrade packages.</para><para>The
three Solaris Live Upgrade packages, <literal>SUNWluu</literal>, <literal>SUNWlur</literal>, and <literal>SUNWlucfg</literal>, comprise the software needed
to upgrade by using Solaris Live Upgrade. These packages include existing
software, new features, and bug fixes. If you do not remove the existing packages
and install the new packages on your system before using Solaris Live Upgrade,
 upgrading to the target release fails.</para><note><para>The <literal>SUNWlucfg</literal> package is introduced in Solaris Express 5/07 build
52. If you are upgrading from build 52 or later, you must remove this package
along with the other two packages. Then install the three packages from the
target release.</para>
</note><screen># <userinput>pkgrm SUNWlucfg SUNWluu SUNWlur</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Install the Solaris Live Upgrade packages.</para><substeps><step><para>Insert the Solaris DVD or CD.</para><para>This media contains
the packages for the release to which you are upgrading.</para>
</step><step><para>Install the packages in the following order from the installation
media or network installation image.</para><screen># <userinput>pkagadd -d <replaceable>path_to_packages</replaceable> SUNWlucfg SUNWlur SUNWluu</userinput></screen><para> In the following example, the packages are installed from the installation
media.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">For SPARC based systems</emphasis>:</para><screen># <userinput>pkgadd -d /media/cdrom/s0/Solaris_11/Product SUNWlucfg SUNWlur SUNWluu</userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">For x86 based systems</emphasis>:</para><screen># <userinput>pkgadd -d /media/cdrom/Solaris_11/Product SUNWlucfg SUNWlur SUNWluu</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
</substeps>
</step><step id="gdzpn"><para>Verify that the packages have been installed successfully.</para><screen># <userinput>pkgchk -v SUNWlucfg SUNWlur SUNWluu</userinput></screen>
</step><step id="gdzrj"><para>Create the new boot environment.</para><screen># <userinput>lucreate [-A '<replaceable>BE_description</replaceable>'] [-c <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable>] \
 -m <replaceable>mountpoint:device[,metadevice]:fs_options</replaceable>[:<replaceable>zonename</replaceable>] [-m ...] -n <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></userinput></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><option>n</option> <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>The name of the boot environment to be created. <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable> must be unique on the system.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>A</option> '<replaceable>BE_description</replaceable>'</term><listitem><para>(Optional) Enables the creation of a boot environment description
that is associated with the boot environment name (BE_name). The description
can be any length and can contain any characters.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>c</option> <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Assigns the name <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable> to the
active boot environment. This option is not required and is only used when
the first boot environment is created. If you run <command>lucreate</command> for
the first time and you omit the <option>c</option> option, the software creates
a default name for you. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>m</option> <replaceable>mountpoint:device[,metadevice]:fs_options</replaceable>[:<replaceable>zonename</replaceable>] [<option>m</option> ...]</term><listitem><para>Specifies the file systems' configuration of the new boot
environment in the <filename>vfstab</filename>. The file systems that are
specified as arguments to <option>m</option> can be on the same disk or they
can be spread across multiple disks. Use this option as many times as needed
to create the number of file systems that are needed. </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><replaceable>mountpoint</replaceable>  can be any valid mount
point or &ndash; (hyphen), indicating a swap partition.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><replaceable>device</replaceable> field can be one of the
following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The name of a disk device, of the form <filename>/dev/dsk/c<replaceable>w</replaceable>t<replaceable>x</replaceable>d<replaceable>y</replaceable>s<replaceable>z</replaceable></filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The name of  a Solaris Volume Manager volume, of the form
/dev/md/dsk/d<replaceable>num</replaceable></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The name of  a Veritas  Volume Manager volume, of the form
/dev/md/vxfs/dsk/d<replaceable>num</replaceable></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The keyword <literal>merged</literal>, indicating that the
file system at the specified mount point is to be merged with its parent</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para><replaceable>fs_options</replaceable> field can be one of
the following: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literal>ufs</literal>, which  indicates a UFS file system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>vxfs</literal>, which  indicates a Veritas file system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>swap</literal>, which  indicates a swap file system.
The swap mount point must be a &ndash; (hyphen).</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For file systems that are logical devices (mirrors), several
keywords specify actions to be applied to the file systems. These keywords
can create a logical device, change the configuration of a logical device,
or delete a logical device. For a description of these keywords, see  <olink targetptr="lucreate-1000" remap="internal">To Create a Boot Environment With RAID-1 Volumes
(Mirrors)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para><replaceable>zonename</replaceable> specifies that a non-global
zone's separate file system be placed on a separate slice. This option is
used when the zone's separate file system is in a shared file system such
as <filename>/zone1/root/export</filename>. This option copies the zone's
separate file system to a new slice and prevents this file system from being
shared. The separate file system was created with the <filename>zonecfg add
fs</filename> command.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>In the following example, a new boot environment named <literal>newbe</literal> is
created.  The root (<literal>/)</literal> file system is placed on <literal>c0t1d0s4</literal>. All non-global zones in the current boot environment are copied
to the new boot environment.  The non-global zone named <literal>zone1</literal> is
given a separate mount point on <literal>c0t1d0s1</literal>.</para><note><para>By default, any file system other than the critical file systems
(root (<filename>/</filename>), <filename>/usr</filename>, and <filename>/opt</filename> file
systems) is shared between the current and new boot environments. The <filename>/export</filename> file system is a shared file system. If you use the <option>m</option> option,
the non-global zone's file system is placed on a separate slice and data is
not shared. This option prevents zone file systems that were created with
the <command>zonecfg add fs</command> command from being shared between the
boot environments.  See <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="zonecfg-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>zonecfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> for
details.</para>
</note><screen># <userinput>lucreate -n newbe -m /:/dev/dsk/c0t1d0s4:ufs</userinput> <userinput>-m /export:/dev/dsk/c0t1d0s1:ufs:zone1</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Upgrade the boot environment.</para><para> The operating system
image to be used for the upgrade is taken from the network.</para><screen># <userinput>luupgrade -u -n <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable> -s <replaceable>os_image_path</replaceable></userinput></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><option>u</option></term><listitem><para>Upgrades an operating system image on a boot environment</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>n</option> <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Specifies the name of the boot environment that is to be upgraded</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>s</option> <replaceable>os_image_path</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Specifies the path name of a directory that contains an operating
system image</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>In this example, the new boot environment, <literal>newbe</literal>,
is upgraded from a network installation image.</para><screen># <userinput>luupgrade -n newbe -u -s /net/server/export/Solaris_11/combined.solaris_wos</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>(Optional) Verify that the boot environment is bootable.</para><para>The <command>lustatus</command> command reports if the boot environment
creation is complete and bootable.</para><screen># <userinput>lustatus</userinput>
boot environment   Is        Active  Active     Can	    Copy
Name               Complete  Now	 OnReboot   Delete	 Status
------------------------------------------------------------------------
c0t1d0s0            yes      yes      yes       no      -
newbe               yes       no       no       yes     -</screen>
</step><step><para>Activate the new boot environment.</para><screen># <userinput>luactivate <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para><replaceable>BE_name</replaceable> specifies the name of the boot environment
that is to be activated.</para><note><para>For an x86 based system, the <command>luactivate</command> command
is required when booting a boot environment for the first time. Subsequent
activations can be made by selecting the boot environment from the GRUB menu.
For step-by-step instructions, see <olink targetptr="gamog" remap="internal">Activating a Boot
Environment With the GRUB Menu</olink>.</para>
</note><para>To successfully activate a boot environment, that boot environment must
meet several conditions. For more information, see <olink targetptr="luupgrade-84" remap="internal">Activating a Boot Environment</olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Reboot.</para><screen># <userinput>init 6</userinput></screen><caution><para>Use only the <command>init</command> or <command>shutdown</command> commands
to reboot. If you use the <command>reboot</command>, <command>halt</command>,
or <command>uadmin</command> commands, the system does not switch boot environments.
The most recently active boot environment is booted again.</para>
</caution><para>The boot environments have switched and the new boot environment is
now the current boot environment.</para>
</step><step><para>(Optional) Fall back to a different boot environment.</para><para> If
the new boot environment is not viable or you want to switch to another boot
environment, see <olink targetptr="luupgrade-85" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Failure Recovery:
Falling Back to the Original Boot Environment (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdzlg"><title>Upgrading a System With Non-Global  Zones Installed
(Example)</title><para>The following procedure provides an example with abbreviated instructions
for upgrading with Solaris Live Upgrade.</para><para>For detailed explanations of steps, see <olink targetptr="gdzpq" remap="internal">Upgrading
With Solaris Live Upgrade When Non-Global Zones Are Installed on a System
(Tasks)</olink>.</para><sect2 id="gdzmn"><title>Upgrading With Solaris Live Upgrade When Non-Global
Zones Are Installed on a System</title><para>The following example provides abbreviated
descriptions of the steps to upgrade a system with non-global zones installed.
In this example, a new boot environment is created by using the <command>lucreate</command> command on a system that is running the Solaris 10 release. This
system has non-global zones installed and has a non-global zone with a separate
file system on a shared file system, <filename>zone1/root/export</filename>.
The new boot environment is upgraded to the Solaris Express 5/07 release
by using the <command>luupgrade</command> command. The upgraded boot environment
is activated by using the <command>luactivate</command> command.</para><note><para>This procedure assumes that the
system is running removable media services. If you have questions about removable
media services that manage discs, refer to <olink targetdoc="sagdfs" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Devices and File Systems</citetitle></olink> for
detailed information.</para>
</note><orderedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Remove the Solaris Live Upgrade packages
from the current boot environment.</emphasis></para><screen># <userinput>pkgrm SUNWlucfg SUNWluu SUNWlur</userinput></screen><note><para>Remove the <literal>SUNWlucfg</literal> package if your current boot
environment is Solaris Express 2/07 build 52 or later. If your boot environment
is build 51 or earlier or another release, this package is not on your system.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Insert the Solaris DVD or CD. Then
install the replacement Solaris Live upgrade packages from the target release.</emphasis></para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">For SPARC based systems</emphasis>:</para><screen># <emphasis role="strong">pkgadd -d /media/cdrom/s0/Solaris_11/Product SUNWlucfg SUNWlur SUNWluu</emphasis></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">For x86 based systems</emphasis>:</para><screen># <emphasis role="strong">pkgadd -d /media/cdrom/Solaris_11/Product SUNWlucfg SUNWlur SUNWluu</emphasis></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Create a boot environment.</emphasis></para><para>In the following example, a new boot environment named <literal>newbe</literal> is
created.  The root (<filename>/</filename>) file system is placed on <literal>c0t1d0s4</literal>. All non-global zones in the current boot environment are copied
to the new boot environment. A separate file system was created with the <command>zonecfg add fs</command> command for <literal>zone1</literal>. This separate
file system <filename>/zone/root/export</filename> is placed on a separate
file system, <literal>c0t1d0s1</literal>. This option prevents the separate
file system from being shared between the current boot environment and the
new boot environment.</para><screen># <userinput>lucreate -n newbe -m /:/dev/dsk/c0t1d0s4:ufs</userinput> <userinput>-m /export:/dev/dsk/c0t1d0s1:ufs:zone1</userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Upgrade the new boot environment. </emphasis></para><para>In this example, <filename>/net/server/export/Solaris_11/combined.solaris_wos</filename> is the path to the network installation image.</para><screen># <userinput>luupgrade -n newbe -u -s  /net/server/export/Solaris_11/combined.solaris_wos</userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">(Optional) Verify that the boot environment
is bootable.</emphasis></para><para>The <command>lustatus</command> command
reports if the boot environment creation is complete.</para><screen># <userinput>lustatus</userinput>
boot environment   Is        Active  Active     Can	    Copy
Name               Complete  Now	 OnReboot   Delete	 Status
------------------------------------------------------------------------
c0t1d0s0            yes      yes      yes       no           -
newbe               yes       no       no       yes          -</screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Activate the new boot environment.</emphasis></para><screen># <userinput>luactivate newbe</userinput>
# <userinput>init 6</userinput></screen><para>The boot environment <literal>newbe</literal> is now active.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">(Optional) Fall back to a different
boot environment.</emphasis> If the new boot environment is not viable or
you want to switch to another boot environment, see <olink targetptr="luupgrade-85" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Failure Recovery: Falling Back to
the Original Boot Environment (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="geayk"><title>Administering Boot Environments That Contain Non-Global
Zones</title><para>The following sections provide information about administering
boot environments that contain non-global zones.</para><task id="gebjm"><title>To View the Configuration of a Boot Environment's
Non-Global Zone File Systems</title><tasksummary><para>Use this procedure to display a list of file
systems for both the global zone and the non-global zones.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&suStepA;<step id="gebif"><para>Display the list of file systems.</para><screen># <userinput>lufslist -n</userinput> <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Specifies the name of the boot environment to view file system
specifics</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</step>
</procedure><example id="gedjb"><title>List File Systems With Non-Global Zones</title><para>The following example displays a list of file systems that include non-global
zones.</para><screen># <userinput>lufslist -n s3</userinput>
boot environment name: s3
This boot environent is currently active.
This boot environment will be active on next system boot.</screen><screen>Filesystem              fstype    device size Mounted on Mount Options
------------------------------------------------------------------
/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s1         swap     2151776256   -        -
/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s3         ufs     10738040832   /        -
/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s7         ufs     10487955456   /export  -
                zone &lt;zone1> within boot environment &lt;s3>
/dev/dsk/c0t0d0s5         ufs      5116329984   /export  -</screen>
</example>
</task><task id="gedjg"><title>To Compare Boot Environments for a System With Non-Global
Zones Installed</title><tasksummary><para>The <command>lucompare</command> command now generates a comparison
of boot environments that includes the contents of any non-global zone.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&suStepA;<step id="gedkf"><para>Compare the current and new boot environments.</para><screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/lucompare -i&nbsp; <replaceable>infile</replaceable> (or) -t -o &nbsp;<replaceable>outfile</replaceable> <replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></userinput></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><option>i</option>&nbsp; <replaceable>infile</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Compare files that are listed in <replaceable>infile</replaceable>.
The files to be compared should have absolute file names. If the entry in
the file is a directory, the comparison is recursive to the directory.  Use
either this option or <option>t</option>, not both.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>t</option></term><listitem><para>Compare only nonbinary files. This comparison uses the <command>file</command>(1) command on each file to determine if the file is a text file.
Use either this option or <option>i</option>, not both.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>o</option> &nbsp;<replaceable>outfile</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Redirect the output of differences to <replaceable>outfile</replaceable>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><replaceable>BE_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Specifies the name of the boot environment that is compared
to the active boot environment.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</step>
</procedure><example id="gedki"><title>Comparing Boot Environments</title><para>In this example, current boot environment (source) is compared to <literal>second_disk</literal> boot environment and the results are sent to a file.</para><screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/lucompare -i&nbsp; /etc/lu/compare/ -o /var/tmp/compare.out second_disk</userinput></screen>
</example>
</task><sect2 id="gebjo"><title>Using the <command>lumount</command> Command on a
System That Contains Non-Global Zones</title><para>The <command>lumount</command> command
provides non-global zones with access to their corresponding file systems
that exist on inactive boot environments.  When the global zone administrator
uses the <command>lumount</command> command to mount an inactive boot environment,
the boot environment is mounted for non-global zones as well.</para><para>In the following example, the appropriate file systems are mounted for
the boot environment, <literal>newbe,</literal> on <filename>/mnt</filename> in
the global zone. For non-global zones that are running, mounted, or ready,
their corresponding file systems within <literal>newbe</literal> are also
made available on <filename>/mnt</filename> within each zone.</para><screen># <userinput>lumount -n newbe /mnt</userinput></screen><para>For more information about mounting, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="lumount-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>lumount</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>