<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub UDT __target_1 _target?><?Pub UDT registeredtm trademark?><chapter id="ewpor"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sk23612" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="jonj"
fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="kathys"
fullname="Kathy Slattery"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="cathleen" fullname=""?><?Pub Tag
atict:user user="eb151805" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="jh118764" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="lh136763"
fullname="Laura Hartman"?><title>Working With the Sun Java Web Console (Tasks)</title><highlights><para><indexterm><primary>Sun Java Web Console</primary></indexterm>This chapter
describes the Sun <trademark>Java</trademark> Web Console, which is used to
administer web-based Sun system management applications that are installed
and registered on your system. </para><itemizedlist><para>Topics in this chapter include the following:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gbyuq" remap="internal">What's New in Administering the Java
Web Console?</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="sunweb-1" remap="internal">Java Web Console (Overview)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="swc123" remap="internal">Getting Started With the Java Web
Console</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gdckg" remap="internal">Managing the Console Service</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="eyamf" remap="internal">Configuring the Java Web Console</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ewppf" remap="internal">Troubleshooting the Java Web Console
Software</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ewpoy" remap="internal">Java Web Console Reference Information</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information about the procedures that are associated with using
the Java Web Console, see <olink targetptr="swctask-1" remap="internal">Getting Started
With the Java Web Console (Task Map)</olink> and  <olink targetptr="gdkcl" remap="internal">Troubleshooting
the Java Web Console Software (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="gbyuq"><title>What's New in Administering the Java Web Console?</title><para>This section includes features that are new in this Solaris release. </para><sect2 id="gdjqg"><title>Java Web Console Server Management</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> The Java Web Console server
is managed as a service by the Service Management Facility (SMF). For more
information about SMF, see <olink targetptr="hbrunlevels-25516" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16,
Managing Services (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ewidh"><title>Applications That Are Available to the Java Web Console</title><para> The <trademark>ZFS</trademark> web-based
management tool is available in the Java Web Console. This tool enables you
to perform much of the administration tasks that you can perform with the
command-line interface (CLI). These capabilities include setting parameters,
viewing the various pools and file systems, and making updates to them. </para><itemizedlist><para>The following are examples of typical procedures that you might perform
with the tool:</para><listitem><para>Create a new storage pool.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Add capacity to an existing pool.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Move (export) a storage pool to another system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Import a previously exported storage pool, to make it available
on another system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>View tables of information about storage pools.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a file system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a <filename>zvol</filename> (virtual volume). </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Take a snapshot of a file system or a <filename>zvol</filename> volume.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Roll back a file system to a previous snapshot.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For more information about using the Solaris ZFS web-based management
tool, see <olink targetdoc="zfsadmin" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris ZFS Administration Guide</citetitle></olink>.</para><note><para>The Sun Java Enterprise System software includes several management
applications that run in the Java Web Console.</para>
</note>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="sunweb-1"><title>Java Web Console (Overview)</title><para><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>(Overview)</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>web-based system management applications</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm>The Java Web Console provides
a common location for users to access web-based system management applications.
You access the web console by logging in through a secure <literal>https</literal> port
with one of several supported web browsers. The single entry point that the
web console provides eliminates the need to learn URLs for multiple applications.
In addition, the single entry point provides user authentication and authorization
for all applications that are registered with the web console.</para><para>All web console-based applications conform to the same user interface
guidelines, which enhances ease of use. The web console also provides auditing
of user sessions and logging service for all registered applications.</para><sect2 id="ewppg"><title>What Is the Java Web Console?</title><para>The Java Web Console is a web page where you can find the Sun system
management web-based applications that are installed and registered on your
system. Registration is automatically a part of an application's installation
process. Thus, registration requires no administrator intervention.</para><itemizedlist><para>The Java Web Console provides the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">A single point of entry for login
and the launching of browser-based system management applications</emphasis></para><para><indexterm><primary>compatibility with other applications</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>compatibility with other applications</secondary></indexterm>The Java Web Console is
Sun's current direction for system management applications. The console provides
a central location from which you can start browser-based management applications
simply by clicking the application names. No compatibility exists between
the Java Web Console and the Solaris Management Console. The Java Web Console is
a web application that you access through a browser, and Solaris Management
Console is a Java application that you start from a command line. Because
the consoles are completely independent, you can run both consoles on the
same system at the same time.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>single sign-on, secure <literal>https</literal> port</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Single sign-on through a secure https port</emphasis></para><para>Single
sign-on in this context means that you do not have to authenticate yourself
to each management application after you authenticate yourself to the web
console. You enter your user name and password just once per console session.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Dynamically organized and aggregated
applications</emphasis></para><para>Applications are installed and displayed
on the console launch page under the category of management tasks that is
most applicable. </para><itemizedlist><para>Categories include the following:</para><listitem><para>Systems</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Storage</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Services</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Desktop applications</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Other</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">A common look and feel</emphasis></para><para>All web console applications use the same user interface (UI) components
and behavior, thereby reducing the learning curve for administrators.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Standard, extensible authentication,
authorization, and auditing mechanisms</emphasis></para><para>The Java Web Console supports
Pluggable Authentication Module (PAM), role-based access control (RBAC) roles,
and Basic Security Module (BSM) auditing.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="gcngp"><title>Java Web Console Management Commands</title><itemizedlist><para>The Java Web Console includes the following management commands:</para><listitem><para><indexterm><primary><command>smcwebserver</command> command</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><command>wcadmin</command> command</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><command>smreg</command> command</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console commands</primary><secondary><command>wcadmin</command></secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console commands</primary><secondary><command>smcwebserver</command></secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console commands</primary><secondary><command>smreg</command></secondary></indexterm><command>smcwebserver</command> &ndash;
This command starts and stops the console's web server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>wcadmin</command> &ndash; <emphasis role="strong">Starting
with the Solaris 10 11/06 release</emphasis>,
this command is used to configure the console, and to register and deploy
console applications. For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="wcadmin-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>wcadmin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>smreg</command> &ndash; If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running at least the Solaris Express 5/06release,
this command is used to register all console applications.</para><para>,
use this command only to register legacy applications that were created for
a version of the console that is not at least Java Web Console 3.0.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The commands are used to perform various tasks that this chapter describes.</para><para>For more information about each command, see the <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="smcwebserver-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>smcwebserver</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="wcadmin-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>wcadmin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, and the <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="smreg-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>smreg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="gcnfo"><title>Supported Web Browsers</title><itemizedlist><para>The Java Web Console can be used in any of the following browsers
while running the Solaris OS:</para><listitem><para>Mozilla (at least Version, 1.4)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Netscape (at least Version, 6.2)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Firefox (at least Version, 1.0)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="swctask-1"><title>Getting Started With the Java Web Console (Task
Map)</title><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Start applications from the Java Web Console's launch page.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The Java Web Console's launch page lists all the registered system management
applications that you have permission to use. You connect to a specific application
by clicking its application name. </para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="swc321" remap="internal">How to Start Applications From the Java Web
Console's Launch Page</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Start, stop, enable, and disable the console server.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can manage the web server that is used to run the console and the
registered applications.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdcki" remap="internal">How to Start the Console Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gdcjp" remap="internal">How to Enable the Console Service to Run at
System Start</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gdbnw" remap="internal">How to Stop the Console Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gdboa" remap="internal">How to Disable the Console Service</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Change the Java Web Console's properties.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You should not have to change any of the web console's default properties. </para><itemizedlist><para>Properties that you might choose to change include the following:</para><listitem><para>Console session timeout</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Logging level</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Audit implementation</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="eyame" remap="internal">How to Change Java Web Console Properties</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="swc123"><title>Getting Started With the Java Web Console</title><para>The Java Web Console's launch page lists the registered system management
applications that you have permission to use, and displays a brief description
of each application. You connect to a specific application by clicking its
application name, which is a link to the actual application. By default, the
selected application opens in the web console window. You can choose to open
applications in separate browser windows by clicking the Start Each Application
in a New Window check box. When you open applications in separate windows,
the web console launch page remains available, so you can return to it and
launch multiple applications under a single login.</para><para><indexterm><primary>starting applications</primary><secondary>Java Web Console launch page</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>starting applications from</secondary></indexterm>To access the
console launch page, type a URL of the following format in the web location
field: </para><para><userinput>https://<replaceable>hostname.domain</replaceable>:6789</userinput></para><itemizedlist><para>where the following applies:</para><listitem><para><literal>https</literal> specifies a Secure Socket Layer (SSL)
connection</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><replaceable>hostname.domain</replaceable> specifies the name
and domain of the server that is hosting the console</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>6789</literal> is the console's assigned port number</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>The first time you access the Java Web Console from a particular
system, you must accept the server's certificate before the web console's
launch page is displayed.</para>
</note><para>If RBAC is enabled on the system, and your user identity is assigned
to a role, you are prompted for a role password after you have successfully
logged in. If you assume a role, authorization checks are made for the assumed
role. You can opt out of assuming a role by selecting NO ROLE, and then authorization
checks are made against your user identity. Following a successful authorization
check, the web console launch page is displayed.</para><task id="swc321"><title>How to Start Applications From the Java Web Console's
Launch Page</title><procedure><step><para>Start a web browser that is compatible with the Java Web Console,
such as  Firefox 1.0.</para><para>See <olink targetptr="gcnfo" remap="internal">Supported Web Browsers</olink> for a list of supported browsers.</para>
</step><step><para>Type the console's URL in the web browser's location field.</para><para>For example, if the management server host is named <literal>sailfish</literal>,
and the domain is <literal>sw</literal>, the URL is <literal>https://sailfish.sw:6789</literal>. This URL takes you to the web console login page.</para>
</step><step><para>Accept the server's certificate.</para><para>You only have to
accept the server's certificate once per browser session, not each time you
login to the console or start an application.</para><para>The login page is displayed as shown in the following figure.</para><figure id="faasq"><title>Java Web Console Login Page</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="LoginPage"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Shows the Java Web Console login page.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</step><step><para>Enter your user name and password, and optionally your RBAC role.</para><para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information
about roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>The console services check your credentials to authenticate them, and
ensure that you are authorized to use the console and registered applications.</para>
</step><step><para>Click the Start Each Application in a New Window check box if
you want to run the application in a new window.</para><para>If you do not
select this option, the application will run in the default window, replacing
the launch page.</para>
</step><step><para>Click the link for the application that you want to run.</para><tip><para>You can also launch an individual application directly and bypass
the launch page by using the following syntax:</para><screen>https://<replaceable>hostname.domain</replaceable>:6789/<replaceable>app-context-name</replaceable></screen><para>where <replaceable>app-context-name</replaceable> is the name that is
used when the application is deployed. </para><itemizedlist><para>To find the application context name, you can do one of the following:</para><listitem><para>Read the application's documentation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Run the <command>wcadmin list</command> <option>a</option> or
the <command>smreg list</command> <option>a</option> command to see a list
of deployed web applications and their context names.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Run the application from the web console's launch page and
note the URL that is displayed in the address location field. You can type
the URL directly the next time you use the application. Or, you can bookmark
the location and access the application through the bookmark.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</tip>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdckg"><title>Managing the Console Service</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>managing the console service</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>managing Java Web Console service</primary>
</indexterm><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> The Java Web Console service
is managed through the Service Management Facility (SMF). You can start, stop,
enable, and disable the console service by using SMF commands, or by using
the <command>smcwebserver</command> script. The FMRI used in SMF for the console
is <literal>system/webconsole:console</literal>.</para><task id="gdcki"><title>How to Start the Console Service</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>starting the console service</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>This procedure starts the server temporarily. If the server was disabled
from starting when the system boots, it will continue to be disabled. If the
server was enabled, it will continue to be enabled.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release</emphasis>, the running <literal>enabled</literal> state displays as <literal>true
(temporary)</literal>, if the server is running while disabled.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Start the server now, without changing the enabled state.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver start</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gdcjp"><title>How to Enable the Console Service to Run at System
Start</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>enabling the console service</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>This procedure enables the console service to run each time the system
starts. The console is not started in the current session.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release</emphasis> this procedure sets the <literal>general/enabled</literal> property
to true in SMF, so that the server is started at the time the system boots.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Enable the server to be started at system boot.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver enable</userinput></screen><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> Alternatively,
if you want to both start the server now, and enable the server to start when
the system boots, use the command:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable system/webconsole:console</userinput></screen><note><para>If you are running the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
you cannot enable the console by using the <command>smcwebserver</command> command.
You must use the <command>svcadm</command> command.</para>
</note>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gdbnw"><title>How to Stop the Console Service</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>stopping the console service</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>This procedure stops the server temporarily. If the server is disabled
from starting when the system boots, it will continue to be disabled. If the
server was enabled, it will continue to be enabled.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release,</emphasis> the running <literal>enabled</literal> state displays as <literal>false
(temporary)</literal> if the server is stopped while enabled.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Stop the server now, without changing the enabled state.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver stop</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gdboa"><title>How to Disable the Console Service</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>disabling the console service</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>When the console server is disabled, the server does not start when
the system boots.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release,</emphasis> this procedure sets the console's <literal>general/enabled</literal> property
to false in SMF , so that the console server does not start when the system
boots.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Disable the server from starting when the system boots.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver disable</userinput></screen><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> Alternatively,
if you want to both stop the server now, and disable the server from starting
when the system boots, use the command:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable system/webconsole:console</userinput></screen><note><para>If you are running the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
you cannot disable the console with the <command>smcwebserver</command> command.
You must use the <command>svcadm</command> command.</para>
</note>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="eyamf"><title>Configuring the Java Web Console</title><para><indexterm><primary>configuring Java Web Console</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>configuring</secondary></indexterm>The Java Web Console is preconfigured to run without administrator
intervention. However, you might choose to change some of the web console's
default behavior by overriding the console's configuration properties. </para><note><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 OS,</emphasis> you
must use the <command>wcadmin</command> command to change these properties.
Previously, the <command>smreg</command> command was used. For more information
about the <command>wcadmin</command> command, see the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>wcadmin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> man
page.</para>
</note><para>Properties in the console's configuration files control the behavior
of the console. To change the behavior, you define new values for properties
to override the default values. The default values of most properties should
not be overridden unless there is a specific need that the default values
do not provide, such as specifying your own login service. </para><itemizedlist><para>In general, the property values that you might consider changing are
the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Console session timeout</emphasis></para><para><indexterm><primary>console session timeout</primary><secondary>changing Java Web Console properties</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>changing properties of</secondary><tertiary>console session timeout</tertiary></indexterm>The web console's session timeout period is controlled by the <literal>session.timeout.value</literal> property. This property controls how long
a web console page can be displayed without user interaction before the session
times out. After the timeout is reached, the user must log in again. The default
value is 15 minutes. You can set a new value, in minutes, to conform to your
own security policy. However, keep in mind that this property controls the
timeout period for all console users and all registered applications. </para><para>See <olink targetptr="eyamm" remap="internal">Example&nbsp;3&ndash;1</olink> for an example
of how to change the session timeout.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Logging level</emphasis></para><para><indexterm><primary>selecting a logging level</primary><secondary>changing Java Web Console properties</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>changing properties of</secondary><tertiary>logging level</tertiary></indexterm>You use logging properties to configure the logging service. The
console log files are created in the <filename>/var/log/webconsole/console</filename> directory.
The <literal>logging.default.level</literal> property determines which messages
are logged. The console logs provide valuable information for troubleshooting
problems. </para><para><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>differences between default logging and debug logging</secondary></indexterm>The logging
level applies to any messages that are written through the logging service,
which by default uses syslog in the Solaris release  The syslog log file is <filename>/var/adm/messages</filename>.   The file <filename>/var/log/webconsole/console/console_debug_log</filename> contains log messages written when the debugging service is enabled.
 This is done by setting the <literal>debug.trace.level</literal>  property
as described in <olink targetptr="faaor" remap="internal">Using the Console Debug Trace Log</olink>.
Although the default logging and debug logging services are separate, all Java Web Console logging
messages to syslog are also written to the <filename>console_debug_log</filename> to
aid in debugging. Generally, the logging service, set with <literal>logging.default.level</literal>, should be always enabled for logging by console applications.
Debug logging, set with <literal>debug.trace.level</literal>, should only
be enabled to investigate problems.</para><itemizedlist><para>The following property values are available for <literal>logging.default.level</literal>:</para><listitem><para><literal>all</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>info</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>off</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>severe</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>warning</literal></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>See <olink targetptr="eyamu" remap="internal">Example&nbsp;3&ndash;2</olink> for an example
that shows how to change the logging level.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Auditing implementation</emphasis></para><para><indexterm><primary>changing Java Web Console properties</primary><secondary>choosing an auditing implementation</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>auditing implementation</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>changing properties of</secondary><tertiary>auditing implementation</tertiary></indexterm>Auditing is the process of generating and logging security-related
management events. An event signifies that a specific user has updated the
management information on a system. The auditing implementation is used by
services and applications that generate audit events. </para><itemizedlist><para>The following audit events are defined by the web console:</para><listitem><para>Login</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Logout</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Role assumption</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>When audit events occur, a record of the event is made in an audit log.
The location of the audit log varies with the auditing implementation that
is in use. The web console's auditing service uses an auditing implementation
that is provided by the underlying operating system.</para><para>The web console supports three auditing implementations: <literal>Solaris</literal>, <literal>Log</literal>, and <literal>None</literal>. You can select an auditing implementation
by specifying one of these keywords for the value of the <literal>audit.default.type</literal> configuration property. Only one auditing implementation is in
effect at a time. </para><itemizedlist><para>The supported auditing implementation types are:</para><listitem><para><literal>Solaris</literal></para><para>The <literal>Solaris</literal> implementation
is the default. This implementation supports the BSM auditing mechanism. The
auditing mechanism writes audit records into a system file in the <filename>/var/audit</filename> directory.</para><para>You can display the records with the <command>praudit</command> command.
For events to be captured, you must enable the BSM auditing mechanism on the
system. In addition, the <filename>/etc/security/audit_control</filename> file
must contain entries that indicate which events should be generated. You must
set the <literal>lo</literal> event as the flag option to see login and logout
events for each user. For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="praudit-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>praudit</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> and <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="bsmconv-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>bsmconv</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages and <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="audittm-1" remap="external">Part&nbsp;VII, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Auditing,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>Log</literal></para><para>You can configure this
implementation to write to the system's <filename>syslog</filename> service.
Audit messages are written to the console log if the logging service has been
enabled at the <literal>info</literal> level. See <olink targetptr="eyamu" remap="internal">Example&nbsp;3&ndash;2</olink> for more information.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>None</literal></para><para><indexterm><primary>audit events</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm>No audit
events are generated. Audit messages are written to the debug trace log, if
enabled.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>See <olink targetptr="eyamv" remap="internal">Example&nbsp;3&ndash;5</olink> for an example
of specifying the auditing implementation.</para><task id="eyame"><title>How to Change Java Web Console Properties</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>configuring properties</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Depending on which Solaris release you are running, change the
selected property value as follows:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>If you are running at least the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console <replaceable>name=value</replaceable></userinput></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><option>p</option></term><listitem><para>Specifies that the object type is a property.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>a console</option></term><listitem><para>Specifies that the property changes are for the application
named <literal>console</literal>. The <option>a console</option> option must
always be used when you are changing console properties.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><replaceable>name=value</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Specifies the property name and the new value for that property.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</step><step><para>If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running at least
the Solaris Express 5/06 release, use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>smreg add -p -c <replaceable>name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step performance="optional"><para>Reset a console property to its default
value.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>If you are running at least the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin remove -p -a console <replaceable>name=value</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running at least
the Solaris Express 5/06 release,  use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>smreg remove -p -c <replaceable>name</replaceable></userinput></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><option>p</option></term><listitem><para>Specifies that the object type is a property.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><option>c</option></term><listitem><para>Specifies that the property changes are for the console application.
The <option>c</option> option must always be used when you are changing console
properties.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><replaceable>name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Specifies the property name and the new value for that property.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure><example id="eyamm"><title>Changing the Java Web Console's Session Timeout Property</title><para><indexterm><primary>session timeout period</primary><secondary>changing Java Web Console properties</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>changing</primary><secondary>Java Web Console properties</secondary><tertiary>session timeout period</tertiary></indexterm>This example
shows how to set the session time out value to 5 minutes.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console session.timeout.value=5</userinput></screen>
</example><example id="eyamu"><title>Configuring the Java Web Console Logging Level</title><para>This example shows you how to set the logging level to <literal>all</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console logging.default.level=all</userinput></screen>
</example><example id="gdhbw"><title>Resetting the Java Web Console Logging Level to the Default Value</title><para>This example shows how to reset the logging level to the default.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin remove -p -a console logging.default.level</userinput></screen>
</example><example id="gdhhd"><title>Specifying a Java Version for the Java Web Console</title><para>This example shows how to set the Java version for the console.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console java.home=/usr/java</userinput></screen>
</example><example id="eyamv"><title>Choosing an Auditing Implementation for the Java Web Console</title><para>This example shows you how to set the auditing implementation to <literal>None</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console audit.default.type=None</userinput></screen><para>The valid auditing types are:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>None</term><listitem><para>No auditing</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Log</term><listitem><para>Audit messages to syslog</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Solaris</term><listitem><para>Audit messages to BSM</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</example>
</task><sect2 id="frjpw"><title>Java Web Console User Identity</title><para><indexterm><primary><literal>noaccess</literal> user/group</primary><secondary>and Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>changing the user identity that runs the console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary><literal>noaccess</literal> user identity</secondary></indexterm>By default, the web
console runs under the user identity, <literal>noaccess</literal>. However,
some system configurations disable the <literal>noaccess</literal> user, or
set the login shell for the <literal>noaccess</literal> user to an invalid
entry to make this user identity unusable. </para><para>When the <literal>noaccess</literal> user is not usable, the web console
server cannot be started or configured, so an alternative user identity must
be specified. Ideally, the user identity should be changed only once, before
the console server is configured at initial startup.</para><para>You can configure the web console to run under an alternative non-root
user identity by using either of the following commands before the console
starts: </para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver start -u <replaceable>username</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>This command starts the web console server under the specified user
identity. The web console server runs under this identity each time the server
is subsequently started if the command is issued before the first console
start.</para><para>If you are running at least the Solaris 10 11/06 release, you can also
use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console com.sun.web.console.user=<replaceable>username</replaceable></userinput></screen><note><para>Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release, when the system initially
starts, the console also starts and is automatically configured to run under <literal>noaccess</literal>. Consequently, the user identity is set to <literal>noaccess</literal> before
you are able to change the user identity. Use the following commands to reset
the console to its initial unconfigured state. Then, specify a different user
identity when you restart the console.</para><screen># smcwebserver stop
# /usr/share/webconsole/private/bin/wcremove -i console
# smcwebserver start -u <replaceable>new_user_identity</replaceable></screen>
</note><para>If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running at
least the Solaris Express 5/06 release, use this command:</para><para>For the Solaris 10, Solaris 10 1/06, Solaris 10 6/06 releases, use this
command:</para><screen># <userinput>smreg add -p -c com.sun.web.console.user=<replaceable>username</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>This command causes the web console server to run under the specified
user identity the next time the server starts, and each time the server is
started.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="faaor"><title>Using the Console Debug Trace Log</title><para>By default, the console does not log debug messages. You can turn on
debug logging to help troubleshoot console service problems.</para><para>Use the <literal>debug.trace.level</literal> property to turn on debug
logging by setting the property to a value other than 0. </para><itemizedlist><para>Available choices include the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">1</emphasis> - Use this setting to
record potentially severe errors.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">2</emphasis> - Use this setting to
record important messages, as well as error messages of the 1 level.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">3</emphasis> - Use this setting to
record all possible messages with full details.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>By default, the debug trace log is created in the <filename>/var/log/webconsole</filename> directory . Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
the log is created in the <filename>/var/log/webconsole/console</filename> directory.
The log file is named <filename>console_debug_log</filename>. Historical logs,
such as <filename>console_debug_log.1</filename> and <filename>console_debug_log.2</filename> might also exist in this directory.  There can be up to five (default
setting) historical logs stored in this directory before the earliest log
is deleted and a new log is created.</para><example id="faaoq"><title>Setting the Console Debug Trace Log Level</title><para>Use the following command to set the debug trace log level to 3.</para><para>For the <emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06</emphasis> release,
use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin add -p -a console debug.trace.level=3</userinput></screen><para><emphasis role="strong">For the Solaris 10, Solaris 10 1/06, and
the Solaris 10 6/06 releases, use this command:</emphasis></para><screen># <userinput>smreg add -p -c debug.trace.level=3</userinput></screen>
</example><example id="faaox"><title>Checking the Status of the <command>debug.trace.level</command> Property</title><para>To check the status of the <literal>debug.trace.level</literal> property,
use the <command>wcadmin list</command> or <command>smreg list</command> command.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis></para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin list -p | grep "debug.trace.level"</userinput></screen><para>If you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> running at least the
Solaris Express 5/06 release, use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>smreg list -p | grep "debug.trace.level"</userinput></screen>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdkcl"><title>Troubleshooting the Java Web Console Software
(Task Map)</title><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Check to determine if the console is running and enabled.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the <command>smcwebserver</command>, <command>wcadmin</command>,
and <command>svcs</command> commands to check if the console is running and
enabled. This information is useful for troubleshooting problems.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdbnk" remap="internal">How to Check if the Console is Running and
Enabled</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>List console resources and properties.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You might need to gather information about the console resources and
properties for troubleshooting purposes.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdbnv" remap="internal">How to List Console Resources and Properties</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Determine if an application is a legacy application.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Current applications are registered and deployed with a single command
while the console server is running. Legacy applications require the console
server to be stopped during registration. If you need to register or unregister
an application, you must first determine if the application is a legacy application</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdjpi" remap="internal">How to Determine if an Application is a Legacy
Application</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>List all registered applications.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can list all applications that are registered with the Java Web
Console. Listing all registered applications provides you with information
that can be helpful in troubleshooting situations.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gcrqd" remap="internal">How to List Deployed Applications</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Register a legacy application with the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you need to use a legacy application, you must first register the
application with the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdcud" remap="internal">How to Register a Legacy Application With the
Java Web Console</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Unregister a legacy application from the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you do not want a legacy application registered with the Java Web
Console, follow the procedure to unregister the legacy application.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdctn" remap="internal">How to Unregister a Legacy Application From
the Java Web Console</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Register a current application with the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Before using a new application, you need to register the application
with the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gcrqq" remap="internal">How to Register a Current Application With
the Java Web Console</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Unregister a current application from the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para>In some situations, you might need to unregister a current application
from the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gcrsu" remap="internal">How to Unregister a Current Application from
the Java Web Console</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Enable remote Access to the Java Web Console.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can enable remote access only to the console, while leaving the
other access restrictions in place.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdhgt" remap="internal">How to Enable Remote Access to the Java Web
Console</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Change the console's internal passwords</para>
</entry><entry><para>The Java Web Console uses internal passwords. To reduce the possibility
of a security breach, you can change these passwords.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdcsa" remap="internal">How to Change the Console's Internal Passwords</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="ewppf"><title>Troubleshooting the Java Web Console Software</title><para><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>troubleshooting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>troubleshooting</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm>The following information is provided to help you troubleshoot
any problems that you might encounter when using the Java Web Console software.</para><sect2 id="gdbnh"><title>Checking Console Status and Properties</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>status</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>properties</secondary>
</indexterm><para>You can use the <command>smcwebserver</command>, <command>wcadmin</command>,
and <command>svcs</command> commands to get different types of information
about the console, which might be useful for troubleshooting problems.</para><task id="gdbnk"><title>How to Check if the Console is Running and Enabled</title><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Check the server status.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver status</userinput>
Sun Java(TM) Web Console is running</screen>
</step><step><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> Check the
console's SMF status and enabled state.</para><screen># <userinput>svcs -l system/webconsole:console</userinput>
fmri         svc:/system/webconsole:console
name         java web console
enabled      true
state        online
next_state   none
state_time   Wed 17 May 2006 01:22:32 PM EDT
logfile      /var/svc/log/system-webconsole:console.log
restarter    svc:/system/svc/restarter:default
contract_id  129
dependency   require_all/none svc:/milestone/multi-user (online)</screen><para>If you start and stop the server with <command>smcwebserver</command> commands
without enabling and disabling, the <literal>enabled</literal> property might
display as <literal>false (temporary)</literal> or <literal>true (temporary)</literal>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gdbnv"><title>How to List Console Resources and Properties</title><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>List the console's resources and properties.</para><para>If you
are running at least the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin list</userinput>

Deployed web applications (application name, context name, status):
 
    console      ROOT            [running]
    console      com_sun_web_ui  [running]
    console      console         [running]
    console      manager         [running]
    legacy       myapp           [running]
 
Registered jar files (application name, identifier, path):
 
    console  audit_jar     /usr/lib/audit/Audit.jar
    console  console_jars  /usr/share/webconsole/lib/*.jar
    console  jato_jar      /usr/share/lib/jato/jato.jar
    console  javahelp_jar  /usr/jdk/packages/javax.help-2.0/lib/*.jar
    console  shared_jars   /usr/share/webconsole/private/container/shared/lib/*.jar
 
Registered login modules (application name, service name, identifier):
 
    console  ConsoleLogin  userlogin
    console  ConsoleLogin  rolelogin
 
Shared service properties (name, value):
 
    <emphasis role="strong">ENABLE            yes</emphasis>
    java.home         /usr/jdk/jdk1.5.0_06</screen><note><para>This <property>ENABLE</property> property is ignored because SMF
uses its own enabled property, which is shown in the previous procedure. The <property>ENABLE</property> property is used on older Solaris systems where the console
server is not managed by SMF.</para>
</note><para>For the Solaris 10, Solaris 10 1/06, and Solaris
10 6/06 releases, use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>smreg list</userinput>

 The list of registered plugin applications:

com.sun.web.console_2.2.4       /usr/share/webconsole/console
com.sun.web.ui_2.2.4    /usr/share/webconsole/com_sun_web_ui
com.sun.web.admin.example_2.2.4 /usr/share/webconsole/example

The list of registered jar files:

com_sun_management_services_api.jar scoped to ALL
com_sun_management_services_impl.jar scoped to ALL
com_sun_management_console_impl.jar scoped to ALL
com_sun_management_cc.jar scoped to ALL
com_sun_management_webcommon.jar scoped to ALL
com_iplanet_jato_jato.jar scoped to ALL
com_sun_management_solaris_impl.jar scoped to ALL
com_sun_management_solaris_implx.jar scoped to ALL

The list of registered login modules for service ConsoleLogin:

com.sun.management.services.authentication.PamLoginModule optional
use_first_pass="true" commandPath="/usr/lib/webconsole";
com.sun.management.services.authentication.RbacRoleLoginModule requisite
force_role_check="true" commandPath="/usr/lib/webconsole";

The list of registered server configuration properties:

session.timeout.value=15
authentication.login.cliservice=ConsoleLogin
logging.default.handler=com.sun.management.services.logging.ConsoleSyslogHandler
logging.default.level=info
logging.default.resource=com.sun.management.services.logging.resources.Resources
logging.default.filter=none
logging.debug.level=off
audit.default.type=None
audit.None.class=com.sun.management.services.audit.LogAuditSession
audit.Log.class=com.sun.management.services.audit.LogAuditSession audit.class.fail=none
authorization.default.type=SolarisRbac
authorization.SolarisRbac.class=
com.sun.management.services.authorization.SolarisRbacAuthorizationService
authorization.PrincipalType.class=
com.sun.management.services.authorization.PrincipalTypeAuthorizationService
debug.trace.level=0
.
.
.
No environment properties have been registered.</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2><sect2 id="gdhhr"><title>Problems Accessing the Console</title><para>Problems with console access might indicate that the console server
is not enabled, or security settings are restrictive. See <olink targetptr="gdbnh" remap="internal">Checking Console Status and Properties</olink> and <olink type="auto-generated" targetptr="ewpla" remap="internal">Java Web Console Security Considerations</olink> for
more information.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="gcrrb"><title>Problems with Application Registration</title><para>This section contains information about solving possible registration
problems with console applications. For information about a particular console
application, you should refer to the application's documentation.</para><note><para>Console applications typically are registered as part of their
installation process, so you should not normally need to register an application
yourself.</para>
</note><para><indexterm><primary>legacy applications</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>legacy applications</secondary></indexterm>Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release,
the web console has changed the approach to application registration but can
still support applications that were developed for earlier versions of the
console. Current applications are registered and deployed with a single command
while the console server is running. Applications that were developed for
the earlier console are known as <emphasis>legacy</emphasis> applications,
and require the console server to be stopped during registration. If you need
to register or unregister an application, you must first determine if the
application is a legacy application, as described in the following procedure.</para><task id="gdjpi"><title>How to Determine if an Application is a Legacy Application</title><procedure><step><para>View the application's <filename>app.xml</filename> file.</para><para>The <filename>app.xml</filename> file is located in the application's <filename>WEB-INF</filename> directory.</para>
</step><step><para>Examine the <literal>registrationInfo</literal> tag in the <filename>app.xml</filename> file.</para><para>For a legacy application, the <literal>registrationInfo</literal> tag is a version 2.<replaceable>x</replaceable> . For example, <literal>registrationInfo version="2.2.4"</literal>.</para><para>For a current application, the version in the <literal>registrationInfo</literal> tag
is at least 3.0. For example, <literal>registrationInfo version="3.0"</literal>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gcrqd"><title>How to List Deployed Applications</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>listing deployed applications</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>List the deployed applications.</para><para>If you are running
at least the Solaris 10 11/06 release, use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin list -a</userinput>

Deployed web applications (application name, context name, status):
 
    console  ROOT            [running]
    console  com_sun_web_ui  [running]
    console  console         [running]
    console  manager         [running]
    legacy   myapp           [running]</screen><para>The command lists all the registered and deployed applications. Legacy
applications are listed with the application name <literal>legacy</literal>.
See <olink targetptr="gdjpi" remap="internal">How to Determine if an Application is a Legacy
Application</olink>. All other listed applications are current applications,
and would be registered as described in <olink targetptr="gcrqq" remap="internal">How to Register
a Current Application With the Java Web Console</olink>.</para><para>Typically, the status that is shown for the applications contains either <literal>running</literal> or <literal>stopped</literal>.  If the status is <literal>running</literal>, the application is currently loaded and available. If the status
is <literal>stopped</literal>, then the application is not currently loaded
and is unavailable.  Sometimes an application registers and deploys successfully,
but does not load because of a problem in the application. If so, the application's
status is <literal>stopped</literal>.  Check the <filename>console_debug_log</filename> to
determine if there is an error with a traceback from the console's underlying
web container, Tomcat, when attempting to load the application. For more information
about the <filename>console_debug_log</filename>, see <olink targetptr="faaor" remap="internal">Using
the Console Debug Trace Log</olink>.</para><para>If all the applications show <literal>stopped</literal> (including the
console application), this usually means the console's web container is not
running. The list of applications in this case is obtained from the static <filename>context.xml</filename> files registered with the web container.</para><para>For the Solaris 10, Solaris 10 1/06, and Solaris 10 6/06 releases,
use this command:</para><screen># <userinput>smreg list -a</userinput>

The list of registered plugin applications:

        com.sun.web.console_2.2.4       /usr/share/webconsole/console
        com.sun.web.ui_2.2.4    /usr/share/webconsole/com_sun_web_ui
        com.sun.web.admin.yourapp_2.2.4 /usr/share/webconsole/yourapp</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gdcud"><title>How to Register a Legacy Application With the Java
Web Console</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>registering applications</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><note><para>This procedure applies to all console applications in the Solaris
10, Solaris 10 1/06, and Solaris 10 6/06 releases. Starting with Solaris 10
11/06 release, this procedure also applies <emphasis>only</emphasis> to those
applications that are identified as legacy applications. See <olink targetptr="gcrqq" remap="internal">How to Register a Current Application With the Java Web
Console</olink> for the registration procedure for current applications. See
also <olink targetptr="gdjpi" remap="internal">How to Determine if an Application is a Legacy
Application</olink>.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Stop the web server.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver stop</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Register the application.</para><screen># <userinput>smreg add -a <replaceable>/directory/containing/application-files</replaceable><replaceable></replaceable></userinput></screen><para>The <command>smreg</command> command manages the information in the
Java Web Console's registration table. This script also performs some additional
work to deploy the application. For additional options to this command, see
the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="smreg-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>smreg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page.</para>
</step><step><para>Restart the web server.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver start</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure><example id="exegm"><title>Registering a Legacy Application</title><para>This example shows how to register a legacy application whose files
are located in the <filename>/usr/share/webconsole/example</filename> directory.
Notice that for legacy applications, the console server must be stopped before
the application is registered, and started after the application is registered.
A warning given by <command>smreg</command> can be ignored because this application
is a legacy console application.</para><screen># <userinput>smcwebserver stop</userinput>
# <userinput>smreg add -a /usr/share/webconsole/example</userinput>

    Warning: smreg is obsolete and is preserved only for
    compatibility with legacy console applications. Use wcadmin instead.

    Type "man wcadmin" or "wcadmin --help" for more information.

Registering com.sun.web.admin.example_<replaceable>version</replaceable>.

# <userinput>smcwebserver start</userinput></screen>
</example>
</task><task id="gdctn"><title>How to Unregister a Legacy Application From the Java
Web Console</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>unregistering applications</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><note><para>This procedure applies to all console applications in the Solaris
10, Solaris 10 1/06, and Solaris 10 6/06 releases. Starting with Solaris 10
11/06 release, this procedure applies <emphasis>only</emphasis> to those applications
that are identified as legacy applications. See <olink targetptr="gcrsu" remap="internal">How
to Unregister a Current Application from the Java Web Console</olink> for
the procedure that describes how to unregister current applications.</para>
</note><para><indexterm><primary>unregistering an application from the Java Web Console</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><command>smreg</command> command</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm>If you do not want a
particular legacy application to display in the web console's launch page,
but you do not want to uninstall the software, you can use the <command>smreg</command> command
to unregister the application. See <olink targetptr="gdjpi" remap="internal">How to Determine
if an Application is a Legacy Application</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Unregister an application.</para><screen># <userinput>smreg remove -a <replaceable>app-name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure><example id="exefu"><title>Unregistering a Legacy Application From the Java Web Console</title><para>This example shows how to unregister a legacy application  with the <replaceable>app-name</replaceable> <literal>com.sun.web.admin.example</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>smreg remove -a com.sun.web.admin.example</userinput>

 Unregistering com.sun.web.admin.example_<replaceable>version</replaceable>.</screen>
</example>
</task><task id="gcrqq"><title>How to Register a Current Application With the Java
Web Console</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>registering applications</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> This procedure
is for updated console applications that can be registered and deployed without
stopping and starting the console server. See <olink targetptr="gdcud" remap="internal">How
to Register a Legacy Application With the Java Web Console</olink> for the
registration procedure for legacy applications and all console applications
that are in the Solaris 10, Solaris 10 1/06, Solaris 10 6/06 releases. See
also <olink targetptr="gdjpi" remap="internal">How to Determine if an Application is a Legacy
Application</olink>.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Register and deploy the application.</para><screen>wcadmin deploy -a <replaceable>app-name</replaceable> -x <replaceable>app-context-name</replaceable> <replaceable>/full path/to/app-name</replaceable></screen>
</step>
</procedure><example id="gcrsv"><title>Registering Current Applications</title><para>This example shows how to register and deploy an application that has
been developed or updated for the current web console.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin deploy -a newexample_1.0 -x newexample /apps/webconsole/newexample</userinput></screen>
</example>
</task><task id="gcrsu"><title>How to Unregister a Current Application from the Java
Web Console</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>unregistering applications</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris 10 11/06:</emphasis> This procedure
is for updated console applications, which can be unregistered and undeployed
without stopping and starting the console server. See <olink targetptr="gdctn" remap="internal">How
to Unregister a Legacy Application From the Java Web Console</olink> for the
unregistration procedure for legacy applications and all console applications
that are in the Solaris 10, Solaris 10 1/06, Solaris 10 6/06 releases. See <olink targetptr="gcrqd" remap="internal">How to List Deployed Applications</olink> and <olink targetptr="gdjpi" remap="internal">How to Determine if an Application is a Legacy Application</olink> to
determine if an application is a legacy or updated application.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Undeploy and unregister the application.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin undeploy -a newexample_1.0 -x newexample</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ewpoy"><title>Java Web Console Reference Information</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>reference information</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>This reference section includes the following topics:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ewpla" remap="internal">Java Web Console Security Considerations</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ewplr" remap="internal">Specifying Authorizations With the
authTypes Tag</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="ewpla"><title>Java Web Console Security Considerations</title><para><indexterm><primary>security considerations</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>security considerations</secondary></indexterm>There are several security considerations
to keep in mind when you use applications that are in the Java Web Console. </para><itemizedlist><para>These security considerations include the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Access to the Java Web Console</emphasis> &ndash;
Whether you can connect to the console through a browser.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Access to applications</emphasis> &ndash;
Whether you can see a particular application in the Java Web Console's
launch page.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Application permissions</emphasis> &ndash;
The levels of permissions that you must have to run parts or all of an application.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Application access to remote systems</emphasis> &ndash;
How security credentials relate to remote systems</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Internal passwords used in the console</emphasis> -
Changing the default passwords that are used internally in the console, starting
with the Solaris 10 11/06 release.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect3 id="gcnvf"><title>Access to the Java Web Console</title><para><indexterm><primary>console access</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>access to console</secondary></indexterm>Permissions to the web console launcher
application are usually open so that any valid user can log in. However, you
can restrict access to the console by specifying the rights in the <literal>authTypes</literal> tag in the web console's <filename>app.xml</filename> file, which
is located in the <filename>/usr/share/webconsole/webapps/console/WEB-INF</filename> directory.
For more information, see <olink targetptr="ewplr" remap="internal">Specifying Authorizations
With the authTypes Tag</olink>.</para><para>Some system configurations
are set up to be very secure, so that attempts to connect from a remote system
to the URLs of the console or registered applications are refused. If your
system is configured to prevent remote access, when you try to access the
console as <literal>https://hostname.domain:6789</literal>, your browser displays
a message such as:</para><screen>Connect to hostname.domain:6789 failed (Connection refused)</screen><para>The SMF profile in effect on the system might be restricting
access. See <olink targetptr="fgoth" remap="internal">SMF Profiles</olink> for more information
about profiles. See <olink type="auto-generated" targetptr="gdhhu" remap="internal">Enabling
Remote Access to the Java Web Console</olink> for a procedure to allow access
to the console from remote systems.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ewplb"><title>Access to Applications in the Java Web Console</title><para><indexterm><primary>application access</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>access to applications</secondary></indexterm>After you successfully log in to the
web console, you might not automatically have access to all of the applications
that are registered in that console . Typically, applications are installed
so that all users can see them in the console launch page. As an administrator,
you can grant and restrict access to applications. </para><para>To restrict access to an application, specify the rights in the <literal>authTypes</literal> tag, which is in the application's <filename>app.xml</filename> file.
 You can find the application's <filename>app.xml</filename> file in the <filename><replaceable>installation-location</replaceable>/WEB-INF/</filename> subdirectory. Typically,
this directory would be located in <filename>/usr/share/webconsole/webapps/<replaceable>app-context-name</replaceable>/WEB-INF</filename>. </para><para>If the application files are not in the usual location, you can locate
the files by using the following command:</para><screen><userinput>wcadmin list --detail -a</userinput></screen><para>This command lists each deployed application, showing when it was deployed
and the path to the application's base directory. The <filename>app.xml</filename> file
is located in the subdirectory <filename>WEB-INF</filename> within the base
directory.</para><para>For more information, see <olink targetptr="ewplr" remap="internal">Specifying Authorizations
With the authTypes Tag</olink>.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ewplg"><title>Application Privileges</title><para><indexterm><primary>application privileges</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>application privileges</secondary></indexterm>If you can see an application's link on
the Java Web Console's launch page, you can run that application. However,
an application might make additional authorization checks based upon the authenticated
user or role identity.  These checks are not controlled by the <literal>authTypes</literal> tag, but are explicitly coded into the application itself.  For
example, an application might grant read access to all authenticated users,
but restrict update access to a few users or a few roles.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ewplm"><title>Application Access to Remote Systems</title><para><indexterm><primary>application access to remote systems</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>application access to remote systems</secondary></indexterm>Having
all the appropriate credentials does not guarantee that you can use an application
to manage every system within the application's scope of operation. Each system
that you administer by using the Java Web Console application has its own
security domain. Having read-and-write permissions on the web console system
does not guarantee that those credentials are automatically sufficient to
administer any other remote system.</para><para>In general, access to remote systems depends on how the security is
implemented in the web application.  Typically, web applications make calls
to <emphasis>agents</emphasis> that perform actions on behalf of the applications.
These applications must be authenticated by the agents based on their web
console credentials and the credentials by which they are known on the agent
system. Depending upon how this agent authentication is done, an authorization
check might also be made on the agent itself, based upon this authenticated
identity.</para><para>For example, in web applications that use remote WBEM agents, authentication
typically uses the user or role identity that initially authenticated to the Java Web Console.
 If this authentication fails on that agent system, access to that system
is denied in the web application.  If authentication succeeds on that agent
system, access might still be denied if the agent makes an access control
check and denies access there. Most applications are written so that the authentication
and authorization checks on the agent never fail if you have been successfully
authenticated on the web console and assumed the correct role.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="gdcpc"><title>Internal Passwords Used in the Console</title><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>internal passwords</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release, the Java Web Console uses
several password-protected internal user names to perform administrative tasks
on the underlying web server, and to encrypt key store and trust store files.
The passwords are set to initial values to enable the console to be installed.
To reduce the possibility of a security breach, you should change the passwords
after installation. See <olink type="auto-generated" targetptr="gdcso" remap="internal">Changing
Internal Passwords for Java Web Console</olink></para>
</sect3>
</sect2><sect2 id="ewplr"><title>Specifying Authorizations With the <literal>authTypes</literal> Tag</title><para><indexterm><primary><literal>authTypes</literal> tag</primary><secondary>Java Web Console</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>using <literal>authTypes</literal> tag</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Java Web Console</primary><secondary>authorizing users of applications</secondary></indexterm>While
most system management web applications do not require any administrator intervention
to use the <literal>authTypes</literal> tag, in some cases, you might need
to change the values of this tag. The <literal>authTypes</literal> tag contains
a set of information that describes the level of authorization that is required
for a user to view an application in the Java Web Console. The web console
determines if a user is authorized to see a particular application, based
on the authorization requirements in the application's <filename>app.xml</filename> file.
Each application can determine whether a user must have proper authorization
to run the application. This determination might be made as part of the application
installation process. Or, you might need to supply the information, depending
on your own security requirements. The product documentation for the application
should contain the information that is necessary to determine whether you
need to specify a particular permission.</para><para>You can nest several <literal>authType</literal> tags within the <literal>authTypes</literal> tag. </para><itemizedlist><para>The <literal>authTypes</literal> tag must contain at least one <literal>authType</literal> tag that provides the following necessary information:</para><listitem><para>Type of authorization check to perform</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><classname>Permission</classname> subclass name</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Parameters that are required to instantiate the <classname>Permission</classname> subclass</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>In the following example, the <literal>authType</literal> tag has one
attribute, <literal>name</literal>. The required <literal>name</literal> attribute
is the name of the authorization service type. Different authorization types
might require different values for the <literal>classType</literal> and <literal>permissionParam</literal> tags. </para><screen>&lt;authTypes&gt;
	&lt;authType name="SolarisRbac"&gt;
	    &lt;classType&gt;
	      com.sun.management.solaris.RbacPermission
	    &lt;/classType&gt;
	    &lt;permissionParam name="permission"&gt;
	      solaris.admin.serialmgr.read
	    &lt;/permissionParam&gt;
	&lt;/authType&gt;
&lt;/authTypes&gt;</screen><para>The following table shows the tags that can be nested within an <literal>authType</literal> tag</para><table frame="topbot" id="ewpll"><title>Nested <literal>authType</literal> Tags</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><?PubTbl tgroup dispwid="7.98in"?><colspec colname="colspec6" colwidth="22.74*"/><colspec colname="colspec7" colwidth="22.74*"/><colspec colname="colspec8" colwidth="53.52*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Tag</para>
</entry><entry><para>Attribute</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><literal>classType</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry><entry><para>The <literal>Permission</literal> subclass name. This tag is a required
tag.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>permissionParam</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>name</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>The parameters that are required to create an instance of the class
specified by <literal>classType</literal>. </para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>The <literal>authTypes</literal> tag and nested <literal>authType</literal> tags
are required elements in the <filename>app.xml</filename> file. If you want
to register an application that is available to anyone, specify the <literal>authType</literal> tag with no content, as shown in the following example.</para><screen>&lt;authTypes&gt;
        &lt;authType name=""&gt;
            &lt;classType&gt;&lt;/classType&gt;
            &lt;permissionParam name=""&gt;&lt;/permissionParam&gt;
        &lt;/authType&gt;
&lt;/authTypes&gt;</screen>
</sect2><sect2 id="gdhhu"><title>Enabling Remote Access to the Java Web Console</title><para>If you can only connect to the console by logging into the system that
is running the console, and then using the URL <literal>https://localhost:6789</literal>,
the system is using a configuration that prevents remote access. Starting
with the Solaris 10 11/06 release, you can enable remote access only to the
console, while leaving the other access restrictions in place, by using the
following procedure:</para><task id="gdhgt"><title>How to Enable Remote Access to the Java Web Console</title><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role on the system where
the console is running.</para><para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged
commands. For more information about roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Set a property to allow the console server to respond to network
requests and restart the console server.</para><screen># <userinput>svccfg -s svc:/system/webconsole setprop options/tcp_listen = true</userinput>
# <userinput>smcwebserver restart</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2><sect2 id="ggfwd"><title>Disabling Remote Access to the Java Web Console</title><para>You can prevent users from connecting to the console from remote systems.
Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release, you can disable remote access
only to the console, while leaving the other access permissions in place,
by using the following procedure:</para><task><title>How to Disable Remote Access to the Java Web Console</title><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role on the system where
the console is running.</para><para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged
commands. For more information about roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Set a property to prevent the console server from responding to
network requests, and restart the console server.</para><screen># <userinput>svccfg -s svc:/system/webconsole setprop options/tcp_listen = false</userinput>
# <userinput>smcwebserver restart</userinput></screen><para>After the restart the console now only responds to a browser on the
same system as the console server process.  You cannot use a proxy in the
browser, only a direct connection.  You can also use the <literal>https://localhost:6789/</literal> URL to access the console.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2><sect2 id="gdcso"><title>Changing Internal Passwords for Java Web Console</title><para>Starting with the Solaris 10 11/06 release, the console uses some internal
user names and passwords. The console's internal user names and passwords
are used only by the console framework, and are never used directly by a user
or system administrator. However, if the passwords were known, a malicious
user could potentially interfere with the console applications. To reduce
the possibility of such a security breach, you should change the passwords.
You do not need to remember the new passwords, because the software uses them
invisibly.</para><task id="gdcsa"><title>How to Change the Console's Internal Passwords</title><tasksummary><para>The passwords are known as the administrative password, keystore password,
and truststore password. You do not need to know the default initial values
in order to change the passwords. This procedure explains how to change all
three passwords with separate commands.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Change the administrative password.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin password -a</userinput></screen><para>You are prompted to enter the new password twice. The password should
be 8 to 32 characters.</para>
</step><step><para>Change the key store password.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin password -k</userinput></screen><para>You are prompted to enter the new password twice. The password should
be 8 to 32 characters.</para>
</step><step><para>Change the trust store password.</para><screen># <userinput>wcadmin password -t</userinput></screen><para>You are prompted to enter the new password twice. The password should
be 8 to 32 characters.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000090966 0?>