<preface id="preface-4"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>The <citetitle>Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle> guide provides procedures for
configuring <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Trusted Extensions on the Solaris Operating System. This guide also describes preparing
the Solaris system to support a secure installation of Solaris Trusted Extensions.</para>&platformnote;
</highlights><sect1 id="preface-6"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is for knowledgeable system administrators and security administrators
who are installing Trusted Extensions software. The level of trust that is required
by your site security policy, and your level of expertise, determines who
can perform the configuration tasks.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-2"><title>Implementing Site Security</title><para>Successfully configuring Trusted Extensions on a system in a way that is
consistent with site security requires understanding the security features
of Trusted Extensions and your site security policy. Before you install the Solaris Trusted Extensions packages,
read <olink targetptr="ovw-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1, Security Planning for Trusted
Extensions</olink> for information about how to ensure site security when
configuring the software.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-3"><title>Trusted Extensions and the Solaris Operating System</title><para>Trusted Extensions installs on top of the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS). Because Trusted Extensions software
can modify the Solaris OS, Trusted Extensions can require specific settings for Solaris installation
options. For details, see <olink targetptr="startinst-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Installing
Solaris Trusted Extensions Software  (Tasks)</olink>. Also, Trusted Extensions books
supplement Solaris books. As administrators, you need access to Solaris books
and Trusted Extensions books.</para><sect2 id="preface-20"><title>How This Book Is Organized</title><para><olink targetptr="ovw-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1, Security Planning for Trusted
Extensions</olink> describes the security issues that you need to consider
when configuring Trusted Extensions software on one or more Solaris systems.</para><para><olink targetptr="tmap-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Installation and Configuration
Roadmap for Trusted Extensions</olink> contains task maps for adding Trusted Extensions software
to Solaris systems.</para><para><olink targetptr="startinst-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Installing Solaris Trusted
Extensions Software  (Tasks)</olink> provides instructions on preparing a Solaris system
for Trusted Extensions software. It also includes instructions on adding the packages.</para><para><olink targetptr="txconf-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Configuring Trusted Extensions
(Tasks)</olink> provides instructions on configuring Trusted Extensions software
on a system with a monitor.</para><para><olink targetptr="txldap-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Configuring LDAP for Trusted
Extensions (Tasks)</olink> provides instructions on configuring LDAP for Trusted Extensions.</para><para><olink targetptr="headl-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Configuring a Headless System
With Trusted Extensions (Tasks)</olink> describes how to configure and administer Trusted Extensions software
on a headless system.</para><para><olink targetptr="appol-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;A, Site Security Policy</olink> addresses
site security policy and places Trusted Extensions in the context of wider organizational
and site security.</para><para><olink targetptr="aptxconf-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;B, Using CDE Actions to
Install Zones in Trusted Extensions</olink> describes how to configure labeled
zones by using Trusted CDE actions.</para><para><olink targetptr="checklist-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;C, Configuration Checklist
for Trusted Extensions</olink> provides a configuration checklist for the
install team.</para><para><olink targetptr="glossary-1" remap="internal">Glossary</olink> defines selected terms
and phrases that are used in this book.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>&tsset;<sect1 id="preface-5"><title>Related Books from Sun Microsystems</title><para>The following books contain information that is useful when you install Solaris Trusted Extensions software.</para><sect2 id="preface-22"><title>Solaris Books</title><para><olink targetdoc="solarisinstall" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Basic Installations</citetitle></olink> &ndash; Provides
guidance on the installation options for the Solaris OS</para><para><olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink> &ndash;
Provides guidance on disk space requirements, installation methods, and configuration
options</para><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv1" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink> &ndash; Describes basic administrative
tasks in the Solaris OS, such as using the Solaris Management Console</para><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv2" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Advanced Administration</citetitle></olink> &ndash;
Describes more advanced administrative tasks in the Solaris OS, such as print
management</para><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv3" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: IP Services</citetitle></olink> &ndash; Describes network configuration
tasks in the Solaris OS</para><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv5" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Naming and Directory Services (DNS, NIS, and LDAP)</citetitle></olink> &ndash;
Describes the naming services in the Solaris OS</para><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv6" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink> &ndash; Describes the security
features in the Solaris OS</para><para><olink targetdoc="sysadrm" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink> &ndash;
Describes the containment features in the Solaris OS</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-21"><title>Books From Elsewhere</title><para>Your site security policy document &ndash; Describes the security policy
and security procedures at your site</para><para><citetitle>Solaris Common Desktop Environment: Advanced User's and System
Administrator's Guide</citetitle> &ndash; Describes the Common Desktop Environment
(CDE)</para><para>The administrator guide for your currently installed operating system &ndash;
Describes how to back up system files</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="gcllh"><title>Related Third-Party Web Site References</title><para>Third-party URLs are referenced in this document and provide additional,
related information.</para><note><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party web
sites that are mentioned in this document. Sun does not endorse and is not
responsible or liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials
that are available on or through such sites or resources. Sun will not be
responsible or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused or alleged
to be caused by or in connection with the use of or reliance on
any such content, goods, or services that are available on or through such
sites or resources.</para>
</note>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>