<preface id="preface-13250"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>Labels, clearances, and handling instructions are used to protect information
on a system that is configured with Solaris Trusted Extensions software. The components of
labels, clearances, and handling instructions are specified in the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file. This guide provides background for creating or modifying
the file. The guide provides examples, and helps you to create and install
a <filename>label_encodings</filename> file that is appropriate for your site.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="preface-1"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is for security administrators. Security administrators are
responsible for defining the organization's labels. Some security administrators
are also responsible for implementing the labels. This book is for definers
and implementers.</para><note><para>Even though Trusted Extensions can be configured with no visible labels,
labels are always being used. Labels provide mandatory access control (MAC),
and MAC is always enforced. Therefore, the site's <filename>label_encodings</filename> file
must be in place before any users or roles are created.</para><para>Trusted Extensions installs
a default <filename>label_encodings</filename> file. The security administrator
must provide a file that is appropriate for the site.</para>
</note><para>The security administrator who implements the labels should be familiar
with Solaris administration. The necessary level of knowledge can be
acquired through training and documentation. For details, see <olink targetptr="sundocs-1" remap="internal">Documentation, Support, and Training</olink>.</para>
</sect1>&tsset;<sect1 id="preface-7"><title>How This Book Is Organized</title><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="overview-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1, Labels in Trusted Extensions Software</olink> discusses labels-related concepts
for the security administrator who prepares the site's <filename>label_encodings</filename> file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planl-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Planning Labels
(Tasks)</olink> provides planning steps for the security administrator who
prepares the site's <filename>label_encodings</filename> file. This chapter
also describes the encodings files that Trusted Extensions provides.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="modifyenc-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Making a Label
Encodings File (Tasks)</olink> describes how to create, customize, and check
the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="printl-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Labeling Printer
Output (Tasks)</olink> describes the labels and handling instructions on printer
output and gives procedures for modifying them.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="localdef-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Customizing
LOCAL DEFINITIONS</olink> describes the optional <literal>LOCAL DEFINITIONS</literal> section
of the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planex-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Example: Planning
an Organization's Labels</olink> models how a site analyzes its label requirements
and creates a <filename>label_encodings</filename> file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appendixa-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;A, Sample Label
Encodings File</olink> contains the example of the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file
from <olink targetptr="planex-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Example: Planning an Organization's
Labels</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>