<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bull rArr sect?><chapter id="chp-aggs"><title>Aggregations</title><highlights><para>When instrumenting the system to answer performance-related questions,
it is useful to consider how data can be aggregated to answer a specific question
rather than thinking in terms of data gathered by individual probes. For example,
if you wanted to know the number of system calls by user ID, you would not
necessarily care about the datum collected at <emphasis>each</emphasis> system
call. You simply want to see a table of user IDs and system calls. Historically,
you would answer this question by gathering data at each system call, and
postprocessing the data using a tool like <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="awk-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>awk</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> or <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="perl-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>perl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.
However, in DTrace the aggregating of data is a first-class operation. This
chapter describes the DTrace facilities for manipulating <firstterm>aggregations</firstterm>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="chp-aggs-1"><title>Aggregating Functions</title><para>An <firstterm>aggregating function</firstterm> is one that has the following
property:</para><literallayout><literal>f(f(x</literal><subscript>0</subscript><literal>) U f(x</literal><subscript>1</subscript><literal>) U ... U f(x</literal><subscript>n</subscript><literal>)) = f(x</literal><subscript>0</subscript> <literal>U x</literal><subscript>1</subscript> <literal>U ... U x</literal><subscript>n</subscript><literal>)</literal></literallayout><para>where <replaceable>x</replaceable><subscript><replaceable>n</replaceable></subscript> is
a set of arbitrary data. That is, applying an aggregating function to subsets
of the whole and then applying it again to the results gives the same result
as applying it to the whole itself. For example, consider a function <literal>SUM</literal> that yields the summation of a given data set. If the raw data
consists of {2, 1, 2, 5, 4, 3, 6, 4, 2}, the result of applying <literal>SUM</literal> to
the entire set is {29}. Similarly, the result of applying <literal>SUM</literal> to
the subset consisting of the first three elements is {5}, the result of applying <literal>SUM</literal> to the set consisting of the subsequent three elements is {12},
and the result of of applying <literal>SUM</literal> to the remaining three
elements is also {12}. <literal>SUM</literal> is an aggregating function because
applying it to the set of these results, {5, 12, 12}, yields the same result,
{29}, as applying <literal>SUM</literal> to the original data.</para><para>Not all functions are aggregating functions. An example of a non-aggregating
function is the function <literal>MEDIAN</literal> that determines the median
element of the set. (The median is defined to be that element of a set for
which as many elements in the set are greater than it as are less than it.)
The <literal>MEDIAN</literal> is derived by sorting the set and selecting
the middle element. Returning to the original raw data, if <literal>MEDIAN</literal> is
applied to the set consisting of the first three elements, the result is {2}.
(The sorted set is {1, 2, 2}; {2} is the set consisting of the middle element.)
Likewise, applying <literal>MEDIAN</literal> to the next three elements yields
{4} and applying <literal>MEDIAN</literal> to the final three elements yields
{4}. Applying <literal>MEDIAN</literal> to each of the subsets thus yields
the set {2, 4, 4}. Applying <literal>MEDIAN</literal> to this set yields the
result {4}. However, sorting the original set yields {1, 2, 2, 2, 3, 4, 4,
5, 6}. Applying <literal>MEDIAN</literal> to this set thus yields {3}. Because
these results do not match, <literal>MEDIAN</literal> is not an aggregating
function.</para><para>Many common functions for understanding a set of data are aggregating
functions. These functions include counting the number of elements in the
set, computing the minimum value of the set, computing the maximum value of
the set, and summing all elements in the set. Determining the arithmetic mean
of the set can be constructed from the function to count the number of elements
in the set and the function to sum the number the elements in the set.</para><para>However, several useful functions are not aggregating functions. These
functions include computing the mode (the most common element) of a set, the
median value of the set, or the standard deviation of the set.</para><para>Applying aggregating functions to data as it is traced has a number
of advantages:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The entire data set need not be stored. Whenever a new element
is to be added to the set, the aggregating function is calculated given the
set consisting of the current intermediate result and the new element. After
the new result is calculated, the new element may be discarded. This process
reduces the amount of storage required by a factor of the number of data points,
which is often quite large.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Data collection does not induce pathological scalability problems.
Aggregating functions enable intermediate results to be kept <emphasis>per-CPU</emphasis> instead
of in a shared data structure. DTrace then applies the aggregating function
to the set consisting of the per-CPU intermediate results to produce the final
system-wide result.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-aggs-2"><title>Aggregations</title><para><indexterm><primary>aggregators</primary></indexterm>DTrace stores the
results of aggregating functions in objects called <firstterm>aggregations</firstterm>.
The aggregation results are indexed using a tuple of expressions similar to
those used for associative arrays. In D, the syntax for an aggregation is:</para><programlisting>@<replaceable>name</replaceable>[ <replaceable>keys</replaceable> ] = <replaceable>aggfunc</replaceable> ( <replaceable>args</replaceable> );</programlisting><para>where <replaceable>name</replaceable> is the name of the aggregation, <replaceable>keys</replaceable> is a comma-separated list of D expressions, <replaceable>aggfunc</replaceable> is one of the DTrace aggregating functions, and <replaceable>args</replaceable> is
a comma-separated list of arguments appropriate for the aggregating function.
The aggregation <replaceable>name</replaceable> is a D identifier that is
prefixed with the special character <literal>@</literal>. All aggregations
named in your D programs are global variables; there are no thread- or clause-local
aggregations. The aggregation names are kept in a separate identifier namespace
from other D global variables. Remember that <literal>a</literal> and <literal>@a</literal> are not the same variable if you reuse names. The special aggregation
name <literal>@</literal> can be used to name an anonymous aggregation in
simple D programs. The D compiler treats this name as an alias for the aggregation
name <literal>@_</literal>.</para><para><indexterm><primary><literal>count</literal></primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>sum</literal></primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>avg</literal></primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>min</literal></primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>max</literal></primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>lquantize</literal></primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>quantize</literal></primary></indexterm>The DTrace aggregating functions are
shown in the following table. Most aggregating functions take just a single
argument that represents the new datum.</para><table frame="topbot" id="chp-aggs-tbl-4"><title>DTrace Aggregating Functions</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><?PubTbl tgroup dispwid="8.88in"?><colspec colwidth="20.45*"/><colspec colwidth="20.45*"/><colspec colwidth="58.10*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Function Name</para>
</entry><entry><para>Arguments</para>
</entry><entry><para>Result</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><literal>count</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>none</para>
</entry><entry><para>The number of times called.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>sum</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>scalar expression</para>
</entry><entry><para>The total value of the specified expressions.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>avg</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>scalar expression</para>
</entry><entry><para>The arithmetic average of the specified expressions.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>min</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>scalar expression</para>
</entry><entry><para>The smallest value among the specified expressions.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>max</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>scalar expression</para>
</entry><entry><para>The largest value among the specified expressions.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>lquantize</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>scalar expression, lower bound, upper bound, step value</para>
</entry><entry><para>A linear frequency distribution, sized by the specified range, of the
values of the specified expressions. Increments the value in the <emphasis>highest</emphasis> bucket that is <emphasis>less</emphasis> than the specified expression.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>quantize</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>scalar expression</para>
</entry><entry><para>A power-of-two frequency distribution of the values of the specified
expressions. Increments the value in the <emphasis>highest</emphasis> power-of-two
bucket that is <emphasis>less</emphasis> than the specified expression.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>For example, to count the number of <olink targetdoc="refman2" targetptr="write-2" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>write</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> system calls in the system,
you could use an informative string as a key and the <function>count</function> aggregating
function:</para><programlisting>syscall::write:entry
{
	@counts["write system calls"] = count();
}</programlisting><para><indexterm><primary><literal>dtrace</literal></primary></indexterm>The <command>dtrace</command> command prints aggregation results by default when the process
terminates, either as the result of an explicit <literal>END</literal> action
or when the user presses Control-C. The following example output shows the
result of running this command, waiting for a few seconds, and pressing Control-C:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s writes.d</userinput>
dtrace: script './writes.d' matched 1 probe
<userinput>^C</userinput>

  write system calls                                              179
#</screen><para><indexterm><primary><literal>execname</literal></primary></indexterm>You
can count system calls per process name using the <literal>execname</literal> variable
as the key to an aggregation:</para><programlisting>syscall::write:entry
{
	@counts[execname] = count();
}</programlisting><para>The following example output shows the result of running this command,
waiting for a few seconds, and pressing Control-C:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s writesbycmd.d</userinput>
dtrace: script './writesbycmd.d' matched 1 probe
<userinput>^C</userinput>

  dtrace                                                            1
  cat                                                               4
  sed                                                               9
  head                                                              9
  grep                                                             14
  find                                                             15
  tail                                                             25
  mountd                                                           28
  expr                                                             72
  sh                                                              291
  tee                                                             814
  def.dir.flp                                                    1996
  make.bin                                                       2010
#</screen><para>Alternatively, you might want to further examine writes organized by
both executable name and file descriptor. The file descriptor is the first
argument to <olink targetdoc="refman2" targetptr="write-2" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>write</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>,
so the following example uses a key consisting of both <literal>execname</literal> and <literal>arg0</literal>:</para><programlisting>syscall::write:entry
{
	@counts[execname, arg0] = count();
}</programlisting><para>Running this command results in a table with both executable name and
file descriptor, as shown in the following example:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s writesbycmdfd.d</userinput>
dtrace: script './writesbycmdfd.d' matched 1 probe
<userinput>^C</userinput>

  cat                                                               1      58
  sed                                                               1      60
  grep                                                              1      89
  tee                                                               1     156
  tee                                                               3     156
  make.bin                                                          5     164
  acomp                                                             1     263
  macrogen                                                          4     286
  cg                                                                1     397
  acomp                                                             3     736
  make.bin                                                          1     880
  iropt                                                             4    1731
#</screen><para>The following example displays the average time spent in the write system
call, organized by process name. This example uses the <function>avg</function> aggregating
function, specifying the expression to average as the argument. The example
averages the wall clock time spent in the system call:</para><programlisting>syscall::write:entry
{
	self-&gt;ts = timestamp;
}

syscall::write:return
/self-&gt;ts/
{
	@time[execname] = avg(timestamp - self-&gt;ts);
	self-&gt;ts = 0;
}</programlisting><para>The following example output shows the result of running this command,
waiting for a few seconds, and pressing Control-C:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s writetime.d</userinput>
dtrace: script './writetime.d' matched 2 probes
<userinput>^C</userinput>

  iropt                                                         31315
  acomp                                                         37037
  make.bin                                                      63736
  tee                                                           68702
  date                                                          84020
  sh                                                            91632
  dtrace                                                       159200
  ctfmerge                                                     321560
  install                                                      343300
  mcs                                                          394400
  get                                                          413695
  ctfconvert                                                   594400
  bringover                                                   1332465
  tail                                                        1335260
#</screen><para>The average can be useful, but often does not provide sufficient detail
to understand the distribution of data points. To understand the distribution
in further detail, use the <function>quantize</function> aggregating function
as shown in the following example:</para><programlisting>syscall::write:entry
{
	self-&gt;ts = timestamp;
}

syscall::write:return
/self-&gt;ts/
{
	@time[execname] = quantize(timestamp - self-&gt;ts);
	self-&gt;ts = 0;
}</programlisting><para>Because each line of output becomes a frequency distribution diagram,
the output of this script is substantially longer than previous ones. The
following example shows a selection of sample output:</para><screen>  lint                                              
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
            8192 |                                         0        
           16384 |                                         2        
           32768 |                                         0        
           65536 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@                      74       
          131072 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@                          59       
          262144 |@@@                                      14       
          524288 |                                         0        

  acomp                                             
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
            4096 |                                         0        
            8192 |@@@@@@@@@@@@                             840      
           16384 |@@@@@@@@@@@                              750      
           32768 |@@                                       165      
           65536 |@@@@@@                                   460      
          131072 |@@@@@@                                   446      
          262144 |                                         16       
          524288 |                                         0        
         1048576 |                                         1        
         2097152 |                                         0        

  iropt                                             
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
            4096 |                                         0        
            8192 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@                  4149     
           16384 |@@@@@@@@@@                               1798     
           32768 |@                                        332      
           65536 |@                                        325      
          131072 |@@                                       431      
          262144 |                                         3        
          524288 |                                         2        
         1048576 |                                         1        
         2097152 |                                         0        </screen><para>Notice that the rows for the frequency distribution are <emphasis>always</emphasis> power-of-two
values. Each rows indicates the count of the number of elements <emphasis>greater
than or equal to</emphasis> the corresponding value, but <emphasis>less than</emphasis> the
next larger row value. For example, the above output shows that <literal>iropt</literal> had
4,149 writes taking between 8,192 nanoseconds and 16,383 nanoseconds, inclusive.</para><para>While <function>quantize</function> is useful for getting quick insight
into the data, you might want to examine a distribution across linear values
instead. To display a linear value distribution, use the <function>lquantize</function> aggregating
function. The <function>lquantize</function> function takes three arguments
in addition to a D expression: a lower bound, an upper bound, and a step.
For example, if you wanted to look at the distribution of writes by file descriptor,
a power-of-two quantization would not be effective. Instead, use a linear
quantization with a small range, as shown in the following example:</para><programlisting>syscall::write:entry
{
	@fds[execname] = lquantize(arg0, 0, 100, 1);
}</programlisting><para>Running this script for several seconds yields a large amount of information.
The following example shows a selection of typical output:</para><screen>  mountd                                            
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
              11 |                                         0        
              12 |@                                        4        
              13 |                                         0        
              14 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@                70       
              15 |                                         0        
              16 |@@@@@@@@@@@@                             34       
              17 |                                         0        

  xemacs-20.4                                       
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
               6 |                                         0        
               7 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@  521      
               8 |                                         0        
               9 |                                         1        
              10 |                                         0        

  make.bin                                          
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
               0 |                                         0        
               1 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@  3596     
               2 |                                         0        
               3 |                                         0        
               4 |                                         42       
               5 |                                         50       
               6 |                                         0        

  acomp                                             
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
               0 |                                         0        
               1 |@@@@@                                    1156     
               2 |                                         0        
               3 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@         6635     
               4 |@                                        297      
               5 |                                         0        

  iropt                                             
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
               2 |                                         0        
               3 |                                         299      
               4 |@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@  20144    
               5 |                                         0        </screen><para>You can also use the <function>lquantize</function> aggregating function
to aggregate on time since some point in the past. This technique allows you
to observe a change in behavior over time. The following example displays
the change in system call behavior over the lifetime of a process executing
the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="date-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>date</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> command:</para><programlisting>syscall::exec:return,
syscall::exece:return
/execname == "date"/
{
	self-&gt;start = vtimestamp;
}

syscall:::entry
/self-&gt;start/
{
	/*
	 * We linearly quantize on the current virtual time minus our
	 * process's start time.  We divide by 1000 to yield microseconds
	 * rather than nanoseconds.  The range runs from 0 to 10 milliseconds
	 * in steps of 100 microseconds; we expect that no date(1) process
	 * will take longer than 10 milliseconds to complete.
	 */
	@a["system calls over time"] =
	    lquantize((vtimestamp - self-&gt;start) / 1000, 0, 10000, 100);
}

syscall::rexit:entry
/self-&gt;start/
{
	self-&gt;start = 0;
}</programlisting><para>The preceding script provides greater insight into system call behavior
when many <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="date-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>date</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> processes
are executed. To see this result, run <command>sh -c 'while true; do date
&gt;/dev/null; done'</command> in one window, while executing the D script in
another. The script produces a profile of the system call behavior of the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="date-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>date</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> command:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s dateprof.d</userinput>
dtrace: script './dateprof.d' matched 218 probes
<userinput>^C</userinput>

  system calls over time
           value  ------------- Distribution ------------- count    
             &lt; 0 |                                         0        
               0 |@@                                       20530    
             100 |@@@@@@                                   48814    
             200 |@@@                                      28119    
             300 |@                                        14646    
             400 |@@@@@                                    41237    
             500 |                                         1259     
             600 |                                         218      
             700 |                                         116      
             800 |@                                        12783    
             900 |@@@                                      28133    
            1000 |                                         7897     
            1100 |@                                        14065    
            1200 |@@@                                      27549    
            1300 |@@@                                      25715    
            1400 |@@@@                                     35011    
            1500 |@@                                       16734    
            1600 |                                         498      
            1700 |                                         256      
            1800 |                                         369      
            1900 |                                         404      
            2000 |                                         320      
            2100 |                                         555      
            2200 |                                         54       
            2300 |                                         17       
            2400 |                                         5        
            2500 |                                         1        
            2600 |                                         7        
            2700 |                                         0        </screen><para>This output provides a rough idea of the different phases of the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="date-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>date</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> command with respect to the
services required of the kernel. To better understand these phases, you might
want to understand which system calls are being called when. If so, you could
change the D script to aggregate on the variable <literal>probefunc</literal> instead
of a constant string.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-aggs-7"><title>Printing Aggregations</title><para><indexterm><primary>aggregator</primary><secondary>output</secondary></indexterm>By default, multiple aggregations are displayed in the order they
are introduced in the D program. You can override this behavior using the <function>printa</function> function to print the aggregations. The <function>printa</function> function
also enables you to precisely format the aggregation data using a format string,
as described in <olink targetptr="chp-fmt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;12, Output Formatting</olink>.</para><para>If an aggregation is not formatted with a <function>printa</function> statement
in your D program, the <command>dtrace</command> command will snapshot the
aggregation data and print the results once after tracing has completed using
the default aggregation format. If a given aggregation is formatted using
a <function>printa</function> statement, the default behavior is disabled.
You can achieve equivalent results by adding the statement <literal>printa(@</literal><replaceable>aggregation-name</replaceable><literal>)</literal> to a <literal>dtrace:::END</literal> probe
clause in your program. The default output format for the <function>avg</function>, <function>count</function>, <function>min</function>, <function>max</function>, and <function>sum</function> aggregating functions displays an integer decimal value corresponding
to the aggregated value for each tuple. The default output format for the <function>lquantize</function> and <function>quantize</function> aggregating functions
displays an ASCII table of the results. Aggregation tuples are printed as
if <function>trace</function> had been applied to each tuple element.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-aggs-normalization"><title>Data Normalization</title><para><indexterm><primary>aggregator</primary><secondary>normalization</secondary></indexterm>When aggregating data over some period of time, you might want
to <emphasis>normalize</emphasis> the data with respect to some constant factor.
This technique enables you to compare disjoint data more easily. For example,
when aggregating system calls, you might want to output system calls as a
per-second rate instead of as an absolute value over the course of the run.
The DTrace <function>normalize</function> action enables you to normalize
data in this way. The parameters to <function>normalize</function> are an
aggregation and a normalization factor. The output of the aggregation shows
each value divided by the normalization factor.</para><para>The following example shows how to aggregate data by system call:</para><programlisting>#pragma D option quiet

BEGIN
{
	/*
	 * Get the start time, in nanoseconds.
	 */
	start = timestamp;
}

syscall:::entry
{
	@func[execname] = count();
}

END
{
	/*
	 * Normalize the aggregation based on the number of seconds we have
	 * been running.  (There are 1,000,000,000 nanoseconds in one second.)
	 */	
	normalize(@func, (timestamp - start) / 1000000000);
}</programlisting><para>Running the above script for a brief period of time results in the following
output on a desktop machine:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s ./normalize.d</userinput>
 <userinput>^C</userinput>
  syslogd                                                           0
  rpc.rusersd                                                       0
  utmpd                                                             0
  xbiff                                                             0
  in.routed                                                         1
  sendmail                                                          2
  echo                                                              2
  FvwmAuto                                                          2
  stty                                                              2
  cut                                                               2
  init                                                              2
  pt_chmod                                                          3
  picld                                                             3
  utmp_update                                                       3
  httpd                                                             4
  xclock                                                            5
  basename                                                          6
  tput                                                              6
  sh                                                                7
  tr                                                                7
  arch                                                              9
  expr                                                             10
  uname                                                            11
  mibiisa                                                          15
  dirname                                                          18
  dtrace                                                           40
  ksh                                                              48
  java                                                             58
  xterm                                                           100
  nscd                                                            120
  fvwm2                                                           154
  prstat                                                          180
  perfbar                                                         188
  Xsun                                                           1309
  .netscape.bin                                                  3005</screen><para><function>normalize</function> sets the normalization factor for the
specified aggregation, but this action does not modify the underlying data. <function>denormalize</function> takes only an aggregation. Adding the denormalize action
to the preceding example returns both raw system call counts and per-second
rates:</para><programlisting>#pragma D option quiet

BEGIN
{
	start = timestamp;
}

syscall:::entry
{
	@func[execname] = count();
}

END
{
	this-&gt;seconds = (timestamp - start) / 1000000000;
	printf("Ran for %d seconds.\n", this-&gt;seconds);

	printf("Per-second rate:\n");
	normalize(@func, this-&gt;seconds);
	printa(@func);

	printf("\nRaw counts:\n");
	denormalize(@func);
	printa(@func);
}</programlisting><para>Running the above script for a brief period of time produces output
similar to the following example:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s ./denorm.d</userinput>
<userinput>^C</userinput>
Ran for 14 seconds.
Per-second rate:

  syslogd                                                           0
  in.routed                                                         0
  xbiff                                                             1
  sendmail                                                          2
  elm                                                               2
  picld                                                             3
  httpd                                                             4
  xclock                                                            6
  FvwmAuto                                                          7
  mibiisa                                                          22
  dtrace                                                           42
  java                                                             55
  xterm                                                            75
  adeptedit                                                       118
  nscd                                                            127
  prstat                                                          179
  perfbar                                                         184
  fvwm2                                                           296
  Xsun                                                            829

Raw counts:

  syslogd                                                           1
  in.routed                                                         4
  xbiff                                                            21
  sendmail                                                         30
  elm                                                              36
  picld                                                            43
  httpd                                                            56
  xclock                                                           91
  FvwmAuto                                                        104
  mibiisa                                                         314
  dtrace                                                          592
  java                                                            774
  xterm                                                          1062
  adeptedit                                                      1665
  nscd                                                           1781
  prstat                                                         2506
  perfbar                                                        2581
  fvwm2                                                          4156
  Xsun                                                          11616</screen><para>Aggregations can also be renormalized. If <function>normalize</function> is
called more than once for the same aggregation, the normalization factor will
be the factor specified in the most recent call. The following example prints
per-second rates over time:</para><example id="ex-renormalize.d"><title><filename>renormalize.d</filename>:
Renormalizing an Aggregation</title><programlisting>#pragma D option quiet

BEGIN
{
	start = timestamp;
}

syscall:::entry
{
	@func[execname] = count();
}

tick-10sec
{
	normalize(@func, (timestamp - start) / 1000000000);
	printa(@func);
}</programlisting>
</example>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-aggs-clear"><title>Clearing Aggregations</title><para><indexterm><primary>aggregator</primary><secondary>clearing</secondary></indexterm>When using DTrace to build simple monitoring scripts, you can
periodically clear the values in an aggregation using the <function>clear</function> function.
This function takes an aggregation as its only parameter. The <function>clear</function> function
clears only the aggregation's <emphasis>values</emphasis>; the aggregation's
keys are retained. Therefore, the presence of a key in an aggregation that
has an associated value of zero indicates that the key <emphasis>had</emphasis> a
non-zero value that was subsequently set to zero as part of a <function>clear</function>.
To discard both an aggregation's values and its keys, use the <function>trunc</function>.
See <olink targetptr="chp-aggs-trunc" remap="internal">Truncating aggregations</olink> for
details.</para><para>The following example adds <function>clear</function> to <olink targetptr="ex-renormalize.d" remap="internal">Example&nbsp;9&ndash;1</olink>:</para><programlisting>#pragma D option quiet

BEGIN
{
	last = timestamp;
}

syscall:::entry
{
	@func[execname] = count();
}

tick-10sec
{
	normalize(@func, (timestamp - last) / 1000000000);
	printa(@func);
	clear(@func);
	last = timestamp;
}</programlisting><para>While <olink targetptr="ex-renormalize.d" remap="internal">Example&nbsp;9&ndash;1</olink> shows
the system call rate over the lifetime of the <command>dtrace</command> invocation,
the preceding example shows the system call rate only for the most recent
ten-second period.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-aggs-trunc"><title>Truncating aggregations</title><para><indexterm><primary>aggregator</primary><secondary>truncating</secondary></indexterm>When looking at aggregation results, you often care only about
the top several results. The keys and values associated with anything other
than the highest values are not interesting. You might also wish to discard
an entire aggregation result, removing both keys <emphasis>and</emphasis> values.
The DTrace <function>trunc</function> function is used for both of these situations.</para><para>The parameters to <function>trunc</function> are an aggregation and
an optional truncation value. Without the truncation value, <function>trunc</function> discards <emphasis>both</emphasis> aggregation values <emphasis>and</emphasis> aggregation keys
for the entire aggregation. When a truncation value <replaceable>n</replaceable> is
present, <function>trunc</function> discards aggregation values and keys <emphasis>except</emphasis> for those values and keys associated with the highest <replaceable>n</replaceable> values. That is, <literal>trunc(@foo, 10)</literal> truncates
the aggregation named <literal>foo</literal> after the top ten values, where <literal>trunc(@foo)</literal> discards the entire aggregation. The entire aggregation
is also discarded if <literal>0</literal> is specified as the truncation value.</para><para>To see the bottom <replaceable>n</replaceable> values instead of the
top <replaceable>n</replaceable>, specify a negative truncation value to <function>trunc</function>. For example, <literal>trunc(@foo, -10)</literal> truncates
the aggregation named <literal>foo</literal> after the bottom ten values.</para><para>The following example augments the system call example to only display
the per-second system call rates of the top ten system-calling applications
in a ten-second period:</para><programlisting>#pragma D option quiet

BEGIN
{
	last = timestamp;
}

syscall:::entry
{
	@func[execname] = count();
}

tick-10sec
{
	trunc(@func, 10);
	normalize(@func, (timestamp - last) / 1000000000);
	printa(@func);
	clear(@func);
	last = timestamp;
}</programlisting><para>The following example shows output from running the above script on
a lightly loaded laptop:</para><screen>  FvwmAuto                                                          7
  telnet                                                           13
  ping                                                             14
  dtrace                                                           27
  xclock                                                           34
  MozillaFirebird-                                                 63
  xterm                                                           133
  fvwm2                                                           146
  acroread                                                        168
  Xsun                                                            616

  telnet                                                            4
  FvwmAuto                                                          5
  ping                                                             14
  dtrace                                                           27
  xclock                                                           35
  fvwm2                                                            69
  xterm                                                            70
  acroread                                                        164
  MozillaFirebird-                                                491
  Xsun                                                           1287</screen>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-aggs-4"><title>Minimizing Drops</title><para><indexterm><primary>aggregator</primary><secondary>drops</secondary></indexterm>Because DTrace buffers some aggregation data in the kernel, space
might not be available when a new key is added to an aggregation. In this
case, the data will be dropped, a counter will be incremented, and <command>dtrace</command> will generate a message indicating an aggregation drop. This situation
rarely occurs because DTrace keeps long-running state (consisting of the aggregation's
key and intermediate result) at user-level where space may grow dynamically.
In the unlikely event that aggregation drops occur, you can increase the aggregation
buffer size with the <literal>aggsize</literal> option to reduce the likelihood
of drops. You can also use this option to minimize the memory footprint of
DTrace. As with any size option, <literal>aggsize</literal> may be specified
with any size suffix. The resizing policy of this buffer is dictated by the <literal>bufresize</literal> option. For more details on buffering, see <olink targetptr="chp-buf" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;11, Buffers and Buffering</olink>. For more
details on options, see <olink targetptr="chp-opt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16, Options
and Tunables</olink>.</para><para>An alternative method to eliminate aggregation drops is to increase
the rate at which aggregation data is consumed at user-level. This rate defaults
to once per second, and may be explicitly tuned with the <literal>aggrate</literal> option.
As with any rate option, <literal>aggrate</literal> may be specified with
any time suffix, but defaults to rate-per-second. For more details on the <literal>aggsize</literal> option, see <olink targetptr="chp-opt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16,
Options and Tunables</olink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000044639 0?>