<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><chapter id="chp-buf"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="palecur" fullname="Paul Echeverri"?><title>Buffers and Buffering</title><highlights><para>Data buffering and management is an essential service provided by the
DTrace framework for its clients, such as <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>. This chapter explores data
buffering in detail and describes options you can use to change DTrace's buffer
management policies.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="chp-buf-1"><title>Principal Buffers</title><para>The <firstterm>principal buffer</firstterm> is present in every DTrace
invocation and is the buffer to which tracing actions record their data by
default. These actions include:</para><informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/><tbody><row><entry><para><function>exit</function></para>
</entry><entry><para><function>printf</function></para>
</entry><entry><para><function>trace</function></para>
</entry><entry><para><function>ustack</function></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><function>printa</function></para>
</entry><entry><para><function>stack</function></para>
</entry><entry><para><function>tracemem</function></para>
</entry><entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>The principal buffers are <emphasis>always</emphasis> allocated on a
per-CPU basis. This policy is not tunable, but tracing and buffer allocation
can be restricted to a single CPU by using the <literal>cpu</literal> option.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-buf-2"><title>Principal Buffer Policies</title><para><indexterm><primary>principal buffer</primary><secondary>policies</secondary></indexterm>DTrace permits tracing in highly constrained contexts in the kernel.
In particular, DTrace permits tracing in contexts in which kernel software
may not reliably allocate memory. The consequence of this flexibility of context
is that there <emphasis>always</emphasis> exists a possibility that DTrace
will attempt to trace data when there isn't space available. DTrace must have
a policy to deal with such situations when they arise, but you might wish
to tune the policy based on the needs of a given experiment. Sometimes the
appropriate policy might be to discard the new data. Other times it might
be desirable to reuse the space containing the oldest recorded data to trace
new data. Most often, the desired policy is to minimize the likelihood of
running out of available space in the first place. To accommodate these varying
demands, DTrace supports several different buffer policies. This support is
implemented with the <literal>bufpolicy</literal> option, and can be set on
a per-consumer basis. See <olink targetptr="chp-opt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16, Options
and Tunables</olink> for more details on setting options.</para><sect2 id="chp-buf-2.1"><title><literal>switch</literal> Policy</title><para><indexterm><primary><literal>switch</literal> buffer policy</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>principal buffer</primary><secondary>policies</secondary><tertiary><literal>switch</literal></tertiary></indexterm>By default, the
principal buffer has a <literal>switch</literal> buffer policy. Under this
policy, per-CPU buffers are allocated in pairs: one buffer is active and the
other buffer is inactive. When a DTrace consumer attempts to read a buffer,
the kernel firsts <emphasis>switches</emphasis> the inactive and active buffers.
Buffer switching is done in such a manner that there is no window in which
tracing data may be lost. Once the buffers are switched, the newly inactive
buffer is copied out to the DTrace consumer. This policy assures that the
consumer always sees a self-consistent buffer: a buffer is never simultaneously
traced to and copied out. This technique also avoids introducing a window
in which tracing is paused or otherwise prevented. The rate at which the buffer
is switched and read out is controlled by the consumer with the <literal>switchrate</literal> option. As with any rate option, <literal>switchrate</literal> may
be specified with any time suffix, but defaults to rate-per-second. For more
details on <literal>switchrate</literal> and other options, see <olink targetptr="chp-opt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16, Options and Tunables</olink>.</para><note><para>To process the principal buffer at user-level at a rate faster
than the default of once per second, tune the value of <literal>switchrate</literal>.
The system processes actions that induce user-level activity (such as <function>printa</function> and <function>system</function>) when the corresponding record
in the principal buffer is processed. The value of <literal>switchrate</literal> dictates
the rate at which the system processes such actions.</para>
</note><para>Under the <literal>switch</literal> policy, if a given
enabled probe would trace more data than there is space available in the active
principal buffer, the data is <emphasis>dropped</emphasis> and a per-CPU drop
count is incremented. In the event of one or more drops, <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> displays a message similar
to the following example:</para><screen>dtrace: 11 drops on CPU 0</screen><para>If a given record is larger than the total buffer size, the record will
be dropped regardless of buffer policy. You can reduce or eliminate drops
by either increasing the size of the principal buffer with the <literal>bufsize</literal> option
or by increasing the switching rate with the <literal>switchrate</literal> option.</para><para>Under the <literal>switch</literal> policy, scratch space for <function>copyin</function>, <function>copyinstr</function>, and <function>alloca</function> is
allocated out of the active buffer.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="chp-buf-2.2"><title><literal>fill</literal> Policy</title><para><indexterm><primary><literal>fill</literal> buffer policy</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>principal buffer</primary><secondary>policies</secondary><tertiary><literal>fill</literal></tertiary></indexterm>For some problems,
you might wish to use a single in-kernel buffer. While this approach can be
implemented with the <literal>switch</literal> policy and appropriate D constructs
by incrementing a variable in D and predicating an <function>exit</function> action
appropriately, such an implementation does not eliminate the possibility of
drops. To request a single, large in-kernel buffer, and continue tracing until
one or more of the per-CPU buffers has filled, use the <literal>fill</literal> buffer
policy. Under this policy, tracing continues until an enabled probe attempts
to trace more data than can fit in the remaining principal buffer space. When
insufficient space remains, the buffer is marked as filled and the consumer
is notified that at least one of its per-CPU buffers has filled. Once <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> detects a single filled buffer,
tracing is stopped, all buffers are processed and <command>dtrace</command> exits.
No further data will be traced to a filled buffer even if the data would fit
in the buffer.</para><para>To use the <literal>fill</literal> policy, set the <literal>bufpolicy</literal> option
to <literal>fill</literal>. For example, the following command traces every
system call entry into a per-CPU 2K buffer with the buffer policy set to <literal>fill</literal>:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -n syscall:::entry -b 2k -x bufpolicy=fill</userinput></screen><sect3 id="chp-buf-fillandend"><title><literal>fill</literal> Policy and <literal>END</literal> Probes</title><para><indexterm><primary><literal>fill</literal> buffer policy</primary><secondary>and <literal>END</literal> probes</secondary></indexterm><literal>END</literal> probes
normally do not fire until tracing has been explicitly stopped by the DTrace
consumer. <literal>END</literal> probes are guaranteed to only fire on one
CPU, but the CPU on which the probe fires is undefined. With <literal>fill</literal> buffers,
tracing is explicitly stopped when at least one of the per-CPU principal buffers
has been marked as filled. If the <literal>fill</literal> policy is selected,
the <literal>END</literal> probe may fire on a CPU that has a filled buffer.
To accommodate <literal>END</literal> tracing in <literal>fill</literal> buffers,
DTrace calculates the amount of space potentially consumed by <literal>END</literal> probes
and <emphasis>subtracts</emphasis> this space from the size of the principal
buffer. If the net size is negative, DTrace will refuse to start, and <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> will output a corresponding
error message:</para><screen>dtrace: END enablings exceed size of principal buffer</screen><para>The reservation mechanism ensures that a full buffer always has sufficient
space for any <literal>END</literal> probes.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2><sect2 id="chp-buf-2.3"><title><literal>ring</literal> Policy</title><para><indexterm><primary><literal>ring</literal> buffer policy</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>principal buffer</primary><secondary>policies</secondary><tertiary><literal>ring</literal></tertiary></indexterm>The DTrace <literal>ring</literal> buffer
policy helps you trace the events leading up to a failure. If reproducing
the failure takes hours or days, you might wish to keep only the most recent
data. Once a principal buffer has filled, tracing wraps around to the first
entry, thereby overwriting older tracing data. You establish the ring buffer
by setting the <literal>bufpolicy</literal> option to the string <literal>ring</literal>:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -s foo.d -x bufpolicy=ring</userinput></screen><para>When used to create a ring buffer, <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> will not display any output
until the process is terminated. At that time, the ring buffer is consumed
and processed. <command>dtrace</command> processes each ring buffer in CPU
order. Within a CPU's buffer, trace records will be displayed in order from
oldest to youngest. Just as with the <literal>switch</literal> buffering policy,
no ordering exists between records from different CPUs are made. If such an
ordering is required, you should trace the <literal>timestamp</literal> variable
as part of your tracing request.</para><para>The following example demonstrates the use of a <literal>#pragma option</literal> directive
to enable ring buffering:</para><programlisting>#pragma D option bufpolicy=ring
#pragma D option bufsize=16k

syscall:::entry
/execname == $1/
{
	trace(timestamp);
}

syscall::rexit:entry
{
	exit(0);
}</programlisting>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-buf-3"><title>Other Buffers</title><para>Principal buffers exist in every DTrace enabling. Beyond principal buffers,
some DTrace consumers may have additional in-kernel data buffers: an <firstterm>aggregation
buffer</firstterm>, discussed in <olink targetptr="chp-aggs" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;9,
Aggregations</olink>, and one or more <firstterm>speculative buffers</firstterm>,
discussed in <olink targetptr="chp-spec" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Speculative Tracing</olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-buf-4"><title>Buffer Sizes</title><para><indexterm><primary>buffer</primary><secondary>sizes</secondary></indexterm>The size of each buffer can be tuned on a per-consumer basis.
Separate options are provided to tune each buffer size, as shown in the following
table:</para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth=""/><colspec colwidth=""/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Buffer</para>
</entry><entry><para>Size Option</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Principal</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>bufsize</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Speculative</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>specsize</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Aggregation</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>aggsize</literal></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>Each of these options is set with a value that denotes the size. As
with any size option, the value may have an optional size suffix. See <olink targetptr="chp-opt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16, Options and Tunables</olink> for more
details. For example, to set the buffer size to one megabyte on the command
line to <command>dtrace</command>, you can use <option>x</option> to set the
option:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -P syscall -x bufsize=1m</userinput></screen><para>Alternatively, you can use the <option>b</option> option to <command>dtrace</command>:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -P syscall -b 1m</userinput></screen><para>Finally, you could can set <literal>bufsize</literal> using <literal>#pragma
D option</literal>:</para><programlisting>#pragma D option bufsize=1m</programlisting><para>The buffer size you select denotes the size of the buffer on <emphasis>each</emphasis> CPU. Moreover, for the <literal>switch</literal> buffer policy, <literal>bufsize</literal> denotes the size of <emphasis>each</emphasis> buffer on
each CPU. The buffer size defaults to four megabytes.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-buf-5"><title>Buffer Resizing Policy</title><para><indexterm><primary>buffer policy</primary><secondary>on resizing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>buffer</primary><secondary>resizing policy</secondary></indexterm>Occasionally, the system might not have adequate free kernel memory
to allocate a buffer of desired size either because not enough memory is available
or because the DTrace consumer has exceeded one of the tunable limits described
in <olink targetptr="chp-opt" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16, Options and Tunables</olink>.
You can configure the policy for buffer allocation failure using <literal>bufresize</literal> option, which defaults to <literal>auto</literal>. Under the <literal>auto</literal> buffer resize policy, the size of a buffer is halved until
a successful allocation occurs. <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> generates
a message if a buffer as allocated is smaller than the requested size:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -P syscall -b 4g</userinput>
dtrace: description 'syscall' matched 430 probes
dtrace: buffer size lowered to 128m
...</screen><para>or:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -P syscall'{@a[probefunc] = count()}' -x aggsize=1g</userinput>
dtrace: description 'syscall' matched 430 probes
dtrace: aggregation size lowered to 128m
...</screen><para>Alternatively, you can require manual intervention after buffer allocation
failure by setting <literal>bufresize</literal> to <literal>manual</literal>.
Under this policy, a failure to allocate will cause DTrace to fail to start:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -P syscall -x bufsize=1g -x bufresize=manual</userinput>
dtrace: description 'syscall' matched 430 probes
dtrace: could not enable tracing: Not enough space
#</screen><para>The buffer resizing policy of <emphasis>all</emphasis> buffers, principal,
speculative and aggregation, is dictated by the <literal>bufresize</literal> option.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000016053 0?>