<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bull rArr sect?><chapter id="chp-usdt"><title>Statically Defined Tracing for User Applications</title><highlights><para>DTrace provides a facility for user application developers to define
customized probes in application code to augment the capabilities of the <literal>pid</literal> provider. These static probes impose little to no overhead when
disabled and are dynamically enabled like all other DTrace probes. You can
use static probes to describe application semantics to users of DTrace without
exposing or requiring implementation knowledge of your applications. This
chapter describes how to define static probes in user applications and how
to use DTrace to enable such probes in user processes.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="chp-usdt-1"><title>Choosing the Probe Points</title><para><indexterm><primary>probe points</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>embedding probe points</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>statically defined tracking (SDT)</primary><see>SDT</see></indexterm>DTrace allows developers to embed
static probe points in application code, including both complete applications
and shared libraries. These probes can be enabled wherever the application
or library is running, either in development or in production. You should
define probes that have a semantic meaning that is readily understood by your
DTrace user community. For example, you could define <literal>query-receive</literal> and <literal>query-respond</literal> probes for a web server that correspond to a client
submitting a request and the web server responding to that request. These
example probes are easily understood by most DTrace users and correspond to
the highest level abstractions for the application, rather than lower level
implementation details. DTrace users might use these probes to understand
the time distribution of requests. If your <literal>query-receive</literal> probe
presented the <acronym>URL</acronym> request strings as an argument, a DTrace
user could determine which requests were generating the most disk I/O by combining
this probe with the <literal>io</literal> provider.</para><para>You should also consider the stability of the abstractions you describe
when choosing probe names and locations. Will this probe persist in future
releases of the application, even if the implementation changes? Does the
probe make sense on all system architectures or is it specific to a particular
instruction set? This chapter will discuss the details of how these decisions
guide your static tracing definitions.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-usdt-2"><title>Adding Probes to an Application</title><para><indexterm><primary>binary construction with probes</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>constructing a binary</primary></indexterm>DTrace probes for libraries
and executables are defined in an <acronym>ELF</acronym> section in the corresponding
application binary. This section describes how to define your probes, add
them to your application source code, and augment your application's build
process to include the DTrace probe definitions.</para><sect2 id="chp-usdt-3"><title>Defining Providers and Probes</title><para>You define DTrace probes in a <literal>.d</literal> source file which
is then used when compiling and linking your application. First, select an
appropriate name for your user application provider. The provider name you
choose will be appended with the process identifier for each process that
is executing your application code. For example, if you chose the provider
name <literal>myserv</literal> for a web server that was executing as process
ID 1203, the DTrace provider name corresponding to this process would be <literal>myserv1203</literal>. In your <literal>.d</literal> source file, add a provider
definition similar to the following example:</para><programlisting>provider myserv {
	...
};			</programlisting><para>Next, add a definition for each probe and the corresponding arguments.
The following example defines the two probes discussed in <olink targetptr="chp-usdt-1" remap="internal">Choosing the Probe Points</olink>. The first probe
has two arguments, both of type <literal>string</literal>, and the second
probe has no arguments. The D compiler converts two consecutive underscores
(<literal>__</literal>) in any probe name to a hyphen (<literal>-</literal>).</para><programlisting>provider myserv {
	probe query__receive(string, string);
	probe query__respond();
};</programlisting><para>You should add stability attributes to your provider definition so that
consumers of your probes understand the likelihood of change in future versions
of your application. See <olink targetptr="chp-stab" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;39, Stability</olink> for
more information on the DTrace stability attributes. Stability attributes
are defined as shown in the following example:</para><example id="ex-myserv.d"><title><filename>myserv.d</filename>: Statically
Defined Application Probes</title><programlisting>#pragma D attributes Evolving/Evolving/Common provider myserv provider
#pragma D attributes Private/Private/Unknown provider myserv module
#pragma D attributes Private/Private/Unknown provider myserv function
#pragma D attributes Evolving/Evolving/Common provider myserv name
#pragma D attributes Evolving/Evolving/Common provider myserv args

provider myserv {
	probe query__receive(string, string);
	probe query__respond();
};</programlisting>
</example><note><para>D scripts that use non-integer arguments from user added probes
must use the <function>copyin</function> and <function>copyinstr</function> functions
to retrieve those arguments. Please see <olink targetptr="chp-user" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;33,
User Process Tracing</olink> for more information.</para>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="chp-usdt-4"><title>Adding Probes to Application Code</title><para>Now that you have defined your probes in a <literal>.d</literal> file,
you need to augment your source code to indicate the locations that should
trigger your probes. Consider the following example C application source code:</para><programlisting>void
main_look(void)
{
	...
	query = wait_for_new_query();
	process_query(query)
	...
}</programlisting><para>To add a probe site, add a reference to the <literal>DTRACE_PROBE()</literal> macro
defined in <literal>&lt;sys/sdt.h&gt;</literal> as shown in the following example:</para><programlisting>#include &lt;sys/sdt.h&gt;
...

void
main_look(void)
{
	...
	query = wait_for_new_query();
	DTRACE_PROBE2(myserv, query__receive, query-&gt;clientname, query-&gt;msg);
	process_query(query)
	...
}</programlisting><para>The suffix <literal>2</literal> in the macro name <literal>DTRACE_PROBE2</literal> refers
the number of arguments that are passed to the probe. The first two arguments
to the probe macro are the provider name and probe name and must correspond
to your D provider and probe definitions. The remaining macro arguments are
the arguments assigned to the DTrace <literal>arg0..9</literal> variables
when the probes fires. Your application source code can contain
multiple references to the same provider and probe name. If multiple references
to the same probe are present in your source code, any of the macro references
will cause the probe to fire.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="chp-usdt-5"><title>Building Applications with Probes</title><para>You must augment the build process for your application to include the
DTrace provider and probe definitions. A typical build process takes each
source file and compiles it to create a corresponding object file. The compiled
object files are then linked together to create the finished application binary,
as shown in the following example:</para><screen>cc -c src1.c
cc -c src2.c
...
cc -o myserv src1.o src2.o ...</screen><para>To include DTrace probe definitions in your application, add appropriate
Makefile rules to your build process to execute the <command>dtrace</command> command
as shown in the following example:</para><screen>cc -c src1.c
cc -c src2.c
...
dtrace -G -32 -s myserv.d src1.o src2.o ...
cc -o myserv myserv.o src1.o src2.o ...</screen><para>The <literal>dtrace</literal> command shown above post-processes the
object files generated by the preceding compiler commands and generates the
object file <literal>myserv.o</literal> from <literal>myserv.d</literal> and
the other object files. The <command>dtrace</command> <option>G</option> option
is used to link provider and probe definitions with a user application. The <option>32</option> option is used to build 32&ndash;bit application binaries. The <option>64</option> option is used to build 64&ndash;bit application binaries.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000008948 0?>