<preface id="eyprf"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>This book describes how to use CD or DVD media to install the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Operating System (Solaris OS) on a nonnetworked system.</para><para>This book does not include instructions about how to set up system hardware
or other peripherals.</para>&platformnote.sgm;
</highlights><sect1 id="eyprg"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is intended for system administrators who are responsible
for installing the Solaris OS. This book provides basic Solaris installation
information for system administrators who perform infrequent Solaris installations
or upgrades.</para><para>If you need advanced Solaris installation information, see <olink type="auto-generated" targetptr="preface-5" remap="internal">Related Books</olink> to find
the book that describes the information.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-5"><title>Related Books</title><para><olink targetptr="preface-tbl-3" remap="internal">Table P&ndash;1</olink> lists related
information that you need when you install the Solaris software.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1" id="preface-tbl-3"><title>Related Information</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="160*"/><colspec colname="column3" colwidth="191*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Information</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Guides you through planning the installation or upgrade of the Solaris
operating system. This book provides overviews of all the Solaris installation
programs. This book also provides overviews of the following features as they
relate to installation:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>GRUB, the open-source boot loader</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Solaris Zones partitioning technology</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>RAID-1 volumes that can be created at installation time</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry rowsep="1"><para><olink targetdoc="soldevelinstall" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express, Developer Edition Installation Guide: Laptop Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Describes how to install the Solaris Express, Developer Edition on an
x86 laptop. The Solaris Express, Developer Edition provides a quick initial
installation of the Solaris Operating System (OS) for x86 based systems. This
release includes the tools, technologies, and platforms to create Solaris, <trademark>Java</trademark>, and Web 2.0 applications.</para><note><para>The 2/07 release of the new Solaris Express, Developer Edition
is only  for x86 platforms. However, developers on SPARC systems can obtain
similar  functionality by downloading Solaris Express, Community Edition and
then installing Sun Studio and NetBeans IDE 5.5 with NetBeans Enterprise Pack
5.5.</para><itemizedlist><para>Downloads are available at the following Web sites:</para><listitem><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/downloads" type="text_url">Solaris Express, Community Edition</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://developers.sun.com/sunstudio/downloads" type="text_url">Sun Studio 11</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.netbeans.info/downloads/index.php" type="text_url">NetBeans IDE 5.5</ulink> with NetBeans Enterprise Pack 5.5.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</note>
</entry>
</row><row><entry rowsep="1"><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Describes how to perform a remote Solaris installation over a local
area network or a wide area network.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry rowsep="1"><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Describes how to  use Solaris Live Upgrade to create and upgrade new
boot environments.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry rowsep="1"><para><olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Describes how to create the files and directories necessary to perform
an unattended custom <trademark>JumpStart</trademark> installation.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry rowsep="1"><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallflash" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Provides instructions for creating Solaris Flash archives and using
Solaris Flash archives to install the Solaris OS on multiple systems.</para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry><para><olink targetdoc="sagdfs" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Devices and File Systems</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Describes how to back up system files and other system administration
tasks.</para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry><para><olink targetdoc="expressrelnt" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Release Notes</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Describes any bugs, known problems, software that is being discontinued,
and patches that are related to the Solaris release.</para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>SPARC: <citetitle>Solaris Sun Hardware Platform Guide</citetitle> on <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com" type="url"></ulink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Contains information about supported hardware.</para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry><para><olink targetdoc="installpkglist" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Package List</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Lists and describes the packages in the Solaris Express OS.</para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>x86: <ulink remap="" url="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl" type="text">Solaris
Hardware Compatibility List</ulink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Contains supported hardware information and device configuration details.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;<sect1 id="eyprj"><title>Platform Conventions</title><para>The following keyboard and mouse conventions are applicable to SPARC
and x86 based systems:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The key referred to as Return is labeled Enter on some keyboards.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>From left to right on a three-button mouse, the default settings
for CDE are SELECT, ADJUST, and MENU. For example, the text says, &ldquo;Click
SELECT&rdquo;  instead of  &ldquo;Click the left mouse button.&rdquo;  Otherwise,
these keys are referred to as mouse button 1, mouse button 2, and mouse button
3.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>From left to right on a two-button mouse, the default settings
are SELECT and MENU. The ADJUST function is obtained by simultaneously pressing
SELECT and the Shift key on the keyboard (Shift-SELECT).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</preface>