<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()?><preface id="preface-1"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>The <citetitle>Solaris Trusted Extensions Developer's Guide</citetitle> describes how to use the application programming interfaces (APIs) to write new trusted applications for systems that are configured with the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Trusted Extensions software. Readers must be familiar with <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> programming and understand security policy concepts.</para>&platformnote;<para>Note that the example programs in this book focus on the APIs being shown and do not perform error checking. Your applications should perform the appropriate error checking.</para>
</highlights>&tsset;<sect1 id="preface-3"><title>How This Book Is Organized</title><para><olink targetptr="api-intro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1, Solaris Trusted Extensions APIs and Security Policy</olink> provides an overview of the Solaris Trusted Extensions APIs and describes how the security policy is enforced within the system.</para><para><olink targetptr="labelapi-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Labels and Clearances</olink> describes the data types and the APIs for managing labels on processes and on device objects. This chapter also describes clearances, how a process acquires a sensitivity label, and when label operations require privileges. Guidelines for handling labels are also provided.</para><para><olink targetptr="labelcode-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Label Code Examples</olink> provides sample code that uses the APIs for labels.</para><para><olink targetptr="labelprint-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Printing and the Label APIs</olink> uses the Trusted Extensions multilevel printing service as an example of using the label APIs.</para><para><olink targetptr="ipcapi-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Interprocess Communications</olink> provides an overview of how the security policy is applied to process-to-process communications within the same workstation and across the network.</para><para><olink targetptr="windowapi-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Trusted X Window System</olink> describes the data types and the APIs that enable administrative applications to access and modify security-related X Window System information. This chapter has a section of code examples.</para><para><olink targetptr="lbuilder-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;7, Label Builder APIs</olink> describes the data types and the APIs for creating a graphical user interface (GUI) for building labels and clearances. This chapter has a section of code examples.</para><para><olink targetptr="webguard" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;8, Trusted Web Guard Prototype</olink> provides an example of a safe web browsing prototype that isolates a web server and its web content from an Internet attack.</para><para><olink targetptr="javatxlabelapis" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;9, Experimental Java Bindings for the Solaris Trusted Extensions Label APIs</olink> describes an experimental set of <trademark>Java</trademark> classes and methods that mirror the label APIs that are provided with the Solaris Trusted Extensions software. This chapter also includes a pointer to the source code and build instructions, so you can use these APIs to create label-aware applications.</para><para><olink targetptr="appa-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;A, Programmer's Reference</olink> provides information about Solaris Trusted Extensions man pages, shared libraries, header files, and abbreviations used in data type names and in interface names. This appendix also provides information about preparing an application for release.</para><para><olink targetptr="appb-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;B, Solaris Trusted Extensions API Reference</olink> provides programming interface listings, including parameter and return value declarations.</para>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>