<!-- 
The contents of this Documentation are subject to the Public Documentation
License Version 1.01 (the "License"); you may only use this Documentation if
you comply with the terms of this License. A copy of the License is
available at http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/documentation/license.
-->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"??><glossary id="glossary-1"><title>Installation and Image Packaging System Glossary</title><glossentry><glossterm>action</glossterm><glossdef><para>A name and a key attribute of a package. A package is a collection
of files, directories, links, drivers, and dependencies in a defined format.
This collection represents the installable objects of a package. This collection
is referred to as an action.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>attribute</glossterm><glossdef><para>A representation of the settings of a package or an action.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>publisher</glossterm><glossdef><para>A forward domain name such as <literal>opensolaris.org</literal> or a reverse domain name such as <literal>org.opensolaris</literal> that
can be used to identify a person, group of persons, or an organization as
the source of one or more packages. The developer-quality packages managed
by Sun and made available through the OpenSolaris repositories such as <ulink url="http://pkg.opensolaris.com" type="text">http://pkg.opensolaris.com/release</ulink> are an example of a publisher.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><command>beadm</command> utility</glossterm><glossdef><para>The user interface for managing boot environments in OpenSolaris
software.  The <command>beadm</command> command is the replacement for the
Solaris Live Upgrade  commands, for example, <command>luupgrade</command>(1M)
and  <command>lucreate</command>(1M). </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>boot environment (BE)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An instance of a bootable OpenSolaris environment consisting
of a set of mount points, file systems, ZFS datasets, and possibly non-global
zones. A boot environment is a collection of mandatory file systems that are
critical to the operation of the Solaris OS. The active boot environment is
the one that is currently booted. Exactly one active boot environment can
be booted. An inactive boot environment is not currently booted, but can be
in a state of waiting for activation on the next reboot. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>catalog</glossterm><glossdef><para>All packages in a repository published by a publisher. The
packages in a catalog are associated with a specific publisher.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>clone</glossterm><glossdef><para>An exact copy. A clone could be an exact copy of an operating
system, a file system, or a volume. This copy has 100 percent compatibility
with the original. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>dataset</glossterm><glossdef><para>A generic name for the following ZFS entities: clones, file
systems, snapshots, or volumes. Each dataset is identified by a unique name
in the ZFS namespace.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Fault Management Resource Identifier (FMRI)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An identifier in a package. Includes descriptive information
about a package, such as the package name, version information, date, and
publisher. The <command>pkg</command> command uses these identifiers when
performing actions on the package. For more information, see <olink type="auto-generated" targetptr="fmri" remap="internal">FMRI</olink> .</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>image</glossterm><glossdef><orderedlist><listitem><para>An image is a location on your system where packages and their
associated files, directories, links, and dependencies can be installed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A collection of software in a package that comprises an entire
operating system. The package is suitable for installation. See ISO image,
network installation image.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>ISO image</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of software that comprises an entire operating
system in a single file.  The ISO image can be made available for distribution
from the Internet. An ISO image contains file systems suitable for creating
a bootable CD or DVD. The ISO image is bootable and is usable for installation
and other purposes.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>mirror</glossterm><glossdef><orderedlist><listitem><para>In IPS, an identical copy of data in a repository.  A repository
can be copied and the data resynchronized to maintain identical repositories
in separate locations.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>In ZFS, a virtual device that stores identical copies of data
on two or more disks. If any disk in a mirror fails, any other disk in that
mirror can provide the same data.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>network installation image</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of software that comprises the entire operating
system. The image can be installed over a local area network (LAN).</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>origin repository</glossterm><glossdef><para>The original repository where the package was first published.
The <command>pkg</command>(5) clients always access the origin repository
to obtain a publisher's catalog, even though the clients might download package
content from a mirror repository.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>package</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of files, directories, links, drivers, and dependencies
in a defined format.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>pool</glossterm><glossdef><para>A logical group of devices describing the layout and physical
characteristics of the available storage. Space for datasets is allocated
from a pool.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>preferred repository</glossterm><glossdef><para>A default repository that is the source for packages.  If
a user does not explicitly specify a repository when installing  and updating
packages, the preferred publisher is chosen as the  source for packages.  </para><para>During the creation of an image, the initially specified publisher 
is marked as the preferred publisher. Any one of the publishers associated
with an image might be set as the preferred publisher by using the <command>set-publisher</command> command with the <option>P</option> option.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>relocatable package</glossterm><glossdef><para>A package that enables a user to specify the installation
path of the package.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>repository</glossterm><glossdef><para>A location where clients can publish and retrieve package
content such as files contained within the package, and package metadata which
includes information about the package such as its name, description, and
so on.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>depot</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of one or more package repositories usually served
by pkg.depotd(1m).</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>rollback</glossterm><glossdef><para>A reversion to the boot environment that ran prior to a specific
transaction. Use rollback when you are activating an environment and the boot
environment that is designated for booting fails or shows some undesirable
behavior. Rollback is known as fallback in Solaris Live Upgrade.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>snapshot</glossterm><glossdef><para>A read-only image of a file system or boot environment at
a given point in time. A snapshot is not bootable.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>tag</glossterm><glossdef><para>In IPS, a representation of the settings of a file.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>upgrade</glossterm><glossdef><para>An installation that merges files with existing files and
preserves modifications where possible. </para><para>An upgrade of the OpenSolaris
OS merges the new version of the OpenSolaris OS with the existing files on
the system's disk or disks. An upgrade saves as many modifications as possible
that you have made to the previous version of the OS.</para><para>The OpenSolaris
release use the <command>pkg image-update</command> command to upgrade all
installed packages in the current image to the latest available version.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>USB image</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of software that comprises an entire operating
system in a single file. The  image that can be copied to a USB flash drive.
The <command>usbcopy</command> utility is the only method of copying and 
is available on the OpenSolaris operating system. The USB image is a bootable
image and is usable for installation and other purposes. <emphasis role="strong">Note</emphasis>: The Distribution Constructor provides a USB image output
that might work in other types of flash memory devices, but due to lack of
driver support in Open Solaris, other devices are unlikely to work.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>ZFS file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A ZFS dataset of type <literal>filesystem</literal>, that
is mounted within the standard system namespace and behaves like other file
systems.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary>