<chapter id="nsov-1"><title>Network Service
(Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides a list of the major topics covered in this book.
In addition it includes a description of the PERL service that is included
in this release.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="nsov-6" remap="internal">Topics for the Solaris 10 Release</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="nsov-8" remap="internal">Perl 5</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="nsov-6"><title>Topics for the Solaris 10 Release</title><para>The following services or utilities are covered in this book:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="nsov-8" remap="internal">Perl 5</olink></term><listitem><para>The Practical Extraction and Report Language (Perl) is a tool
that can be used to generate scripts to assist with system administration
tasks.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="nca-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Managing Web
Cache Servers</olink></term><listitem><para>NCA provides improved web server performance by caching web
pages.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="time-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Time-Related
Services</olink></term><listitem><para>NTP and time-related utilities can be used to synchronize
time for many systems.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="rfsintro-2" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Managing
Network File Systems (Overview)</olink></term><listitem><para>NFS is a protocol that provides the ability to access file
systems from a remote host.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="slparch-16" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;7, SLP (Overview)</olink></term><listitem><para>SLP is a dynamic service discovery protocol.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="mailintro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;12, Mail Services
(Overview)</olink></term><listitem><para>Mail services allow for a message to be sent to one or more
people while routing the message over whatever networks are necessary.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="pppsvrconfig.intro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;15,
Solaris PPP 4.0 (Overview)</olink></term><listitem><para>PPP is a protocol that provides point-to-point links between
remote hosts.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="uucpov-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;24, UUCP (Overview)</olink></term><listitem><para>UUCP enables hosts to exchange files</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><olink targetptr="wwrsov" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;27, Working With
Remote Systems (Overview)</olink></term><listitem><para>These commands are used to access files on remote systems.
The commands include <command>ftp</command>, <command>rlogin</command> and <command>rcp</command>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1><sect1 id="nsov-8"><title>Perl 5</title><para>This Solaris release includes Practical Extraction and Report Language
(Perl) 5.8.4, a powerful general-purpose programming language that is generally
available as free software. Perl has emerged as the standard development tool
for complex system administration task because of its excellent process, file,
and text manipulation features.</para><para>Perl 5 includes a dynamically loadable module framework, which allows
the addition of new capabilities for specific tasks. Many modules are freely
available from the Comprehensive Perl Archive Network (CPAN) at <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org" type="text">http://www.cpan.org</ulink>. If you
wish to build and install add-on modules from CPAN       using <command>gcc</command>,
you can do so using the <filename>/usr/perl5/5.8.4/bin/perlgcc</filename> script.
See the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>perlgcc</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page for details.</para><sect2 id="nsov-9"><title>Accessing Perl Documentation</title><para>Several sources of information about Perl are included in this Solaris
release. The same information is available by using these two mechanisms.</para><para>You can access the man pages by adding <filename>/usr/perl5/man</filename> to
your MANPATH environment variable. This example displays the Perl overview.</para><screen>% <userinput>setenv MANPATH ${MANPATH}:/usr/perl5/man</userinput>
% <userinput>man perl</userinput></screen><para>You can access additional documentation by using the <command>perldoc</command> utility.
This example displays the same overview information.</para><screen>% <userinput>/usr/perl5/bin/perldoc perl</userinput></screen><para>The <filename>perl</filename> overview page lists of all the documentation
that is included with the release.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="nsov-10"><title>Perl Compatibility Issues</title><para>In general, the 5.8.4 version of Perl is compatible with the previous
version. Scripts do not have to be rebuilt or recompiled to function. However,
any XSUB-based (.xs) modules require recompilation and reinstallation.</para><para>In the Solaris 10 release, you can access the older version of Perl
as <command>/usr/perl5/5.6.1/bin/perl</command>. The older version might not
be supported in future releases and this version should only be used until
the new modules are rebuilt.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="nsov-11"><title>Changes to the Solaris Version of Perl</title><para>The Solaris version of Perl was compiled to include system malloc, 64-bit
integer and large file support. In addition, appropriate patches have been
applied. For a full list of all configuration information, review the results
from this command.</para><screen>% <userinput>/usr/perl5/bin/perlbug -dv</userinput>
---
Flags:
    category=
    severity=
---
Site configuration information for perl v5.8.4:
 .
 .</screen><para>You can generate a shorter list by using <command>perl</command> <option>V</option>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>