<chapter xml:id="smbservertasks"><title>illumos SMB Service Administration (Tasks)</title><para>This chapter provides instructions on how to configure the illumos SMB service to run as a standalone server (workgroup mode) or in an existing Windows environment (domain mode). This chapter also describes how to manage SMB shares to be accessed by SMB clients.</para><itemizedlist><para>This chapter covers the following topics:</para>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="configuringservicestm"/></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><xref linkend="configuringoperationmodetm"/></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><xref linkend="managingsmbsharestm"/></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><xref linkend="managingsmbgroupsuserstm"/></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><xref linkend="migratingfromsamba"/></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For a high-level overview of the illumos SMB service configuration process, see <xref linkend="processoverview"/>.</para>
<para>Many of the tasks in this section require that you:</para>
<blockquote>&rolestepsmb;</blockquote>
<para>&roleinfo;</para>
<sect1 xml:id="configuringservicestm"><title>Configuring the SMB Service</title><para>This section provides information about configuring the illumos SMB service. Depending on the "operation mode" you plan to use ("domain mode" or "workgroup mode") there are different configuration requirements.
For information about configuring other applicable services, see <xref linkend="processoverview"/>.</para>

<step><para>If the Samba service is running on the illumos system, you must disable it. Only one SMB service may run in a given zone. See <xref linkend="disablesambatask"/>.</para></step>

<step><para>Enable the illumos SMB service.</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable -r smb/server</userinput></screen><para>This command enables the illumos SMB service and any service on which it depends, such as the <command>idmap</command> service.</para></step>

<step><para>Edit the <filename>/etc/pam.conf</filename> file to support creation of an encrypted version of local user passwords for SMB.</para><para>Add the following line after the other "password" lines:</para><screen>other	password required	pam_smb_passwd.so.1	nowarn</screen><para>See the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam_smb_passwd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page.</para>
</step>
<step><para>Set the password for any local users who will connect via SMB.</para>
<screen># <userinput>passwd <replaceable>username</replaceable></userinput></screen>
<para>The illumos SMB service cannot use the Unix version of the local user's encrypted password for authentication. Therefore, you must generate an SMB version of the local user's password for the SMB service to use. When the SMB PAM module is installed, the <command>passwd</command> command generates such an encrypted version of the password.</para>
</step>

</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="configuringoperationmodetm"><title>Joining a Domain or Workgroup (Task Map)</title><para>The following table points to the tasks that you can use to configure the operation mode of the illumos SMB server.</para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Configure the illumos SMB service in domain mode.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the <command>smbadm join -u <replaceable>username</replaceable> <replaceable>domain-name</replaceable></command> command to join the domain.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="configuredomainmodetask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Configure the illumos SMB service in workgroup mode.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the <command>smbadm join -w <replaceable>workgroup-name</replaceable></command> command to join the workgroup.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="configureworkgroupmodetask"/></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<sect2 xml:id="configuredomainmodetask"><title>How to Configure the illumos SMB Service in Domain Mode</title>
<task><tasksummary><para>This section describes how to join a domain.
An Active Directory (AD) environment is required for this task.</para>
</tasksummary><taskprerequisites><para>The <firstterm>Active Directory (AD)</firstterm> service is a Windows namespace that is integrated with the Domain Name Service (DNS). AD runs only on domain controllers. In addition to storing and making data available, AD protects network objects from unauthorized access and replicates objects across a network so that data is not lost if one domain controller fails.</para><para>For the illumos SMB service to integrate seamlessly into a Windows AD environment, the following must exist on the network:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>A Windows AD domain controller</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An optional Active Directory DNS server that permits dynamic updates to use the dynamic DNS (DDNS) capability</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>In order to participate in an AD domain, the system must be configured to use DNS for host lookup. Ensure that the <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename> and <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> files are configured correctly for the appropriate AD domain.</para>
</taskprerequisites><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>To successfully complete the join process, ensure that the system clock on the illumos system is within five minutes of the system clock of the domain controller (DC).</para><para>You can accomplish this task in one of these ways:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>Manually adjust the system clock on either the illumos system or the DC to match the other.</para>
</step><step><para>Configure both the illumos system and the DC to use the same time source (NTP server).</para>
</step><step><para>Synchronize the system clock on the illumos system with the system clock of the DC by running the following command on the illumos system:</para><screen># <userinput>ntpdate <replaceable>DC-hostname</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>For example, to synchronize with the DC called <literal>dc.westsales.example.com</literal>, type:</para><screen># <userinput>ntpdate dc.westsales.example.com</userinput></screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Join the Windows domain.</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm join -u <replaceable>username</replaceable> <replaceable>domain-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is an AD user with sufficient rights to create and/or update the machine account.
The <replaceable>domain-name</replaceable> is a fully qualified domain name of the AD domain in which this server will become a member.</para>
<!-- Need to document the -c container option, here and smbadm(8) -->
</step>
</procedure><example xml:id="configuredomainmodeexample"><title>Configuring the illumos SMB Service in Domain Mode</title><para>This example shows the steps taken to configure the illumos SMB service in domain mode. User <literal>dana</literal> has Domain Administrator privileges. The name of the domain being joined is <literal>westsales.example.com</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable -r smb/server</userinput>
# <userinput>smbadm join -u dana westsales.example.com</userinput>
Enter domain password:
Joining 'westsales.example.com' ... this may take a minute ...
Successfully joined domain 'westsales.example.com'</screen>
</example>
<para>After successfully joining an AD domain, you can enable the illumos SMB service to publish SMB shares in the AD directory. To do so, create or update SMB shares and specify the share container for each share that you want to publish. To create SMB shares, see <xref linkend="createstaticsmbsharezfstask"/> and <xref linkend="createstaticsmbsharetask"/>.</para>
<note><para>Note that many old copies of this document that can be found via web searches, and most of those instruct you to edit the <filename>krb5.conf</filename> file as part of joining a domain.  The illumos SMB server no longer needs that customization after
<link xl:href="http://illumos.org/issues/6352">illumos issue 6352</link>
was resolved in late 2015.</para></note>
</task>
</sect2>
<sect2 xml:id="configureworkgroupmodetask"><title>How to Configure the illumos SMB Service in Workgroup Mode</title> 
<task><tasksummary>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>(Optional) Change the illumos SMB service to operate in a different workgroup.</para><para>By default, the illumos SMB service operates in a workgroup called <literal>WORKGROUP</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm join -w <replaceable>workgroup-name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure><example xml:id="configureworkgroupmodeexample"><title>Configuring the illumos SMB Service in Workgroup Mode</title><para>This example shows how to configure the illumos SMB service in workgroup mode. The name of the workgroup being joined is <literal>myworkgroup</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable -r smb/server</userinput>
# <userinput>smbadm join -w myworkgroup</userinput></screen><para>Then, use the <literal>sharesmb</literal> property to configure SMB sharing for an existing ZFS dataset called <literal>ztank/myfs</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>zfs set sharesmb=on ztank/myfs</userinput></screen><para>Finally, generate the SMB password for user <literal>cal</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>passwd cal</userinput></screen><para>Now, you are ready to have SMB clients access the SMB shares on your illumos SMB service.</para>
</example>
</task>
<para>After you join a workgroup, you can access SMB shares. To create SMB shares, see <xref linkend="createstaticsmbsharezfstask"/> and <xref linkend="createstaticsmbsharetask"/>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managingsmbsharestm"><title>Managing SMB Shares (Task Map)</title><para>You can add, view, and update SMB shares. A directory must exist before it can be shared. For more information about SMB shares, see <xref linkend="smbshares"/>.</para><para>The following table points to the tasks that you can use to manage SMB shares.</para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Configure cross-protocol locking.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the <command>mount</command> or the <command>zfs create</command> command to configure cross-protocol locking. These commands enable this locking by setting the <literal>nbmand</literal> option.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="configurecrossprotocollockingtask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Create an SMB share by using the ZFS <literal>sharesmb</literal> property.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use this procedure if you want to make a file or directory available to clients. You might use this procedure if you are familiar with the ZFS <literal>sharenfs</literal> property.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="createstaticsmbsharezfstask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Create an SMB share by using the <command>sharemgr</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use this procedure if you want to make a file or directory available to clients. If you specify an AD container, <command>sharemgr</command> will attempt to publish those shares in AD.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="createstaticsmbsharetask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Modify the properties of an SMB share by using the <command>sharemgr</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use this procedure to change share property values.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="modifysmbsharetask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Remove an SMB share by using the <command>sharemgr</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para>When you remove a share, it can no longer be accessed by a system. If you are connected to the share when it is removed, the share is not removed until there are no more connections to that share. At that time, the share is removed.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="removesmbsharetask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Create an autohome share rule.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Specify custom share rules for autohome shares.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="createspecificautohomeshareruletask"/></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><task xml:id="configurecrossprotocollockingtask"><title>How to Configure Cross-Protocol Locking</title><tasksummary><para>The SMB protocol assumes mandatory locking, but UNIX traditionally uses advisory locking. The illumos OS can be configured to use mandatory locking on a per mount basis by using the non-blocking mandatory locking (<literal>nbmand</literal>) mount option.</para><para>When set, the <literal>nbmand</literal> mount option enforces mandatory cross-protocol share reservations and byte-range locking.</para><para>When the <literal>nbmand</literal> mount option is not set, the illumos SMB service will enforce mandatory share reservations and byte-range locking internally for all SMB clients. However, without <literal>nbmand</literal> set, there is only limited coordination with NFS and local processes.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestep;<step><para>Set the <literal>nbmand</literal> mount option for an existing file system by doing one of the following:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>Set the option by using the <command>mount</command> command.</para><screen># <userinput>mount -o nbmand=on <replaceable>fsname</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>For example, the following command sets the <literal>nbmand</literal> mount option for the <filename>ztank/myfs</filename> file system:</para><screen># <userinput>mount -o nbmand ztank/myfs</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Set the option by using the <command>zfs create</command> command.</para><para>When using ZFS, you can also set the <literal>nbmand</literal> option when the file system is created, so that the file system uses <literal>nbmand</literal> automatically:</para><screen># <userinput>zfs create -o nbmand=on <replaceable>fsname</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>The following example combines the <literal>nbmand</literal> option with the mixed-case sensitivity option:</para><screen># <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on -o mountpoint=mntpt ztank/myfs</userinput></screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="createstaticsmbsharezfstask"><title>How to Create an SMB Share (<command>zfs</command>)</title><tasksummary><para>This procedure describes how to use the ZFS <literal>sharesmb</literal> property to create shares on the illumos SMB service.</para><para>To create an autohome share, you must have defined autohome rules. For more information, see <xref linkend="createspecificautohomeshareruletask"/>.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Create a ZFS pool and a mixed-case ZFS file system that supports cross-protocol locking.</para><screen># <userinput>zpool create <replaceable>pool-name</replaceable> <replaceable>vdev</replaceable></userinput>
# <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on <replaceable>fsname</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Enable SMB sharing for the ZFS file system.</para><screen># <userinput>zfs set sharesmb=on <replaceable>fsname</replaceable></userinput></screen><note><para>The resource name for the share is automatically constructed by the <command>zfs</command> command when the share is created. The resource name is based on the dataset name, unless you specify a resource name. Any characters that are illegal for resource names are replaced by an underscore character (<literal>_</literal>).</para>
</note><para>To specify a resource name for the share, specify a name for the <literal>sharesmb</literal> property, <command>sharesmb=name=</command><replaceable>resource-name</replaceable>.</para>
</step><step><para>Verify how the file system is shared.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr show -vp</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure><example xml:id="zfssharesmbexample"><title>Using <literal>sharesmb</literal> to Manage SMB Shares</title><itemizedlist><para>The following examples use the <literal>sharesmb</literal> property to enable SMB sharing for ZFS pools and file systems.</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Inherited SMB sharing for ZFS file systems in a pool.</emphasis> The following commands create a pool and enable SMB sharing for that pool. When you create the ZFS file systems in that pool, the file systems inherit the SMB sharing as well as the resource name.</para><screen># <userinput>zpool create sandbox c0t3d0</userinput>
# <userinput>zfs set sharesmb=on sandbox</userinput>
# <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on sandbox/fs1</userinput>
# <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on sandbox/fs2</userinput></screen><para>The <command>sharemgr show -vp</command> command shows how the top level file system has a resource name of <filename>sandbox</filename>, but the children have the dataset name added to the resource name.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr show -vp</userinput>
default nfs=()
mygroup smb=()
zfs nfs=() smb=()
     zfs/sandbox smb=()
           sandbox=/sandbox
           sandbox_fs1=/sandbox/fs1       smb=()
           sandbox_fs2=/sandbox/fs2       smb=()</screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">SMB sharing for a ZFS file system.</emphasis> The following commands create a ZFS pool and a mixed-case file system that supports cross-protocol locking:</para><screen># <userinput>zpool create sandbox c0t3d0</userinput>
# <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on sandbox/fs1</userinput></screen><para>Next, you can enable SMB sharing for the <filename>sandbox/fs1</filename> file system and for any of its children by setting the <literal>sharesmb</literal> property to <literal>on</literal>.</para><screen># <userinput>zfs set sharesmb=on sandbox/fs1</userinput></screen><para>Because SMB shares must have a resource name, ZFS constructs a resource name from the dataset name. Any characters in the dataset name that are illegal in resource names are replaced by the underscore character (<literal>_</literal>). In this example, the resource name <filename>sandbox_fs1</filename> is based on the dataset name <filename>sandbox/fs1</filename>.</para><para>You can use the <command>sharemgr show -vp</command> command to verify how the file system is shared.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr show -vp</userinput>
default nfs=()
mygroup smb=()
zfs nfs=() smb=()
     zfs/sandbox/fs1 smb=()
           sandbox_fs1=/sandbox/fs1</screen><para>The following commands create another file system in the <filename>sandbox</filename> pool called <filename>fs2</filename> and associate that file system with the <filename>myshare</filename> resource name:</para><screen># <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on sandbox/fs2</userinput>
# <userinput>zfs set sharesmb=name=myshare sandbox/fs2</userinput></screen><para>Use the <command>sharemgr show -vp</command> command to verify how the file systems are shared.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr show -vp</userinput>
default nfs=()
mygroup smb=()
zfs nfs=() smb=()
     zfs/sandbox/fs1 smb=()
           sandbox_fs1=/sandbox/fs1
     zfs/sandbox/fs2 smb=()
           myshare=/sandbox/fs2</screen><para>The following command creates a sub file system of <filename>sandbox/fs2</filename> called <filename>sandbox/fs2/fs2_sub1</filename>:</para><screen># <userinput>zfs create -o casesensitivity=mixed -o nbmand=on sandbox/fs2/fs2_sub1</userinput></screen><para>This new file system inherits part of its resource name from its parent and also inherits sharing over SMB, if enabled. Because the resource name for <filename>sandbox/fs2</filename> is <filename>myshare</filename>, the resource name for <filename>sandbox/fs2/fs2_sub1</filename> is <filename>myshare_fs2_sub1</filename>.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr show -vp</userinput>
default nfs=()
mygroup smb=()
zfs nfs=() smb=()
     zfs/sandbox/fs1 smb=()
           sandbox_fs1=/sandbox/fs1
     zfs/sandbox/fs2 smb=()
           myshare=/sandbox/fs2
           myshare_fs2_sub1=/sandbox/fs2/fs2_sub1</screen><para>If you disable SMB sharing for <filename>sandbox/fs2</filename>, that file system and its children are affected.</para><screen># <userinput>zfs set sharesmb=off sandbox/fs2</userinput>
# <userinput>sharemgr show -vp</userinput>
default nfs=()
mygroup smb=()
zfs nfs=() smb=()
     zfs/sandbox/fs1 smb=()
           sandbox_fs1=/sandbox/fs1</screen><para>The <command>sharemgr show -vp</command> output shows that the <filename>sandbox/fs2</filename> file system and its children are no longer shared over SMB.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</example>
</task><task xml:id="createstaticsmbsharetask"><title>How to Create an SMB Share (<command>sharemgr</command>)</title><tasksummary><para>This procedure describes how to create a share definition on the illumos SMB service and make the share available to clients.</para><para>To create an autohome share, you must have defined autohome rules. For more information, see <xref linkend="createspecificautohomeshareruletask"/>.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Define a share in the default share group or in another share group.</para><para>A share name can include any alphanumeric characters, but not the characters listed here:</para><screen>" / \ [ ] : | + ; , ? * =</screen><para>Create a share group and add a share to that group.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr create -P smb <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput>
# <userinput>sharemgr add-share -r <replaceable>resource-name</replaceable> -s <replaceable>share-path</replaceable> <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>If AD is enabled, specify the AD container where the share will be published.</para><note><para>The container must already exist for the share to be published in that container. The system does not create container objects in the AD <firstterm>tree</firstterm>.</para>
</note><screen># <userinput>sharemgr set [-hnv] -P smb [-S <replaceable>option-set</replaceable>] [-p <replaceable>property</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable> &hellip; \
[-s <replaceable>share-path</replaceable>] <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="modifysmbsharetask"><title>How to Modify SMB Share Properties (<command>sharemgr</command>)</title><tasksummary><para>Use this procedure to change properties on a share.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Modify the SMB share properties.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>Modify properties for a single share.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr set-share [-r <replaceable>resource-name</replaceable>] [-d "<replaceable>description</replaceable>"] -s <replaceable>share-path</replaceable> <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>For example, the following command changes the description for the <filename>/files/acme.sales.logs</filename> share in the <literal>nw-sales</literal> group:</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr set-share -d "Sales logs for Acme" -s /files/acme.sales.logs nw-sales</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Modify properties for a share group.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr set [-hnv] -P smb [-S <replaceable>option-set</replaceable>] [-p <replaceable>property</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable>] &hellip; \
[-s <replaceable>share-path</replaceable>] <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>For example, in domain mode you can configure shares to be published in an AD container. The following command specifies that shares in the <literal>nw-sales</literal> share group will be published in the default container. Note that <literal>filesvr</literal> is the machine account of the system that is running the illumos SMB service.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr set -P smb -p ad-container=cn=filesvr,cn=Computers nw-sales</userinput></screen><para>If you want to publish shares to a non-default container, you must modify the ACLs of that container to give the illumos SMB service permission to publish and unpublish shares.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="removesmbsharetask"><title>How to Remove an SMB Share (<command>sharemgr</command>)</title><tasksummary><para>This procedure describes how to remove an SMB share. When you remove an SMB share, the definition of the share is removed from the server. You can re-create such a share with the <command>sharemgr add-share</command> command.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Remove an SMB share.</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr remove-share -s <replaceable>share-path</replaceable> <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>For example, to remove share <filename>/sales/share1</filename> from share group <filename>mysharegroup</filename>, type:</para><screen># <userinput>sharemgr remove-share -s /sales/share1 mysharegroup</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="createspecificautohomeshareruletask"><title>How to Create a Specific Autohome Share Rule</title><tasksummary><para>The autohome share feature eliminates the administrative task of defining and maintaining home directory shares for each user that accesses the system through the SMB protocol. The system creates autohome shares when a user logs in, and removes them when the user logs out. This procedure describes how to configure autohome shares by adding rules to a configuration file.</para><para>For information about the <filename>smbautohome</filename> format, see <xref linkend="autohomeentries"/> and the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbautohome</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Edit the <filename>/etc/smbautohome</filename> file.</para><para>An autohome entry must be on a single line in the following format:</para><programlisting><replaceable>key</replaceable>	<replaceable>location</replaceable>	[<replaceable>container</replaceable>]</programlisting><substeps><step><para>Specify the user name in the key field.</para><itemizedlist><para>Usually this field is a user name, but it can also be one of the following:</para><listitem><para><literal>+nsswitch</literal> <emphasis role="strong">&ndash;</emphasis> Uses the naming service to match users to home directories if no rule matches.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Asterisk (*) &ndash;</emphasis> Matches a user name to a home directory that uses the same name.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para>Specify the location of the user's home directory in the location field.</para><itemizedlist><para>Specify the absolute path excluding the user name, or use one of the following substitution characters:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Question mark (?) &ndash;</emphasis> Substitutes for the first character of the user name.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Ampersand (&amp;) &ndash;</emphasis> Substitutes for a complete user name.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For example, the following rule maps to <filename>/home/a/amy</filename>:</para><screen>amy             /home/?/&amp;</screen><para>For more information about the path, see <xref linkend="autohomeshares"/>.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="managingsmbgroupsuserstm"><title>Managing SMB Groups (Task Map)</title><para>This section describes how to manage SMB groups and privileges for the illumos SMB service.</para><note><para>SMB groups apply only to users that are connected through SMB.</para>
</note><para>For information about SMB groups and local users, see <xref linkend="localsmbgroupsusers"/>.</para><para>The following table points to the tasks that you can use to manage SMB groups through the illumos SMB service.</para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Create an SMB group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Create an SMB group to manage users.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="createsmbgrouptask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Add a member to an SMB group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Add a member to an SMB group by using the <command>smbadm</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="addmembertosmbgrouptask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Remove a member from an SMB group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Remove a member from an SMB group by using the <command>smbadm</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="removememberfromsmbgrouptask"/></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Modify SMB group properties.</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><para>An SMB group can grant the following privileges:</para><listitem><para><literal>backup</literal>. Permit group members to back up file system objects.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>restore</literal>. Permit group members to restore file system objects.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>take-ownership</literal>. Permit group members to take ownership of file system objects.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>You can specify a description of the SMB group if you modify the value of the <literal>description</literal> property.</para>
</entry><entry><para><xref linkend="modifysmbgroupprivstask"/></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>You use the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> command to manage SMB groups on the system that runs the illumos SMB service.</para><task xml:id="createsmbgrouptask"><title>How to Create an SMB Group</title><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Choose the name of the group to create.</para><para>You might choose a name that reflects a common set of tasks that the group can perform or the organization to which the group members belong.</para>
</step><step><para>Create the SMB group.</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm create [-d <replaceable>description</replaceable>] <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>The <option>d</option> option is used to specify a textual description of the SMB group.</para><para>For example, to create a group called <literal>wsales</literal>, type:</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm create -d "Sales Force for the Western Region" wsales</userinput></screen><para>In order to provide proper identity mapping between SMB groups and Unix groups, an SMB group must have a corresponding Unix group. This requirement has two consequences. First, the group name must conform to the intersection of the Windows and Unix group name rules. Thus, an SMB group name can be up to eight (8) characters long and contain only lowercase characters and numbers. Second, a Unix group has to be created before an SMB group can be created. The Unix group is created by using the <command>groupadd</command> command. See the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>groupadd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="addmembertosmbgrouptask"><title>How to Add a Member to an SMB Group</title><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Add a user to the SMB group.</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm add-member -m <replaceable>member-name</replaceable> [[-m <replaceable>member-name</replaceable>] &hellip;] <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para><replaceable>member-name</replaceable> can be specified as [<replaceable>domain-name</replaceable><literal>\\</literal>]<replaceable>username</replaceable> or [<replaceable>domain-name</replaceable><literal>/</literal>]<replaceable>username</replaceable>. The domain name is the domain in which the user can be authenticated. By default, the domain name is the name of the domain that you joined.</para><para>You must escape the backslash character (<literal>\</literal>) because it is a special character in the most shell programs.</para><para>For example, to add user <literal>terry</literal> of the <literal>sales</literal> domain to the <literal>wsales</literal> group, type:</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm add-member -m sales\\terry wsales</userinput></screen><para>To add a local user to an SMB group, specify the illumos host name rather than the domain name. For example, to add local user <literal>terry</literal> of the <literal>solarsystem</literal> host to the <literal>wsales</literal> group, type:</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm add-member -m solarsystem\\terry wsales</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="removememberfromsmbgrouptask"><title>How to Remove a Member From an SMB Group</title><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Remove a user from the SMB group.</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm remove-member -m <replaceable>member-name</replaceable> [[-m <replaceable>member-name</replaceable>] &hellip;] <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para><replaceable>member-name</replaceable> can be specified as [<replaceable>domain-name</replaceable><literal>\\</literal>]<replaceable>username</replaceable> or [<replaceable>domain-name</replaceable><literal>/</literal>]<replaceable>username</replaceable>. The domain name is the domain in which the user can be authenticated. By default, the domain name is the name of the domain that you joined.</para><para>For example, to remove user <literal>terry</literal> of the <literal>sales</literal> domain from the <literal>wsales</literal> group, type:</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm remove-member -m sales\\terry wsales</userinput></screen><para>To remove a local user from an SMB group, specify the illumos host name rather than the domain name. For example, to remove local user <literal>terry</literal> of the <literal>solarsystem</literal> host from the <literal>wsales</literal> group, type:</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm remove-member -m solarsystem\\terry wsales</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task xml:id="modifysmbgroupprivstask"><title>How to Modify SMB Group Properties</title><procedure>&rolestepsmb;<step><para>Modify one or more SMB group properties.</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm set -p <replaceable>property</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable> [[-p <replaceable>property</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable>] &hellip;] <replaceable>group-name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>You can specify one or more property-value pairs on the command line. Each property-value pair must be preceded by the <option>p</option> option. Valid values for privileges are <literal>on</literal> or <literal>off</literal>. The value of the <literal>description</literal> property is an arbitrary text string.</para><para>For example, to grant the <literal>backup</literal> privilege and to modify the description of the <literal>wsales</literal> group, type:</para><screen># <userinput>smbadm set -p backup=on \
-p description="Sales force for the Western region" wsales</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="migratingfromsamba"><title>Disabling the Samba Service</title><para>The Samba and SMB services cannot be used simultaneously on a single illumos system. If you want to run the illumos SMB service, you must first ensure that any running Samba service is disabled.</para><para>If your illumos system is running the Samba service, disable it before starting the illumos SMB service.</para><task xml:id="disablesambatask"><title>How to Disable the Samba Service</title><procedure>&rolestep;<step><para>Verify that the Samba service is running.</para><screen># <userinput>svcs | grep samba</userinput></screen><para>For example, the following command shows that the Samba service is running:</para><screen># <userinput>svcs | grep samba</userinput>
legacy_run     Aug_03   lrc:/etc/rc3_d/S90samba</screen>
</step><step><para>Disable the Samba service.</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable svc:/network/samba</userinput>
# <userinput>svcadm disable svc:/network/wins</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
</chapter>
