<chapter id="intro-1"><title>Where to Find Solaris Installation Planning
Information</title><highlights><para>This book describes how to install the Solaris OS remotely over
a local area network or a wide area network.</para><para>This chapter describes the preparations for completing a successful
installation. Many preparatory tasks are common to all Solaris installations,
and so are described in one master planning document.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="gdlyq"><title>Where to Find Planning and System Requirement Information</title><para>The <olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink> provides
system requirements and high-level planning information, such as planning
guidelines for file systems, and upgrade planning and much more. The following
list describes the chapters in the planning book.</para><informaltable frame="topbot" pgwide="100"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="61.61*"/><colspec colwidth="38.39*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Chapter Descriptions From the Planning Guide</para>
</entry><entry><para>Reference</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>This chapter describes new features in the Solaris installation programs.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="gaufd" remap="external">Chapter 2, <citetitle remap="chapter">What&rsquo;s New in Solaris Installation,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter provides you with information about decisions you need
to make before you install or upgrade the Solaris OS. For example, you'll
find information on deciding when to use a network installation image or DVD
media and descriptions of all the Solaris installation programs.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="planning-8" remap="external">Chapter 3, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Installation and Upgrade (Roadmap),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter describes system requirements to install or upgrade to
the Solaris OS. General guidelines for planning the disk space and default
swap space allocation are also provided. Upgrade limitations are also described.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="diskspace-1" remap="external">Chapter 4, <citetitle remap="chapter">System Requirements, Guidelines, and Upgrade (Planning),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter contains checklists to help you gather all of the information
that you need to install or upgrade your system. This is useful if you are
doing an interactive installation. You'll have all the information in the
checklist that you'll need to do an interactive installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="gatherinfo-1" remap="external">Chapter 5, <citetitle remap="chapter">Gathering Information Before Installation or Upgrade (Planning),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This book part includes chapters that provide overviews of several technologies
that relate to a Solaris OS installation or upgrade. Guidelines and requirements
related to these technologies are also included. These chapters include information
about GRUB based booting, Solaris Zones partitioning technology, and RAID-1
volumes that can be created at installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" targetptr="epucs" remap="external">Part&nbsp;II, <citetitle remap="chapter">Understanding Installations That Relate to GRUB, Solaris Zones, and RAID-1 Volumes,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
</chapter>