<chapter id="netinstalloverview-28995"><title>Installing From the Network (Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides an introduction on how to set up your local area
network and systems to install the Solaris software from the network instead
of from DVD or CD media. This chapter provides overview information on the
following topics.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstalloverview-1" remap="internal">Network Installation
Introduction</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="bootdiskette-31" remap="internal">Overview of Booting and
Installing Over the Network With PXE</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information on how to install a client over a wide area network,
see <olink targetptr="wanbootoverview-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;9, WAN Boot (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="netinstalloverview-1"><title>Network Installation Introduction</title><para>This section provides you with information you need before you can perform
an installation from the network.  Network installations enable you to install
the Solaris software from a system, called an install server, that has access
to the current Solaris release disc images. You copy the contents of the current Solaris release DVD or
CD media to the install server's hard disk. Then, you can install the Solaris
software from the network by using any of the Solaris installation methods.</para><sect2 id="netinstalloverview-36"><title>Required Servers for Network Installation</title><para>To install the Solaris OS from the network, the systems to be installed
require the following servers to be present on the network.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Install server &ndash;</emphasis> A
networked system that contains the current Solaris release disc images from which you can
install current Solaris release on other systems on the network. You create an install server
by copying the images from the following media:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Solaris DVD</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Solaris Software CDs</para><para>After you copy the image
from the Solaris Software CDs, you can also copy the image from the Solaris Languages CDs as
necessary for your installation requirements.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>You can enable a single install server to provide disc images for different
Solaris releases and for multiple platforms by copying the images on to the
install server's hard disk. For example, a single install server could contain
the disc images for the SPARC platform and x86 platform.</para><itemizedlist><para>For details about how to create an install server, refer to one of the
following sections.</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstall-57799" remap="internal">To Create a SPARC Install
Server With SPARC or x86 DVD Media</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstall-104" remap="internal">To Create an x86 Install
Server With SPARC or x86 DVD Media</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstall-50" remap="internal">To Create a SPARC Install
Server With SPARC or x86 CD Media</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstall-35" remap="internal">Creating a Cross-Platform
Install Server for CD Media</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Boot server &ndash;</emphasis> A server
system that provides client systems on the same network subnet with the information
that they need to boot in order to install the OS. A boot server and
install server are typically the same system. However, if the system on which
the current Solaris release is to be installed is located in a different subnet than the
install server and you are not using DHCP, a boot server is required on that
subnet.</para><para>A single boot server can provide current Solaris release boot software
for multiple releases, including the  current Solaris release boot software for different
platforms. For example, a SPARC boot server can provide the Solaris 9 and
 current Solaris release boot software for SPARC based systems. The same SPARC boot server
can also provide the  current Solaris release boot software for x86 based systems.</para><note><para>When using DHCP, you do not need to create a separate boot server.
For more information, see <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-38" remap="internal">Preconfiguring
System Configuration Information With the DHCP Service (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</note><para>For details about how to create a boot server, refer to one of the following
sections:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstalldvd-38" remap="internal">Creating a Boot Server
on a Subnet With a DVD Image</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="netinstall-38" remap="internal">Creating a Boot Server on
a Subnet With a CD Image</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">(Optional) DHCP server &ndash;</emphasis> A
server that uses the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) to provide
the network parameters that are necessary for installation. You can configure
a DHCP server to configure and install specific clients, all clients on a
specific network, or an entire class of clients. When using DHCP, you do not
need to create a separate boot server.</para><para>After you have created
the install server, you add clients to the network with the <command>add_install_client</command> command and the <option>d</option> option. The <option>d</option> option
enables you to set up client systems for Solaris installation from the network
by using DHCP.</para><para>For information on DHCP options for installation
parameters, see <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-38" remap="internal">Preconfiguring System Configuration
Information With the DHCP Service (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">(Optional) Name server &ndash;</emphasis> A
system that manages a distributed network database, such as DNS, NIS, NIS+,
or LDAP, that contains information about systems on the network.</para><para>For
details about how to create a name server, refer to <olink targetdoc="sysadv5" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Naming and Directory Services (DNS, NIS, and LDAP)</citetitle></olink>.</para><note><para>The install server and name server can be the same or different
systems.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><olink targetptr="netinstall-60243" remap="internal">Figure 4&ndash;1</olink> illustrates
the servers that are typically used for network installation. Note that this
sample network does not include a DHCP server.</para><figure id="netinstall-60243"><title>Network Installation Servers</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig103.epsi"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>This illustration depicts the servers that are typically
used for network installation.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="bootdiskette-31" arch="x86"><title>Overview of Booting and Installing
Over the Network With PXE</title><para>This section provides an overview of the Preboot Execution Environment
(PXE).</para><sect2 id="bootdiskette-677" arch="x86"><title>What is PXE?</title><para>PXE
network boot is a &ldquo;direct&rdquo; network boot. No boot media is required
on the client system. With PXE, you can install an x86 based client over the
network by using DHCP.</para><para>PXE network boot is available only for devices that implement the Intel
Preboot Execution Environment specification. To determine if your system supports
PXE network boot, see your hardware manufacturer's documentation.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="bootdiskette-733" arch="x86"><title>Guidelines for Booting With
PXE</title><itemizedlist><para>To boot over the network by using PXE, you need the following systems.</para><listitem><para>An install server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A DHCP server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An x86 client that supports PXE</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>When you are preparing to use PXE to install a client over the network,
consider the following issues.</para><listitem><para>Set up only one DHCP server on the subnet that includes the
client system that you want to install. The PXE network boot does not work
properly over subnets that include multiple DHCP servers.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Some early versions of PXE firmware have a variety of shortcomings.
If you experience difficulty with a particular PXE adapter, obtain firmware
upgrade information from  the adapter manufacturer's web site. Refer to the <olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="elxl-7d" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>elxl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7D</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> and <olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="iprb-7d" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>iprb</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7D</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages for more information.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>