<appendix id="remotecd-2"><title>Installing or Upgrading Remotely (Tasks)</title><highlights><para>This appendix describes how to use the Solaris installation program
to install or upgrade to the Solaris OS on a machine or domain that does
not have a directly attached DVD-ROM or CD-ROM drive.</para><note><para>If you are installing or upgrading the Solaris OS on a multi&ndash;domain
server, refer to the system controller or system service processor documentation
before beginning the installation process.</para>
</note>
</highlights><sect1 id="webstart-79" arch="sparc"><title>Using the Solaris Installation
Program to Install or Upgrade From a Remote DVD-ROM or CD-ROM</title><para>If you want to install the Solaris OS on a machine or domain that
does not have a directly attached DVD-ROM or CD-ROM drive, you can use a drive
that is attached to another machine. Both machines must be connected to the
same subnet. Use the following instructions to complete the installation.</para><task id="remotecd-1" arch="sparc"><title>To Install or Upgrade From a Remote
DVD-ROM and CD-ROM</title><tasksummary><note><para>This procedure assumes that the system is running the Volume Manager.
If you are not using the Volume Manager to manage media, refer to <olink targetdoc="sagdfs" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Devices and File Systems</citetitle></olink>. This procedure also assumes you are using
the <command>share</command> command instead of the <command>sharemgr</command> utility.</para>
</note><para>In the following procedure, the remote system with the DVD-ROM or CD-ROM
is identified as <replaceable>remote system</replaceable>. The
system that is the client to be installed is identified as <replaceable>client
system</replaceable>.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step id="webstart-step-86"><para>Identify a system that is running the Solaris OS and
has a DVD-ROM or CD-ROM drive.</para>
</step><step id="webstart-step-87"><para>On the <replaceable>remote system</replaceable> with
the DVD-ROM or CD-ROM drive, insert the Solaris DVD or the Solaris Software for SPARC Platforms - 1 CD in
the drive.</para><para>The Volume Manager mounts the disc.</para>
</step><step id="webstart-step-89"><para>On the remote system, change directories
to the DVD or CD where the <command>add_install_client</command> command is
located.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For DVD media, type:</para><screen><replaceable>remote system</replaceable># <userinput>cd /cdrom/cdrom0/s0/Solaris_11/Tools</userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>For CD media, type:</para><screen><replaceable>remote system</replaceable># <userinput>cd /cdrom/cdrom0/s0</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step id="webstart-step-90"><para>On the remote system, add the system that
you want to install as a client.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For DVD media, type:</para><screen><replaceable>remote  system</replaceable># <userinput>./add_install_client</userinput> \
<userinput><replaceable>client_system_name</replaceable> <replaceable>arch</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>For CD media, type:</para><screen><replaceable>remote  system</replaceable># <userinput>./add_install_client -s <replaceable>remote_system_name</replaceable>:</userinput> \
<userinput>/cdrom/cdrom0/s0 <replaceable>client_system_name</replaceable> <replaceable>arch</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><variablelist><varlistentry><term><replaceable>remote_system_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>The name of the system with the DVD-ROM or CD-ROM drive</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><replaceable>client_system_name</replaceable></term><listitem><para>The name of the machine you want to install</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><replaceable>arch</replaceable></term><listitem><para>The platform group of the machine you want to install, for
example sun4u. On the system that you want to install, find the platform group
by using the <command>uname</command> <option>m</option> command.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</step><step id="webstart-step-91"><para>Boot the <replaceable>client system</replaceable> that
you want to install.</para><screen><replaceable>client system:</replaceable> ok <userinput>boot net</userinput></screen><para>The installation begins.</para>
</step><step id="webstart-step-92"><para>Follow the instructions to type system configuration
information if needed.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If you are using DVD media, follow the instructions on the
screen to complete the installation. You are finished.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are using CD media, the machine reboots and the Solaris
installation program begins. After the Welcome panel, the Specify Media panel
appears with Network File System selected. Proceed to <olink targetptr="webstart-step-93" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;7</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step id="webstart-step-93"><para>On the Specify Media panel, click Next. </para><para>The Specify Network File System Path panel appears and the text field
contains the installation path.</para><para><replaceable>client_system_ip_address</replaceable>:<filename>/cdrom/cdrom0/s0</filename></para>
</step><step id="webstart-step-94"><para>On the remote system where the DVD or CD
is mounted, change directories to <filename>root</filename>.</para><screen><replaceable>remote  system</replaceable># <userinput>cd /</userinput></screen>
</step><step id="remotecd-step-10"><para>On the remote system, check for the path
to the slice that has been shared.</para><screen><replaceable>remote  system</replaceable># <userinput>share</userinput></screen>
</step><step id="webstart-step-95"><para>On the remote system, unshare the Solaris DVD or Solaris Software for SPARC Platforms - 1 CD by
using the path that is found in <olink targetptr="remotecd-step-10" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;9</olink>.
If paths lead to two slices, <command>unshare</command> both slices.</para><screen><replaceable>remote  system</replaceable># <userinput>unshare <replaceable>absolute_path</replaceable></userinput></screen><variablelist><varlistentry><term><replaceable>absolute_path</replaceable></term><listitem><para>Is the absolute path shown in the <command>share</command> command</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>In this example, slice 0 and slice 1 are unshared.</para><screen><replaceable>remote  system</replaceable># <userinput>unshare /cdrom/cdrom0/s0</userinput>
<replaceable>remote system</replaceable># <userinput>unshare /cdrom/cdrom0/s1</userinput></screen>
</step><step id="webstart-step-99"><para>On the client system that you are installing,
continue the Solaris installation by clicking Next.</para>
</step><step id="webstart-step-100"><para>If the Solaris installation program prompts
you to insert the Solaris Software - 2 CD, repeat <olink targetptr="remotecd-step-10" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;9</olink> through <olink targetptr="webstart-step-99" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;11</olink> to unshare the Solaris Software - 1 CD
and to export and install the Solaris Software - 2 CD.</para>
</step><step id="esxiv"><para>If the Solaris installation program prompts you to
insert additional Solaris Software CDs, repeat <olink targetptr="remotecd-step-10" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;9</olink> through <olink targetptr="webstart-step-99" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;11</olink> to unshare the Solaris Software CDs
and to export and install the additional CDs.</para>
</step><step id="webstart-step-101"><para>If the Solaris installation program prompts
you to insert the first Solaris Languages CD, repeat <olink targetptr="remotecd-step-10" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;9</olink>  through <olink targetptr="webstart-step-99" remap="internal">Step&nbsp;11</olink> to unshare the Solaris Software CDs
and to export and install each Solaris Languages CD.</para><para>When you export a Solaris Languages CD,
an installer window appears on the machine where the CD-ROM is mounted.  Ignore
the installer window while you install the Solaris Languages CD. After you
complete the installation of the Solaris Languages CD, close the installer
window.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
</appendix>