<chapter id="wanbootplanning-1"><title>Preparing to Install With WAN Boot (Planning)</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes how to prepare your network for a WAN boot installation.
This chapter describes the following topics.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanbootoverview-3" remap="internal">WAN Boot Requirements
and Guidelines</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-107" remap="internal">WAN Boot Security Limitations</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-19" remap="internal">Gathering Information
for WAN Boot Installations</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="wanbootoverview-3"><title>WAN Boot Requirements
and Guidelines</title><para>The section describes
the system requirements to perform a WAN boot installation.</para><table frame="topbot" id="wanboottasks2-tbl-114"><title>System Requirements
for WAN Boot Installation</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33.30*"/><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="64.38*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>System and Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>Requirements</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>WAN
boot server &ndash; The WAN boot server is a web server that provides the <command>wanboot</command> program, the configuration and security files, and the WAN
boot miniroot.</para>
</entry><entry><para></para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Operating system &ndash; Solaris 9 12/03 OS, or compatible
version</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Must be configured as web server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Web server software must support HTTP 1.1</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you want to use digital certificates, the web server software
must support HTTPS</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Install server &ndash;
The install server provides the Solaris Flash archive and custom JumpStart
files that are required to install the client.</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Available disk space &ndash;  space for each Solaris Flash archive</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Media drive &ndash;  CD-ROM or DVD-ROM drive</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Operating system &ndash;  Solaris 9 12/03 OS, or compatible
version</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>If the install server is a different system than the WAN boot server,
the install server must meet these additional requirements. </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Must be configured as a web server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Web server software must support HTTP 1.1</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you want to use digital certificates, the web server software
must support HTTPS</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Client system &ndash;
The remote system you want to install over a WAN</para>
</entry><entry><para></para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Memory
- Minimum of 512 Mbytes of RAM</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>CPU &ndash; UltraSPARC II processor minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Hard disk &ndash; At least 2 Gbytes of hard disk space</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>OBP &ndash; WAN
boot-enabled PROM</para><para>If the client does not have the appropriate
PROM, the client must have a CD-ROM drive.</para><para>To determine if your
client has a WAN boot-enabled PROM, see <olink targetptr="wanboottasks-13" remap="internal">To
Check the Client OBP for WAN Boot Support</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Optional)
DHCP server &ndash; You can use a DHCP server to provide client configuration
information.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you are using a SunOS DHCP server, you must perform one of the following
tasks.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Upgrade the server to be an EDHCP server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Rename Sun vendor options to satisfy the eight-character limit
on options. For more information about the WAN installation-specific Sun vendor
options, see <olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-46" remap="internal">(Optional) Providing Configuration
Information With a DHCP Server</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>If the DHCP server is on a different subnet than the client, you must
configure a BOOTP relay agent. For more information about how to configure
a BOOTP relay agent, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv3" targetptr="chapter3-20" remap="external">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Configuring the DHCP Service (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: IP Services</citetitle></olink>. </para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Optional) Logging server &ndash; By default,
all booting and installation log messages are displayed on the client console
during a WAN installation. If you want to view these messages on another system,
you can specify a system to serve as a logging server.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Must be configured as web server.</para><note><para>If you use HTTPS during your installation, the logging server
must be the same system as the WAN boot server.</para>
</note>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Optional)
Proxy server &ndash; You can configure the WAN boot feature to use an HTTP
proxy during the download of the installation data and files.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If the installation uses HTTPS, the proxy server must be configured
to tunnel HTTPS.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><sect2 id="wanbootplanning-9"><title>Web Server Software Requirements and
Guidelines</title><para>The web server software you use on your WAN boot server and install
server must meet the following requirements.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Operating
system requirements &ndash; WAN boot provides a Common Gateway Interface (CGI)
program (<filename>wanboot-cgi</filename>) that converts data and files into
a specific format that the client machine expects. To perform a WAN boot installation
with these scripts, the web server software must run on the Solaris 9 12/03 OS,
or compatible version.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>File size limitations &ndash; Your web server software might
limit the size of the files you can transmit over HTTP. Check your web server
documentation to make sure the software can transmit files that are the size
of a Solaris Flash archive.</para><note><para>The <command>flarcreate</command> command no longer has size limitations on individual files. You
can create a Solaris Flash archive that  contains individual files over
4 Gbytes.</para><para>For more information, see <olink targetdoc="solinstallflash" targetptr="gbwbm" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Creating an Archive That Contains Large Files</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>SSL support &ndash;
If you want to use HTTPS in your WAN boot installation, the web server software
must support SSL version 3.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="wanbootplanning-4"><title>Server Configuration Options</title><para>You can customize the configuration of the servers that are required
by WAN boot to meet your network needs. You can host all the servers on one
system, or place the servers on multiple systems.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Single server</emphasis> &ndash; If
you want to centralize the WAN boot data and files on one system, you can
host all the servers on the same machine. You can administer all your different
servers on one system, and you only need to configure one system as a web
server. However, a single server might not be able to support the volume of
traffic that is required for a large number of simultaneous WAN boot installations.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Multiple servers</emphasis> &ndash;
If you want to distribute the installation data and files across your network,
you can host these servers on multiple machines. You might set up a central
WAN boot server, and configure multiple install servers to host Solaris Flash
archives across your network. If you host the install server and logging server
on independent machines, you must configure those servers as web servers.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="wanbootplanning-6"><title>Storing Installation and Configuration
Files in the Document Root Directory</title><para>The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program transmits the following files during a WAN boot installation.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><filename>wanboot</filename> program</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>WAN boot miniroot</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Custom JumpStart files</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Solaris Flash archive</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>To enable the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program to transmit these
files you must store these files in a directory that is accessible to the
web server software. One way to make these files accessible is to place these
files in the <firstterm>document root</firstterm> on your web server.</para><para>The
document root, or primary document directory, is the directory on your web
server where you store files you want to make available to clients. You can
name and configure this directory in your web server software. See your web
server documentation for more information about setting up the document root
directory on your web server.</para><para>You might want to create different subdirectories of the document root
directory to store your different installation and configuration files. For
example, you might want to create specific subdirectories for each group of
clients that you want to install. If you plan to install several different
releases of the Solaris OS across your network, you might create subdirectories
for each release.</para><para><olink targetptr="wanbootplanning-fig-18" remap="internal">Figure 10&ndash;1</olink> shows a basic sample structure for a document root
directory. In this example, the WAN boot server and install server are on
the same machine. The server is running the Apache web server software.</para><figure id="wanbootplanning-fig-18"><title>Sample Structure for Document Root
Directory</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="document-root-directory"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The context describes the graphic.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>This sample document directory uses the following structure.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The <filename>/opt/apache/htdocs</filename> directory is the
document root directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The WAN boot miniroot (<filename>miniroot</filename>) directory contains the WAN boot miniroot.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <filename>wanboot</filename> directory contains the <filename>wanboot</filename> program.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The
Solaris Flash (<filename>flash</filename>) directory contains  the custom
JumpStart files that are required to install the client and the subdirectory <filename>archives</filename>. The <filename>archives</filename> directory contains
the current Solaris release Flash archive.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>If the WAN boot server and the install server are different systems,
you might want to store the <filename>flash</filename> directory on the install
server. Ensure that these files and directories are accessible to the WAN
boot server.</para>
</note><para>For information about how to create the document root directory, see
your web server documentation. For detailed instructions about how to create
and store these installation files, see <olink targetptr="wanboottasks-29" remap="internal">Creating
the Custom JumpStart Installation Files</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="wanboottasks2-501"><title>Storing Configuration and Security Information
in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> Hierarchy</title><para>The <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory contains the configuration
information, private key, digital certificate, and certificate authority that
are required for a WAN boot installation. This section describes the files
and directories you can create in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory
to customize your WAN boot installation.</para><sect3 id="wanboottasks2-116"><title>Customizing the Scope of the WAN Boot
Installation</title><para>During the installation, the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program searches for the client information in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory on the WAN boot server. The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program converts this information into the WAN boot file system,
and then transmits the WAN boot file system to the client. You can create
subdirectories within the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory to customize
the scope of the WAN installation. Use the following directory structures
to define how configuration information is shared among the clients that you
want to install.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Global
configuration</emphasis> &ndash; If you want all the clients on your network
to share configuration information, store the files that you want to share
in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Network-specific
configuration</emphasis> &ndash; If you want only those machines on a specific
subnet to share configuration information, store the configuration files that
you want to share in a subdirectory of <filename>/etc/netboot</filename>.
Have the subdirectory follow this naming convention.</para><screen>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable></screen><para>In this example, <replaceable>net-ip</replaceable> is the IP address
of the client's subnet. For example, if you want all systems on the subnet
with the IP address of 192.168.255.0 to share configuration files, create
a <filename>/etc/netboot/192.168.255.0</filename> directory. Then, store the
configuration files in this directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Client-specific configuration</emphasis> &ndash; If you want only a specific client to use the boot file
system, store the boot file system files in a subdirectory of <filename>/etc/netboot</filename>. Have the subdirectory follow this naming convention.</para><screen>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable>/<replaceable>client-ID</replaceable></screen><para>In this example, <replaceable>net-ip</replaceable> is the IP address
of the subnet. <replaceable>client-ID</replaceable> is either the client ID
that is assigned by the DHCP server, or a user-specified client ID. For example,
if you want a system with the client ID 010003BA152A42 on the subnet 192.168.255.0
to use specific configuration files, create a <filename>/etc/netboot/192.168.255.0/010003BA152A42</filename> directory. Then, store the appropriate files in this directory.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3><sect3 id="wanbootplanning-13"><title>Specifying Security and Configuration
Information in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> Directory</title><para>You specify the security and configuration
information by creating the following files and storing the files in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><filename>wanboot.conf</filename> &ndash;
This file specifies the client configuration information for a WAN boot installation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>System
configuration file (<filename>system.conf</filename>) &ndash; This system
configuration file specifies the location of the client's <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file
and custom JumpStart files.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>keystore</filename> &ndash;
This file contains the client's HMAC SHA1 hashing key, 3DES or AES encryption
key, and SSL private key.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>truststore</filename> &ndash;
This file contains the digital certificates of certificate signing authorities
that the client should trust. These trusted certificates instruct the client
to trust the server during the installation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>certstore</filename> &ndash;
This file contains the client's digital certificate.</para><note><para>The <filename>certstore</filename> file must be located in the
client ID directory. See <olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-116" remap="internal">Customizing
the Scope of the WAN Boot Installation</olink> for more information about
subdirectories of the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For detailed instructions on how to create and store these files, see
the following procedures.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-71" remap="internal">To Create the System Configuration
File</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-43" remap="internal">To Create the wanboot.conf
File</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-51" remap="internal">(Optional) To Create a
Hashing Key and an Encryption Key</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-93" remap="internal">(Optional) To Use Digital
Certificates for Server and Client Authentication</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3><sect3 id="wanbootplanning-14"><title>Sharing Security and Configuration Information
in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> Directory</title><para>To install clients on your network, you might want to share security
and configuration files among several different clients, or across entire
subnets. You can share these files by distributing your configuration information
throughout the <filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable>/<replaceable>client-ID</replaceable></filename>, <filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable></filename>,
and <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directories. The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program
searches these directories for the configuration information that best fits
the client, and uses that information during the installation.</para><para>The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program searches for client information in the following
order.</para><orderedlist><listitem><para><filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable>/<replaceable>client-ID</replaceable></filename> &ndash; The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program
first checks for configuration information that is specific to the client
machine. If the <filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable>/<replaceable>client-ID</replaceable></filename> directory contains all the client configuration
information, the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program does not check for
configuration information elsewhere in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable></filename> &ndash;
If all the required information is not located in the <filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable>/<replaceable>client-ID</replaceable></filename> directory,
the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program then checks for subnet configuration
information in the <filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable></filename> directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>/etc/netboot</filename> &ndash; If the remaining
information is not located in the <filename>/etc/netboot/<replaceable>net-ip</replaceable></filename> directory,
the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program then checks for global configuration
information in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist><para><olink targetptr="wanbootplanning-fig-16" remap="internal">Figure 10&ndash;2</olink> demonstrates
how you can set up the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory to customize
your WAN boot installations.</para><figure id="wanbootplanning-fig-16"><title>Sample <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> Directory</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="netboot-directory"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The context describes the graphic.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>The <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory layout in <olink targetptr="wanbootplanning-fig-16" remap="internal">Figure 10&ndash;2</olink> enables you to
perform the following WAN boot installations.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>When you install the client 010003BA152A42, the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program uses the following files in the <filename>/etc/netboot/192.168.255.0/010003BA152A42</filename> directory.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><filename>system.conf</filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>keystore</filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>truststore</filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>certstore</filename></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program then uses the <filename>wanboot.conf</filename> file in the <filename>/etc/netboot/192.168.255.0</filename> directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>When you install a client that is located on the 192.168.255.0
subnet, the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program uses the <filename>wanboot.conf</filename>, <filename>keystore</filename>, and <filename>truststore</filename> files
in the <filename>/etc/netboot/192.168.255.0</filename> directory. The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program then uses the <filename>system.conf</filename> file in
the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>When you install a client machine that is not located on the
192.168.255.0 subnet, the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program uses the
following files in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><filename>wanboot.conf</filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>system.conf</filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>keystore</filename></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>truststore</filename></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2><sect2 id="wanbootplanning-7"><title>Storing the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> Program</title><para>The <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program transmits the data and
files from the WAN boot server to the client. You must ensure that this program
is in a directory on the WAN boot server that is accessible to the client.
One method to make this program accessible to the client is to store this
program in the <filename>cgi-bin</filename> directory of the WAN boot server.
You might need to configure your web server software to use the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program as a CGI program. See your web server documentation for
information about CGI program requirements.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="wanboottasks2-70"><title>Digital Certificate Requirements</title><para>If you want to add security to your WAN boot installation, you can use
digital certificates to enable server and the client authentication. WAN boot
can use a digital certificate to establish the identity of the server or the
client during an online transaction. Digital certificates are issued by a
certificate authority (CA). These certificates contain a serial number, expiration
dates, a copy of the certificate holder's public key, and the certificate
authority's digital signature.</para><para>If you want to require server or both client and server authentication
during your installation, you must install digital certificates on the server.
Follow these guidelines when you use digital certificates.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If you want to use digital certificates, the digital certificates
must be formatted as part of a Public-Key Cryptography Standards #12 (PKCS#12)
file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you create your own certificates, you must create the certificates
as PKCS#12 files.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you receive your certificates from third-party certificate
authorities, request your certificates in the PKCS#12 format.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For detailed instructions on how to use PKCS#12 certificates during
your WAN boot installation, see <olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-93" remap="internal">(Optional)
To Use Digital Certificates for Server and Client Authentication</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="wanboottasks2-107"><title>WAN Boot Security Limitations</title><para>While WAN boot provides several different security features, WAN boot does
not address these potential insecurities.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Denial of service (DoS) attacks</emphasis> &ndash; A denial of service attack
can take many forms, with the goal of preventing users from accessing a specific
service. A DoS attack can overwhelm a network with large amounts of data,
or aggressively consume limited resources. Other DoS attacks manipulate the
data that is transmitted between systems in transit. The WAN boot installation method does
not protect servers or clients from DoS attacks.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Corrupted
binaries on the servers</emphasis> &ndash; The WAN boot installation method does not
check the integrity of the WAN boot miniroot or the Solaris Flash archive
before you perform your installation. Before you perform your installation,
check the integrity of your Solaris binaries against the Solaris Fingerprint
Database at <ulink url="http://sunsolve.sun.com" type="text">http://sunsolve.sun.com</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Encryption key and hashing key privacy</emphasis> &ndash; If
you use encryption keys or a hashing key with WAN boot, you must
type the key value on the command line during your installation. Follow the
precautions that are necessary for your network to make sure that these key
values remain private.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Compromise of the network naming service</emphasis> &ndash;
If you use a naming service on your network, check the integrity of your name
servers before you perform your WAN boot installation.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="wanboottasks2-19"><title>Gathering Information for WAN Boot Installations</title><para>You need to gather a wide variety of information to configure your network
for a WAN boot installation. You might want to write down this information
as you prepare to install over a WAN.</para><para>Use the following worksheets to record the WAN boot installation information
for your network.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanboottasks2-tbl-104" remap="internal">Table 10&ndash;2</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="wanbootplanning-tbl-17" remap="internal">Table 10&ndash;3</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><table frame="topbot" id="wanboottasks2-tbl-104"><title>Worksheet for Collecting
Server Information</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="colspec10" colwidth="46.59*"/><colspec colname="colspec11" colwidth="53.41*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Information Needed</para>
</entry><entry><para>Notes</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Install server information</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Path to the WAN boot miniroot on install server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Path to the custom JumpStart files on the install server</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>WAN boot server information</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Path to the <filename>wanboot</filename> program on the WAN
boot server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>URL of the <filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program on the
WAN boot server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Path to the client's subdirectory in the <filename>/etc/netboot</filename> hierarchy
on the WAN boot server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>(Optional) File name of the PKCS#12 certificate file</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>(Optional) Host names of any machines other than the WAN boot
server that are required for WAN installation</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>(Optional) IP address and TCP port number of the network's
proxy server</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Optional server information</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>URL of the <filename>bootlog-cgi</filename> script on logging
server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>IP address and TCP port number of the network's proxy server</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><table frame="topbot" id="wanbootplanning-tbl-17"><title>Worksheet for Collecting
Client Information</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="46.59*"/><colspec colwidth="53.41*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Information</para>
</entry><entry><para>Notes</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>IP address for the client's subnet</para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>IP address for the client's router</para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>IP address of the client</para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Subnet mask for the client</para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Host name for the client</para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>MAC address of the client</para>
</entry><entry><para></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
</chapter>