<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub UDT __target_1 _target?><?Pub UDT registeredtm trademark?><?Pub EntList bull rArr sect hyphen?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()chapter()chapter()appendix()?><glossary id="gdqrm"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="1"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="jonj" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="jh118764"
fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="wsm" fullname=""?><title>Glossary</title><para>The following are terms that are commonly used throughout this book.
Note that some of these terms are not limited to printing.</para><glossentry id="glos-alias"><glossterm>alias</glossterm><glossdef><para>An alternative name that can be assigned to a printer.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-allow"><glossterm>allow list</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that includes a list of users who have access to forms
or printers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-attach"><glossterm>attached printer</glossterm><glossdef><para>A hardware printing device that is directly connected to a
system. An attached printer is sometimes referred to as a <emphasis>local
printer</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="gloss-ban"><glossterm>banner page</glossterm><glossdef><para>A cover page that is printed with each print request. This
page displays the name of the user who submitted the print request, the request
ID, and the date/time the request was printed. Banner pages can be disabled
by using the <command>lpadmin</command> command in Solaris Print Manager.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-baud"><glossterm>baud rate</glossterm><glossdef><para>The rate at which information is transmitted between devices,
for example, between a computer and a printer. Baud rate measures the number
of events, or signal changes, that occur in one second.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-bsd2"><glossterm>BSD print server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A print server that uses the Berkeley Software Distribution
(BSD) version of the UNIX operating system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-proto"><glossterm>BSD printing protocol</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glos-1179" remap="internal">RFC-1179 (Line Printer Daemon
Protocol)</olink></para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Common Internet File System (CIFS)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A protocol that follows the client-server model for sharing
files and services over the network and is based on the Server Message Block
(SMB) protocol.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-daem"><glossterm>daemon</glossterm><glossdef><para>A special type of program that starts itself and carries out
a specific task without any need for user input. Daemons are typically used
to handle print jobs that have been queued for printing.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-def"><glossterm>default printer</glossterm><glossdef><para>The printer that you designate as the default destination
for all print requests. If no printer name is used, the default printer is
used.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-deny"><glossterm>deny list</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that includes a list of users who are denied access
to forms or printers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-dest"><glossterm>destination or network printer access
name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The internal name of the printer node port that is used by
the printer subsystem to access the printer. The access name is the name of
the printer node or the name of the printer node with a printer vendor port
designation. Any printer vendor port designation is explicitly defined in
the printer vendor documentation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-uri"><glossterm>device URI</glossterm><glossdef><para>The device Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) contains the
type of interface and the device path for printing on the Internet. A device
URI can be used with the IPP, RFC-1179, and Server Message Block (SMB) printing
protocols.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-dns"><glossterm>Domain Name System (DNS)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A service that provides the naming policy and mechanisms for
mapping domain and machine names to IP addresses outside of the enterprise,
such as those IP addresses on the Internet.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-filt"><glossterm>filter</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that converts a print request into a format that can
be processed by a particular type of printer.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-form"><glossterm>form</glossterm><glossdef><para>A form is a printed paper stock, such as letterhead or blank
checks. A form can also be a software file that contains printing characteristics,
such as page length, page width, number of pages, line pitch, character pitch,
character set choice, ribbon color, and alignment pattern.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-ippd"><glossterm>Internet Printing Protocol (IPP)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An Internet protocol that provides universal solutions to
printing documents on the Internet.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-ippl"><glossterm>IPP listening service</glossterm><glossdef><para>A service that monitors the network for service requests,
accepts the requests, and then invokes services in response to these service
requests. In the Solaris OS, the listening service provides server-side support
for printing on a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-ldap"><glossterm>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol
(LDAP)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A standard extensible directory access protocol that is used
by LDAP naming service clients and servers to communicate with each other.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-loca"><glossterm>local printer</glossterm><glossdef><para>A print queue that has been defined on a system that is local
to you.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-netw"><glossterm>network&hyphen;attached printer</glossterm><glossdef><para>A hardware printing device that is connected directly to a
network. A network printer transfers data directly over the network to the
output device. The printer or network connection hardware has its own system
name and IP address.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-nisd"><glossterm>Network Information Service (NIS) database</glossterm><glossdef><para>A distributed database that contains key information about
the systems and the users on a network. The NIS database is stored on a master
server and all replica or slave servers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="nis-term"><glossterm>Network Information Service Plus (NIS+)
database</glossterm><glossdef><para>A distributed database that contains hierarchical information
about the systems and the users on a network. The NIS+ database is stored
on the master server and all replica or slave servers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="ggdco"><glossterm>Open Standard Print API (PAPI)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A programming  specification for cross-platform and cross-print
system printing.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-papi"><glossterm>PAPI</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="ggdco" remap="internal">Open Standard Print API (PAPI)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-ppdf"><glossterm>PostScript Printer Description (PPD)
file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that describes the fonts, paper sizes, resolution,
and other capabilities that are standard for a particular printer.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-ppdm"><glossterm>PPD File Manager Utility</glossterm><glossdef><para>A command-line utility for administering PostScript Printer
Description (PPD) files that are used with the Solaris print subsystem.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-princ"><glossterm>print client</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system that has the Solaris printing software installed
on it and that has been enabled to access remote printers on a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-prinj"><glossterm>print job</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file to be printed. A print job is also referred to as a <emphasis>print request</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-queu"><glossterm>print queue</glossterm><glossdef><orderedlist><listitem><para>Refers to the setup and configuration of a printer.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A temporary lineup of print requests that are scheduled to
print on a printer.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-prinr"><glossterm>print request</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file to be printed. A print request is also referred to
as a <emphasis>print job</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-sched"><glossterm>print scheduler</glossterm><glossdef><para>A program that schedules print requests. In the Solaris OS,
the print scheduler is the <command>lpsched</command> daemon.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-serv"><glossterm>print server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system with a local printer configured on it that makes
the printer available to other systems on a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-spool"><glossterm>print spooler</glossterm><glossdef><para>Software that intercepts a print request and then sends it
to disk or memory, where the request is held until the printer is ready to
print it. The term, spooler, is an acronym for <emphasis>Simultaneous Peripheral Operations On&hyphen;line</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-host"><glossterm>printer-host device</glossterm><glossdef><para>The software and hardware, supplied by a vendor, that provides
network printer support for a non-network-capable printer. The combination
of the printer-host device with one or more printers attached to it creates
a <emphasis>network printer</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-drive"><glossterm>printer driver</glossterm><glossdef><para>A program that is used to convert the input file (or job data)
into a format that is specific to the target printer.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-inter"><glossterm>printer interface program</glossterm><glossdef><para>A program, or interface script, that is the interface between
the LP scheduler and the printers. The printer interface program enables insertion
of customized software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-name"><glossterm>printer name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The name that is typed on the command line when you use print
commands. You select the printer name at the time of the printer's configuration.
Any one physical printer can have several printer or print queue names. Each
name provides access to the printer.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-node"><glossterm>printer node</glossterm><glossdef><para>Either the physical printer or the printer-host device. The
printer node is the physical printer when network support resides in the physical
printer. The printer node is the printer-host device when an external device
is used to provide the network interface. The printer node name is the system
name that is provided with the IP address.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-pprot"><glossterm>printing protocols</glossterm><glossdef><para>Over-the-wire protocols that enable communication between
a print client and a print server and between a print server and a printer.
The supported protocols for communication between a print client and printer
server are IPP and RFC-1179. The supported protocols for communication between
a print server and a printer are TCP/IP, RFC-1179, and IPP. Often, the documentation
from the printer vendor supplies the information regarding the protocol to
select.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-col"><glossterm>protocol</glossterm><glossdef><para>A set of formal rules that describe how to transmit data across
a network. See <olink targetptr="glos-pprot" remap="internal">printing protocols</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-remo"><glossterm>remote printer</glossterm><glossdef><para>A hardware printing device that has its print queue defined
on a system that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> local to you.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-1179"><glossterm>RFC-1179 (Line Printer Daemon Protocol)</glossterm><glossdef><para>Defines a standard method by which print jobs can be transferred
between hosts by using the TCP/IP protocol. The RFC describes the protocols
with which a line printer daemon client can control printing. Also known as the BSD or LPD protocol.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-samb"><glossterm>Samba</glossterm><glossdef><para>An open-source free software suite that provides file and
print services to Server Message Block (SMB) Common Internet
File System (CIFS) clients, including the numerous versions of Windows.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-smbp"><glossterm>Server Message Block (SMB)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A protocol that enables clients to access files and to request
services from a server on a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-prtmg"><glossterm>Solaris Print Manager</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Java technology-based GUI that enables you to manage local
and remote printer configuration.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-unif"><glossterm>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An addressing technology for identifying resources on the
Internet or on a private intranet. URIs can be used with application-level
protocols, which are called <emphasis>URI schemes</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glos-uris"><glossterm>URI scheme</glossterm><glossdef><para>A scheme that enables the inline inclusion of small data items,
as if they were being referenced as an external resource.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary><?Pub *0000015499 0?>