<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub UDT __target_1 _target?><?Pub UDT registeredtm trademark?><?Pub CX solbook(?><chapter id="printsetup-33230"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="1"?><?Pub Tag
atict:user user="jonj" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="jh118764" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="wsm"
fullname=""?><title>Setting Up Printing Services (Tasks)</title><indexterm id="printsvc-1"><primary>printing services</primary><secondary>setting up</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="ggcvl"><primary>setting up printing services</primary>
</indexterm><highlights><para>This chapter describes how to set up the print services, as well as
how to set up printers and make those printers accessible to systems on the
network.</para><itemizedlist><para>This is a list of the information in this chapter:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="printsetup-2" remap="internal">Setting Up Solaris Printing
Services (Task Map)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ermlj" remap="internal">Using Solaris Print Manager</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="geduc" remap="internal">Setting Up the Internet Printing
Protocol</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfjfe" remap="internal">Enabling and Disabling Printing Services
(Task Map)</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For overview information, see <olink targetptr="printintro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1,
Introduction to Printing in the Solaris Operating System</olink>.</para><para>For printer setup information, see <olink targetptr="printers-33230" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4,
Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="printsetup-2"><title>Setting Up Solaris Printing Services (Task
Map)</title><informaltable frame="all" id="gfhat"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><?PubTbl tgroup dispwid="902.00px"?><colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="31.84*"/><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="31.84*"/><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="34.16*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Set up printing services with Solaris Print Manager</para>
</entry><entry><para>To use Solaris Print Manager, there is very little configuration required.
However, there are some guidelines and requirements for running the tool.
Also, you must also have appropriate privileges to use many of the tool's
features.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="printder-1" remap="internal">Determining a Method to Use for Printer
Setup and Administration</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="printsetup-6" remap="internal">How to Start Solaris Print Manager</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Set up the Internet Printing Protocol.</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><para>Setting up the IPP services involves configuring both server and client
data:</para><listitem><para>For IPP server-side support, you can customize the listening
service by adding directives to the Apache configuration file on the server.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For IPP client-side support, queue configuration data is stored in the <command>printers.conf</command> configuration database. This database contains entries
for each configured print queue.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gedvx" remap="internal">How to Configure IPP Server Data</olink></para><para></para><para></para><para><olink targetptr="gedut" remap="internal">How to Configure IPP Client Data</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="ermlj"><title>Using Solaris Print Manager</title><para>Solaris Print Manager is a Java-based graphical user interface that
enables you to manage local and remote printer configuration. This tool can
be used in the following naming service environments: LDAP, NIS, NIS+,  and
files. You must be logged in as superuser to use this tool. </para><para>Use Solaris Print
Manager to set up print servers (Add New Attached Printer or Add a Network
Printer) and print clients (Add Access to Printer). An <emphasis>attached
printer</emphasis> is a printer that is physically cabled to the print server.
A <emphasis>network printer</emphasis> is physically attached to the network.
Adding <emphasis>access</emphasis> to a printer, or adding <emphasis>remote
access</emphasis> to a printer, is the process of giving print clients (all
those machines that are not the server) access to the printer. For more information
about printing terms, see <olink targetptr="gdqrm" remap="internal">Glossary</olink>.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris Express 5/06:</emphasis> Starting
with this release, the Solaris print system can use and recognize <literal>localhost</literal> as the host name in the print system databases. Previously, <filename>/bin/hostname</filename> was used to generate the print host name. These improvements
were made to enable print servers to maintain the same print host name, independent
of the machine host name. For more information, see <olink targetptr="gfjoa" remap="internal">How
to Use Solaris Print Manager to Add a Print Queue With the Local Host  Specified
as the Host Name</olink>.</para><sect2 id="ermkb"><title>Solaris Print Manager Options and Selectable Attributes</title><indexterm><primary>Solaris Print Manager</primary><secondary>modifications to printer definitions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>You can add, modify, or delete a print queue and add printer access by using the Solaris
Print Manager GUI tool. Most
of the options that can be used with the <command>lpadmin</command> command
are also available in Solaris Print Manager.</para><note><para>You must superuser equivalent privileges to gain access to some of the
options in Solaris Print Manager. Options and selectable attributes within
the tool can vary, depending on the user's role.</para>
</note><para>For a detailed description of all the printer definitions that you can
set or reset by using Solaris Print Manager, see <olink targetptr="set-attr1" remap="internal">Setting
Printer Definitions by Using Solaris Print Manager</olink>.</para><para>For step-by-step instructions on setting up new printers with Solaris
Print Manager, see <olink targetptr="printsetup-33230" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Setting
Up Printing Services (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ermlv"><title>Solaris Print Manager and Special Characters</title><para>Solaris Print Manager checks user input for the various text fields
in the input screens. There are two types of checking: general illegal input
and input that is illegal for specific fields.</para><itemizedlist><para>Solaris Print Manager does not accept the following characters as input,
except for the help screens:</para><listitem><para>Shell metacharacters, such as &ldquo;\$^&amp;*(){}`'|;:?&lt;&gt;,
except for the destination field on the network printer screen, which accepts
colons (:)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Multibyte characters</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Pound signs (#), spaces, or tabs, except the description field,
which accepts tabs</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="gfgyd"><title>Starting Solaris Print Manager</title><itemizedlist><para>To start Solaris Print Manager, use either of the following methods:</para><listitem><para>Select the Solaris LP Print Manager application in the GNOME
Desktop.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Type the appropriate command from the command line.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><task id="printsetup-6"><title>How to Start Solaris Print Manager</title><indexterm><primary>printers</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Solaris Print Manager</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>starting</primary>
</indexterm><procedure><step id="printsetup-step-1"><para><indexterm id="printsetup-ix264"><primary>Solaris Print Manager</primary><secondary>prerequisites for using</secondary></indexterm>Verify that the following prerequisites are met. To use Solaris
Print Manager, you must meet the following requirements: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Have a bitmapped display monitor, such as the standard display
monitor that comes with a Sun workstation. Solaris Print Manager can be used
only on a system with a console that is a bitmapped screen.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Be running an X Window System, such as the  GNOME Desktop Environment, or be using
the remote display feature on a system running an <command>xhost</command> environment.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Be logged in as superuser or an equivalent role on the print
server to install an attached or network printer, or on the print client to
add access to a printer.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Have the required access privileges for managing the LDAP,
NIS, or NIS+ database.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If your naming service is LDAP, you must have the following
items.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The distinguished name (DN) of a printer administrator and
password in the directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The name or IP address of an LDAP server hosting the administered
domain. This information is usually displayed and selected automatically.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>If your naming service is NIS, you must have the root password
for the NIS master.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you naming service is NIS+, you might need to complete
the following steps.</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Log in to the NIS+ master as superuser.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Identify the group that owns the printers table.</para><screen># <userinput>niscat -o printers.org_dir.</userinput><replaceable>domain-name</replaceable><userinput>.com</userinput>
            .
            .
            .
         Group		: "admin.<replaceable>domain-name</replaceable>.com"</screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>If necessary, add the system that runs Solaris Print Manager
to the NIS+ admin group authorized to update the <filename>printers.org_dir<?Pub
_bookmark Command="[Quick Mark]"?>.</filename><replaceable>&lt;domain&gt;</replaceable> file.</para><screen># <userinput>nisgrpadm -a admin.</userinput><replaceable>domain-name</replaceable><userinput>.com</userinput> <replaceable>hostname</replaceable></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>As superuser, log in to the system that runs Solaris Print
Manager. Your NIS+ configuration might make it necessary to run the <command>/usr/bin/keylogin</command> command. For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="keylogin-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>keylogin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Have the <literal>SUNWppm</literal> package installed.</para><screen># <userinput>pkginfo | grep SUNWppm</userinput>
system      SUNWppm        Solaris Print Manager</screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step id="printsetup-step-2"><para>Start Solaris Print Manager by using one
of the following methods:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Select the Solaris LP Print Manager in the GNOME Desktop.</para><para>System &rarr; Administration &rarr; Solaris LP Print Manager</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Type the following command:</para><screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/printmgr &amp;</userinput></screen><note><para>You can also start Solaris Print Manager by using the original
path of the <command>printmgr</command> command:</para><screen># <userinput>/usr/sadm/admin/bin/printgr &amp;</userinput></screen>
</note><para>The Select Naming Service window overlays the Solaris Print Manager
main window.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>If Solaris Print Manager fails to start from the GNOME Desktop menu or from
the command line, check the following:</para><listitem><para>Superuser (<literal>root</literal>) might not have permission
to connect to the X-server process on the local system or the remote system.
In this case, type the following:</para><screen>$ <userinput>ssh -X</userinput><replaceable>hostname</replaceable>
$ <userinput>su</userinput>
(<emphasis>Enter root's password</emphasis>)
# <userinput>/usr/sbin/printmgr &amp;</userinput></screen><para>Replace <replaceable>hostname</replaceable> with either the local system
name or the remote system name before restarting Solaris Print Manager.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Verify that the <literal>SUNWppm</literal> package is installed
on the local system or the remote system.</para><screen>$ <userinput>pkginfo | grep SUNWppm</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step id="printsetup-step-3"><para>Select the naming service that is used
in your network from the Select Naming Service window. The choices are: LDAP,
NIS, NIS+, or files.</para>
</step><step id="printsetup-step-4"><para>Check that the domain name is correct. </para><para>The Solaris Print Manager main menu is displayed after the naming service
is loaded successfully. </para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="geduc"><title>Setting Up the Internet Printing Protocol</title><indexterm><primary>IPP (Overview)</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP</primary><secondary>Apache Web Server</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Apache Web Server</primary><secondary>IPP</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP listening service</primary><secondary>Apache Web Server</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The IPP listening service provides an IPP network protocol service that
enables print client systems a means of interacting with a print service on
the system that is running the listener. This listener implements server-side
IPP protocol support, which includes a broad set of standard operations and
attributes. The listener is implemented on Solaris as an Apache module and
a series of shared libraries containing IPP operation and wire support. The
IPP software stack is installed when the Solaris OS is installed on the system.
The listening service is an SMF service that depends on the print service
to run. As a result, IPP is automatically enabled on a print server when the
first print queue has been added . It is also disabled when the last print
queue has been removed. If you make configuration changes, you will need to
restart the listener. For more information, see <olink targetptr="gedfg" remap="internal">How
to Restart the IPP Network Listening Service</olink>.</para><para>The IPP listening service implementation is embedded under the Apache
Web Server. The web server receives IPP operations through HTTP POST requests.
When an HTTP POST request is received it is passed on to the Apache IPP module
(<filename>mod_ipp.so</filename>). Based on configuration, the Apache Web
Service might provide an authentication service and it might also use encryption
between client and server. The listening service runs as it's own dedicated
instance of Apache.</para><para>IPP support in the Solaris OS is split into server-side and client-side
support. Both the server-side and client-side support share some common elements,
as well as elements that are unique to the client or server operation. As
a result, the IPP client and server components share a code base that implements
these common elements. Table <olink targetptr="geddv" remap="internal">Table&nbsp;A&ndash;1</olink> describes
the components that make up IPP support in the Solaris OS.</para><sect2 id="gedwa"><title>Configuring IPP Server and Client Data</title><indexterm><primary>configuring</primary><secondary>IPP server and client data</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP server and client configuration</primary>
</indexterm><para>The Apache configuration for this web server instance runs as the <literal>lp</literal> print service user, which provides enough privileges to support
all of the existing IPP operations, but limits access to print service specific
resources. The listening service runs as its own web server instance, specifically
configured to support IPP, which is intended to minimize potential security
risks.</para><para>On the server-side, IPP configuration changes are made to the <filename>/etc/apache/httpd-standalone-ipp.conf</filename> file.
On the client-side, IPP configuration changes are made to the <filename>/etc/printers.conf</filename> file.</para><note><para>If you make any configuration changes, you need to restart the
service to load the new configuration. For more information, see <olink targetptr="printadmin-29920" remap="internal">How to Restart the Print Scheduler</olink>.</para>
</note><para>The IPP listening service configuration file, <filename>/etc/apache/httpd-standalone-ipp.conf</filename>, is like any normal Apache 1.3 configuration file. The configuration
files takes any Apache 1.3 configuration directives that you want to use.</para><itemizedlist><para>The default configuration includes the following features: </para><listitem><para>Listening on port 631.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Loading of a minimal set of Apache modules.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Enabling all supported IPP operations at the <filename>/printers/</filename> path, for example <filename>ipp://server/printers/</filename>,
without requiring authentication.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The default operations that are enabled for<filename>/printers/</filename> is
limited to a set of operations that poses less of a security risk. However,
all operations are enabled at the <filename>/admin/</filename> path, for example <filename>ipp://server/admin/</filename>, with basic authentication required.</para><itemizedlist><para>The <command>mod_ipp</command> Apache configuration options to choose
from are:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ipp-conformance</emphasis> - Selects
the level of protocol checking. The default is automatic, allowing maximum
client interaction.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ipp-operation</emphasis> - Allows
you to selectively enable or disable IPP operation support for one more IPP
operations.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ipp-default-user</emphasis> - Selects
the user name to use when contacting the local print service.</para><para>The
default is <literal>lp</literal> user, which allows for more functional proxying.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ipp-default-service</emphasis> - Selects
the default print service where print requests are directed.</para><para>The
default is the <command>lpsched</command> daemon.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>Conformance checking types are:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Automatic </emphasis>&ndash; Only
check that the requested operation is supported by the protocol listener.
(default)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">1.0</emphasis> &ndash; Check that
the request conforms to IPP, 1.0</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">1.1</emphasis> &ndash; Check that
the request conforms to IPP, 1.1</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="gedwc"><title>IPP Keywords for Apache Web Server Configuration</title><indexterm><primary>keywords</primary><secondary>IPP</secondary><tertiary>Apache Web Server</tertiary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP keywords</primary><secondary>Apache Web Server configuration</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The following syntax is used for the IPP operations keywords:</para><para><replaceable>ipp-operation</replaceable> <replaceable>operation</replaceable> <replaceable>enable</replaceable> | <replaceable>disable</replaceable></para><para>For more information about the IPP operation keywords that are used
to configure the Apache Web Server, see <olink targetptr="gedvz" remap="internal">IPP Operation
Keywords</olink>.</para>
</sect2><task id="gedvx"><title>How to Configure IPP Server Data</title><indexterm><primary>IPP server configuration (How To)</primary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Open the <filename>/etc/apache/httpd-standalone-ipp.conf</filename> file
in a text editor.</para>
</step><step><para>Add the desired IPP server configuration data.</para><para>For
example:</para><screen>if mod_ipp is loaded User lp run as "lp"
URI: ipp://{host]/printers/{queue}
SetHandler application/ipp use mod_ipp for this location
ipp-conformance strict enable strict protocol checking (default)
ipp-operation all enable enable all supported operations</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gedut"><title>How to Configure IPP Client Data</title><indexterm><primary>IPP client configuration (How To)</primary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>Under PAPI support, the <literal>bsdaddr</literal> value (<literal>server,q</literal>) is converted to it's equivalent <literal>printer-uri-supported</literal> value
(<literal>lpd://server/printers/q</literal>), when the <literal>printer-uri-supported</literal> value is missing from the printers database. However, in some situations,
such as when there is a mix of client systems and the queue is on an IPP capable server, you might
need to manually configure this data.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Open the <filename>/etc/printers.conf</filename> file in a text
editor. Add the desired IPP client configuration data.</para><para>For example:</para><screen>/etc/printers.conf:queue: \
    :bsdaddr=server,queue,Solaris: \
    :printer-uri-supported=ipp\://server/printers/queue:</screen>
</step>
</procedure><taskrelated role="see-also"><para>For additional information about printing with IPP, <olink targetptr="fddwm" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;A, Using the Internet Printing Protocol</olink>.</para><para>For more information about administering printers by using IPP, see <olink targetptr="gedvp" remap="internal">Administering Printers by Using the Internet Printing Protocol
(Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</taskrelated>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfjfe"><title>Enabling and Disabling Printing Services (Task Map)</title><table frame="all" id="gfjgg"><title>Enabling and Disabling Printing Services:
Task Map</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Enable, disable, and restart the IPP network listening service through
the Service Management Facility (SMF).</para>
</entry><entry><para>The IPP listener provides server-side support for IPP. This service
is controlled by SMF. You can enable, disable, and restart the IPP network
listening service by using he <command>svcadm</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gedcs" remap="internal">How to Enable the IPP Network Listening Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gedcw" remap="internal">How to Disable the IPP Network Listening Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gedfg" remap="internal">How to Restart the IPP Network Listening Service</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Enable, disable, and restart the RFC-1179 network listening service
through SMF.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The RFC-1179 network listening service is controlled by SMF. You can
enable, disable, and restart the RFC-1179 network listening service by using
the <command>svcadm</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gedcu" remap="internal">How to Enable the RFC-1179 Network Listening
Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gedgj" remap="internal">How to Disable the RFC-1179 Network Listening
Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gedgl" remap="internal">How to Restart the RFC-1179 Network Listening
Service</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>You can enable, disable, and restart the SMB network service through
SMF.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Server-side support for the SMB network service is controlled by SMF
and is available through Samba. You can enable, disable, and restart the SMB
network listening service by using the <command>svcadm</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="smb-1" remap="internal">How to Enable the SMB Network Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="smb-2" remap="internal">How to Disable the SMB Network Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="smb-3" remap="internal">How to Restart the SMB Network Service</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1><sect1 id="gffff"><title>Administering Network Printing Services</title><para>Network services for the IPP, RFC-1179, and the SMB protocols
are managed by SMF. </para><itemizedlist><para>The FMRI descriptions for these printing services are as follows:</para><listitem><para>For the IPP listening service, the FMRI is <filename>svc:/application/print/ipp-listener</filename>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the RFC-1179 listening service, the FMRI is <command>svc:/application/print/rfc1179-listener</command>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the SMB network service (server-side support), the FMRI
is <filename>svc:/network/samba</filename> or <filename>svc:/network/wins</filename>.
This service is available through Samba.</para><para>For more information
about SMF services and using the <command>svcadm</command> command, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="hbrunlevels-25516" remap="external">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Services (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><task id="gedcs"><title>How to Enable the IPP Network Listening Service</title><indexterm><primary>IPP network service</primary><secondary>how to enable</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>how to enable IPP network service</primary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To enable the IPP network service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable application/print/ipp-listener</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gedcw"><title>How to Disable the IPP Network Listening Service</title><indexterm><primary>disabling IPP network service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP network service</primary><secondary>disabling</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To disable the IPP network service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable application/print/ipp-listener</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gedfg"><title>How to Restart the IPP Network Listening Service</title><indexterm><primary>restarting IPP network service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP network service</primary><secondary>restarting</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To restart the IPP network service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm restart application/print/ipp-listener</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gedcu"><title>How to Enable the RFC-1179 Network Listening Service</title><indexterm><primary>enabling RFC-1179 network service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>RFC-1179 network service</primary><secondary>enabling</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To enable the RFC-1179 network listening service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable application/print/rfc1179</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gedgj"><title>How to Disable the RFC-1179 Network Listening Service</title><indexterm><primary>disabling RFC-1179 network service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>RFC-1179 network service</primary><secondary>disabling</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To disable the RFC-1179 network service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable application/print/rfc1179</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gedgl"><title>How to Restart the RFC-1179 Network Listening Service</title><indexterm><primary>restarting the RFC-1179 network service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>RFC-1179 network service</primary><secondary>restarting</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To restart the RFC-1179 network service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm restart application/print/rfc1179</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="smb-1"><title>How to Enable the SMB Network Service</title><indexterm><primary>SMB network service</primary><secondary>how to enable</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>how to enable SMB network service</primary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To enable the SMB network service, type one of the following commands:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable application/print/samba</userinput></screen><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable application/print/wins</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="smb-2"><title>How to Disable the SMB Network Service</title><indexterm><primary>disabling IPP network service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>IPP network service</primary><secondary>disabling</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To disable the SMB network service, type one of the following
commands:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable application/network/samba</userinput></screen><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable application/network/wins</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="smb-3"><title>How to Restart the SMB Network Service</title><indexterm><primary>restarting SMB service</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>SMB network service</primary><secondary>restarting</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para><para>Roles
contain authorizations and privileged commands. For more information about
roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>To restart the SMB network service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm restart application/network/samba</userinput></screen><screen># <userinput>svcadm restart application/network/wins</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000039599 0?>