<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub UDT __target_1 _target?><?Pub UDT registeredtm trademark?><?Pub EntList bull rArr sect hyphen?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()chapter()chapter()?><chapter id="printdesktop-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="1"?><?Pub Tag
atict:user user="jonj" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="jh118764" fullname="Juanita Heieck"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="wsm"
fullname=""?><title>Setting Up and Administering Printers From the Desktop
(Tasks)</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes how to set up and manage printers by using the <trademark>OpenSolaris</trademark> Print Manager graphical user interface (GUI). For
more information about using the OpenSolaris Print Manager, see the online
help.</para><note><para>The OpenSolaris Print Manager GUI and the Solaris Print Manager
Java&hyphen;based GUI are two different applications. Both applications can
be accessed from the desktop and can be used to manage printers. Using Solaris
Print Manager requires superuser privileges. For information about using Solaris
Print Manager, see <olink targetptr="printadmin-15883" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Administering
Printers by Using Solaris Print Manager and LP Print Commands (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</note><itemizedlist><para>This is a list of information in this chapter:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ghopb" remap="internal">Introduction to the OpenSolaris Print
Manager</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfnqz" remap="internal">Managing Network Device Discovery
Services (Task Map)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ghola" remap="internal">Managing Printers and Printer Queues
(Task Map)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ghopy" remap="internal">Managing Printer Groups and Print
Jobs (Task Map)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ghphk" remap="internal">Managing Print Manager and Printer
Preferences (Task Map)</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information about how to set up printing services see <olink targetptr="printsetup-33230" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Setting Up Printing Services
(Tasks)</olink>.</para><para>For information about setting up printers, see <olink targetptr="printers-33230" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Setting Up Printers (Tasks)</olink></para><para>For information about how to administer printers after you have set
them up, see <olink targetptr="printadmin-15883" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Administering
Printers by Using Solaris Print Manager and LP Print Commands (Tasks)</olink>.</para><para>For overview information about printing services and printers, see <olink targetptr="printintro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1, Introduction to Printing in the Solaris
Operating System</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="ghopb"><title>Introduction to the OpenSolaris Print Manager</title><para>The OpenSolaris Print Manager application is a GUI that you can use
to manage local and remote printer queues, printer groups, and print jobs
from the desktop. Print Manager enables you to perform many aspects of printer
administration. You can launch the OpenSolaris Print Manager from the Main Menubar on
the desktop panel. See <olink targetptr="ghomo" remap="internal">Getting Started With the OpenSolaris
Print Manager</olink> for instructions.</para><para>When you launch the Print Manager application, the Print Manager window
opens. In some instances, you can open the Print Manager window by clicking
the panel notification icon that appears in the desktop panel or by choosing
Printers from the panel notification icon's context menu. From here, you can
create and manage printer queues, groups, and jobs, as well as view or change
printer preferences and perform searches. See <olink targetptr="ghoqr" remap="internal">About
the Print Manager Window</olink>.</para><para>When you plug a new USB printer into your computer, or when a new network
printer is discovered by the system, a notification is displayed on the desktop
and a configuration dialog automatically opens. This dialog allows you to
finish configuring the new printer. For more information about the auto&hyphen;discovery
feature, see <olink targetptr="ghorb" remap="internal">Adding Newly Discovered Printers From
the Desktop</olink>.</para><sect2 id="ghomp"><title>Common Tasks That You Can Perform With OpenSolaris
Print Manager</title><indexterm><primary>tasks you can perform with the OpenSolaris Print Manager</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</primary><secondary>task types</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para><emphasis role="strong">In an office:</emphasis></para><listitem><para>Add a new local or network printer</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Print to a preconfigured network printer.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Customize and change your printer settings.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Monitor your print jobs</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Cancel your print jobs</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para><emphasis role="strong">At home or on the road:</emphasis></para><listitem><para>At home, plug in and configure a USB printer.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>In the office, print to network printers, depending on your
location and the task.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>At customer site, identify and print to nearby network printer
with suitable capabilities.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>On the road, submit print jobs to an offline printer queue.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Monitor or cancel your print jobs</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfnqz"><title>Managing Network Device Discovery Services (Task
Map)</title><informaltable frame="all"><indexterm><primary>managing network device discovery</primary><secondary>enabling HAL add&hyphen;on module</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>automatic printer discovery</primary><secondary>managing HAL add&hyphen;on module</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>HAL add&hyphen;on module</primary><secondary>enabling and disabling (Task Map)</secondary>
</indexterm><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Initiate the HAL add-on module for network device discovery.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Before the system can actively scan the network for network&hyphen;attached
printers, you must first initiate the HAL add-on module that discovers devices
on a network. You can enable this service from the desktop or by using the <command>svcadm</command> command.</para>
</entry><entry><para> <olink targetptr="gfznn" remap="internal">How to Enable the Network Device Discovery
Service</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gfzng" remap="internal">How to Initiate the Network Device Discovery Services by Using SMF</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Obtain information about printers that are discovered by the system
by using the command line.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You might need to obtain information about printers that have been discovered
by your system. You can obtain this information by using the command line.
The output shows all of the devices that have been discovered by the system.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfnsb" remap="internal">How to Determine Which Printers Are Known to
the System</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><sect2 id="gievo"><title>How Auto&hyphen;Discovery of Devices Works</title><para>Discovery of devices, including printers, is accomplished through the
Hardware Abstraction Layer (HAL) device registry (database) component. HAL
uses D-BUS messaging to notify interested applications about changes to its
registry. <emphasis>D-BUS</emphasis> is a messaging bus that passes messages
between applications and broadcasts signals that interested applications are
able to detect. This messaging service is used by HAL and a number of other
applications. HAL provides the framework for device discovery and notification
of device configuration changes on a system. In the Solaris release, this
support has been extended to detecting printers that are added or removed
from a local system.</para><para>The HAL daemon, <command>hald</command>, provides a view of devices
that are attached to a local system. This view is updated automatically, as
a system's hardware configuration changes, by hotplugging or by other methods.
HAL's internal database, also called the <emphasis>HAL device tree</emphasis>,
is where device information is stored and maintained. HAL devices are uniquely
identified in the HAL database through a <emphasis>Universal Device Identifier</emphasis> (UDI).
This database is populated with properties of each device in the HAL database.</para><para>The automatic printing configuration feature works with the HAL daemon
by listening for <emphasis>sysevents</emphasis>. When a hotplug-capable printer
is added to a system, HAL creates a new node in the HAL device tree, as shown
in the following example:</para><screen remap="wide">/org/freedesktop/Hal/devices/pci_0_0/pci1022_74606/pci108e_534d_3_1/printer_2_0_if0/print</screen><para>When the device node has been successfully registered in the HAL database,
HAL signals interested applications that the device is available. Device removal
works similarly.</para><para> For more information about HAL, see <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/project/tamarack/" type="url"></ulink>.</para><para>The network device discovery components are standard  service interfaces
that are offered by classes of network&hyphen;attached devices. This module
is capable of actively scanning a network for new devices. The service is
directly controlled through the <command>svcadm</command> interface. For more
information, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="svcadm-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>svcadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page. <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="svcadm-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>svcadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.
To determine the device type, an active scan is performed through a Simple
Network Management Protocol version 1 (SNMPv1) broadcast. Be default, the
SNMP based network&hyphen;attached printer discovery service probes the network
for printers every 60 seconds. This property is configurable. See <olink targetptr="gholw" remap="internal">Configuring Auto-Discovery Settings for Network&hyphen;Attached Printers</olink>.
During this active scan, SNMP determines the device type by attempting to
connect to the device.</para><note><para>Only active device discovery is available in this Solaris OS.
Passive device discovery through the Multicast DNS (mDNS) is not available.</para>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="ghorb"><title>Adding Newly Discovered Printers From the Desktop</title><indexterm><primary>adding printers with the OpenSolaris Print Manager</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</primary><secondary>adding printers</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>HAL</primary><secondary>auto&hyphen;discovery of printers</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>auto&hyphen;discovery of printers</primary><secondary>HAL</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Hardware Abstraction Layer</primary><secondary>HAL</secondary>
</indexterm><para>You can use OpenSolaris Print Manager to configure newly discovered
directly attached or newly discovered network&hyphen;attached printers from
the desktop. By default, the system automatically discovers directly attached
USB printers. The system also discovers network&hyphen;attached printers,
if the network device discovery service has been enabled. See <olink targetptr="gfznn" remap="internal">How to Enable the Network Device Discovery Service</olink>.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Adding a Directly Attached USB Printer</emphasis></para><para>When a new USB printer is connected to the system and discovered , the
Add Printer Queue dialog, populated with printer configuration data, automatically
opens on the desktop. From here, you can modify the existing configuration
information and then create the new printer queue. After the new printer queue
is created, it appears in the Queue pane of the Print Manager window. For
more information, see <olink targetptr="ghoqw" remap="internal">How To Set Up Auto-Discovered
Printers by Using the OpenSolaris Print Manager</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Adding a Network&hyphen;Attached Printer</emphasis></para><para>Network&hyphen;attached printers are auto&hyphen;discovered the same
way as directly attached printers. This support is designed and implemented
through a HAL add-on module, <filename>/usr/lib/hal/hald-addon-network-discovery</filename>.
When a new network&hyphen;attached printer is discovered by the system, a
printer queue is automatically created. At the same time, a notification message
is displayed next to a printer icon located in the panel notification area
of the desktop. Clicking this notification message launches the OpenSolaris
Print Manager application. From here, you can view or change the configuration
data for the newly discovered network&hyphen;attached printer. To do so, select
the printer queue in the Queue pane of the Print Manager window and choose
Properties from the Printer menu. For more information, see <olink targetptr="ghoqw" remap="internal">How To Set Up Auto-Discovered Printers by Using the OpenSolaris
Print Manager</olink>.</para><itemizedlist><para>To utilize the network device discovery feature, the following conditions
must be met:</para><listitem><para>The network device discovery service, <filename>network/device-discovery/printers:snmp</filename>, must be enabled.</para><para>You can enable this service from
the desktop or by using SMF commands. For more information, see <olink targetptr="gfnqz" remap="internal">Managing Network Device Discovery Services (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Network&hyphen;attached printers must support SNMP queries,
which means the device must be &ldquo;known&rdquo; to the system.</para><para>For
more information, see <olink targetptr="gfnsb" remap="internal">How to Determine Which Printers
Are Known to the System</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Network-attached printers must be on the same subnet as the
system that is querying the network.</para><para>The service is not capable
of discovering network-attached printers that are more than one hop away.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>OpenSolaris Print Manager Preferences for desktop notifications
of network printing events must be turned on.</para><para>For more information,
see <olink targetptr="ggbqt" remap="internal">Managing Print Manager and Printer Preferences</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>In the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release, attempts to enable the HAL
add&hyphen;on module from the desktop or by using SMF commands, cause the
system to revert to maintenance state. This problem does not occur if you
are running a supported Solaris Express Community Edition release. To enable
this service in the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release, you must first install the
SUNWSmmgr package. For detailed instructions, go to <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/indiana/resources/relnotes/200811/x86/" type="url"></ulink>.</para>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="ghoqj"><title>Notification of Printing Events in the Desktop</title><indexterm><primary>notifications in the desktop</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>desktop notifications</primary><secondary>printer discovery</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer discovery</primary><secondary>desktop notifications</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>The panel notification icon is a printer icon that is displayed in panel
notification area of the desktop to notify you when:</para><listitem><para>One or more print jobs are processing</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>One or more printers have been discovered</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>To get more information, click the printer icon.</para><listitem><para>If one or more print jobs are processing normally, a Job List
window opens for each printer queue that has a pending print job.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If one or more printer queues have been discovered, the Printer
Queue Properties dialog or the Print Manager application opens, allowing you
to check the configuration of the new printer queues.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>Notification messages that are not manually closed disappear after
5 seconds.</para>
</note><para>Preferences for notification messages can be viewed and changed in the
Printer Preferences dialog. For more information, see <olink targetptr="ggbqt" remap="internal">Managing
Print Manager and Printer Preferences</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="gholb"><title>Panel Notification Icon Context Menu</title><indexterm><primary>panel notification icon</primary><secondary>context menu</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>context menu</primary><secondary>panel notification icon</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>menu</primary><secondary>panel notification icon</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The following table describes the menu items that are available when
you right-click the panel notification icon.</para><informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><?PubTbl tgroup dispwid="1161.00px"?><colspec colwidth="32.23*"/><colspec colwidth="33.77*"/><thead><row><entry><para>When Print Jobs Are Processing Normally</para>
</entry><entry><para>When Printers/Queues Are Discovered</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><emphasis role="strong">Show Queue:</emphasis> Opens a Job List window
for each queue in which you have a pending print job.</para>
</entry><entry><para><emphasis role="strong">Open Print Manager:</emphasis> opens the Print
Manager window, with the All Printers group selected, and all new queues selected
within the group.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><replaceable>queuename</replaceable> <emphasis role="strong">Properties:</emphasis> Opens
the associated Printer Properties window.</para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>queue&hyphen;name</replaceable> <emphasis role="strong">Properties:</emphasis> Opens the associated Printer Properties window. Hidden if more
than one new queue was discovered.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><emphasis role="strong">Print Manager Preferences:</emphasis> Opens
the Print Manager Preferences dialog.</para>
</entry><entry><para><emphasis role="strong">Print Manager Preferences:</emphasis> Opens
the Print Manager Preferences dialog.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>For more information about viewing or changes preferences for notifications,
see <olink targetptr="ggbqt" remap="internal">Managing Print Manager and Printer Preferences</olink>.</para>
</sect2><task id="gfznn"><title>How to Enable the Network Device Discovery Service</title><tasksummary><para>By default, the OpenSolaris Print Manager automatically discovers and
configures USB printers that are directly connected to your system. Print
Manager also has the ability to discover and configure printers that are on
a network after the network device discovery service has been enabled.</para><note><para>Note that in the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release, this service cannot
be enabled from the desktop until you install the SUNWSmmgr package. If you
attempt to enable the service before installing this package, the system reverts
to maintenance state. For detailed instructions, go to <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/indiana/resources/relnotes/200811/x86/" type="url"></ulink>.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>From the Main Menubar, select:</para><para>System-&gt; Administration-&gt;
Services</para><para>The Services settings window is displayed.</para>
</step><step><para>To initiate the device discovery add-on module, select the Hardware
Abstraction Layer network&hyphen;attached printer discovery (<literal>network/device-discovery/printers:snmp</literal>) option.</para>
</step><step><para>Save your changes.</para><para>To disable auto&hyphen;discovery
of devices, deselect this option.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfzng"><title>How to Initiate the Network Device Discovery Services
by Using SMF</title><indexterm><primary>initiating network device discovery</primary><secondary>using SMF</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>SMF</primary><secondary>using to initiate network device discovery</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>network device discovery</primary><secondary>how to initiate using SMF</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>device&hyphen;discovery/printers</filename></primary><secondary>initiating the service</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>This procedure describes how to initiate, as well as disable, the network <filename>device-discovery/printers</filename> service (the HAL add-on module) by using
the SMF.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Become superuser or assume an equivalent role.</para>
</step><step><para>Determine whether the SMF <filename>device-discovery/printers</filename> service
is online.</para><screen># <userinput>svcs device-discovery/printers</userinput></screen><para>If the service is online, the following output is displayed:</para><screen>STATE          STIME    FMRI
online         13:30:22 svc:/network/device-discovery/printers:snmp</screen><para>If the service is offline, the following output is displayed:</para><screen>STATE          STIME    FMRI
disabled       Dec_12   svc:/network/device-discovery/printers:snmp</screen>
</step><step><para>To enable or disable the service instance, use the appropriate
command.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To enable the service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm enable printers:snmp</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>To disable the service, type:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm disable printers:snmp</userinput></screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Verify that the HAL add-on module has been enabled or disabled.</para><para>If the module has been successfully enabled, the output is as follows:</para><screen># <userinput>svcs device-discovery/printers</userinput>
STATE          STIME    FMRI
online         13:30:22 svc:/network/device-discovery/printers:snmp </screen><para>If the module has been successfully disabled, the output is as follows:</para><screen># <userinput>svcs device-discovery/printers</userinput>
STATE          STIME    FMRI
disabled       Dec_12   svc:/network/device-discovery/printers:snmp</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfnsb"><title>How to Determine Which Printers Are Known to the System</title><indexterm><primary>obtaining information about discovered printers</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>discovered printers</primary><secondary>obtaining information from the command line</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure remap="single-step"><step><para>On the system that you want to get information about discovered
printers, type:</para><screen>system% <userinput>hal-find-by-capability --capability printer</userinput></screen><para>The output shows you all of the printers that have been discovered by
the system.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To obtain additional details about discovered printers, type:</para><screen>zsh% <userinput>for udi in $(hal-find-by-capability --capability printer) ;
do ; lshal --show $udi --long ; done</userinput></screen><para>Or, if you are using a shell that does not support the use of <userinput>$(<replaceable>command</replaceable>)</userinput>, type:</para><screen>sh% <userinput>for udi in `hal-find-by-capability --capability printer` ;
do ; lshal --show $udi --long ; done</userinput></screen>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure><example id="gfnrh"><title>Determining Which Printers Are Known to the System</title><para>This example shows all of the devices discovered by the system, <literal>snoopy</literal>.</para><screen remap="wide">snoopy% <userinput>hal-find-by-capability --capability printer</userinput>
/org/freedesktop/Hal/devices/pci_0_0/pci1022_7460_6/pci108e_534d_3_1/printer_2_printer_0
    snoopy%</screen>
</example><example id="gfohl"><title>Obtaining Additional Details about Printers That Are Known to the System</title><indexterm><primary>obtaining details about discovered printers </primary><secondary>example of</secondary>
</indexterm><screen remap="wide" width="100">    zsh% <userinput>for udi in $(hal-find-by-capability --capability printer) ; \
do ; lshal --show $udi --long ; done udi = \
'/org/freedesktop/Hal/devices/pci_0_0/pci1022_\
7460_6/pci108e_534d_3_1/printer_2_printer_0'</userinput>
      info.claimed.uid = 24656  (0x6050)  (int)
      info.claimed.service = 'gnome-volume-manager'  (string)
      info.claimed = true  (bool)
      printer.commandset = {'PJL', 'MLC', 'BIDI-ECP', 'PCLXL', 'PCL',
    'PDF', 'PJL', 'MIME', 'POSTSCRIPT'} (string list)
      printer.description = 'Hewlett-Packard color LaserJet 4650'  (string)
      printer.serial = '00000D920NSL'  (string)
      printer.product = 'hp color LaserJet 4650'  (string)
      printer.vendor = 'Hewlett-Packard'  (string)
      printer.device = '/dev/printers/1'  (string)
      info.capabilities = {'printer'} (string list)
      info.category = 'printer'  (string)
      info.solaris.driver = 'usbprn'  (string)
      solaris.devfs_path =
    '/pci@0,0/pci1022,7460@6/pci108e,534d@3,1/printer@2:printer'  (string)
      info.product = 'printer'  (string)
      info.udi =
    '/org/freedesktop/Hal/devices/pci_0_0/pci1022_7460_6/pci108e_534d_3_1/printer_2_printer_0'...)
      info.parent =
    '/org/freedesktop/Hal/devices/pci_0_0/pci1022_7460_6/pci108e_534d_3_1/printer_2_if0_0'...)

    zsh%</screen>
</example>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="ghola"><title>Managing Printers and Printer Queues (Task Map)</title><informaltable frame="all"><indexterm><primary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</primary><secondary>managing printers (task map)</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>managing printers and printer queues</primary><secondary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>setting up automatically discovered printers</primary><secondary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>setting up printers manually</primary><secondary>using OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer setup</primary><secondary>using OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Launch the OpenSolaris Print Manager GUI.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can set up and manage printer queues, printer groups, and print
jobs by using the OpenSolaris Print Manager. This application is accessible
from the desktop.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghomo" remap="internal">Getting Started With the OpenSolaris Print
Manager</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Configure newly discovered printers by using the OpenSolaris Print Manager.</para>
</entry><entry><para>When the system discovers a new printer, you are notified that the printer
has been discovered. In addition, the printer queue process begins. The Add
Printer Queue dialog enables you to check and change printer configuration
information. This dialog is displayed on the desktop when a new printer is
discovered.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghoqw" remap="internal">How To Set Up Auto-Discovered Printers by Using
the OpenSolaris Print Manager</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Manually set up printers by using the OpenSolaris Print Manager.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If, for any reason, a printer is not discovered by the system, you use
manually add the printer by using the OpenSolaris Print Manager.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghooi" remap="internal">How to Manually Add a Printer by Using the
OpenSolaris Print Manager</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Check or change preferences for an existing printer queue.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can view or change preferences for an existing printer queue by
using the OpenSolaris Print Manager.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghont" remap="internal">How to View or Change Printer Queue Properties</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Delete a printer queue.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can delete existing printer queues in the Queue pane of the Print
Manager window.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghoon" remap="internal">How to Delete a Printer Queue</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Pause or resume a printer queue.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can pause and resume printer queues in the Queue pane of the Print
Manager window.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghooj" remap="internal">How to Pause or Resume a Printer Queue</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="ghomo"><title>Getting Started With the OpenSolaris Print Manager</title><para>From theMain Menubar on the desktop panel, choose:</para><para>System &gt; Administration &gt; Print Manager</para><para>The Print Manager application launches, and the Print Manager window
opens.</para><sect2 id="ghoqr"><title>About the Print Manager Window</title><indexterm><primary>Print Manager window</primary><secondary>description of</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>description of the Print Manager window</primary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>The Print Manager window is divided into three panes: Queue, Group,
and Job.</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Queue Pane (Top right pane)</emphasis></para><para>Shows the printers and printer queues in the currently-selected group
and their current status. When you launch Print Manager, the Job pane for
the default printer queue is displayed. To display the Job pane for another
printer queue, select the printer in the Queue pane.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Group Pane (Left pane)</emphasis></para><para>Allows you to organize printers into arbitrary collections, or by criteria,
such as name, location, manufacturer and capability.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Job Pane (Bottom right pane when a
printer queue is selected)</emphasis></para><para>Shows the status of print
jobs in the currently-selected printer queue.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><tip><para>You can have more than one Print Manager window open at any given
time. Having more than one Print Manager window open at the same time can
be useful to compare the contents of different groups or to drag and drop
(move or copy) printer queues between various windows.</para>
</tip><itemizedlist><para>You can open a new Print Manager window in one of the following ways:</para><listitem><para>By choosing New Window from the View menu.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>By double-clicking a group in the Group pane.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>By right-clicking in the Group pane, then choosing Open in
New Window.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>When you close a single Print Manager window, any other open Print Manager
windows remain open until you manually close them or quit the Print Manager
application.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfnwy"><title>Setting Up Printers by Using the OpenSolaris Print
Manager</title><para>When you connect a new local USB printer to your computer, the printer
is auto-discovered, and the Add Printer Queue dialog opens automatically.
This dialog contains configuration information about the printer. If you choose,
you can provide additional configuration information for the printer in this
dialog.</para><para>The Add Printer Queue dialog allows you to check or change the configuration
information for a <emphasis>newly discovered</emphasis> local or network printer.
You can also use this dialog to manually add a printer that, for any reason,
was not automatically discovered.</para><para>The Add Printer Queue dialog is opened from the Printer menu or by clicking
the Add icon on the toolbar. The Add Printer Queue dialog looks and behaves
almost the same as the Printer Queue Properties dialog, with a few minor differences. </para><note><para>In the Print Manager Preferences dialog, you can turn off the
automatic appearance of the configuration dialog when you connect a new local
USB printer.</para>
</note><para>When a new network printer is auto-discovered, a printer queue is automatically
created for the new printer. At the same time, a notification message appears
on the desktop in the panel notification area. Clicking the message launches
Print Manager. From here, you can customize the configuration information
for the new network printer queue.</para><para>To enable the automatic detection of network printers, first select
the Auto-detect network printers option in the Network tab of the Print Manager
Preferences dialog.</para><task id="ghoqw"><title>How To Set Up Auto-Discovered Printers by Using the
OpenSolaris Print Manager</title><tasksummary><para>Use this procedure to complete the setup of a new <emphasis>local</emphasis> or
a new <emphasis>network</emphasis> printer queue that has been auto-discovered.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>To configure the new printer queue, enter all the appropriate
information for the printer in the dialog.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ospm-add-filled" width="100"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Graphic of the Add Printer Queue dialog that contains
preconfigured settings for a new directly attached or new network&hyphen;attached
printer.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><substeps><step><para>In the Connection section of the dialog, select the connection
type from the drop-down menu.</para><para>If you are adding a local printer
queue, the connection type is Local Device.</para>
</step><step><para>Enter the name or IP address of the print server. (Applies to
network printer queues only)</para>
</step>
</substeps><note><para>For a local printer queue, no print server or IP address is required.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>In the Printer Details section of the dialog, enter all the appropriate
information.</para>
</step><step><para>To set the printer queue as the default, select the Set as default
printer queue check box.</para>
</step><step><para>To add the new printer queue, click Add.</para><para>The new printer
queue is displayed in the Queue pane of the Print Manager window.</para>
</step><step performance="optional"><para>To print a test page, click the Print Test
Page button.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ghooi"><title>How to Manually Add a Printer by Using the OpenSolaris
Print Manager</title><tasksummary><para>Use this procedure to <emphasis>manually</emphasis> add a new printer
queue for a local or a network printer, if for some reason, the printer is
not auto-discovered.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>From the Printer Menu, choose Add Printer Queue.</para><para>The
Add Printer Queue dialog opens.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ospm-add-empty" width="100"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Graphic of the Add Printer Queue dialog that contains
preconfigured settings for a new directly attached or new network&hyphen;attached
printer.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</step><step><para>To configure the new printer queue, enter all the appropriate
information for the printer in the dialog:</para><substeps><step><para>In the Connection section of the dialog, select the connection
type from the drop-down menu.</para><para>If you are adding a local printer
queue, the connection type is Local Device.</para>
</step><step><para>Enter the name or IP address of the print server. (Applies to
network printer queues only)</para>
</step>
</substeps><note><para>For local printer queues, no print server or IP address is required.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>In the Printer Details section of the dialog, enter all the appropriate
information.</para>
</step><step><para>To set the printer as the default, select the Set Printer as Default
checkbox.</para>
</step><step><para>To add the printer queue, click Add.</para><para>The new printer
queue is displayed in the Queue pane of the Print Manager window.</para>
</step><step performance="optional"><para>To print a test page, click the Print Test
Page button.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><sect2 id="ghopj"><title>Managing Printer Queues</title><indexterm><primary>printers queues</primary><secondary>how to manage</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>managing printer queues</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>queues</primary><secondary>managing</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Print Manager for OpenSolaris</primary><secondary>managing printer queues</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The Print Manager Queue pane lists all the printers in the currently
selected group. You can manage printer queues in the Queue pane of the Print
Manager window or from the application's Printer menu.</para><para>The Queue pane shows the type, name, and current status of each printer
queue. The default printer queue is marked, if the queue is in the currently-selected
group. Double-clicking a printer queue icon opens its job list in a new Job
List window, where you can view the status of any pending print jobs.</para><para>From the View menu, you can choose to view the printer queues in the
Queue pane as icons or as a list.</para><para>From the Sort by menu item, you can choose from the following sort options:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Name</term><listitem><para>Sorts printer queues by name, in the locale's sort order.
This is the default sort order.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Description</term><listitem><para>Sorts printer queues by description, in the locale's alphabetical
order.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Status</term><listitem><para>Sorts printer queues by Ready printers first (alphabetical),
then by printers with one or more pending print jobs.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Number of Jobs</term><listitem><para>Sorts printer queues by number of pending print jobs, from
lowest to highest.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2><task id="ghont"><title>How to View or Change Printer Queue Properties</title><indexterm><primary>changing printer queue properties</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer queue properties</primary><secondary>changing</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>queue properties</primary><secondary>how to change</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer queue properties dialog</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>dialogs</primary><secondary>printer queue properties</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>The properties dialog for a printer queue allows you to edit the properties
of an <emphasis>existing</emphasis> printer queue. Open this dialog from the
Properties menu item in the Printer menu. This dialog looks and behaves almost
the same as the Add Printer Queue dialog.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>In the Queue pane, select the printer queue in which to view or
change properties.</para>
</step><step><para>From the Printer menu, choose Properties.</para><para>The properties
dialog for the printer queue is displayed.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ospm_queueprop_dialog"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Graphic of the printer queue properties dialog, which
is used to check or modify properties of an existing printer queue.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><stepalternatives><step><para>You can also right-click the printer, then choose Properties from
the popup menu that is shown.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>To change settings for the printer queue, type or select the new
information, then click OK.</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Type</term><listitem><para>Connection type: Internet Printing Protocol (IPP), Remote
IPP, Line Printer Daemon (LPD), Remote LPD, Socket or Local Device</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Printer Name or IP</term><listitem><para>Hostname or IP address of the remote printer. (IPP, LPD, Socket
only)</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Print Server</term><listitem><para>Hostname or IP address of the print server. (Remote IPP, Remote
LPD only)</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Queue Name</term><listitem><para>Name of the remote printer queue. (IPP, Remote IPP, LPD, Remote
LPD only) </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Port</term><listitem><para>Port number through which to communicate with the printer
queue, default = 9100. (Socket only)</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Device</term><listitem><para>Path to the local printer device, default = <filename>/dev/printers/0</filename>. (Local Device only)</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Local queue name</term><listitem><para>Local name for the printer queue.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Description</term><listitem><para>Optional text description of the printer queue.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Manufacturer</term><listitem><para>List of printer manufacturers for which PostScript Printer
Description (PPD) files are installed.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Model</term><listitem><para>List of printer models that are available for the selected
manufacturer.</para><note><para>The printer manufacturer and model is discovered. If the exact
model is not available, a similar model is provided.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Driver</term><listitem><para>List of drivers that are available for the selected printer
model.</para><para>Note that this field is blank until you have entered the minimum amount
of information about the printer queue.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>To print a test page, click the Print Test Page button.</para><para>To add the printer queue, click the OK button.</para><para>To set the printer queue as the default in the application print dialogs,
select the Set as default printer queue checkbox.</para><note><para>Some printer queue settings cannot be changed after a printer
queue has been created.</para>
</note>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ghoon"><title>How to Delete a Printer Queue</title><indexterm><primary>deleting printer queues</primary><secondary>how to</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer queue</primary><secondary>how to delete</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Print Manager for OpenSolaris</primary><secondary>deleting printer queues</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>To permanently delete a printer queue, you must first select the All
Printers group in the Group pane. If you delete a printer queue when another
printer group is selected, the queue is deleted <emphasis>only</emphasis> from
that printer group.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>In the Group pane of the Print Manager window, select the All
Printers group.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To delete a printer queue from a specific printer group <emphasis>only</emphasis>, select the group from which to delete the queue.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>In the Queue pane, select the printer queue that you want to delete.</para>
</step><step><para>From the Edit menu, choose Delete.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>You can also right-click the printer, then choose Delete from
the submenu that is shown.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>To delete the printer, click Yes in the confirmation alert that
is displayed. To cancel the operation, click No.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ghooj"><title>How to Pause or Resume a Printer Queue</title><indexterm><primary>pausing a printer queue</primary><secondary>how to</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer queue</primary><secondary>pausing and resuming</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>resuming a printer queue</primary><secondary>how to</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>Pausing a printer queue suspends the processing of any documents for
the queue.</para><note><para>You can only pause printer queues that you own.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>In the Queue pane, select the printer queue you want to pause.</para>
</step><step><para>From the Printer menu, choose Pause.</para><para>The queue icon
and status text are updated to indicate the queue is online, but that processing
of the queue has been paused.</para>
</step><step><para>To resume processing of the printer queue, from the Printer menu,
choose Resume.</para><para>The Resume menu item is only available when a printer
queue is paused.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="ghopy"><title>Managing Printer Groups and Print Jobs (Task Map)</title><indexterm><primary>printer groups</primary><secondary>how to manage (Task Map)</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>print jobs</primary><secondary>how to manage (Task Map)</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>managing printer groups and print jobs</primary><secondary>how to</secondary>
</indexterm><table frame="all" id="ghomz"><title>Managing Printer Groups and Print Jobs
by Using the OpenSolaris Print Manager</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Create a new printer group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can create custom printer groups that contain printers that meet
various criteria. Printer groups are created and managed in the Group pane
of the Print Manager window.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghoov" remap="internal">How to Create a New Printer Group</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Create a new search group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Search groups are printer groups that you create, based on the results
of a search.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gholl" remap="internal">How to Create a New Search Group</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Create a new search group from filtered data.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can create a new search group by using a filter in the Queue Pane
of the Print Manager. A search group created in this manner contains only
those printers that meet the search criteria for the filter.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghoqk" remap="internal">How to Create a New Search Group by Using a
Queue Pane Filter</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>View or change properties of an existing search group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can view or change the properties of an existing search group that
you created.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghpgo" remap="internal">How to View or Change an Existing Search Group's
Properties</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Delete a printer group.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can use the OpenSolaris Print Manager to delete printer groups that
you have created. Printer groups are managed in the Group pane of the Print
Manager window.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghoqs" remap="internal">How to Delete a Printer Group</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Delete a print job.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Print jobs can be managed and deleted in the Job pane of the Print Manager
window.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghoqe" remap="internal">How to Delete a Print Job</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1><sect1 id="ghpbd"><title>Managing Printer Groups</title><indexterm><primary>types of printer groups</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer group types</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Print Manager for OpenSolaris</primary><secondary>printer group types</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Print Manager has three types of printer groups:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>System groups</term><listitem><para>These groups cannot be created or deleted. However you can
edit the contents of these groups. By default, there are two system groups,
All Printers and Favorites. </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>All Printers</para><para>This group contains all the printer
queues that are currently known to the system. All other groups are views
of the All Printers group. </para><para>To delete a printer queue permanently, you must delete it from the All
Printers group. Deleting a printer queue from another group only removes the
queue from that group. The printer queue remains on the system until it is
deleted from the All Printers group.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Favorites</para><para>You can use the Favorites group to store
the printer queues that you use most often.</para><note><para>When you print a document from an application, only the printer
queues in your Favorites group are shown in the application's Print dialog.
 If your Favorites group is empty, the printer queues in the All Printers
group are shown in the application's Print dialog instead.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Regular groups</term><listitem><para>These groups are named groups to which you can copy or drag
any printer that is known to the system.  For example, you might have a Home
or an Office printer group.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Search groups</term><listitem><para>These groups contain the results of searches that you perform.
 The contents of search groups are updated dynamically.  For example, when
a new local printer is connected, or a new network printer is discovered,
its printer queue is automatically added to all of the search groups that
have matching search criteria.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><task id="ghoov"><title>How to Create a New Printer Group</title><indexterm><primary>printer group</primary><secondary>creating</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>creating a printer group</primary><secondary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>From the Group menu, choose New Group.</para><para>A new group
with the default name, <literal>Untitled N</literal>, is created in the Group
pane of the Print Manager window.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To create a new printer group by using a keyboard shortcut, press <command>Ctrl+N</command></para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Type a name for the new group.</para>
</step><step><para>Press <command>Enter</command> to save the new group name. Press <command>Esc</command> to revert to the original name.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gholl"><title>How to Create a New Search Group</title><procedure><step><para>From the Group menu, choose New Search Group.</para><para>A new
search group with the default name, <literal>Untitled N</literal>, is created
in the Group pane.</para><para>The New Search Group dialog opens.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To create a new search group by using the toolbar, click the New
Search Group button.</para>
</step><step><para>To create a new search group by using a keyboard shortcut, press <command>Ctrl+S</command>.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>In the Search Group Properties dialog:</para><substeps><step><para>Enter the name of the search group in the Group name field.</para>
</step><step><para>Choose whether you want to include printer queues that match any
or all of your search terms by using the Show printers that match buttons.</para>
</step><step><para>From the drop-down menus, select how you would like to search.</para>
</step><step><para>To enter any additional search terms, click the Add ( <literal>+</literal>)
button.</para><para>If additional search terms are provided, the Remove (<literal>-</literal>) button is visible. To delete an entire search term (row), click
the Remove (<literal>-</literal>) button.</para>
</step><step><para>To create the new search group, click OK.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ghoqk"><title>How to Create a New Search Group by Using a Queue
Pane Filter</title><indexterm><primary>search group</primary><secondary>how to create</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>creating a search group</primary><secondary>using a Queue pane filter</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Queue pane filter</primary><secondary>using to create a search group</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>In the Group pane, select a group that includes all of the printer
queues you want to include in the new search group.</para>
</step><step><para>Filter the Queue pane view by using the filter box that is located
in the toolbar.</para>
</step><step><para>From the filter box drop-down menu, select Save Filter as Search
Group.</para><para>A new search group with the default name you entered is
created in the Group pane.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ghpgo"><title>How to View or Change an Existing Search Group's Properties</title><indexterm><primary>group properties</primary><secondary>how to change</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>changing group properties</primary><secondary>how to</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>search group properties</primary><secondary>changing</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>In the Group pane, select the search group.</para>
</step><step><para>From the Group menu, choose Properties.</para><para>The Search
Group Properties dialog is displayed, allowing you to view or change the properties
of the search group.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To change the name of search group, enter the new name in the
Group name field.</para>
</step><step><para>Make any necessary changes to the search criteria.</para>
</step><step><para>To provide additional search terms, click the Add (<literal>+</literal>)
button.</para><para>If you provided additional search terms that you want
to delete, the Remove (<literal>-</literal>) button is visible. To delete
a search term (entire row), click the Remove (<literal>-</literal>) button.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>To save your changes, click OK.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ghoqs"><title>How to Delete a Printer Group</title><indexterm><primary>printer group</primary><secondary>deleting</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>deleting a printer group</primary><secondary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>You can delete printer groups and search groups that you have created.</para><note><para>You cannot delete the All Printers or the Favorites groups.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>In the Group pane, select the group that you want to delete.</para>
</step><step><para>From the Edit menu, choose Delete.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To delete a group by using the toolbar option, click the Delete
button.</para>
</step><step><para>To delete a group by using a keyboard shortcut, press the <command>Delete</command> key.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>To permanently delete the group, click Yes in the confirmation
alert that is displayed. To cancel, click No.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="ghooh"><title>Managing Print Jobs</title><indexterm><primary>managing print jobs</primary><secondary>description</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>print jobs</primary><secondary>managing</secondary>
</indexterm><para>You can manage print jobs in the Job pane of the Print Manager window.</para><note><para>The Job pane is shown <emphasis>only</emphasis> if a single printer
queue is selected in the Queue pane. If multiple queues are selected, the <interface>Job</interface> pane is automatically hidden. The pane reappears when you
select a single printer queue again.</para>
</note><para>The <emphasis>job list</emphasis> for any printer queue can be opened
in a separate Job List window.  To open a Job List window for a particular
printer queue, double-click the printer queue icon.</para><para>The Job pane and Job List windows are automatically updated every few
seconds.  You can also manually update the Job pane and the Job List window
by selecting Refresh from the View menu or by clicking the Refresh button
on the toolbar.</para><para>The Job List window allows you to view a list of print jobs that are
currently queued for printing. You can open the Job List window by double-clicking
a queue in the Queue Pane or by clicking the panel notification icon when
one or more print jobs are processing normally. You can also open the window
from the Print Manager window by choosing View &gt; Job List Only.</para><para>By default, when the Print Manager window opens, the Job pane for the
default printer is shown. To view print jobs for another printer queue, select
the printer queue whose jobs you want to view. The Job pane for the printer
queue you selected is displayed. To view the job list only, click the Job
List Only icon on the toolbar.</para><task id="ghoqe"><title>How to Delete a Print Job</title><indexterm><primary>deleting a print job</primary><secondary>using OpenSolaris Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>job</primary><secondary>deleting with Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>print job</primary><secondary>how to delete</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>In the Queue pane, select the printer queue that is processing
the print job you want to delete.</para><para>The Job pane for the selected
printer queue is displayed.</para>
</step><step><para>In the Job pane, select the print job that you want to delete.</para>
</step><step><para>From the Edit menu, choose Delete.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To delete a print job by using the toolbar, click the Delete button.</para>
</step><step><para>To delete a print job by using a keyboard shortcut, press <command>Delete</command>.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>To delete the print job, click Yes in the confirmation alert that
is displayed. To leave the print job in the queue, click No.</para><note><para>You can only delete your own print jobs or print jobs from printer
queues that you own.</para>
</note>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="ghphk"><title>Managing Print Manager and Printer Preferences (Task
Map)</title><informaltable frame="all"><indexterm><primary>OpenSolaris Print Manager</primary><secondary>managing printer preferences with (Task Map)</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>managing print manager and printer preferences</primary><secondary>Print Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer preferences</primary><secondary>managing</secondary>
</indexterm><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec colwidth="33*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>View or change preferences for Print Manager.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Behavior of the Print Manager application is set in the Print Manager
tab of the Printer Preference dialog. You can change certain default settings
for the application in this dialog.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghomq" remap="internal">Setting Print Manager Preferences</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Configure preferences for local USB printer discovery.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The Local tab of the Printer Preferences dialog is where preferences
for how directly attached printers are auto&hyphen;discovered is located.
You can view or change some of these settings.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghomh" remap="internal">Setting Preferences for Local USB Printer Discovery</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Configure preferences for network&hyphen;attached printer discovery.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The Network tab of the Printer Preferences dialog is where preferences
for how network&hyphen;attached printers are auto&hyphen;discovered is located.
You can view or change some of these settings.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ghonn" remap="internal">Settings Preferences for Network&hyphen;Attached Printer Discovery</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="ggbqt"><title>Managing Print Manager and Printer Preferences</title><itemizedlist><para>You can view or edit Print Manager preferences in one of the following
ways:</para><listitem><para>If the Print Manager application choose Preferences from the
Edit menu.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If the Print Manager application is <emphasis>not</emphasis> open,
from the Main Menubar, select System &gt; Preferences &gt; Printers.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The Print Manager Preferences dialog is displayed, allowing you set
preferences for Print Manager behavior, as well as settings for local and
remote printer queues.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ospm-prefs-pm"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Graphic displaying Print Manager preferences window,
with the Print Manager tab shown.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><para>The Print Manager Preferences dialog contains the following three tabs:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Print Manager</term><listitem><para>Controls the behavior of the Print Manager application.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Local Printers</term><listitem><para>Controls auto&hyphen;discovery, print queue configuration,
and notification preferences for local printers.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Network Printers</term><listitem><para>Controls auto&hyphen;discovery, notification, and group preferences
for network&hyphen;attached printers.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><sect2 id="ghomq"><title>Setting Print Manager Preferences</title><indexterm><primary>Print Manager behavior</primary><secondary>how to change</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>default behavior for Print Manager</primary><secondary>changing</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>preferences for Print Manager</primary><secondary>how to change</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The Print Manager tab controls the behavior of the Print Manager application.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Notifications</para><para>This setting controls the panel
notification icon that is displayed in the desktop panel. By default, Auto-hide
printer icon from notification area is enabled. To disable notifications,
deselect the checkbox. You can also change the number of seconds the icon
is displayed before it is hidden. The default is 5 seconds.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Unavailable printers</para><para>This setting controls Print
Manager behavior when a printer queue becomes unavailable. By default, unavailable
printer queues are shown and marked as offline in the Queue pane. If you want
to hide unavailable printer queues in the Queue pane, choose this setting
instead.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ghomh"><title>Setting Preferences for Local USB Printer Discovery</title><indexterm><primary>local USB printer discovery</primary><secondary>setting preferences for</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>preferences for local USB printer discovery</primary><secondary>setting</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The Local Printers tab controls the behavior of local printers.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ospm-prefs-local"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Graphic showing the local tab of the Print Manager Preferences
dialog.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><para>You can change the following preferences:</para><itemizedlist><para>When a new printer is connected:</para><listitem><para>Show Printer Properties window</para><para>This setting is
the default. If unchecked, a panel notification icon and message is displayed
for a few seconds. From here, you can click the icon to open the Printer Queue
Properties dialog.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>When a printer is disconnected:</para><listitem><para>Show notification message</para><para>Check this setting to
receive a notification message when a local printer goes offline. Otherwise,
you will not receive any notification.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>When a printer is reconnected:</para><listitem><para>Ask before printing pending documents</para><para>If this
setting is selected, when a local printer is reconnected, and its printer
queue contains any documents to be printed, the queue is paused and an alert
is shown.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ghonn"><title>Settings Preferences for Network&hyphen;Attached
Printer Discovery</title><indexterm><primary>network printer discovery</primary><secondary>setting preferences for</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>preferences for network&hyphen;attached printer discovery</primary><secondary>setting</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The Network Printers tab of the Print Preferences dialog controls the
Print Manager application's behavior when a network&hyphen;attached printer
is auto&hyphen;discovered and preconfigured.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ospm-prefs-net"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Graphic showing the Network tab of the OpenSolaris Print
Manager application's Preferences dialog.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><itemizedlist><para>You can change the following settings:</para><listitem><para>Auto-detect network printers</para><para>If this setting is
selected, the network is scanned periodically for new printer queues, according
to the settings in the Configuration sub-dialog.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Show new printer notification messages:</para><para>The two
options for this setting are Immediately or Never.</para><para>Choose Immediately if you want to see a panel notification message when
a network printer is discovered.  Choose Never if you prefer to receive no
message when a network printer is discovered.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Add discovered printers to:</para><para>All printers group
only &ndash; If selected, all new network printer queues are only be added
to the All Printers group in Print Manager.</para><para>All printers group and &ndash; Contains a drop-down list with all the
regular groups, plus the Favorites group.</para><para>If selected, all new network printer queues are added to the All Printers
group and an additional group of your choice.  You can select the additional
group from the drop-down list.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="gholw"><title>Configuring Auto-Discovery Settings for Network&hyphen;Attached
Printers</title><indexterm><primary>auto&hyphen;discovery settings</primary><secondary>network printers</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>configuring settings</primary><secondary>auto&hyphen;discovery of network printers</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>network printers</primary><secondary>configuring auto&hyphen;discovery settings</secondary>
</indexterm><para>This sub-dialog contains settings that control the type of network printers
that are discovered and the parameters for doing so.</para><para>By default, the Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) service is
available. You might need to enable this service, depending on the Solaris
release you are running. Any other available print services will be listed
here.</para><note><para>In the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release, attempts to enable the HAL
add&hyphen;on module from the desktop or by using SMF commands, cause the
system to revert to maintenance state. This problem does not occur if you
are running a supported Solaris Express Community Edition release. To enable
this service in the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release, you must first install the
SUNWSmmgr package. Detailed instructions can be found at <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/indiana/resources/relnotes/200811/x86/" type="url"></ulink>.</para>
</note><para>The controls on the right-hand side of the configuration sub-dialog
are dictated according to the service that is selected in the list. Some services
may have advanced controls in the form of an expander section. The expander
is collapsed by default.</para><para>The ability to edit some of these controls requires certain Role-Based
Access Control (RBAC) privileges. If you are not logged in with the appropriate
RBAC privileges, the controls are visible, but they are read-only.  To find
out what you or your system administrator need to do to allow the editing
of these controls, click the Details button.</para><para>For instructions, see <olink targetptr="gfznn" remap="internal">How to Enable the Network Device Discovery Service</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000071984 0?>