<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><chapter id="chp-stab"><title>Stability</title><highlights><para>Sun often provides developers with early access to new technologies
as well as observability tools that allow users to peer into the internal
implementation details of user and kernel software. Unfortunately, new technologies
and internal implementation details are both prone to changes as interfaces
and implementations evolve and mature when software is upgraded or patched.
Sun documents application and interface stability levels using a set of labels
described in the <olink targetdoc="refman5" targetptr="attributes-5" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>attributes</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page to help set user expectations for what kinds of changes might occur in
different kinds of future releases.</para><para>No one stability attribute appropriately describes the arbitrary set
of entities and services that can be accessed from a D program. DTrace and
the D compiler therefore include features to dynamically compute and describe
the stability levels of D programs you create. This chapter discusses the
DTrace features for determining program stability to help you design stable
D programs. You can use the DTrace stability features to inform you of the
stability attributes of your D programs, or to produce compile-time errors
when your program has undesirable interface dependencies.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="chp-stab-1"><title>Stability Levels</title><para><indexterm><primary>stability</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>levels</secondary></indexterm>DTrace provides two types
of stability attributes for entities such as built-in variables, functions,
and probes: a <firstterm>stability level</firstterm> and an architectural <firstterm>dependency class</firstterm>. The DTrace stability level assists you in making
risk assessments when developing scripts and tools based on DTrace by indicating
how likely an interface or DTrace entity is to change in a future release
or patch. The DTrace dependency class tells you whether an interface is common
to all Solaris platforms and processors, or whether the interface is associated
with a particular architecture such as SPARC processors only. The two types
of attributes used to describe interfaces can vary independently.</para><para><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary></indexterm>The stability values used by DTrace appear in the following list
in order from lowest to highest stability. The more stable interfaces can
be used by all D programs and layered applications because Sun will endeavor
to ensure that these continue to work in future minor releases. Applications
that depend only on Stable interfaces should reliably continue to function
correctly on future minor releases and will not be broken by interim patches.
The less stable interfaces allow experimentation, prototyping, tuning, and
debugging on your current system, but should be used with the understanding
that they might change incompatibly or even be dropped or replaced with alternatives
in future minor releases.</para><para>The DTrace stability values also help you understand the stability of
the software entities you are observing, in addition to the stability of the
DTrace interfaces themselves. Therefore, DTrace stability values also tell
you how likely your D programs and layered tools are to require corresponding
changes when you upgrade or change the software stack you are observing.</para><variablelist termlength="narrow"><varlistentry><term>Internal</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>internal stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>internal</tertiary></indexterm>The interface is private to DTrace
and represents an implementation detail of DTrace. Internal interfaces might
change in minor or micro releases.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Private</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>private stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>private</tertiary></indexterm>The interface is private to Sun and
represents an interface developed for use by other Sun products that is not
yet publicly documented for use by customers and ISVs. Private interfaces
might change in minor or micro releases.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Obsolete</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>obsolete stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>obsolete</tertiary></indexterm>The interface is supported in the
current release but is scheduled to be removed, most likely in a future minor
release. When support of an interface is to be discontinued, Sun will attempt
to provide notification before discontinuing the interface. The D compiler
might produce warning messages if you attempt to use an Obsolete interface.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>External</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>external stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>external</tertiary></indexterm>The interface is controlled by an
entity other than Sun. At Sun's discretion, Sun can deliver updated and possibly
incompatible versions of such interfaces as part of any release, subject to
their availability from the controlling entity. Sun makes no claims regarding
either source or binary compatibility for External interfaces between any
two releases. Applications based on these interfaces might not work in future
releases, including patches that contain External interfaces.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Unstable</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>unstable stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>unstable</tertiary></indexterm>The interface is provided to give
developers early access to new or rapidly changing technology or to an implementation
artifact that is essential for observing or debugging system behavior for
which a more stable solution is anticipated in the future. Sun makes no claims
about either source or binary compatibility for Unstable interfaces from one
minor release to another.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Evolving</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>evolving stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>evolving</tertiary></indexterm>The interface might eventually become
Standard or Stable but is still in transition. Sun will make reasonable efforts
to ensure compatibility with previous releases as it evolves. When non-upward
compatible changes become necessary, they will occur in minor and major releases.
These changes will be avoided in micro releases whenever possible. If such
a change is necessary, it will be documented in the release notes for the
affected release, and when feasible, Sun will provide migration aids for binary
compatibility and continued D program development.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Stable</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>stable stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>stable</tertiary></indexterm>The interface is a mature interface under Sun's control. Sun will
try to avoid non-upward-compatible changes to these interfaces, especially
in minor or micro releases. If support of a Stable interface must be discontinued,
Sun will attempt to provide notification and the stability level changes to
Obsolete.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Standard</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>standard stability value</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>values</secondary><tertiary>standard</tertiary></indexterm>The interface complies with an industry
standard. The corresponding documentation for the interface will describe
the standard to which the interface conforms. Standards are typically controlled
by a standards development organization, and changes can be made to the interface
in accordance with approved changes to the standard. This stability level
can also apply to interfaces that have been adopted without a
formal standard by an industry convention. Support is provided for only the
specified versions of a standard; support for later versions is not guaranteed.
If the standards development organization approves a non-upward-compatible
change to a Standard interface that Sun decides to support, Sun will announce
a compatibility and migration strategy.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-stab-2"><title>Dependency Classes</title><para><indexterm><primary>dependency classes</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary></indexterm>Since Solaris and
DTrace support a variety of operating platforms and processors, DTrace also
labels interfaces with a <firstterm>dependency class</firstterm> that tells
you whether an interface is common to all Solaris platforms and processors,
or whether the interface is associated with a particular system architecture.
The dependency class is orthogonal to the stability levels described earlier.
For example, a DTrace interface can be Stable but only supported on SPARC
microprocessors, or it can be Unstable but common to all Solaris systems.
The DTrace dependency classes are described in the following list in order
from least common (that is, most specific to a particular architecture) to
most common (that is, common to all architectures).</para><variablelist termlength="narrow"><varlistentry><term>Unknown</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary><secondary>unknown</secondary></indexterm>The interface has an unknown set
of architectural dependencies. DTrace does not necessarily know the architectural
dependencies of all entities, such as data types defined in the operating
system implementation. The Unknown label is typically applied to interfaces
of very low stability for which dependencies cannot be computed. The interface
might not be available when using DTrace on <emphasis>any</emphasis> architecture
other than the one you are currently using.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>CPU</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary><secondary>CPU</secondary></indexterm>The interface is specific to the CPU
model of the current system. You can use the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="psrinfo-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>psrinfo</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> utility's <option>v</option> option
to display the current CPU model and implementation names. Interfaces with
CPU model dependencies might not be available on other CPU implementations,
even if those CPUs export the same instruction set architecture (ISA). For
example, a CPU-dependent interface on an UltraSPARC-III+ microprocessor might
not be available on an UltraSPARC-II microprocessor, even though both processors
support the SPARC instruction set.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Platform</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary><secondary>platform</secondary></indexterm>The interface is specific to the
hardware platform of the current system. A platform typically associates a
set of system components and architectural characteristics such as a set of
supported CPU models with a system name such as <literal>SUNW,Ultra-Enterprise-10000</literal>. You can display the current platform name using the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="uname-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>uname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> <option>i</option> option.
The interface might not be available on other hardware platforms.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Group</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary><secondary>group</secondary></indexterm>The interface is specific to the hardware
platform group of the current system. A platform group typically associates
a set of platforms with related characteristics together under a single name,
such as <literal>sun4u</literal>. You can display the current platform group
name using the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="uname-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>uname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> <option>m</option> option. The interface is available on other platforms in the platform
group, but might not be available on hardware platforms that are not members
of the group.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>ISA</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary><secondary>ISA</secondary></indexterm>The interface is specific to the instruction
set architecture (ISA) supported by the microprocessors on this system. The
ISA describes a specification for software that can be executed on the microprocessor,
including details such as assembly language instructions and registers. You
can display the native instruction sets supported by the system using the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="isainfo-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>isainfo</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> utility. The interface might
not be supported on systems that do not export any of the same instruction
sets. For example, an ISA-dependent interface on a Solaris SPARC system might
not be supported on a Solaris x86 system.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Common</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>interface dependency classes</primary><secondary>common</secondary></indexterm>The interface is common to all Solaris
systems regardless of the underlying hardware. DTrace programs and layered
applications that depend only on Common interfaces can be executed and deployed
on other Solaris systems with the same Solaris and DTrace revisions. The majority
of DTrace interfaces are Common, so you can use them wherever you use Solaris.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-stab-3"><title>Interface Attributes</title><para><indexterm><primary>interface attributes</primary></indexterm>DTrace
describes interfaces using a triplet of attributes consisting of two stability
levels and a dependency class. By convention, the interface attributes are
written in the following order, separated by slashes:</para><literallayout><replaceable>name-stability</replaceable> <literal>/</literal> <replaceable>data-stability</replaceable> <literal>/</literal> <replaceable>dependency-class</replaceable></literallayout><para>The <firstterm>name stability</firstterm> of an interface describes
the stability level associated with its name as it appears in your D program
or on the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dtrace-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dtrace</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> command-line.
For example, the <literal>execname</literal> D variable is a Stable name:
Sun guarantees that this identifier will continue to be supported in your
D programs according to the rules described for Stable interfaces above.</para><para>The <firstterm>data stability</firstterm> of an interface is distinct
from the stability associated with the interface name. This stability level
describes Sun's commitment to maintaining the data formats used by the interface
and any associated data semantics. For example, the <literal>pid</literal> D
variable is a Stable interface: process IDs are a Stable concept in Solaris,
and Sun guarantees that the <literal>pid</literal> variable will be of type <literal>pid_t</literal> with the semantic that it is set to the process ID corresponding
to the thread that fired a given probe in accordance with the rules for Stable
interfaces.</para><para>The <firstterm>dependency class</firstterm> of an interface is distinct
from its name and data stability, and describes whether the interface is specific
to the current operating platform or microprocessor.</para><para>DTrace and the D compiler track the stability attributes for all of
the DTrace interface entities, including providers, probe descriptions, D
variables, D functions, types, and program statements themselves, as we'll
see shortly. Notice that all three values can vary independently. For example,
the <literal>curthread</literal> D variable has Stable/Private/Common attributes:
the variable name is Stable and is Common to all Solaris operating platforms,
but this variable provides access to a Private data format that is an artifact
of the Solaris kernel implementation. Most D variables are provided with Stable/Stable/Common
attributes, as are the variables you define.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-stab-4"><title>Stability Computations and Reports</title><para><indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>of stability reports</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>reports</secondary><tertiary>example of use</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>reports</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>computations</secondary></indexterm>The D compiler performs stability
computations for each of the probe descriptions and action statements in your
D programs. You can use the <command>dtrace</command> <option>v</option> option
to display a report of your program's stability. The following example uses
a program written on the command line:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -v -n dtrace:::BEGIN'{exit(0);}'</userinput>
dtrace: description 'dtrace:::BEGIN' matched 1 probe
Stability data for description dtrace:::BEGIN:
        Minimum probe description attributes
                Identifier Names: Evolving
                Data Semantics:   Evolving
                Dependency Class: Common
        Minimum probe statement attributes
                Identifier Names: Stable
                Data Semantics:   Stable
                Dependency Class: Common
CPU     ID                    FUNCTION:NAME
  0      1                           :BEGIN</screen><para>You may also wish to combine the <command>dtrace</command> <option>v</option> option
with the <option>e</option> option, which tells dtrace to compile but not
execute your D program, so that you can determine program stability without
having to enable any probes and execute your program. Here is another example
stability report:</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -ev -n dtrace:::BEGIN'{trace(curthread-&gt;t_procp);}'</userinput>
Stability data for description dtrace:::BEGIN:
        Minimum probe description attributes
                Identifier Names: Evolving
                Data Semantics:   Evolving
                Dependency Class: Common
        Minimum probe statement attributes
                Identifier Names: Stable
                Data Semantics:   Private
                Dependency Class: Common
#</screen><para>Notice that in our new program, we have referenced the D variable <literal>curthread</literal>, which has a Stable name, but Private data semantics (that
is, if you look at it, you are accessing Private implementation details of
the kernel), and this status is now reflected in the program's stability report.
Stability attributes in the program report are computed by selecting the minimum
stability level and class out of the corresponding values for each interface
attributes triplet.</para><para>Stability attributes are computed for a probe description by taking
the minimum stability attributes of all <emphasis>specified</emphasis> probe
description fields according to the attributes published by the provider.
The attributes of the available DTrace providers are shown in the chapter
corresponding to each provider. DTrace providers export a stability attributes
triplet for each of the four description fields for all probes published by
that provider. Therefore, a provider's name may have a greater stability than
the individual probes it exports. For example, the probe description:</para><programlisting>fbt:::</programlisting><para>indicating that DTrace should trace entry and return from all kernel
functions, has greater stability than the probe description:</para><programlisting>fbt:foo:bar:entry</programlisting><para>which names a specific internal function <function>bar</function> in
the kernel module <literal>foo</literal>. For simplicity, most providers use
a single set of attributes for all of the individual <literal></literal><replaceable>module</replaceable><literal>:</literal><replaceable>function</replaceable><literal>:</literal><replaceable>name</replaceable><literal></literal> values that
they publish. Providers also specify attributes for the <literal>args[]</literal> array,
as the stability of any probe arguments varies by provider.</para><para>If the provider field is not specified in a probe description, then
the description is assigned the stability attributes Unstable/Unstable/Common
because the description might end up matching probes of providers that do
not yet exist when used on a future Solaris version. As such, Sun is not able
to provide guarantees about the future stability and behavior of this program.
You should always explicitly specify the provider when writing your D program
clauses. In addition, any probe description fields that contain pattern matching
characters (see <olink targetptr="chp-prog" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, D Program Structure</olink>)
or macro variables such as <literal>$1</literal> (see <olink targetptr="chp-script" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;15, Scripting</olink>) are treated as
if they are unspecified because these description patterns might expand to
match providers or probes released by Sun in future versions of DTrace and
the Solaris OS.</para><para>Stability attributes are computed for most D language statements by
taking the minimum stability and class of the entities in the statement. For
example, the following D language entities have the following attributes:</para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth=""/><colspec colwidth=""/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Entity</para>
</entry><entry><para>Attributes</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>D built-in variable <literal>curthread</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>Stable/Private/Common</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>D user-defined variable <literal>x</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>Stable/Stable/Common</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>If you write the following D program statement:</para><programlisting>x += curthread-&gt;t_pri;</programlisting><para>then the resulting attributes of the statement are Stable/Private/Common,
the minimum attributes associated with the operands <literal>curthread</literal> and <literal>x</literal>. The stability of an expression is computed by taking the minimum
stability attributes of each of the operands.</para><para>Any D variables you define in your program are automatically assigned
the attributes Stable/Stable/Common. In addition, the D language grammar and
D operators are implicitly assigned the attributes Stable/Stable/Common. References
to kernel symbols using the backquote (<literal>`</literal>) operator are
always assigned the attributes Private/Private/Unknown because they reflect
implementation artifacts. Types that you define in your D program source code,
specifically those that are associated with the C and D type namespace, are
assigned the attributes Stable/Stable/Common. Types that are defined in the
operating system implementation and provided by other type namespaces are
assigned the attributes Private/Private/Unknown. The D type cast operator
yields an expression whose stability attributes are the minimum of the input
expression's attributes and the attributes of the cast output type.</para><para>If you use the C preprocessor to include C system header files, these
types will be associated with the C type namespace and will be assigned the
attributes Stable/Stable/Common as the D compiler has no choice but to assume
that you are taking responsibility for these declarations. It is therefore
possible to mislead yourself about your program's stability if you use the
C preprocessor to include a header file containing implementation artifacts.
You should always consult the documentation corresponding to the header files
you are including in order to determine the correct stability levels.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="chp-stab-5"><title>Stability Enforcement</title><para><indexterm><primary>stability</primary><secondary>enforcement</secondary></indexterm>When developing a DTrace script or layered tool, you may wish
to identify the specific source of stability issues or ensure that your program
has a desired set of stability attributes. You can use the <command>dtrace
-x amin=<replaceable>attributes</replaceable></command> option to force the
D compiler to produce an error when any attributes computation results in
a triplet of attributes less than the minimum values you specify on the command-line.
The following example demonstrates the use of <option>x amin</option> using
a snippet of D program source. Notice that attributes are specified using
three labels delimited by <literal>/</literal> in the usual order.</para><screen><userinput># dtrace -x amin=Evolving/Evolving/Common \</userinput>
    <userinput>-ev -n dtrace:::BEGIN'{trace(curthread-&gt;t_procp);}'</userinput>
dtrace: invalid probe specifier dtrace:::BEGIN{trace(curthread-&gt;t_procp);}: \
    in action list: attributes for scalar curthread (Stable/Private/Common) \
    are less than predefined minimum
#</screen>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000026368 0?>