<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()?><preface id="preface-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Preface</title><highlights><para><citetitle>System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle> is
part of a multivolume set that covers a significant part of the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Operating System (Solaris OS) administration information. This book
assumes that you have already installed  a Solaris Express Community Edition release, and you have set up any
networking software that you plan to use. The Solaris OS is part of the Solaris
product family, which includes many features, such as the Java Desktop System.</para>&platformnote;
</highlights><sect1 id="preface-9"><title id="preface-2">Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is intended for anyone who is responsible for administering
one or more systems that run  a Solaris Express Community Edition release.
To use this book, you should have more than two years of <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> system administration experience. Attending
training courses in UNIX system administration might be helpful.</para>
</sect1>&sagset;<sect1 id="preface-4"><title>Related Third-Party Web Site References</title><para>Third party URLs are referenced in this document and provide additional,
related information.</para><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party web sites
mentioned in this document. Sun does not endorse and is not responsible or
liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials that are
available on or through such sites or resources. Sun will not be responsible
or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused by or in connection
with the use of or reliance on any such content, goods, or services that are
available on or through such sites or resources.</para>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface><?Pub *0000002513 0?>