<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()part(title()partintro()?><chapter id="secov-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Security Services (Overview)</title><highlights><itemizedlist><para>To maintain the security of the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS), Solaris software provides
the following features:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secov-6" remap="internal">System Security</olink> &ndash;
The ability to prevent intrusion, to protect machine resources and devices
from misuse, and to protect files from malicious modification or unintentional
modification by users or intruders</para><para>For a general discussion of
system security, see <olink targetptr="concept-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Managing
Machine Security (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secov-4" remap="internal">Solaris Cryptographic Services</olink> &ndash;
The ability to scramble data so that only the sender and the designated receiver
can read the contents, and to manage cryptographic providers and public key
objects</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secov-5" remap="internal">Authentication Services</olink> &ndash;
The ability to securely identify a user, which requires the user's name and
some form of proof, typically a password</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secov-7" remap="internal">Authentication With Encryption</olink> &ndash;
The ability to ensure that authenticated parties can communicate without interception,
modification, or spoofing</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secov-9" remap="internal">Solaris Auditing</olink> &ndash;
The ability to identify the source of security changes to the system, including
file access, security-related system calls, and authentication failures</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secov-8" remap="internal">Security Policy</olink> &ndash;
The design and implementation of security guidelines for a computer or network
of computers</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="secov-6"><title>System Security</title><itemizedlist><para>System security ensures that the system's resources are used properly.
Access controls can restrict who is permitted access to resources on the system.
The Solaris OS features for system security and access control include the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Login administration tools &ndash;</emphasis> Commands
for monitoring and controlling a user's ability to log in. See <olink targetptr="secsys-25" remap="internal">Securing Logins and Passwords (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Hardware access &ndash;</emphasis> Commands
for limiting access to the PROM, and for restricting who can boot the system.
See <olink targetptr="secsys-29" remap="internal">Controlling Access to System Hardware (Task
Map)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Resource access &ndash;</emphasis> Tools
and strategies for maximizing the appropriate use of machine resources while
minimizing the misuse of those resources. See <olink targetptr="concept-13" remap="internal">Controlling
Access to Machine Resources</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Role-based access control (RBAC) &ndash;</emphasis> An
architecture for creating special, restricted user accounts that are permitted
to perform specific administrative tasks. See <olink targetptr="rbac-1" remap="internal">Role-Based
Access Control (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Privileges &ndash;</emphasis> Discrete
rights on processes to perform operations. These process rights are enforced
in the kernel. See <olink targetptr="prbac-2" remap="internal">Privileges (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Device management &ndash;</emphasis> Device <emphasis>policy</emphasis> additionally protects devices that are already protected
by UNIX permissions. Device <emphasis>allocation</emphasis> controls access
to peripheral devices, such as a microphone or CD-ROM drive. Upon deallocation,
device-clean scripts can then erase any data from the device. See <olink targetptr="concept-42" remap="internal">Controlling Access to Devices</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Basic Audit Reporting Tool (BART) &ndash;</emphasis> A snapshot, called a <emphasis>manifest</emphasis>, of the file
attributes of files on a system. By comparing the manifests across systems
or on one system over time, changes to files can be monitored to reduce security
risks. See <olink targetptr="bart-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Using the Basic Audit Reporting Tool (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">File permissions &ndash;</emphasis> Attributes
of a file or directory. Permissions restrict the users and groups that are
permitted to read, write, or execute a file, or search a directory. See <olink targetptr="secfile-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;7, Controlling Access to Files (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Antivirus software &ndash;</emphasis> A vscan service checks
files for viruses before an application uses the files. A file
system can invoke this service to scan files in real time for the most recent
virus definitions before the files are accessed by any clients of the file
system.</para><para>The real-time scan is performed by third-party applications.
A file can be scanned when it is opened and after it is closed. See <olink targetptr="vscan-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Virus Scanning Service (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="secov-4"><title>Solaris Cryptographic Services</title><para>Cryptography is the science of encrypting and decrypting data. Cryptography
is used to insure integrity, privacy, and authenticity. Integrity means that
the data has not been altered. Privacy means that the data is not readable
by others. Authenticity for data means that what was delivered is what was
sent. User authentication means that the user has supplied one or more proofs
of identity. Authentication mechanisms mathematically verify the source of
the data or the proof of identity. Encryption mechanisms scramble data so
that the data is not readable by a casual observer. Cryptographic services
provide authentication and encryption mechanisms to applications and users.</para><para>Cryptographic algorithms use hashing, chaining, and other mathematical
techniques to create ciphers that are difficult to break. Authentication mechanisms
require that the sender and the receiver compute an identical number from
the data. Encryption mechanisms rely on the sender and the receiver sharing
information about the method of encryption. This information enables only
the receiver and the sender to decrypt the message. The Solaris OS provides a
centralized cryptographic framework, and provides encryption mechanisms that
are tied to particular applications.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong"><trademark>Solaris</trademark> Cryptographic
Framework &ndash;</emphasis> A central framework of cryptographic services
for kernel-level and user-level consumers. Uses include passwords, IPsec,
and third-party applications. The cryptographic framework includes a number
of software encryption modules. The framework enables you to specify which
software encryption modules or hardware encryption sources an application
can use. The framework is built on the PKCS #11 v2 library. This library is
implemented according to  the following standard: RSA Security Inc. PKCS #11
Cryptographic Token Interface (Cryptoki). The library provides an API for
third-party developers to plug in the cryptographic requirements for their
applications. See <olink targetptr="scf-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Solaris Cryptographic
Framework (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Encryption mechanisms per application &ndash;</emphasis></para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For the use of DES in Secure RPC, see <olink targetptr="auth-2" remap="internal">Overview
of Secure RPC</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the use of DES, 3DES, AES, and ARCFOUR in the Kerberos
service, see <olink targetptr="intro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;21, Introduction to the
Kerberos Service</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the use of RSA, DSA, and ciphers such as Blowfish in Solaris
Secure Shell, see <olink targetptr="sshuser-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, Using Solaris
Secure Shell (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the use of cryptographic algorithms in passwords, see <olink targetptr="secsys-15" remap="internal">Changing the Password Algorithm (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>In the Solaris Express Community Edition,
the Key Management Framework (KMF) provides a central utility for managing
public key objects, including policy, keys, and certificates. KMF manages
these objects for OpenSSL, NSS, and PKCS #11 public key technologies. See <olink targetptr="kmf-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;15, Solaris Key Management Framework</olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="secov-5"><title>Authentication Services</title><itemizedlist><para>Authentication is a mechanism that identifies a user or service based
on predefined criteria. Authentication services range from simple name-password
pairs to more elaborate challenge-response systems, such as smart cards and
biometrics. Strong authentication mechanisms rely on a user supplying information
that only that person knows, and a personal item that can be verified. A user
name is an example of information that the person knows. A smart card or a
fingerprint, for example, can be verified. The Solaris features for authentication
include the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Secure RPC &ndash;</emphasis> An authentication
mechanism that uses the <olink targetptr="glossary-154" remap="internal">Diffie-Hellman protocol</olink> to
protect NFS mounts and a name service, such as NIS or NIS+. See <olink targetptr="auth-2" remap="internal">Overview of Secure RPC</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Pluggable Authentication Module (PAM) &ndash;</emphasis> A framework that enables various authentication technologies to
be plugged into a system entry service without recompiling the service. Some
of the system entry services include <command>login</command> and <command>ftp</command>.
See <olink targetptr="pam-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;17, Using PAM</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Simple Authentication and Security
Layer (SASL) &ndash;</emphasis> A framework that provides authentication and
security services to network protocols. See <olink targetptr="sasl-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;18,
Using SASL</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris Secure Shell &ndash;</emphasis> A
secure remote login and transfer protocol that encrypts communications over
an insecure network. See <olink targetptr="sshuser-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, Using
Solaris Secure Shell (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Kerberos service &ndash;</emphasis> A
client-server architecture that provides encryption with authentication. See <olink targetptr="intro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;21, Introduction to the Kerberos Service</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="secov-7"><title>Authentication With Encryption</title><itemizedlist><para>Authentication with encryption is the basis of secure communication.
Authentication helps ensure that the source and the destination are the intended
parties. Encryption codes the communication at the source, and decodes the
communication at the destination. Encryption prevents intruders from reading
any transmissions that the intruders might manage to intercept. The Solaris
features for secure communication include the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris Secure Shell &ndash;</emphasis> A
protocol for protecting data transfers and interactive user network sessions
from eavesdropping, session hijacking, and &ldquo;man-in-the-middle&rdquo;
attacks. Strong authentication is provided through public key cryptography.
X windows services and other network services can be tunneled safely over
Secure Shell connections for additional protection. See <olink targetptr="sshuser-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, Using Solaris Secure Shell (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Kerberos service &ndash;</emphasis> A
client-server architecture that provides authentication with encryption. See <olink targetptr="intro-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;21, Introduction to the Kerberos Service</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Internet Protocol Security Architecture
(IPsec) &ndash;</emphasis> An architecture that provides IP datagram protection.
Protections include confidentiality, strong integrity of the data, data authentication,
and partial sequence integrity. See <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="ipsec-ov-1" remap="external">Chapter 19, <citetitle remap="chapter">IP Security Architecture (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: IP Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="secov-9"><title>Solaris Auditing</title><para>Auditing is a fundamental concept of system security and maintainability.
Auditing is the process of examining the history of actions and events on
a system to determine what happened. The history is kept in a log of what
was done, when it was done, by whom, and what was affected. See <olink targetptr="auditov-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;28, Solaris Auditing (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="secov-8"><title>Security Policy</title><indexterm><primary>policies</primary><secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>policy</primary><secondary>definition in Solaris OS</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>policy overview</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The phrase security policy, or <olink targetptr="glossary-19" remap="internal">policy</olink>,
is used throughout this book to refer to an organization's security guidelines.
Your site's security policy is the set of rules that define the sensitivity
of the information that is being processed and the measures that are used
to protect the information from unauthorized access. Security technologies
such as Solaris Secure Shell, authentication, RBAC, authorization, privileges, and resource
control provide measures to protect information.</para><para>Some security technologies also use the word policy when describing
specific aspects of their implementation.  For example, Solaris auditing uses
audit policy options to configure some aspects of auditing policy. The following
table points to glossary, man page, and information on features that use the
word policy to describe specific aspects of their implementation.</para><table frame="topbot" id="secov-3"><title>Use of Policy in the Solaris OS</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="33.22*"/><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="30.92*"/><colspec colwidth="34.85*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Glossary Definition</para>
</entry><entry><para>Selected Man Pages</para>
</entry><entry><para>Further Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-52" remap="internal">audit policy</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="audit-control-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>audit_control</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="audit-user-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>audit_user</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="auditconfig-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>auditconfig</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="auditov-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;28, Solaris Auditing (Overview)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-86" remap="internal">policy in the cryptographic framework</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="cryptoadm-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>cryptoadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="scf-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Solaris Cryptographic Framework
(Overview)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-97" remap="internal">device policy</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="getdevpolicy-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>getdevpolicy</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="concept-42" remap="internal">Controlling Access to Devices</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-85" remap="internal">Kerberos policy</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="krb5.conf-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>krb5.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="aadmin-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;25, Administering Kerberos
Principals and Policies (Tasks)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-107" remap="internal">network policies</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="ipfilter-5" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipfilter</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="ifconfig-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ifconfig</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="ike.config-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ike.config</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="ipsecconf-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsecconf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="routeadm-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>routeadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="ipsectm-1" remap="external">Part&nbsp;III, <citetitle remap="chapter">IP Security,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: IP Services</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-87" remap="internal">password policy</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="passwd-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>passwd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="nsswitch.conf-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>nsswitch.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="crypt.conf-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>crypt.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="policy.conf-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>policy.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="concept-2" remap="internal">Maintaining Login Control</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-140" remap="internal">policy for public key technologies</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="kmfcfg-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>kmfcfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="kmf-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;15, Solaris Key Management Framework</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><olink targetptr="glossary-68" remap="internal">RBAC policy</olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="rbac-5" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>rbac</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="rbacref-13" remap="internal">exec_attr Database</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000021251 0?>