<glossary id="glossary-1"><title>Glossary</title><glossentry><glossterm>AMD-V </glossterm><glossdef><para>AMD's extensions that make the x86 architecture HVM-capable.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>backend driver</glossterm><glossdef><para>Half of a virtual driver, providing an interface between the
virtual device and an underlying real device. See frontend driver.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>bare metal environment</glossterm><glossdef><para>A virtual environment where the virtualization product is
directly installed on physical hardware, acting like a host operating system.
The opposite of a hosted environment.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-13"><glossterm>blessed</glossterm><glossdef><para>In Perl, the term used to denote class membership of an object.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>brand</glossterm><glossdef><para>An instance of the BrandZ functionality, which provides non-global
zones that contain non-native operating environments used for running applications.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>branded zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>An isolated environment in which to run non-native applications
in non-global zones.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-2"><glossterm>cap</glossterm><glossdef><para>A limit that is placed on system resource usage.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-3"><glossterm>capping</glossterm><glossdef><para>The process of placing a limit on system resource usage.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-49"><glossterm>default pool</glossterm><glossdef><para>The pool created by the system when pools are enabled.</para><para>See also <olink targetptr="glossary-8" remap="internal">resource pool</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-50"><glossterm>default processor set</glossterm><glossdef><para>The processor set created by the system when pools are enabled.</para><para>See also <olink targetptr="glossary-51" remap="internal">processor set</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-55"><glossterm>disjoint</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of set in which the members of the set do not overlap
and are not duplicated.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>domain </glossterm><glossdef><para>Virtual machine instance.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>domU </glossterm><glossdef><para>Completely unprivileged domain; only virtual devices are accessible.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>dom0 </glossterm><glossdef><para>Fully privileged domain, can create and destroy other domains,
access real hardware, and so forth.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-29"><glossterm>dynamic configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>Information about the disposition of resources within the
resource pools framework for a given system at a point in time.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-57"><glossterm>dynamic reconfiguration</glossterm><glossdef><para>On SPARC based systems, the ability to reconfigure hardware
while the system is running. Also known as DR.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-6"><glossterm>extended accounting</glossterm><glossdef><para>A flexible way to record resource consumption on a task basis
or process basis in the Solaris Operating System.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7"><glossterm>fair share scheduler</glossterm><glossdef><para>A scheduling class, also known as FSS, that allows you to
allocate CPU time that is based on shares. Shares define the portion of the
system's CPU resources allocated to a project.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="ggbov"><glossterm>frontend driver </glossterm><glossdef><para>A virtual device and its associated driver in a guest domain
that communicates with a backend hosted in another guest domain. See backend
driver.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-48"><glossterm>FSS</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-7" remap="internal">fair share scheduler</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-40"><glossterm>global administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>An administrator with superuser privileges or the Primary
Administrator role. When logged in to the global zone, the global administrator
can monitor and control the system as a whole.</para><para>See also <olink targetptr="glossary-42" remap="internal">zone administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>global scope</glossterm><glossdef><para>Actions that apply to resource control values for every resource
control on the system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-39"><glossterm>global zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>The zone contained on every Solaris system. When non-global
zones are in use, the global zone is both the default zone for the system
and the zone used for system-wide administrative control.</para><para>See
also <olink targetptr="glossary-41" remap="internal">non-global zone</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-36"><glossterm>heap</glossterm><glossdef><para>Process-allocated scratch memory.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>HVM </glossterm><glossdef><para>Hardware-assisted virtual machine. These are virtual machines
that can take advantage of Intel-VT and AMD-V extensions.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>hypervisor</glossterm><glossdef><para>A layer between software environments and physical hardware
that virtualizes the system's hardware.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Linux branded zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>Non-global zone that provides a Linux environment for applications.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>local scope</glossterm><glossdef><para>Local actions taken on a process that attempts to exceed the
control value.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-27"><glossterm>locked memory</glossterm><glossdef><para>Memory that cannot be paged.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-31"><glossterm>memory cap enforcement threshold</glossterm><glossdef><para>The percentage of physical memory utilization on the system
that will trigger cap enforcement by the resource capping daemon.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-56"><glossterm>naming service database</glossterm><glossdef><para>In the Projects and Tasks (Overview) chapter of this document,
a reference to both LDAP containers and NIS maps.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-41"><glossterm>non-global zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>A virtualized operating system environment created within
a single instance of the Solaris Operating System. The Solaris Zones software
partitioning technology is used to virtualize operating system services.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-58"><glossterm>non-global zone administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-42" remap="internal">zone administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-4"><glossterm>page in</glossterm><glossdef><para>To read data from a file into physical memory one page at
a time.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-5"><glossterm>page out</glossterm><glossdef><para>To relocate pages to an area outside of physical memory.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="ggbny"><glossterm>paravirtualization </glossterm><glossdef><para>The paravirtualized domU operating system is ported to run
on top of the hypervisor, and uses virtual network, disk, and console devices.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-21"><glossterm>pool</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-8" remap="internal">resource pool</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-46"><glossterm>pool daemon</glossterm><glossdef><para>The <literal>poold</literal> system daemon that is active
when dynamic resource allocation is required.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-9"><glossterm>project</glossterm><glossdef><para>A network-wide administrative identifier for related work.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-51"><glossterm>processor set</glossterm><glossdef><para>A disjoint grouping of CPUs. Each processor set can contain
zero or more processors. A processor set is represented in the resource pools
configuration as a resource element. Also referred to as a pset.</para><para>See
also <olink targetptr="glossary-55" remap="internal">disjoint</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-35"><glossterm>resident set size</glossterm><glossdef><para>The size of the resident set. The resident set is the set
of pages that are resident in physical memory.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-10"><glossterm>resource</glossterm><glossdef><para>An aspect of the computing system that can be manipulated
with the intent to change application behavior.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-30"><glossterm>resource capping daemon</glossterm><glossdef><para>A daemon that regulates the consumption of physical memory
by processes running in projects that have resource caps defined.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-44"><glossterm>resource consumer</glossterm><glossdef><para>Fundamentally, a Solaris process. Process model entities such
as the project and the task provide ways of discussing resource consumption
in terms of aggregated resource consumption.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-11"><glossterm>resource control</glossterm><glossdef><para>A per-process, per-task, or per-project limit on the consumption
of a resource.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-14"><glossterm>resource management</glossterm><glossdef><para>A functionality that enables you to control how applications
use available system resources.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-43"><glossterm>resource partition</glossterm><glossdef><para>An exclusive subset of a resource. All of the partitions of
a resource sum to represent the total amount of the resource available in
a single executing Solaris instance.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-8"><glossterm>resource pool</glossterm><glossdef><para>A configuration mechanism that is used to partition machine
resources. A resource pool represents an association between groups of resources
that can be partitioned.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-22"><glossterm>resource set</glossterm><glossdef><para>A process-bindable resource. Most often used to refer to the
objects constructed by a kernel subsystem offering some form of partitioning.
Examples of resource sets include scheduling classes and processor sets.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-32"><glossterm>RSS</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-35" remap="internal">resident set size</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-26"><glossterm>scanner</glossterm><glossdef><para>A kernel thread that identifies infrequently used pages. During
low memory conditions, the scanner reclaims pages that have not been recently
used.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Solaris Containers for Linux Applications</glossterm><glossdef><para>A technology that enables the creation of a runtime environment
for Linux applications in a non-global zone on x86 or x64 machines running
the Solaris Operating System.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Solaris Container</glossterm><glossdef><para>A complete runtime environment for applications. Resource
management and Solaris Zones software partitioning technology are both parts
of the container.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-47"><glossterm>Solaris Zones</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software partitioning technology used to virtualize operating
system services and provide an isolated, secure environment in which to run
applications.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>sparse root zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of non-global zone that has <literal>inherit-pkg-dir</literal> resources
and optimizes the sharing of objects.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-28"><glossterm>static pools configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>A representation of the way in which an administrator would
like a system to be configured with respect to resource pools functionality.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-15"><glossterm>task</glossterm><glossdef><para>In resource management, a process collective that represents
a set of work over time. Each task is associated with one project.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>VT-x </glossterm><glossdef><para>Intel's extensions that make the x86 architecture HVM-capable.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>whole root zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of non-global zone that does not have <literal>inherit-pkg-dir</literal> resources.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-34"><glossterm>working set size</glossterm><glossdef><para>The size of the working set. The working set is the set of
pages that the project workload actively uses during its processing cycle.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-52"><glossterm>workload</glossterm><glossdef><para>An aggregation of all processes of an application or group
of applications.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-33"><glossterm>WSS</glossterm><glossdef><para>See also <olink targetptr="glossary-34" remap="internal">working set size</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-42"><glossterm>zone administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>An administrator having the Zone Management profile. The privileges
of a zone administrator are confined to a non-global zone.</para><para>See
also <olink targetptr="glossary-40" remap="internal">global administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-54"><glossterm>zone state</glossterm><glossdef><para>The status of a non-global zone. The zone state is one of
configured, incomplete, installed, ready, running, or shutting down.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary>