<preface id="preface-1"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para><citetitle>System Administration Guide: Virtualization Using the Solaris
Operating System</citetitle> is part of a multivolume set that covers a significant
part of the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Operating System administration
information. This book assumes that you have already installed the operating
system and set up any networking software that you plan to use.</para><note><para>This Solaris release supports systems that use the <trademark class="registered">SPARC</trademark> and x86 families of processor architectures: <trademark class="registered">UltraSPARC</trademark>, SPARC64, AMD64, Pentium, and Xeon
EM64T. The supported systems appear in the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware
Compatibility List</citetitle> at <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl" type="text">http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl</ulink>. This document cites any
implementation differences between the platform types.</para>
</note>
</highlights><sect1 id="gfvph"><title>About the Sun xVM Hypervisor</title><para>The <trademark>Sun</trademark> xVM Hypervisor is based
on the work of the Xen community. The hypervisor supports multiple operating
system instances simultaneously. In a running system, the hypervisor fits
between the hardware and the operating system. The hypervisor virtualizes
the system's hardware to transparently share and partition the system's resources,
such as CPUs, memory, and network interface cards (NICs),  among the user
domains.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-10"><title>About Solaris Containers</title><para>A Solaris Container is a complete runtime environment for applications.
Solaris Resource Manager and Solaris Zones software partitioning technology
are both parts of the container. These components address different qualities
the container can deliver and work together to create a complete container.
The zones portion of the container provides a virtual mapping from the application
to the platform resources. Zones allow application components to be isolated
from one another even though the zones share a single instance of the Solaris
Operating System. Resource management features permit you to allocate the
quantity of resources that a workload receives.</para><para>The container establishes boundaries for resource consumption, such
as CPU. These boundaries can be expanded to adapt to changing processing requirements
of the application running in the container.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdutc"><title>About Solaris Containers for Linux Applications</title><para>Solaris Containers for Linux Applications use Sun's BrandZ technology
to run Linux applications on the Solaris Operating System. Linux applications
run unmodified in the secure environment provided by the non-global zone feature.
This enables you to use the Solaris system to develop, test, and deploy Linux
applications.</para><para>To use this feature, see <olink targetptr="gchhk" remap="internal">Part&nbsp;III, Branded
Zones</olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfjgk"><title>About Using Solaris Zones on a Solaris Trusted Extensions
System</title><para>For information on using zones on a Solaris Trusted Extensions system,
see <olink targetdoc="trsoladmproc" targetptr="managezones-1" remap="external">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Zones in Trusted Extensions (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Administrator&rsquo;s Procedures</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-9"><title id="preface-2">Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is intended for anyone responsible for administering one or
more systems that run the Solaris release. To use this book, you should have
at least one to two years of <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> system
administration experience.</para>
</sect1>&sagset;&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>