<sect1 id="gehwl"><title>Related Books</title><para><olink targetdoc="rscmgrdevgd" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Containers: Resource Management and Solaris Zones Developer&rsquo;s Guide</citetitle></olink> describes
how to write applications that partition and manage system resources and discusses
which APIs to use. Programming examples and a discussion of programming issues
to consider when writing an application are also provided.</para><para><citetitle>Understanding the Solaris xVM Server Architecture</citetitle>,
Part No 820-3089-102, discusses the Solaris xVM Server architecture, the new
approach to virtualization for x86 and x64 systems that makes it possible
to run multiple disparate operating systems and applications on a single server.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="eqqfd"><title>Related Third-Party Web Site References</title><para>Third-party URLs are referenced in this document and provide additional,
related information. </para><note><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party web
sites mentioned in this document. Sun does not endorse and is not responsible
or liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials that
are available on or through such sites or resources.  Sun will not be responsible
or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused or alleged to be
caused by or in connection with use of or reliance on any such content, goods,
or services that are available on or through such sites or resources.</para>
</note>
</sect1><sect1 id="gbeqs"><title>Documentation, Support, and Training</title><para>The Sun web site provides information about the following additional
resources:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.sun.com/documentation/" type="text_url">Documentation</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.sun.com/support/" type="text_url">Support</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.sun.com/training/" type="text_url">Training</ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>