<preface id="preface-3" role="introduction"><title>Solaris Virtualization Product Overview</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides a brief overview of virtualization using the Solaris
Operating System.</para>
</highlights><sect1><title>About Virtualization</title><para>The goal of virtualization is to move from managing individual datacenter
components to managing pools of resources. Successful server virtualization
can lead to improved server utilization and more efficient use of server assets.
Server virtualization is also important for successful server consolidation
projects that maintain the isolation of separate systems.</para><para>Virtualization is driven by the need to consolidate multiple hosts and
services on a single machine. Virtualization reduces costs through the sharing
of hardware, infrastructure, and administration. Benefits include the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Increased hardware utilization</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Greater flexibility in resource allocation</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Reduced power requirements </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Fewer management costs</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Lower cost of ownership</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Administrative and resource boundaries between applications
on a system</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Virtualization products offered by Sun Microsystems include the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Logical Domains (LDoms), the SPARC hypervisor virtualization
solution for running multiple operating system instances on a single machine
simultaneously</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><trademark>Sun</trademark> xVM hypervisor, the x86 hypervisor
virtualization solution for running multiple operating system instances on
a single machine simultaneously</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Native and branded zones containers, which provide isolated
execution environments within a Solaris operating system instance and can
be run within a Solaris guest domain</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Resource management features, which enable you to control
how applications use available system resources</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Network virtualization features</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Operating system-level virtualization features, such as zones or resource
management, can be used in LDoms and in Sun xVM guest domains that have a
Solaris release installed in them. Network virtualization is used throughout
virtualization technologies.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="ggdat"><title>Associated OpenSolaris Communities</title><para>The <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/" type="text_url">OpenSolaris
Xen, Zones, BrandZ, and Networking communities</ulink> provide information,
discussion groups, and the ability to participate in feature development for
the technologies discussed in this guide. Also visit the Logical Domains community
for information about LDoms technology and links to documentation.</para>
</sect1>
</preface>