<chapter id="z.login.ov-1"><title>Non-Global Zone Login (Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter discusses logging in to zones from the global zone.</para><para>The following topics are covered in this chapter:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="z.login.ov-2" remap="internal">zlogin Command</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="z.login.ov-14" remap="internal">Internal Zone Configuration</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="z.login.ov-9" remap="internal">Non-Global Zone Login Methods</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="z.login.ov-10" remap="internal">Interactive and Non-Interactive
Modes</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="z.login.ov-11" remap="internal">Failsafe Mode</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="z.login.ov-13" remap="internal">Remote Login</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For procedures and usage information, see <olink targetptr="z.login.task-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;22, Logging In to Non-Global Zones (Tasks)</olink>.</para><para>For information about logging into <literal>lx</literal> branded zones,
see <olink targetptr="gdgck" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;34, Logging In to lx Branded Zones
(Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="z.login.ov-2"><title><command>zlogin</command> Command</title><para>After you install a zone, you must log in to the zone to complete
its application environment. You might log in to the zone to perform administrative
tasks as well. Unless the <option>C</option> option is used to connect to
the zone console, logging in to a zone using <command>zlogin</command> starts
a new task. A task cannot span two zones.</para><para>The <command>zlogin</command> command is used to log in from the global
zone to any zone that is in the running state or the ready state.</para><note><para>Only the <command>zlogin</command> command with the <option>C</option> option
can be used to log in to a zone that is not in the running state.</para>
</note><para>As described in <olink targetptr="z.login.task-14" remap="internal">How to Use Non-Interactive
Mode to Access a Zone</olink>, you can use the <command>zlogin</command> command
in non-interactive mode by supplying a command to run inside a zone. However,
the command or any files the command acts upon cannot reside on NFS. The command
will fail if any of its open files or any portion of its address space resides
on NFS. The address space includes the command executable itself and the command's
linked libraries.</para><para>The <command>zlogin</command> command can only be used by the global
administrator operating in the global zone. See the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="zlogin-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>zlogin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page for
more information.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="z.login.ov-14"><title>Internal Zone Configuration</title><para>After installation, the zone is in an unconfigured state. The
zone does not have an internal configuration for naming services, its locale
and time zone have not been set, and various other configuration tasks have
not been performed. Therefore, the <literal>sysidtool</literal> programs are
run the first time a zone is booted. For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="sysidtool-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidtool</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para><para>Two methods are available for performing the required configuration:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Zone console login, which initiates a series of questions
from the system. Be prepared to respond to the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Language</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Type of terminal being used</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Host name</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Security policy (Kerberos or standard UNIX)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Naming service type (<literal>None</literal> is a valid response)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Naming service domain</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Name server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Default time zone</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Root password</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The procedure is described in <olink targetptr="z.login.task-31" remap="internal">Performing
the Initial Internal Zone Configuration</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An <filename>/etc/sysidcfg</filename> file, which you can
create and place inside the zone before you boot the zone for the first time.
See the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="sysidcfg-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidcfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page for more information.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="z.login.ov-9"><title>Non-Global Zone Login Methods</title><para>This section describes the methods you can use to log in to a zone.</para><sect2 id="z.login.ov-17"><title>Zone Console Login</title><para>Each zone maintains a virtual console, <literal>/dev/console</literal>. Performing actions on the console is referred to as console mode.
Console login to a zone is available when the zone is in the installed state.
The zone console is closely analogous to a serial console on a system. Connections
to the console persist across zone reboots. To understand how console mode
differs from a login session such as <command>telnet</command>, see <olink targetptr="z.login.ov-13" remap="internal">Remote Login</olink>.</para><para>The zone console is accessed by using the <command>zlogin</command> command
with the <option>C</option> option and the <replaceable>zonename</replaceable>.
The zone does not have to be in the running state.</para><para>Processes inside the zone can open and write messages to the console.
If the <command>zlogin</command> <option>C</option> process exits, another
process can then access the console.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="z.login.ov-18"><title>User Login Methods</title><para>To log in to the zone with a user name, use the <command>zlogin</command> command
with the <option>l</option> option, the user name, and the <replaceable>zonename</replaceable>.
For example, the administrator of the global zone can log in as a normal user
in the non-global zone by specifying the <option>l</option> option to <command>zlogin</command>:</para><screen>global# <userinput>zlogin -l <replaceable>user</replaceable> <replaceable>zonename</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>To log in as user <literal>root</literal>, use the <command>zlogin</command> command
without options.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="z.login.ov-11"><title>Failsafe Mode</title><para>If a login problem occurs and you cannot use the <command>zlogin</command> command
or the <command>zlogin</command> command with the <option>C</option> option
to access the zone, an alternative is provided. You can enter the zone by
using the <command>zlogin</command> command with the <option>S</option> (safe)
option. Only use this mode to recover a damaged zone when other forms of login
are not succeeding. In this minimal environment, it might be possible to diagnose
why the zone login is failing.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="z.login.ov-13"><title>Remote Login</title><para>The
ability to remotely log in to a zone is dependent on the selection of network
services that you establish. By default, a non-global zone is installed with
the limited networking configuration (<literal>/var/svc/profile/generic_limited_net.xml</literal>), and only the <command>ssh</command> login is enabled. Logins
through <command>rlogin</command> and <command>telnet</command> can be added
if needed, either by using the <command>netservices</command> command to switch
the zone to the open networking configuration or by enabling the services
using SMF.</para><para>For more information about changing the network profile or using SMF
commands to add services to zones, see <olink targetptr="gdpau" remap="internal">Switching
the Non-Global Zone to a Different Networking Service Configuration</olink>. For more information about login commands, see <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="rlogin-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>rlogin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="ssh-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ssh</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>, and <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="telnet-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>telnet</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</sect1><sect1 id="z.login.ov-10"><title>Interactive and Non-Interactive Modes</title><para>Two other methods for accessing the zone and for executing commands
inside the zone are also provided by the <command>zlogin</command> command.
These methods are interactive mode and non-interactive mode.</para><sect2 id="z.login.ov-4"><title>Interactive Mode</title><para>In interactive mode, a new pseudo-terminal is allocated for use
inside the zone. Unlike console mode, in which exclusive access to the console
device is granted, an arbitrary number of <command>zlogin</command> sessions
can be open at any time in interactive mode. Interactive mode is activated
when you do not include a command to be issued. Programs that require a terminal
device, such as an editor, operate correctly in this mode.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="z.login.ov-12"><title>Non-Interactive Mode</title><para>Non-interactive mode is used to run shell-scripts which administer
the zone. Non-interactive mode does not allocate a new pseudo-terminal. Non-interactive
mode is enabled when you supply a command to be run inside the zone.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>