<chapter id="gfydr"><title>Configuring and Managing the Solaris Internet
Storage Name Service (iSNS)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides an overview of the Internet Storage Name Service
(iSNS), and describes how to configure the Solaris iSNS server, manage the
iSNS server, and manage iSNS clients. Solaris iSNS is available starting in
the Solaris 10 Update 5 release. This chapter discusses the following topics:</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfycs" remap="internal">The iSNS Technology (Overview)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfybz" remap="internal">Configuring the iSNS Server</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyda" remap="internal">Managing the iSNS Server and Clients</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggdbv" remap="internal">Configuring the iSNS Server in a
Cluster</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="gfycs"><title>The iSNS Technology (Overview)</title><para>The Internet Storage Name Service (iSNS) is a protocol that allows dynamic
discovery of iSCSI initiators and targets within an IP storage area network <firstterm>SAN</firstterm>. The iSNS protocol enables identification, connection to,
and management of iSCSI devices by providing the following services:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Name registration and discovery</emphasis>:
The source of data that is to be stored (known as the <firstterm> initiator</firstterm>)
and the storage object (known as the <firstterm>target</firstterm>) register
their attributes and address, and then can obtain information about accessible
storage devices dynamically.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Discovery domains and logon control</emphasis>:
Resources in a typical storage network are divided into groups called <firstterm>discovery domains</firstterm>, which can be administered through network management
applications. Discovery domains enhance security by providing access control
to targets that are not enabled with their own access controls, while limiting
the logon process of each initiator to a relevant subset of the available
targets in the network.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">State-change notification</emphasis>:
The iSNS server notifies relevant iSNS clients of network events, for example,
a newly created disk Logical Unit Number (LUN), storage resources going offline,
discovery domain membership changes and link failures in a network. These
notifications let a network quickly adapt to changes in topology, which is
key to scalability and availability. This is an optional service.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Entity status inquiry</emphasis>:
The iSNS server verifies that a iSNS client is available. As a result, a status
change notification might be issued. This is an optional service.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>In a simple configuration, the source of data that is to be stored (the initiator) exchanges
data with a storage object (the target). The initiator can locate the target
and the target always recognizes the initiator. For example, the Sun <trademark>StorageTek</trademark> 5320 Network Attached Storage (NAS) appliance is a iSCSI target
because it stores data. The data comes from various iSCSI clients such as
a data management applications or network interface cards which act as initiators.
However, in large and complex configurations, it is difficult and time-consuming
to configure every initiator for every target and for every target to recognize
every initiator. The iSNS server resolves this by using discovery and security
mechanisms to dynamically and automatically identify initiators and targets,
and manage their connections to authorized resources.</para><para>After a Solaris system has been configured as an iSNS server,
all targets and initiators can register with the server. The targets and initiators
become iSCSI <firstterm>clients</firstterm> or <firstterm>nodes</firstterm> of
the iSNS server. These clients are members of the <firstterm>default discovery
domain</firstterm>, the only domain in the <firstterm>default discovery domain
set</firstterm>. When you enable the default discovery domain set, the iSNS
server can provide the iSCSI Name Service (iSNS) for the clients in a simple
manner. </para><para>To take advantage of the iSCSI Name Service's abilities, create several
discovery domain sets and discovery domains. Then assign the clients to different
domains, overlapping their memberships. The iSNS server keeps track of the
clients' status as a member of one or more discovery domains. For example,
when a new storage device is added to the storage network and is registered
with the iSNS server, it is in the default discovery domain in the default
discovery domain set. You then assign this target to the discovery domains
whose initiators will use it as a resource. The iSNS server then removes this
target as a member of the default discovery domain in the default discovery
domain set.</para><para>All initiators and targets are assigned to at least one discovery domain.
Assigning an initiator to one discovery domain restricts its access to those
targets in the same discovery domain set. Assigning an initiator to several
discovery domains allows it to find and use targets in all of the discovery
domain sets that include the initiator's discovery domain. You can manage
access to clients by disabling and enabling their discovery domain sets without
affecting the clients in other discovery domain sets.</para><para>For example, a site has two discovery domain sets in addition to the
default one: Production and Research. Within the two discovery domain sets
are three domains in addition to the default one: Development, Operations,
and Finance. The Development discovery domain is in the Research discovery
domain set, Operations is in the Production domain set, and Finance is a member
of both discovery domain sets. Each client has been assigned to the discovery
domain set that uses it the most. A data application in the Operations discovery
domain can locate and get access to storage devices in the Production discovery
domain set because it is a member of that discovery domain set but it cannot
get access to a storage device in the Research discovery domain set. A data
application in the Finance discovery domain can locate storage devices in
both the Production and Research discovery domain sets because it is a member
of both sets. If the Research discovery domain set were disabled, initiators
in the Finance discovery domain would not have access to the Research storage
devices but would continue to have access to those in the Production discovery
domain set. </para>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfybz"><title>Configuring the iSNS Server</title><para>You can configure the iSNS server using as described in the following
task maps and sections. </para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colname="colspec3" colwidth="3.16*"/><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="40.89*"/><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="45.15*"/><thead><row><entry namest="colspec3" nameend="colspec0" colsep="1"><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry namest="colspec3" nameend="colspec2" colsep="1"><para>1. Accept the default properties of the iSNS server or change them.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para>A. Notification of state changes of the server</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfygh" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para>B. Number of attempts to determine a client's availability</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfygt" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para>C. Location of file that stores client data.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfyhj" remap="internal">How to Specify the Data Store Location (CLI)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="colspec3" nameend="colspec0"><para>2. Enable the iSNS server and display the settings.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfydt" remap="internal"></olink></para><para><olink targetptr="ggcpf" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="colspec3" nameend="colspec0" colsep="1"><para>3. Register all clients with the iSNS server.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the client's management interface's iSCSI configuration function
to specify the IP address of the iSNS server and to allow discovery.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="colspec3" nameend="colspec0"><para>4. Enable the default discovery domain set.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ggcuf" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>After these tasks, the iSNS server is operating in a minimal manner.
All of the clients are in the default discovery domain and are unassigned.
Each one can identify and get access to all of the other ones.</para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="3.16*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="40.89*"/><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="45.15*"/><tbody><row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><para>5. Create the discovery domain sets for your site.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfyvv" remap="internal">How to Create the Discovery Domain Sets (CLI)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><para>6. Create the discovery domains for your site.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfywd" remap="internal">How to Create the Discovery Domains (CLI)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><para>7. Add each discovery domain to one or more discovery domain set.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ggcof" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><para>8. Assign clients to one or more discovery domains.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gfyuq" remap="internal">How to Assign Clients to One or More Discovery
Domains (CLI)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"><para>9. Verify the membership of clients in discover domains and the membership
of discovery domains in discovery domain sets.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="ggcra" remap="internal"></olink></para><para><olink targetptr="ggcqm" remap="internal"></olink></para><para><olink targetptr="gfzqn" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para>The next section provides instructions for setting up the iSNS environment.
The following topics are discussed:</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyii" remap="internal">Setting Up the iSNS Administrative
Settings</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfybi" remap="internal">Using the Command Line Interface
to Configure iSNS</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="gfyii"><title>Setting Up the iSNS Administrative Settings</title><para>This section provides the procedures for changing the default administrative
settings of the iSNS service and for starting the iSNS daemon. If you change
a setting after the iSNS server has been started, you need to refresh the
iSNS server. If you change the data store location, you need to restart the
iSNS server.</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfygh" remap="internal">How to Set Notifications for Changes
in Server State</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfygt" remap="internal">How to Set the Number of Retries
for Client Inquiries</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyhj" remap="internal">How to Specify the Data Store Location</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfydt" remap="internal">How to Enable the iSNS Server Daemon</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggdbd" remap="internal">How to Disable the iSNS Server Daemon</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>See the man page for the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>isns</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> command details about these operations.</para><task id="gfygh"><title>How to Set Notifications for Changes in Server State</title><tasksummary><para>By default, all clients are notified when the iSNS server is not available.
To disable these notifications, change the <parameter>Management_SCNs_Enabled</parameter> property.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Use the svccfg command to disable the property:</para><screen># <userinput>svccfg -s svc:/network/isns_server setprop\config/Management_SCNs_Enabled=no</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Reload the server configuration:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm refresh svc:/network/isns_server </userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfygt"><title>How to Set the Number of Retries for Client Inquiries</title><tasksummary><para>The default number of retries is 3. If the server does not get a response
to three inquiries, it registers that client as unavailable. To change the
number of retries, change the value of the <parameter>ESI Retry Threshold</parameter> property.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Use the svccfg command to change the property to, for example,
6 retries:</para><screen># <userinput>svccfg -s svc:/network/isns_server setprop\config/ESI_retry_threshold_count=6</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Reload the server configuration:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm refresh svc:/network/isns_server </userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfyhj"><title>How to Specify the Data Store Location</title><tasksummary><para>The default location and name for the file that contains the client
data is <filename>/etc/isns/isnsdata.xml</filename> If you have a complex
network environment that includes one or more backup iSNS servers, the data
store must reside in a common location so that all servers can use it. Use
the <parameter>data_store_location</parameter> property to specify the new
location. You can also change the name of the file.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Use the svccfg command to change the location to, for example, <filename>/etc/isns2/isns_data.xml</filename>:</para><screen remap="wide"><userinput>svccfg -s svc:/network/isns_server setprop\config/data_store_location="/etc/isns2/isns_data.xml"</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>If you change the data store location after the server has been
enabled, you must restart the server:</para><screen># <userinput>svcadm restart svc:/network/isns_server </userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfydt"><title>How to Enable the iSNS Server Daemon</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Set the server to start each time the system boots: </para><screen>#<userinput>svcadm -v enable svc:/network/isns_server</userinput>
        svc:/network/isns_server:default enabled</screen>
</step><step><para>Verify the state of the iSNS service:</para><screen>#<userinput>svcs svc:/network/isns_server:default</userinput>
        STATE         STIME        FMRI
        online        11:50:04     svcs svc:/network/isns_server:default</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggdbd"><title>How to Disable the iSNS Server Daemon</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Set the server to start each time the system boots: </para><screen>#<userinput>svcadm -v disable svc:/network/isns_server</userinput>
        svc:/network/isns_server:default disabled</screen>
</step><step><para>Verify the state of the iSNS service:</para><screen>#<userinput>svcs svc:/network/isns_server:default</userinput>
        STATE         STIME        FMRI
        disabled      11:51:05     svc:/network/isns_server:default</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2><sect2 id="gfybi"><title>Using the Command Line Interface to Configure iSNS</title><para>This section provides the procedures for configuring the iSNS server
using the command line interface. The following topics are discussed:</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcpf" remap="internal">How to Display the Current Server
Configuration</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcuf" remap="internal">How to Enable the Default Discovery
Domain Set</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyvv" remap="internal">How to Create the Discovery Domain
Sets</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfywd" remap="internal">How to Create the Discovery Domains</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcof" remap="internal">How to Add a Discovery Domain to
a Discovery Domain Set</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyuq" remap="internal">How to Assign Clients to a Discovery
Domain</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>These procedures use the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>isnsadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> command. See the man page for a complete
description of all of the command options.</para><task id="ggcpf"><title>How to Display the Current Server Configuration</title><procedure remap="single-step"><step><para>The following command shows the properties of the iSNS server:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm show-config</userinput>
        Data Store Location: /etc/isns/isnsdata.xml
        Entity Status Inquiry Non-Response Threshold: 3
        Management SCN Enabled: yes
        Authorized Control Node Names: -</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggcuf"><title>How to Enable the Default Discovery Domain Set</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Activate the default discovery domain set:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm enable-dd-set Default</userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfyvv"><title>How to Create the Discovery Domain Sets</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Create a discovery domain set:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm create-dd-set <replaceable>set_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Enable the discovery domain set:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm enable-dd-set <replaceable>set_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>View all the discovery domain sets, including the new one:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set -v</userinput>
        DD Set name: Default
            State: Enabled
        DD Set name:<replaceable>set_name</replaceable>
            State: Enabled</screen><para>The list of discovery domain sets includes the default discovery domain
set as well as the new one. </para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfywd"><title>How to Create the Discovery Domains</title><tasksummary><para>New discovery domains are members of the default discovery domain set.
After you create them, you add them to the new discovery domain set.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Create the discovery domain:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm create-dd <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>View the new discovery domain in the Default discovery domain
set:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set Default</userinput>
         DD name: <replaceable>name</replaceable>
             DD set(s): Default</screen>
</step><step><para>Create other discovery domains.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggcof"><title>How to Add a Discovery Domain to a Discovery Domain
Set</title><tasksummary><para>This task removes the discovery domain from the default discovery domain
set and adds it the discovery domain set that you specify. Because the new
discovery domain set has been enabled, all the clients in its discovery domains
can be discovered by the iSNS server.</para><para>You do not need to have privileges to list the members of the discovery
domains and discovery domain sets.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>List the discovery domains to identify the one you want to add.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd -v Default</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>List the discovery domain sets to identify the one you want as
the container for the new discovery domain.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Move the discovery domain to the discovery domain set that you
want:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm add-dd <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable> -s <replaceable>set_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>View the new addition to the discovery domain set:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set -v <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfyuq"><title>How to Assign Clients to a Discovery Domain</title><taskprerequisites><para>Use the client's management interface to register the client. Using
the iSCSI configuration function, specify the IP address of the iSNS server
and allow discovery of the client by the iSNS server.</para>
</taskprerequisites><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Verify that the client has been registered with the iSNS server:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-node</userinput> 
       iSCSI Name: iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:000e0c9f10da.45173FEA.engr
	      Alias: STK5320_NAS
	      Type: Target
	      .
       iSCSI Name: iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:000e0c9f10da.454F00A2.acct
	      Alias:
	      Type: Initiator
	     </screen><para>The output shows the clients' iSCSI names.</para>
</step><step><para>Verify the name of the discovery domain:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Add the client to the discovery domain:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm add-node  -d <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable> <replaceable>iSCSI_Name</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>For example, to add the target called &ldquo;STK5320_NAS&rdquo; to the
Eng-dd discovery domain:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm add-node -d Eng-dd  iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:000e0c9f10da.454F00A2.engr</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>List all the clients in the discovery domain to verify the client
has been added:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd -v <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable></userinput> 
    </screen><para>For example, to check the Eng-dd discovery domain:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd -v Eng-dd</userinput>
     	 DD name:	Eng-dd
          DD set: Development-dds
         iSCSI Name:	iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:000e0c9f10da.45173FEA.engr
	        iSCSI Name:	iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:000e0c9f10da.454F00A2.acct
	        iSCSI name: iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:e00000000000.46fd8e2b</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfyda"><title>Managing the iSNS Server and Clients</title><para>This section describes how to maintain the iSNS discovery domain sets
and their members, the initiators and targets. As the site grows, continue
to add clients, discovery domains, and discovery domain sets as described
in the following sections: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyvv" remap="internal">How to Create the Discovery Domain
Sets</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfywd" remap="internal">How to Create the Discovery Domains</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcof" remap="internal">How to Add a Discovery Domain to
a Discovery Domain Set</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfyuq" remap="internal">How to Assign Clients to a Discovery
Domain</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>This section provides the other procedures for managing the iSNS server,
using the command line interface. The following topics are discussed:</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcra" remap="internal">How to Display the Status of a Discovery
Domain Set</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcqm" remap="internal">How to Display the Status of a Discovery
Domain</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gfzqn" remap="internal">How to Display the Status of Clients</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcpp" remap="internal">How to Remove a Client from a Discovery
Domain</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcoq" remap="internal">How to Remove a Discovery Domain
from a Discovery Domain Set</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggcyb" remap="internal">How to Disable a Discovery Domain
Set</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ggdgg" remap="internal">How to Remove a Discovery Domain
Set</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><task id="ggcra"><title>How to Display the Status of a Discovery Domain Set</title><procedure remap="single-step"><step><para>Show the status of the discovery domain set and list the discovery
domains that are its members:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set -v <replaceable>set_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggcqm"><title>How to Display the Status of a Discovery Domain</title><procedure remap="single-step"><step><para>Show the status of the discovery domain and lists the clients
that are its members:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd -v <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="gfzqn"><title>How to Display the Status of Clients</title><procedure remap="single-step"><step><para>Select one of the following to display client status:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Show the status of all clients:</emphasis></para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-node -v </userinput></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Show the status of only the clients
that are targets, that is, storage objects:</emphasis></para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-node -t</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggcpp"><title>How to Remove a Client from a Discovery Domain</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>List the clients to identify the one you want to remove.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-node -v</userinput>
       iSCSI Name: iqn.1986-03.com.sun:01:000e0c9f10da.45173FEA.engr
	      Alias: STK5320_NAS
	      Type: Target
	      Network Entity: SE5310
	      Portal: 172.20.57.95:3260
		      Portal Group: 1
	      Portal: 172.20.56.95:3260
		      Portal Group: 1
	      DD Name: Research,Finance</screen><para>The output shows the client's iSCSI name and the name of the discovery
domains of which it is a member.</para>
</step><step><para>Remove the client from the discovery domain.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm remove-node -d <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable> <replaceable>iSCSI_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggcoq"><title>How to Remove a Discovery Domain from a Discovery
Domain Set</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>List the discovery domains to identify the one you want to remove.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd -v</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Remove the discovery domain from the discovery domain set.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm remove-dd <replaceable>set_name</replaceable> <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggcyb"><title>How to Disable a Discovery Domain Set</title><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>Deactivate a discovery domain set:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm disable-dd-set <replaceable>set_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Verify that the state of the discovery domain set has changed
to Disabled:</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set <replaceable>set_name</replaceable></userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ggdgg"><title>How to Remove a Discovery Domain Set</title><tasksummary><para>After you remove a discovery domain set, its discovery domains remain.
A discovery domain must be a member of at least one discovery domain set.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure>&rolestepsns;<step><para>List the discovery domain sets to identify the one you want to
remove.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm list-dd-set -v</userinput></screen>
</step><step><para>Remove the discovery domain set.</para><screen>#<userinput>isnsadm remove-dd-set <replaceable>set_name</replaceable> </userinput></screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="ggdbv"><title>Configuring High Availability of iSNS Server Using
Sun Cluster</title><para>This section described how to configure the iSNS service to work with
Sun Cluster 3.2 as a Service Management Facility (SMF) proxy resource so that
Sun Cluster can manage the failover of the iSNS service to other cluster nodes.</para><para> For information about Sun Cluster, see <citetitle>Sun Cluster Concepts Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle> (http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2969). To configure Sun Cluster
to manage the failover of the iSNS service, use the following general procedure:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Encapsulate the iSNS service. Use the Sun Cluster SMF proxy
resource type, <parameter>SUNW.Proxy_SMF_failover</parameter> to encapsulate
the iSNS SMF service, registering it with the <command>clresourcetype register</command>.
For instructions on how to encapsulate SMF services with Sun Cluster, see <citetitle>Enabling Solaris SMF
Services to Run With Sun Cluster</citetitle> (http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2974/gcjaz?a=view) . </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a resource group for the iSNS service, using the <command>clresourcegroup create</command> command. See <citetitle>Creating a Resource Group</citetitle> (http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2974).</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Add an iSNS resource to the resource group, using the <command>clresource
create</command> command. Specify the type as <parameter>SUNW.Proxy_SMF_failover</parameter> and
specify the  <parameter>Proxied_service_instances</parameter> property as
the path to a file that contains the properties for the iSNS service. Place
the file in a cluster file system so that each node shares the file. For information
on cluster file systems, see <citetitle>How to Create a Cluster File System</citetitle> (http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2970/6n57ljhns?a=view)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Specify the iSNS data store location as described in <olink targetptr="gfyhj" remap="internal">How to Specify the
Data Store Location</olink>, specifying
the mount point for the cluster file system in the path. Specify the same
data store file property on all nodes of the cluster so that all nodes share
the data store.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Set the cluster resource group online, using the <command>clresourcegroup
online</command> command.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist><para>Because you cannot use <command>svcadm</command> to disable, enable,
or refresh SMF services that have been encapsulated as a proxy resource, use
the following general procedure to change the properties of the iSNS service:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Set the iSNS resource group offline.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Disable the iSNS proxy resource.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Change the property of the iSNS service on all nodes of the
cluster node list.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Re-enable the iSNS proxy resource.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Set the iSNS resource group online.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>