<preface id="preface-13"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para><citetitle>Solaris Express Developer Edition What's New</citetitle> summarizes all features in the most current Software Express release.</para><note><para>This <trademark>Solaris</trademark> release supports systems that
use the <trademark class="registered">SPARC</trademark> and x86  families
of processor architectures:  <trademark class="registered">UltraSPARC</trademark>,
SPARC64, AMD64, Pentium, and Xeon EM64T. The supported systems appear in the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware Compatibility List</citetitle> at <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl" type="url"></ulink>. This document cites
any implementation differences between the platform types.</para><itemizedlist><para>In this document these x86 related terms mean the following:</para><listitem><para>&ldquo;x86&rdquo; refers to the larger family of 64-bit and
 32-bit x86 compatible products.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>&ldquo;x64&rdquo; points out specific 64-bit information about
AMD64 or EM64T systems.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>&ldquo;32-bit x86&rdquo; points out specific 32-bit information
about x86 based systems.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For supported systems, see the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware Compatibility
List</citetitle>.</para>
</note>
</highlights><sect1 id="preface-14"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book provides introductory descriptions of the new Software Express
features for users, developers, and system administrators.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-16"><title>Optional Feature Licensing</title><para>Certain optional features and products that are described in this document
might require individual licensing for use. Refer to the Software License
Agreement.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-18"><title>Related Third-Party Web Site References</title><para>Third-party URLs are referenced in this document and provide additional,
related information.</para><note><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party Web
sites mentioned in this document. Sun does not endorse and is not responsible
or liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials that
are available on or through such sites or resources.  Sun will not be responsible
or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused by or in connection
with use of or reliance on any such content, goods, or services that are available
on or through such sites or resources. </para>
</note>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>