<appendix id="ref-1"><title>Interface Changes
in the Solaris Trusted Extensions Release</title><para>Many interfaces changed between the Trusted Solaris 8 releases and the current
release. For a list of new interfaces, see <olink targetptr="trans-14" remap="internal">New
Interfaces in Trusted Extensions Software</olink>.</para><itemizedlist><para>The following tables list every interface change, the current man page,
and the reason for the change. Changes can be one of the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">No change &ndash;</emphasis> The interface
is originally a Trusted Solaris interface, and has not significantly changed for
this release.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Remains unsupported &ndash;</emphasis> Due
to security issues, the interface is not supported in Solaris Trusted Extensions software.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Removed -</emphasis> Due to changes
in the architecture, the interface was removed. A <literal>None</literal> entry
in the second column indicates a removed interface. The Note column contains <literal>Removed</literal> or an explanation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Replaced &ndash;</emphasis> The interface
is renamed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Has new options -</emphasis> For a Solaris interface,
the interface provides options that are specific to Trusted Extensions software.
For an interface that is unique to Trusted Extensions, the Solaris Trusted Extensions options
are different from the options in Trusted Solaris software.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Obsolete &ndash;</emphasis> A Trusted Solaris interface
has been replaced with a Trusted Extensions interface with a new name and new
parameters. Many label interfaces have been replaced with interfaces that
hide the internals of the label. Although recompiled programs that use the
obsolete interfaces might work, programs and scripts should be written to
use the new interfaces.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Support removed &ndash;</emphasis> Support
for a feature, such as CMW labels, was removed entirely, or removed from this
interface.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Use</emphasis> <replaceable>interface</replaceable> <emphasis role="strong">&ndash;</emphasis> Use an equivalent Solaris interface.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Works as in Solaris OS &ndash;</emphasis> Due
to changes in the architecture, Solaris Trusted Extensions software does not modify the Solaris OS interface.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>&zpriv;&zucmd;&zscmd;&zscall;&zlib;&zdb;&zdrv;
</appendix>