<chapter id="about-softpart-1"><title>Soft
Partitions (Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides information about Solaris Volume Manager soft partitions.
For information about related tasks, see <olink targetptr="tasks-softpart-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Soft Partitions (Tasks)</olink>.</para><para>This chapter contains the following information:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="about-softpart-6" remap="internal">Overview of Soft Partitions</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="about-softpart-8" remap="internal">Configuration Guidelines
for Soft Partitions</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="about-softpart-6"><title>Overview of Soft Partitions</title><para>As the storage capacity of disks has increased, disk arrays present
larger logical devices to Solaris systems. In order to create more manageable
file systems or partition sizes, users might need to subdivide disks or logical
volumes into more than eight partitions. Solaris Volume Manager's soft partition feature
addresses this need.</para><para>Solaris Volume Manager can support up to 8192 logical volumes per disk set. This
number includes the local, or unspecified, disk set. Solaris Volume
Manager configures volumes dynamically as they are needed.</para><para>You can use soft partitions to divide a disk slice or logical
volume into as many partitions as needed. You must provide a name for each
division, or <firstterm>soft partition</firstterm>, just like you do for other
storage volumes, such as stripes or mirrors. A soft partition, once named,
can be accessed by applications, including file systems, as long as the soft
partition is not included in another volume. Once included in a volume, the
soft partition should no longer be directly accessed.</para><para>Soft partitions can be placed directly above a disk slice, or
on top of a mirror, stripe, or RAID-5 volume. A soft partition may not be
both above and below other volumes. For example, a soft partition built on
a stripe with a mirror built on the soft partition is not allowed.</para><para>A soft partition appears to file systems and other applications as a
single contiguous logical volume. However, the soft partition actually comprises
a series of <firstterm>extents</firstterm> that could be located at arbitrary
locations on the underlying media. In addition to the soft partitions, extent
headers (also called <firstterm>system recovery data areas</firstterm>) on
disk record information about the soft partitions to facilitate recovery in
the event of a catastrophic system failure. </para>
</sect1><sect1 id="about-softpart-8"><title>Configuration Guidelines for Soft Partitions</title><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Slices that are used for soft partitions cannot be used for
other purposes.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>When you partition a disk and build file systems on the resulting
slices, you cannot later extend a slice without modifying or destroying the
disk format. Soft partitions behave differently. You can extend a soft partition
up to the amount of space on the underlying device without moving or destroying
data on other soft partitions.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>While it is technically possible to manually place
extents of soft partitions at arbitrary locations on disk, you should allow
the system to place them automatically. For an example of an extent that has
been manually placed, see the output of the <command>metastat</command> command
in <olink targetptr="tasks-basics-28" remap="internal">Viewing the Solaris Volume Manager Configuration</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can build soft partitions on any slice. However, creating
a single slice that occupies the entire disk and then creating soft partitions
on that slice is the most efficient way to use soft partitions at the disk
level.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The maximum size of a soft partition is limited to the size
of the slice or logical volume on which it is built. Because of this limitation,
you should build a volume on top of your disk slices, then build soft partitions
on top of the volume. This strategy allows you to add components to the volume
later, and then expand the soft partitions as needed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For maximum flexibility and high availability, build RAID-1
(mirror) or RAID-5 volumes on disk slices, then create soft partitions on
the mirror or RAID-5 volume.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="about-softpart-2"><title>Scenario&mdash;Soft Partitions</title><para>Soft partitions provide tools with which to subdivide larger storage
spaces into more manageable spaces. For example, in other scenarios (<olink targetptr="about-mirrors-8" remap="internal">Scenario&mdash;RAID-1 Volumes (Mirrors)</olink> or <olink targetptr="about-raid5-9a" remap="internal">Scenario&mdash;RAID-5 Volumes</olink>), large storage
aggregations provided redundant storage of many gigabytes. However, many possible
scenarios would not initially, require so much space. Soft partitions allow
you to subdivide that storage space into more manageable partitions. Each
of those partitions can have a complete file system. For example, you could
create 1000 soft partitions on top of a RAID-1 or RAID-5 volume so that each
of your users can have a home directory on a separate file system. If a user
needs more space, you could simply expand the soft partition. </para>
</sect1>
</chapter>