<chapter id="eoqra"><title>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster (Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides an overview of Solaris Volume Manager for Sun
Cluster.</para><para>This chapter includes the following information:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="eoqrd" remap="internal">Introduction to Solaris Volume Manager
for Sun Cluster</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="eqqcx" remap="internal">Multi-Owner Disk Set Concepts</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="eoqsi" remap="internal">Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster
Configuration</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="eqqcy" remap="internal">RAID&ndash;1 (Mirror) Volumes in
Multi-Owner Disk Sets</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="eoqrd"><title>Introduction to Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster</title><para>Starting with the Solaris 9 9/04 release, Solaris Volume Manager can manage storage
in a Sun Cluster environment using multi-owner disk sets. <firstterm>Multi-owner
disk sets</firstterm> allow multiple nodes to share ownership of a disk set
and to simultaneously write to the shared disks. Previously, shared disk sets
were visible from all participating hosts in the disk set, but only one host
could access it at a time. Multi-owner disk sets work with Sun Cluster  and
with applications such as Oracle Real Application Clusters.</para><para>Multi-owner disk sets and Solaris Volume Manager shared disk sets can coexist
on the same node. However, moving disk sets between the two configurations
is not supported.</para><note><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster device id support for multi-owner disk sets is not available.
Therefore, importing multi-owner disk sets from one system to another is not
supported at this time.</para>
</note><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster creates the same components that you can create with Solaris Volume Manager,
including stripes, concatenations, mirrors, soft partitions, and hot spares. Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster does
not support RAID-5 volumes and transactional volumes.</para><para>The following figure shows the association between the software and
the shared storage in a typical cluster configuration.</para><figure id="eupvi"><title>Sample Cluster Configuration</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="newoverview"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The diagram titled Sample Cluster Configuration shows
the association between the software and the shared storage in a typical cluster
configuration.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>Each node has local storage as well as at least one path to shared storage.
The multi-owner disk sets in the cluster are managed by Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster, which is part
of the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS).</para><sect2 id="exlvs"><title>Prerequisite: Required Software Components for Multi-Owner
Disk Set Functionality</title><para>To use Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster, the following software must be installed in addition
to the Solaris OS:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sun Cluster initial cluster framework</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Sun Cluster Support for Oracle Real Application Clusters software</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Oracle Real Application Clusters software</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>For information on setting up Sun Cluster and Oracle Real Application
Clusters software, see <olink targetdoc="clustinstall" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Sun
Cluster Software Installation Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle></olink> and <olink targetdoc="sc31ds403opsrac" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Sun Cluster Data Service
for Oracle Real Application Clusters Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</note>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="eqqcx"><title>Multi-Owner Disk Set Concepts</title><para>The storage managed by Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster is grouped into multi-owner disk sets. Multi-owner
disk sets allow multiple nodes to share ownership of a disk set and to simultaneously
write to the shared disks. An instance of an application such as Oracle Real
Application Clusters runs on each node in the cluster, so multi-owner disk sets provide
scalability. Since each instance of the application directly accesses the
shared storage, multi-owner disk sets also enhance the performance of the
application.</para><note><para>Multi-owner disk set functionality is enabled only in a Sun Cluster
environment. <firstterm>Nodes</firstterm> are the physical machines that are
part of a Sun Cluster system.</para>
</note><para>Each multi-owner disk set is associated with a list of nodes. These nodes
share ownership of the disk set. The following <command>metaset</command> <option>s</option> <replaceable>disk-set</replaceable> command shows the output for
a multi-owner disk set.</para><screen># <userinput>metaset -s blue</userinput>

Multi-owner Set name = blue, Set number = 1, Master = nodeone

Host                Owner          Member
  nodeone           multi-owner   Yes 
  nodetwo           multi-owner   Yes 

Drive    Dbase

d9       Yes  

d13      Yes  </screen><para>This output shows <computeroutput>nodeone</computeroutput> and<computeroutput> nodetwo</computeroutput> in the list of nodes that share ownership of the
disk set. Additionally, <computeroutput>nodeone</computeroutput> is designated
as the <firstterm>master node</firstterm>.</para><para>Each multi-owner disk set has a master node. After a disk set is created,
the node that adds the first disk to the disk set becomes the master node
of the disk set. The master node creates, deletes, and updates the state database
replicas in the disk set.</para><note><para>For more information on state database replicas, see <olink targetptr="about-state-db-replicas-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, State Database (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</note><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster can support disk sets with different, yet overlapping, node lists.
Because each disk set has a master node, multiple masters can exist simultaneously
on the same cluster.</para><para>The following output from the <command>metaset</command> command shows
that <computeroutput>nodeone</computeroutput> becomes the master node when
the first disk is added to the disk set.</para><screen>nodeone# <userinput>metaset -s red</userinput>
Multi-owner Set name = red, Set number = 1, Master = 

Host                Owner          Member
  nodeone                           Yes 
  nodetwo                           Yes 
nodeone# <userinput>metaset -s red -a /dev/did/dsk/d9</userinput>
nodeone# <userinput>metaset -s red</userinput>

Multi-owner Set name = red, Set number = 1, Master = nodeone 

Host                Owner          Member
  nodeone           multi-owner     Yes 
  nodetwo           multi-owner     Yes 

Drive     Dbase

d9        Yes  </screen><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster can support disk sets with different, yet overlapping, node lists.
Because each disk set has a master node, multiple masters can exist simultaneously
on the same cluster.</para><sect2 id="exlvt"><title>Tasks Associated With Multi-Owner Disk Sets</title><caution><para>Before configuring multi-owner disk sets, you must have the following
software installed, in addition to the Solaris OS:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Sun Cluster initial cluster framework</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Sun Cluster Support for Oracle Real Application Clusters software</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Oracle Real Application Clusters software</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information on setting up Sun Cluster and Oracle Real Application
Clusters software, see <olink targetdoc="clustinstall" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Sun
Cluster Software Installation Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle></olink> and <olink targetdoc="sc31ds403opsrac" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Sun Cluster Data Service
for Oracle Real Application Clusters Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</caution><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster generally uses the same set of Solaris Volume Manager commands to perform
tasks associated with disk sets. Some command options unique to multi-owner disk sets have
been added to the <command>metaset</command> command. For example, the task
to create a multi-owner disk set requires the <option>M</option> to the <command>metaset</command> command. The following output shows you how to create a multi-owner disk set using
the <command>metaset</command> <option>s</option> <replaceable>diskset-name</replaceable> <option>a</option> <option>M</option> <option>h</option> <replaceable>hostname</replaceable> command.</para><screen># <userinput>metaset -s red -a -M -h nodeone</userinput>
# <userinput>metaset</userinput>
Multi-owner Set name = red, Set number = 1, Master = 

Host                Owner          Member
  nodeone                          Yes </screen><para>In addition, some of the <command>metaset</command> command options,
such as the commands to take and release disk sets, are not used with multi-owner disk sets.
For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="metaset-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>metaset</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page.</para><para>Another example of how tasks differ in a Sun Cluster environment occurs
when working with disks. Sun Cluster assigns each disk a unique device ID
(DID) number. Rather than using the c<replaceable>n</replaceable>t<replaceable>n</replaceable>d<replaceable>n</replaceable> format to identify a disk, use the Sun Cluster DID path name, <filename>/dev/did/dsk/d<replaceable>N</replaceable></filename>. The variable <replaceable>N</replaceable> is the device number assigned by Sun Cluster.</para><para>The following output shows you how to add a disk to a multi-owner disk
set using the <command>metaset</command> <option>s</option> <replaceable>diskset-name</replaceable> <option>a</option> <replaceable>disk-name</replaceable> command
and the Sun Cluster DID path name to identify the disk.</para><screen>nodeone# <userinput>metaset -s red</userinput>
Multi-owner Set name = red
Multi-owner Set name = red, Set number = 1, Master = 

Host                Owner          Member
  nodeone                           Yes 
  nodetwo                           Yes 
nodeone# <userinput>metaset -s red -a /dev/did/dsk/d13</userinput>
nodeone# <userinput>metaset -s red</userinput>
Multi-owner Set name = red, Set number = 1, Master = nodeone

Host                Owner          Member
  nodeone            multi-owner   Yes

Drive Dbase

d13   Yes</screen><para>For information on creating multi-owner disk sets for the Oracle Real Application
Clusters, see <olink targetdoc="sc31ds403opsrac" targetptr="opsrac-installation-29" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Creating a Multi-Owner
Disk Set in Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster for the Oracle Real Application
Clusters Database</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Sun Cluster Data
Service for Oracle Real Application Clusters Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>For tasks that are associated with disk sets, see <olink targetptr="tasks-disksets-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, Disk Sets (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="eoqsi"><title>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster Configuration</title><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster supports the following configuration:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster supports up to 32 disk sets. These disk sets can include
any combination of multi-owner disk sets, shared disk sets, and the local disk
set.</para><note><para>For more information on different types of disk sets, see <olink targetptr="eqqda" remap="internal">Types of Disk Sets</olink>.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>Each multi-owner disk set supports a maximum of 8192 volumes
per disk set.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The default size for a state database replica is 16 Mbytes.
The minimum size is 16 Mbytes. The maximum size is 256 Mbytes.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Many of the extension properties for Sun Cluster Support for Oracle
Real Application Clusters specify timeouts for steps in reconfiguration processes.
For further information about setting timeouts, refer to <olink targetdoc="sc31ds403opsrac" targetptr="ch8_ops-8" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Tuning
Sun Cluster Support for Oracle Real Application Clusters</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Sun Cluster Data Service for Oracle Real Application Clusters
Guide for Solaris OS</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="eqqcy"><title>RAID&ndash;1 (Mirror) Volumes in Multi-Owner Disk
Sets</title><para>A RAID&ndash;1 volume, or mirror, created in a multi-owner disk set functions
identically to a RAID-1 volume in a Solaris Volume Manager shared disk set. However,
RAID-1 volumes in multi-owner disk sets have some additional features.</para><sect2 id="eqqcm"><title>Mirror Ownership With Multi-Owner Disk Sets</title><para>The concept of mirror ownership is unique to multi-owner disk sets. Unlike
a RAID-1 volume in a Solaris Volume Manager shared disk set, a RAID-1 volume in a multi-owner disk set usually
has an owner associated with it. The ownership of the mirror volume is chosen
by the volume manager. The owner of the volume is one of the nodes designated
in the node list for the disk set. Only the owner of the RAID-1 volume can
write to the volume. If a non-owner node wants to write to the volume, the
ownership switches to the node doing the write operation. The following output
from the <command>metastat</command> <option>s</option> <replaceable>diskset-name</replaceable> command shows <computeroutput>nodeone</computeroutput> as the
owner of the RAID-1 volume, <computeroutput>d24</computeroutput>.</para><screen># <userinput>metastat -s red</userinput>
red/d24: Mirror
    Submirror 0: red/d20
      State: Okay
    Submirror 1: red/d21
      State: Okay
    Pass: 1
    Read option: roundrobin (default)
    Write option: parallel (default)
    Resync option: optimizedresync
    Owner: nodeone
    Size: 825930 blocks (403 MB)</screen>
</sect2><sect2 id="eqqct"><title>Data Management and Recovery Processes</title><para>As with RAID-1 volumes in Solaris Volume Manager, RAID-1 volumes in Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster perform
operations to ensure consistent data. Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster provides RAID-1 volumes with
two options for data management and recovery.</para><sect3 id="eqqcu"><title>Optimized Resynchronization for Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster</title><para>Optimized resynchronization in Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster functions identically to optimized
resynchronization in Solaris Volume Manager. However, in a multi-owner disk set, a RAID-1
volume with the resynchronization option set to optimized resynchronization
always has a mirror owner. The following output from the <command>metastat</command> <option>s</option> <replaceable>diskset-name</replaceable> command shows the resynchronization
option set to <computeroutput>optimizedresync</computeroutput> (for optimized
resynchronization).</para><screen># <userinput>metastat -s red</userinput>
red/d24: Mirror
    Submirror 0: red/d20
      State: Okay
    Submirror 1: red/d21
      State: Okay
    Pass: 1
    Read option: roundrobin (default)
    Write option: parallel (default)
    Resync option: optimizedresync
    Owner: nodeone
    Size: 825930 blocks (403 MB)</screen><para>For more information on optimized resynchronization, see <olink targetptr="about-metadevices-15" remap="internal">Optimized Resynchronization</olink>.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="eqqcv"><title>Application-Based Recovery and Directed Mirror Reads</title><para>To optimize data recovery in Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster, applications such as Oracle Real
Application Clusters require the ability to manage and control the recovery
of data. Enabling an application to control the recovery improves the performance
of the recovery. The ioctls <literal>DKIOGETVOLCAP</literal>, <literal>DKIOSETVOLCAP</literal>, and <literal>DKIODMR</literal> provide support for an application's
data management recovery in a cluster environment. These ioctls provide an
application with the following capabilities:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Application Based Recovery (ABR)&mdash;Allows the application
to control the recovery of data on mirrored volumes</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Directed Mirror Reads&mdash;Allows the application to direct
reads to specific submirrors and to determine the state of the data</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For more information on the ioctls used with application-based data
management recovery, see the <olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="dkio-7i" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dkio</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7I</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page.</para><para>A RAID-1 volume with the resynchronization option set to application-based
recovery only has a mirror owner during the application-based recovery process.
The following output from the <command>metastat</command> <option>s</option> <replaceable>diskset-name</replaceable> command shows a RAID-1 volume in a normal state.
The resynchronization option is set to application-based recovery. There is
no mirror owner.</para><screen># <userinput>metastat -s red</userinput>
red/d24: Mirror
    Submirror 0: red/d20
      State: Okay
    Submirror 1: red/d21
      State: Okay
    Pass: 1
    Read option: roundrobin (default)
    Write option: parallel (default)
    Resync option: application based
    Owner: None
    Size: 825930 blocks (403 MB)</screen>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>