<preface id="preface-1"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>The <citetitle>Solaris Volume Manager Administration Guide</citetitle> explains how to use <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Volume Manager to manage your system's storage needs. Solaris Volume Manager enables
you to create, modify, and use RAID-0 (concatenation and stripe) volumes,
RAID-1 (mirror) volumes,</para><note><para>This Solaris release supports systems that use the <trademark class="registered">SPARC</trademark> and x86 families of processor architectures: <trademark class="registered">UltraSPARC</trademark>, SPARC64, AMD64, Pentium, and Xeon
EM64T. The supported systems appear in the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware
Compatibility List</citetitle> at <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl" type="url">http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl</ulink>. This document cites any
implementation differences between the platform types.</para><para>In this
document these x86 related terms mean the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>x86 refers to the larger family of 64-bit and 32-bit x86 compatible
products.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>x64 points out specific 64-bit information about AMD64 or
EM64T systems.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>32-bit x86 points out specific 32-bit information about x86
based systems.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For supported systems, see the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware Compatibility
List</citetitle>.</para>
</note>
</highlights><sect1 id="preface-9"><title id="preface-2">Who Should Use This Book</title><para>System and storage administrators can use this book to identify:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Tasks supported by Solaris Volume Manager</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ways to use Solaris Volume Manager to provide more reliable and accessible
data</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-4"><title>How This Book Is Organized</title><para>The<citetitle> Solaris Volume Manager Administration Guide</citetitle> includes the following information:</para><para><olink targetptr="roadmap-10" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;1, Getting Started With Solaris
Volume Manager</olink> provides a detailed &ldquo;roadmap&rdquo; to the concepts
and tasks described in this book. Use this chapter as a navigational aid to
the book's content.</para><para><olink targetptr="storage-overview-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Storage Management
Concepts</olink> provides an introduction to general storage management concepts
for those readers who are new to this technology.</para><para><olink targetptr="basics-23185" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Solaris Volume Manager
Overview</olink> describes Solaris Volume Manager. This chapter introduces essential
product-related concepts and explains how to access Solaris Volume Manager tools.</para><para><olink targetptr="eoqra" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Solaris Volume Manager for Sun Cluster (Overview)</olink> provides an introduction to multi-owner disk sets. Multi-owner disk
sets enhance the use of Solaris Volume Manager in a <trademark>Sun</trademark> Cluster
environment.</para><para><olink targetptr="svm-scenario-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Configuring and Using
Solaris Volume Manager (Scenario)</olink> provides the storage configuration
scenario used throughout this book. This scenario is intended to help you
understand the Solaris Volume Manager product.</para><para><olink targetptr="about-state-db-replicas-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, State Database
(Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to state databases and state
database replicas.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-state-db-replicas-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;7, State Database
(Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related to state databases and
state database replicas. </para><para><olink targetptr="about-metadevices-22802" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;8, RAID-0 (Stripe
and Concatenation) Volumes (Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to
RAID-0 (stripe and concatenation) volumes.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-metadevices-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;9, RAID-0 (Stripe
and Concatenation) Volumes (Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related
to RAID-0 (stripe and concatenation) volumes.</para><para><olink targetptr="about-mirrors-2" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;10, RAID-1 (Mirror)
Volumes (Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to RAID-1 (mirror) volumes.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-mirrors-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;11, RAID-1 (Mirror)
Volumes (Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related to RAID-1 (mirror)
volumes.</para><para><olink targetptr="about-softpart-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;12, Soft Partitions
(Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to Solaris Volume Manager's soft partitioning
feature.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-softpart-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Soft Partitions
(Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related to soft partitioning.</para><para><olink targetptr="about-raid5-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;14, RAID-5 Volumes (Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to RAID-5 volumes.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-raid5-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;15, RAID-5 Volumes (Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related to RAID-5 volumes.</para><para><olink targetptr="about-hotspares-40444" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;16, Hot Spare
Pools (Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to hot spares and hot
spare pools.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-hotspares-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;17, Hot Spare Pools
(Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related to hot spares and hot
spare pools.</para><para><olink targetptr="about-disksets-31856" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;18,
Disk Sets (Overview)</olink> describes concepts related to disk sets.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-disksets-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, Disk Sets (Tasks)</olink> explains how to perform tasks related to disk sets.</para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-basics-2" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;20, Maintaining Solaris
Volume Manager (Tasks)</olink> explains some general maintenance tasks that
are not related to a specific Solaris Volume Manager component.</para><para><olink targetptr="best-practices-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;21, Best Practices
for Solaris Volume Manager</olink> provides some &ldquo;best practices&rdquo;
information about configuring and using Solaris Volume Manager.</para><para><olink targetptr="topdown-tasks-chap" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;23, Top-Down Volume
Creation (Tasks)</olink> describes concepts of and tasks related to the Solaris Volume Manager top-down
volume creation feature. </para><para><olink targetptr="tasks-snmp-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;24, Monitoring and Error
Reporting (Tasks)</olink> provides concepts and instructions for using the Solaris Volume Manager SNMP
agent and for other error-checking approaches.</para><para><olink targetptr="troubleshoottasks-33506" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;25, Troubleshooting
Solaris Volume Manager (Tasks)</olink> provides information about troubleshooting
and solving common problems in the Solaris Volume Manager environment.</para><para><olink targetptr="appendfiles-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;A, Important Solaris
Volume Manager Files</olink> lists important Solaris Volume Manager files.</para><para><olink targetptr="quick-reference-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;B, Solaris Volume
Manager Quick Reference</olink> provides tables that summarize commands and
other helpful information.</para><para><olink targetptr="append-cim-wbem-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;C, Solaris Volume
Manager CIM/WBEM API</olink> provides a brief introduction to the CIM/WBEM
API that allows open Solaris Volume Manager management from WBEM-compliant management
tools.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-5"><title>Related Books</title><para>Solaris Volume Manager is one of several system administration tools available
for the Solaris operating system. Information about overall system administration
features and functions, as well as related tools are provided in the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv1" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv2" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Advanced Administration</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="sagdfs" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Devices and File Systems</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>