<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><appendix id="appol-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Site Security Policy</title><indexterm><primary>site security policy</primary><secondary>tasks involved</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>site security policy</secondary>
</indexterm><highlights><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><para>This appendix discusses site security policy issues, and suggests reference
books and web sites for further information:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appol-11" remap="internal">Site Security Policy and Trusted
Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appol-2" remap="internal">Computer Security Recommendations</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appol-3" remap="internal">Physical Security Recommendations</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appol-4" remap="internal">Personnel Security Recommendations</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appol-5" remap="internal">Common Security Violations</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="appol-6" remap="internal">Additional Security References</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="appol-12"><title>Creating and Managing a Security Policy</title><itemizedlist><para>Each Solaris Trusted Extensions site is unique and must determine its own security policy.
Perform the following tasks when creating and managing a security policy.</para><listitem><para>Establish a security team.  The security team needs to have
representation from top-level management, personnel management, computer system
management and administrators, and facilities management. The team must review Trusted Extensions administrators'
policies and procedures, and recommend general security policies that apply
to all system users.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Educate management and administration personnel about the
site security policy.  All personnel involved in the management and administration
of the site must be educated about the security policy. Security policies
must not be made available to regular users because this policy information
has direct bearing on the security of the computer systems.</para>
</listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><para>Educate users about Trusted Extensions software and the security policy.
 All users must be familiar with the <olink targetdoc="trssug" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions User&rsquo;s Guide</citetitle></olink>.
Because the users are usually the first to know when a system is not functioning
normally, the user must become acquainted with the system and report any problems
to a system administrator. A secure environment needs the users to notify
the system administrators immediately if they notice any of the following:</para><listitem><para>A discrepancy in the last login time that is reported at the
beginning of each session</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An unusual change to file data</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A lost or stolen human-readable printout</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The inability to operate a user function</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Enforce the security policy. If the security policy is not
followed and enforced, the data contained in the system that is configured
with Trusted Extensions is not secure. Procedures must be established to record
any problems and the measures that were taken to resolve the incidents.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Periodically review the security policy.  The security team
must perform a periodic review of the security policy and all incidents that
occurred since the last review. Adjustments to the policy can then lead to
increased security.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="appol-11"><title>Site Security Policy and Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>site security policy</primary><secondary>Trusted Extensions configuration decisions</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>decisions to make</primary><secondary>based on site security policy</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>The security administrator must design the Trusted Extensions network based
on the site's security policy. The security policy dictates configuration
decisions, such as the following:</para><listitem><para>How much auditing is done for all users and for which classes
of events</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>How much auditing is done for users in roles and for which
classes of events</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>How audit data is managed, archived, and reviewed</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Which labels are used in the system and whether the <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> and <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> labels will viewable by regular
users</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Which user clearances are assigned to individuals</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Which devices (if any) can be allocated by which regular users</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Which label ranges are defined for systems, printers, and
other devices</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether Trusted Extensions is used in an evaluated configuration
or not</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="appol-2"><title>Computer Security Recommendations</title><indexterm><primary>site security policy</primary><secondary>recommendations</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Consider the following list of guidelines when you develop a security
policy for your site.</para><listitem><para>Assign the maximum label of a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions to
not be greater than the maximum security level of work being done at the site.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Manually record system reboots, power failures, and shutdowns
in a site log.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Document file system damage, and analyze all affected files
for potential security policy violations.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Restrict operating manuals and administrator documentation
to individuals with a valid need for access to that information.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Report and document unusual or unexpected behavior of any Trusted Extensions software,
and determine the cause.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If possible, assign at least two individuals to administer
systems that are configured with Trusted Extensions. Assign one person the security
administrator authorization for security-related decisions. Assign the other
person the system administrator authorization for system management tasks.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Establish a regular backup routine.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Assign authorizations only to users who need them and who
can be trusted to use them properly.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Assign privileges to programs only they need the privileges
to do their work, and only when the programs have been scrutinized and proven
to be trustworthy in their use of privilege. Review the privileges on existing Trusted Extensions programs
as a guide to setting privileges on new programs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Review and analyze audit information regularly. Investigate
any irregular events to determine the cause of the event.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Minimize the number of administration IDs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Minimize the number of setuid and setgid programs. Use authorizations,
privileges, and roles to execute the program and to prevent misuse.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ensure that an administrator regularly verifies that regular
users have a valid login shell.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ensure that an administrator must regularly verifies that
regular users have valid user ID values and not system administration ID values.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="appol-3"><title>Physical Security Recommendations</title><indexterm><primary>site security policy</primary><secondary>physical access recommendations</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Consider the following list of guidelines  when you develop a security
policy for your site.</para><listitem><para>Restrict access to the systems that are configured with Trusted Extensions.
The most secure locations are generally interior rooms that are not on the
ground floor.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Monitor and document access to systems that are configured
with Trusted Extensions.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Secure computer equipment to large objects such as tables
and desks to prevent theft. When equipment is secured to a wooden object,
increase the strength of the object by adding metal plates.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Consider removable storage media for sensitive information.
Lock up all removable media when the media are not in use.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Store system backups and archives in a secure location that
is separate from the location of the systems.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Restrict physical access to the backup and archival media
in the same manner as you restrict access to the systems.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Install a high-temperature alarm in the computer facility
to indicate when the temperature is outside the range of the manufacturer's
specifications. A suggested range is 10&deg;C to 32&deg;C (50&deg;F to 90&deg;F).</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Install a water alarm in the computer facility to indicate
water on the floor, in the subfloor cavity, and in the ceiling.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Install a smoke alarm to indicate fire, and install a fire-suppression
system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Install a humidity alarm to indicate too much or too little
humidity.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Consider TEMPEST shielding if machines do not have it. TEMPEST
shielding might be appropriate for facility walls, floors, and ceilings.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Allow only certified technicians to open and close TEMPEST
equipment to ensure its ability to shield electromagnetic radiation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Check for physical gaps that allow entrance to the facility
or to the rooms that contain computer equipment. Look for openings under raised
floors, in suspended ceilings, in roof ventilation equipment, and in adjoining
walls between original and secondary additions.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Prohibit eating, drinking, and smoking in computer facilities
or near computer equipment. Establish areas where these activities can occur
without threat to the computer equipment.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Protect architectural drawings and diagrams of the computer
facility.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Restrict the use of building diagrams, floor maps, and photographs
of the computer facility.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="appol-4"><title>Personnel Security Recommendations</title><indexterm><primary>site security policy</primary><secondary>personnel recommendations</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Consider the following list of guidelines when you develop a security
policy for your site.</para><listitem><para>Inspect packages, documents, and storage media when they arrive
and before they leave a secure site.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Require identification badges on all personnel and visitors
at all times.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Use identification badges that are difficult to copy or counterfeit.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Establish areas that are prohibited for visitors, and clearly
mark the areas.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Escort visitors at all times.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="appol-5"><title>Common Security Violations</title><indexterm><primary>site security policy</primary><secondary>common violations</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Because no computer is completely secure, a computer facility is only
as secure as the people who use it. Most actions that violate security are
easily resolved by careful users or additional equipment. However, the following
list gives examples of problems that can occur:</para><listitem><para>Users give passwords to other individuals who should not have
access to the system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users write down passwords, and lose or leave the passwords
in insecure locations.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users set their passwords to easily guessed words or easily
guessed names.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users learn passwords by watching other users type a password.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Unauthorized users remove, replace, or physically tamper with
hardware.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users leave their systems unattended without locking the screen.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users change the permissions on a file to allow other users
to read the file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users change the labels on a file to allow other users to
read the file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users discard sensitive hardcopy documents without shredding
them, or users leave sensitive hardcopy documents in insecure locations.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users leave access doors unlocked.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users lose their keys.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users do not lock up removable storage media.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Computer screens are visible through exterior windows.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Network cables are tapped.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Electronic eavesdropping captures signals emitted from computer
equipment.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Power outages, surges, and spikes destroy data.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Earthquakes, floods, tornadoes, hurricanes, and lightning
destroy data.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>External electromagnetic radiation interference such as sun-spot
activity scrambles files.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="appol-6"><title>Additional Security References</title><indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>publications</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>publications</primary><secondary>security and UNIX</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Government publications describe in detail the standards, policies,
methods, and terminology associated with computer security. Other publications
listed here are guides for system administrators of <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> systems and are useful in gaining a thorough understanding
of UNIX security problems and solutions.</para><para>The web also provides resources. In particular, the <ulink url="http://www.cert.org" type="text_url">CERT</ulink> web site alerts companies
and users to security holes in the software. The <ulink url="http://www.sans.org/index.php" type="text_url">SANS Institute</ulink> offers
training, an extensive glossary of terms, and an updated list of top threats
from the Internet.</para><sect2 id="appol-7"><title>U.S. Government Publications</title><itemizedlist><para>The U.S. government offers many of its publications on the web. The
Computer Security Resource Center (CSRC) of the National Institute of Standards
and Technology (NIST) publishes articles on computer security. The following
are a sample of the publications that can be downloaded from the <ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/index.html" type="text_url">NIST site</ulink>.</para><listitem><para><citetitle>An Introduction to Computer Security: The NIST
Handbook</citetitle>. SP 800-12, October 1995.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Standard Security Label for Information Transfer</citetitle>.
FIPS-188, September 1994.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Swanson, Marianne and Barbara Guttman. <citetitle>Generally
Accepted Principles and Practices for Securing Information Technology Systems</citetitle>.
SP 800-14, September 1996.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Tracy, Miles, Wayne Jensen, and Scott Bisker. <citetitle>Guidelines
on Electronic Mail Security</citetitle>. SP 800-45, September 2002. Section
E.7 concerns securely configuring LDAP for mail.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Wilson, Mark and Joan Hash. <citetitle>Building an Information
Technology Security Awareness and Training Program</citetitle>. SP 800-61,
January 2004. Includes a useful glossary.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Grace, Tim, Karen Kent, and Brian Kim. <citetitle>Computer
Security Incident Handling Guidelines</citetitle>. SP 800-50, September 2002.
Section E.7 concerns securely configuring LDAP for mail.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Scarfone, Karen,Wayne Jansen, and Miles Tracy. <citetitle><ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-123" type="text">Guide
to General Server Security</ulink></citetitle> SP 800-123, July 2008.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Souppaya, Murugiah, John Wack, and Karen Kent. <citetitle><ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-70" type="text">Security
Configuration Checklists Program for IT Products</ulink></citetitle>. SP 800-70, May 2005.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="appol-8"><title>UNIX Security Publications</title><para>Chirillo, John and Edgar Danielyan. <citetitle><trademark>Sun</trademark> Certified Security Administration for <trademark>Solaris</trademark> 9 &amp; 10 Study Guide</citetitle>. McGraw-Hill/Osborne,
2005.</para><para>Garfinkel, Simson, Gene Spafford, and Alan Schwartz. <citetitle>Practical
UNIX and Internet Security, 3rd Edition</citetitle>. O'Reilly &amp; Associates,
Inc, Sebastopol, CA, 2006.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="appol-9"><title>General Computer Security Publications</title><para>Brunette, Glenn M. and Christoph L. <citetitle>Toward Systemically Secure
IT Architectures</citetitle>. Sun Microsystems, Inc, June 2005.</para><para>Kaufman, Charlie, Radia Perlman, and Mike Speciner. <citetitle>Network
Security: Private Communication in a Public World, 2nd Edition</citetitle>.
Prentice-Hall, 2002.</para><para>Pfleeger, Charles P. and Shari Lawrence Pfleeger. <citetitle>Security
in Computing</citetitle>. Prentice Hall PTR, 2006.</para><para><citetitle>Privacy for Pragmatists: A Privacy Practitioner's Guide to
Sustainable Compliance</citetitle>. Sun Microsystems, Inc, August 2005.</para><para>Rhodes-Ousley, Mark, Roberta Bragg, and Keith Strassberg. <citetitle>Network
Security: The Complete Reference</citetitle>. McGraw-Hill/Osborne, 2004.</para><para>Stoll, Cliff. <citetitle>The Cuckoo's Egg</citetitle>. Doubleday, 1989.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="appol-10"><title>General UNIX Publications</title><para>Bach, Maurice J. <citetitle>The Design of the UNIX Operating System</citetitle>.
Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, NJ, 1986.</para><para>Nemeth, Evi, Garth Snyder, and Scott Seebas. <citetitle>UNIX System
Administration Handbook</citetitle>. Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, NJ,
1989.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</appendix><?Pub *0000019261 0?>