<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><chapter><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="10"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Devices in Trusted Extensions (Overview)</title><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><highlights><para>This chapter describes the extensions that Solaris Trusted Extensions provides to Solaris device
protection.</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="managedev-52" remap="internal">Device Protection With Trusted
Extensions Software</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="managedev-50" remap="internal">Device Allocation Manager
GUI</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="managedev-25" remap="internal">Enforcement of Device Security
in Trusted Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="managedev-40" remap="internal">Devices in Trusted Extensions
(Reference)</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="managedev-52"><title>Device Protection With Trusted Extensions Software</title><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>accessing devices</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>accessing </primary><secondary>devices</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>allocating</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>device allocation</primary><secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>protecting</primary><secondary>devices</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>restricting</primary><secondary>access to devices</secondary>
</indexterm><para>On a Solaris system, devices can be protected by allocation and
by authorization. By default, devices are available to regular users without
an authorization. A system that is configured with Trusted Extensions software
uses the device protection mechanisms of the Solaris OS.</para><para>However, by default, Trusted Extensions requires that a device be allocated
for use, and that the user be authorized to use the device. In addition, devices
are protected by labels. Trusted Extensions provides a graphical user interface
(GUI) for administrators to manage devices. The same interface is used by
users to allocate devices.</para><note><para>In Trusted Extensions, users cannot use the <command>allocate</command> and <command>deallocate</command> commands. Users must use the Device Allocation Manager.
In Solaris Trusted Extensions (JDS), the title of the GUI is Device Manager.</para>
</note><para>For information about device protection in the Solaris OS, see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="devtask-1" remap="external">Chapter 5, <citetitle remap="chapter">Controlling Access to Devices (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para><itemizedlist><para>On a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions, two roles protect
devices.</para><listitem><para>The System Administrator role controls access to peripheral
devices.</para><para>The system administrator makes a device allocatable.
Devices that the system administrator makes nonallocatable cannot be used
by anyone. Allocatable devices can be allocated only by authorized users.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The Security Administrator role restricts the labels at which
a device can be accessed and sets device policy. The security administrator
decides who is authorized to allocate a device.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>The following are the main features of device control with Trusted Extensions software:</para><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Allocate Device authorization</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>authorizations</primary><secondary>Allocate Device</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>diskettes</primary><secondary>accessing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>CD-ROM drives</primary><secondary>accessing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>tape devices</primary><secondary>accessing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>accessing devices</secondary></indexterm>By default, an unauthorized
user on a Trusted Extensions system cannot allocate devices such as tape drives,
CD-ROM drives, or diskette drives.</para><para>A regular user with the Allocate
Device authorization can import or export information at the label at which
the user allocates the device.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users invoke the Device Allocation Manager to allocate devices
when they are logged in directly. To allocate a device remotely, users must
have access to the global zone. Typically, only roles have access to the global
zone.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The label range of each device can be restricted by the security
administrator. Regular users are limited to accessing devices whose label
range includes the labels at which the users are allowed to work. The default
label range of a device is <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> to <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Label ranges can be restricted for both allocatable and nonallocatable
devices. Nonallocatable devices are devices such as frame buffers and printers.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="managedev-11"><title>Device Label Ranges</title><para>To prevent users from copying sensitive information, each allocatable
device has a label range. To use an allocatable device, the user must be currently
operating at a label within the device's label range. If the user is not,
allocation is denied. The user's current label is applied to data that is
imported or exported while the device is allocated to the user. The label
of exported data is displayed when the device is deallocated. The user must
physically label the medium that contains the exported data.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="managedev-32"><title>Effects of Label Range on a Device</title><indexterm><primary>label ranges</primary><secondary>setting on frame buffers</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>restricting</primary><secondary>access to computer based on label</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>computer access</primary><secondary>restricting</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>label ranges</primary><secondary>setting on printers</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>nonallocatable devices</primary><secondary>setting label range</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>setting label range for nonallocatable</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printers</primary><secondary>setting label range</secondary>
</indexterm><para>To restrict direct login access through the console, the security administrator
can set a restricted label range on the frame buffer.</para><para>For example, a restricted label range might be specified to limit access
to a publicly accessible system. The label range enables users to access the
system only at a label within the frame buffer's label range.</para><para>When a host has a local printer, a restricted label range on the printer
limits the jobs that can be printed on the printer.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="managedev-39"><title>Device Access Policies</title><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>access policy</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access policy</primary><secondary>devices</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>setting policy</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>policy defaults</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions follows the same device policies as the Solaris OS.
The security administrator can change default policies and define new policies.
The <command>getdevpolicy</command> command retrieves information about device
policy, and the <command>update_drv</command> command changes device policy.
For more information, see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="devtask-10" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring Device Policy (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.
See also the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="getdevpolicy-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>getdevpolicy</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> and <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="update-drv-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>update_drv</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="managedev-30"><title>Device-Clean Scripts</title><indexterm><primary><command>device-clean</command> scripts</primary><secondary>requirements</secondary>
</indexterm><para>A device-clean script is run when a device is allocated or deallocated.
The Solaris OS provides scripts for tape drives, CD-ROM drives, and diskette
drives. If your site adds allocatable device types to the system, the added
devices might need scripts. To see existing scripts, go to the <filename class="directory">/etc/security/lib</filename> directory. For more information,
see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="devtask-38" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Device-Clean Scripts</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>For Trusted Extensions software, device-clean scripts must satisfy certain
requirements. These requirements are described in the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="device-clean-5" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>device_clean</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="managedev-50"><title>Device Allocation Manager GUI</title><indexterm><primary>actions</primary><secondary>Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>accessing</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Front Panel</primary><secondary>Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Tools subpanel</primary><secondary>Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Device Allocation Manager</primary><secondary>description</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>allocating</primary><secondary>using Device Allocation Manager</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The Device Allocation Manager is used by administrators to administer
allocatable and nonallocatable devices. The Device Allocation Manager is also
used by regular users to allocate and deallocate devices. The users must have
the Allocate Device authorization. In a Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) workspace, the Device Allocation
Manager is opened from the Front Panel. The icon appears as follows:</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="DevAlloc.epsi"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Shows the Device Allocation icon.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><para>In a Solaris Trusted Extensions (JDS) workspace, the GUI is called the Device Manager. This GUI
is started from the Trusted Path menu by selecting Allocate Device. In Trusted CDE,
you can also start the GUI from the Trusted Path menu. The following figure
shows a Device Allocation Manager that was opened by a user who can allocate
the <literal>audio</literal> device.</para><figure><title>Device Allocation Manager Opened by a User</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="devmgr.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Dialog box titled Device Allocation Manager shows the
user name, and the devices that are available to that user.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>Users see an empty list when they are not authorized to allocate devices.
Or, an empty list might indicate that the allocatable devices are currently
allocated by another user or are in an error state. If a user cannot see a
device in the Available Devices list, the user needs to contact the responsible
administrator.</para><para>The Device Administration feature is available to roles that have either
one or both of the authorizations that are needed to administer devices. The
administration authorizations are Configure Device Attributes, and Revoke
or Reclaim Device. The following figure shows a Device Allocation Administration
dialog box.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="devadmin.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Dialog box titled Device Allocation Administration shows
a list of devices and status. Shows the Revoke, Reclaim, New, and Configure
buttons.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><para>In a Solaris Trusted Extensions (JDS), the Device Administration button is called Administration.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="managedev-25"><title>Enforcement of Device Security in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>security training</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>security policy</primary><secondary>users and devices</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>The security administrator decides who can allocate devices and makes
sure that any user who is authorized to use devices is trained. The user is
trusted to do the following:</para><listitem><para>Properly label and handle any media containing exported sensitive
information so that the information does not become available to anyone who
should not see it.</para><para>For example, if information at a label of <constant>NEED TO KNOW ENGINEERING</constant> is stored on a diskette, the person who
exports the information must physically label the disk with the <constant>NEED
TO KNOW ENGINEERING</constant> label. The diskette must be stored where it
is accessible only to members of the engineering group with a need to know.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ensure that labels are properly maintained on any information
being imported (read) from media on these devices.</para><para>An authorized
user must allocate the device at the label that matches the label of the information
that is being imported. For example, if a user allocates a diskette drive
at <constant>PUBLIC</constant>, the user must only import information labeled <constant>PUBLIC</constant>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>Security Administrator role</primary><secondary>enforcing security</secondary></indexterm>The security administrator is also responsible
for enforcing proper compliance with these security requirements.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="managedev-40"><title>Devices in Trusted Extensions (Reference)</title><para>Trusted Extensions device protection uses Solaris interfaces and Trusted Extensions interfaces.</para><para>For Solaris command-line interfaces, see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="devtask-16" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Device Protection (Reference)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>Administrators who do not have access to the Device Allocation Manager
can administer allocatable devices by using the command line. The <command>allocate</command> and <command>deallocate</command> commands have administrative
options. For examples, see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="devtask-13" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Forcibly Allocating a Device</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink> and <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="devtask-31" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Forcibly Deallocating a Device</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>For Trusted Extensions command-line interfaces, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="add-allocatable-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>add_allocatable</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> and <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="remove-allocatable-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>remove_allocatable</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000016402 0?>