<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><glossary id="glossary-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag
atict:user user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Glossary</title><glossentry id="glossary-2"><glossterm>accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>A set of sensitivity labels that are approved for a class
of users or resources. A set of valid <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>s.
See also <olink targetptr="glossary-123" remap="internal">system accreditation range</olink> and <olink targetptr="glossary-138" remap="internal">user accreditation range</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-5"><glossterm>administrative role</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="glossary-104" remap="internal">role</olink><?Pub _bookmark
Command="[Quick Mark]"?> that gives required <olink targetptr="glossary-9" remap="internal">authorization</olink>s, privileged commands, privileged actions, and the Trusted Path <olink targetptr="glossary-112" remap="internal">security attribute</olink> to allow the role to perform
administrative tasks. Roles perform a subset of Solaris superuser's
capabilities, such as backup or auditing.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7"><glossterm>allocation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A mechanism by which access to a <olink targetptr="glossary-28" remap="internal">device</olink> is controlled. See <olink targetptr="glossary-29" remap="internal">device allocation</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-9"><glossterm>authorization</glossterm><glossdef><para>A right granted to a user or role to perform an action that
would otherwise not be allowed by security policy. Authorizations are granted
in <olink targetptr="glossary-54" remap="internal">rights profile</olink>s. Certain commands
require the user to have certain authorizations to succeed. For example, to
print a PostScript file requires the Print Postscript authorization.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-10"><glossterm>application search path</glossterm><glossdef><para>In <olink targetptr="glossary-15" remap="internal">CDE</olink>, the search
path is used by the <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink> to find
applications and certain configuration information. The application search
path is controlled by a <olink targetptr="glossary-131" remap="internal">trusted role</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-15"><glossterm>CDE</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-21" remap="internal">Common Desktop Environment</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-91"><glossterm>CIPSO label</glossterm><glossdef><para>Common IP Security Option. CIPSO is the label standard that Trusted Extensions implements.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-47"><glossterm>classification</glossterm><glossdef><para>The hierarchical component of a <olink targetptr="glossary-16" remap="internal">clearance</olink> or a <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>. A classification
indicates a hierarchical level of security, for example, <literal>TOP SECRET</literal> or <literal>UNCLASSIFIED</literal>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-16"><glossterm>clearance</glossterm><glossdef><para>The upper limit of the set of labels at which a user can work.
The lower limit is the <olink targetptr="glossary-78" remap="internal">minimum label</olink> that
is assigned by the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>.
A clearance can be one of two types, a session clearance or a <olink targetptr="glossary-139" remap="internal">user clearance</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-17"><glossterm>client</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system connected to a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-18"><glossterm>closed network</glossterm><glossdef><para>A network of systems that are configured with Trusted Extensions.
The network is cut off from any non-Trusted Extensions host. The cutoff can be
physical, where no wire extends past the Trusted Extensions network. The cutoff
can be in the software, where the Trusted Extensions hosts recognize only Trusted Extensions hosts.
Data entry from outside the network is restricted to peripherals attached
to Trusted Extensions hosts. Contrast with <olink targetptr="glossary-90" remap="internal">open
network</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-21"><glossterm>Common Desktop Environment</glossterm><glossdef><para>The historical windowing environment for administering Trusted Extensions software. Trusted Extensions modifies
the environment to create Trusted CDE. The
GNOME desktop is also modified to create a Trusted GNOME desktop.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-53"><glossterm>compartment</glossterm><glossdef><para>A nonhierarchical component of a <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink> that is used with the <olink targetptr="glossary-47" remap="internal">classification</olink> component
to form a <olink targetptr="glossary-16" remap="internal">clearance</olink> or a <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>. A compartment represents a  collection
of information, such as would be used by an engineering department or a multidisciplinary
project team.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-22"><glossterm>.copy_files file</glossterm><glossdef><para>An optional setup file on a multilabel system. This file contains
a list of startup files, such as <filename>.cshrc</filename> or <filename>.mozilla</filename>, that the user environment or user applications require in order
for the system or application to behave well. The files that are listed in <filename>.copy_files</filename> are then <emphasis>copied</emphasis> to the user's
home directory at higher labels, when those directories are created. See also <olink targetptr="glossary-72" remap="internal">.link_files file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-26"><glossterm>DAC</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-31" remap="internal">discretionary access control</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-28"><glossterm>device</glossterm><glossdef><para>Devices include printers, computers, tape drives, floppy drives,
CD-ROM drives, DVD drives, audio devices, and internal pseudo terminal devices.
Devices are subject to the read equal write equal <olink targetptr="glossary-74" remap="internal">MAC</olink> policy. Access to removable devices, such as DVD drives, are controlled
by<olink targetptr="glossary-29" remap="internal">device allocation</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-29"><glossterm>device allocation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A mechanism for protecting the information on an allocatable <olink targetptr="glossary-28" remap="internal">device</olink> from access by anybody except the user
who allocates the device. Until a device is deallocated, no one but the user
who allocated a device can access any information that is associated with
the device. For a user to allocate a device, that user must have been granted
the Device Allocation authorization by the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security
administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-31"><glossterm>discretionary access control</glossterm><glossdef><para>The type of access that is granted or that is denied by the
owner of a file or directory at the discretion of the owner. Solaris Trusted Extensions provides
two kinds of discretionary access controls (DAC), UNIX <olink targetptr="glossary-96" remap="internal">permission bits</olink> and ACLs.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-34"><glossterm>domain</glossterm><glossdef><para>A part of the Internet naming hierarchy. It represents a group
of <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink>s on a local network that
share administrative files.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-151"><glossterm>domain of interpretation (DOI)</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
the domain of  interpretation is used to differentiate between  different <filename>label_encodings</filename> files that might have similar labels defined. The
DOI is a set of rules that translates the security attributes on network packets
to the representation of those  security attributes by the local <filename>label_encodings</filename> file. When systems have the same DOI, they share that set of rules
and can translate the labeled network packets.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-36"><glossterm>domain name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The identification of a group of <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink>s on a local network. A domain name consists of a sequence of
component names separated by periods (for example: <literal>example1.town.state.country.org</literal>). As you read a domain name from left to right, the component names
identify more general, and usually remote, areas of administrative authority.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-42"><glossterm>evaluated configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>One or more Trusted Extensions hosts that are running in a configuration
that has been certified as meeting specific criteria by a certification authority.
In the United States, those criteria are the TCSEC. The evaluating and certifying
body is the NSA. Trusted Extensions software that is configured on the Solaris 10&nbsp;11/06 release
is certified to the Common Criteria v2.3 [August 2005], an ISO standard, to
Evaluation Assurance Level (EAL) 4, and against a number of protection profiles.</para><para>The Common Criteria v2 (CCv2) and protection profiles make the earlier
TCSEC U.S. standard obsolete through level B1+. A mutual recognition agreement
for CCv2 has been signed by the United States, the United Kingdom, Canada,
Denmark, the Netherlands, Germany, and France.</para><para>The Trusted Extensions configuration
target provides functionality that is similar to the TCSEC C2 and B1 levels,
with some additional functionality.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-48"><glossterm>file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of files and directories that, when set into
a logical hierarchy, make up an organized, structured set of information.
File systems can be mounted from your local <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink> or a remote system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-51"><glossterm>GFI</glossterm><glossdef><para>Government Furnished Information. In this manual, it refers
to a U.S. government-provided <olink targetptr="glossary-69" remap="internal">label_encodings
file</olink>. In order to use a GFI with Trusted Extensions software, you must
add the Sun-specific <literal>LOCAL DEFINITIONS</literal> section to the end
of the GFI. For details, see <olink targetdoc="trsollbladmin" targetptr="localdef-1" remap="external">Chapter 5, <citetitle remap="chapter">Customizing LOCAL DEFINITIONS,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Label Administration</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-52"><glossterm>host name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The name by which a <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink> is
known to other systems on a network. This name must be unique among all the <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink>s within a given domain. Usually, a
domain identifies a  single organization. A host name can be any combination
of letters, numbers, and minus sign (&minus;), but it cannot begin or end
with a minus sign.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-56"><glossterm>initial label</glossterm><glossdef><para>The <olink targetptr="glossary-78" remap="internal">minimum label</olink> assigned
to a user or role, and the label of the user's initial workspace. The initial
label is the lowest label at which the user or role can work.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-59"><glossterm>initial setup team</glossterm><glossdef><para>A team of at least two people who together oversee the enabling
and configuration of Solaris Trusted Extensions software. One team member is responsible for
security decisions, and the other for system administration decisions.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-61"><glossterm>IP address</glossterm><glossdef><para>Internet protocol address. A unique number that identifies
a networked system so it can communicate by means of Internet protocols. In
IPv4, the address consists of four numbers separated by periods. Most often,
each part of the IP address is a number between 0 and 225. However, the first
number must be less than 224 and the last number cannot be 0.</para><para>IP
addresses are logically divided into two parts: the network, and the <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink> on the network. The network number
is similar to a telephone area code. In relation to the network, the system
number is similar to a phone number.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-66"><glossterm>label</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security identifier that is assigned to an object. The label
is based on the level at which the information in that object should be protected.
Depending on how the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> has
configured the user, a user can see the <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity
label</olink>, or no labels at all. Labels are defined in the <olink targetptr="glossary-69" remap="internal">label_encodings file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-67"><glossterm>label configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Trusted Extensions installation choice of single-label or multilabel
sensitivity labels. In most circumstances, label configuration is identical
on all systems at your site.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-68"><glossterm>labeled host</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="glossary-150" remap="internal">labeled system</olink> that
is part of a trusted network of labeled systems.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-150"><glossterm>labeled system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A labeled system is a system that is running a multilevel
operating system, such as Trusted Extensions or SELinux with MLS enabled. The
system can send and receive network packets that are labeled with a Common
IP Security Option (CIPSO) in the header of the packet.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-152"><glossterm>labeled zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
every zone is assigned a unique label. Although the global zone is labeled, <emphasis>labeled zone</emphasis> typically refers to a non-global zone that is assigned
a label. Labeled zones have two different characteristics from non-global
zones on a Solaris system that is not configured with labels. First,
labeled zones must use the same pool of user IDs and group IDs. Second, labeled
zones can share IP addresses.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-69"><glossterm>label_encodings file</glossterm><glossdef><para>The file where the complete <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity
label</olink> is defined, as are accreditation ranges, label view, default
label visibility, default user clearance, and other aspects of labels.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-70"><glossterm>label range</glossterm><glossdef><para>A set of <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity label</olink>s
that are assigned to commands, zones, and allocatable <olink targetptr="glossary-28" remap="internal">device</olink>s. The range is specified by designating
a maximum label and a minimum label. For commands, the minimum and maximum
labels limit the labels at which the command can be executed. Remote hosts
that do not recognize labels are assigned a single <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity label</olink>, as are any other hosts
that the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> wants
to restrict to a single label. A label range limits the labels at which devices
can be allocated and restrict the labels at which information can be stored
or processed when using the device.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-158"><glossterm>label relationships</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
 a label can dominate another label, be equal to another label, or be disjoint
from another label. For example, the label <literal>Top Secret</literal> 
dominates the label <literal>Secret</literal>.  For two systems with the same <olink targetptr="glossary-151" remap="internal">domain of interpretation (DOI)</olink>, the label <literal>Top Secret</literal> on one system is equal to the label <literal>Top Secret</literal> on
the other system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-98"><glossterm>label set</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-24" remap="internal">security label set</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-72"><glossterm>.link_files file</glossterm><glossdef><para>An optional setup file on a multilabel system. This file contains
a list of startup files, such as <filename>.cshrc</filename> or <filename>.mozilla</filename>, that the user environment or user applications require in order
for the system or application to behave well. The files that are listed in <filename>.link_files</filename> are then <emphasis>linked</emphasis> to the user's
home directory at higher labels, when those directories are created. See also <olink targetptr="glossary-22" remap="internal">.copy_files file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-74"><glossterm>MAC</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-75" remap="internal">mandatory access control</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-75"><glossterm>mandatory access control</glossterm><glossdef><para>Access control that is based on comparing the <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity label</olink> of a file, directory, or <olink targetptr="glossary-28" remap="internal">device</olink> to the sensitivity label of the process
that is trying to access it. The <olink targetptr="glossary-74" remap="internal">MAC</olink> rule,
read equal&ndash;read down, applies when a process at one label attempts to
read a file at a lower label. The <acronym>MAC</acronym> rule, write equal-read
down, applies when a process at one label attempts to write to a directory
at another label.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-78"><glossterm>minimum label</glossterm><glossdef><para>The lower bound of a user's <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity
label</olink>s and the lower bound of the system's sensitivity labels. The
minimum label set by the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> when
specifying a user's <olink targetptr="glossary-112" remap="internal">security attribute</olink>s
is the sensitivity label of the user's first workspace at first login. The
sensitivity label that is specified in the minimum label field by the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> in the <filename>label_encodings</filename>  file sets the lower bound for the system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-154"><glossterm>multilevel desktop</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
users can run a desktop at a particular label. If the user is authorized to
work at more than one label, the user can create a separate workspace to work
at each label. On this multilevel desktop, authorized users can cut and paste
between windows at different labels, receive mail at different labels, and
view and use labeled windows in workspaces of a different label.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-155"><glossterm>multilevel port (MLP)</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
an MLP is used to provide multilevel service in a zone. By default, the X
server is a multilevel service that is defined in the global zone. An MLP
is specified by port number and protocol. For example, the MLP of the X server
for the multilevel desktop is specified by 6000-6003 and TCP.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-84"><glossterm>naming service</glossterm><glossdef><para>A distributed network database that contains key system information
about all the <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink>s on a network,
so that the systems can communicate with each other. With a naming service,
the system information can be maintained, managed, and accessed on a network-wide
basis. Sun supports the LDAP naming service. Without such a service, each <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink> has to maintain its own copy of the
system information in the local <filename>/etc</filename> files.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-86"><glossterm>networked systems</glossterm><glossdef><para>A group of systems that are connected through hardware and
software, sometimes referred to as a local area network (<acronym>LAN</acronym>).
One or more servers are usually needed when systems are networked.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-89"><glossterm>non-networked systems</glossterm><glossdef><para>Computers that are not connected to a network or do not rely
on other hosts.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-90"><glossterm>open network</glossterm><glossdef><para>A network of Solaris Trusted Extensions hosts that is connected physically
to other networks and that uses Trusted Extensions software to communicate with
non-Trusted Extensions hosts. Contrast with <olink targetptr="glossary-18" remap="internal">closed
network</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-93"><glossterm>outside the evaluated configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>When software that has been proved to be able satisfy the
criteria for an <olink targetptr="glossary-42" remap="internal">evaluated configuration</olink>,
is configured with settings that do not satisfy security criteria, the software
is described as being <emphasis>outside the evaluated configuration</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-96"><glossterm>permission bits</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of <olink targetptr="glossary-31" remap="internal">discretionary access
control</olink> in which the owner specifies a set of bits to signify who
can read, write, or execute a file or directory. Three different sets of permissions
are assigned to each file or directory: one set for the owner, one set for
the owner's group, and one set for all others.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-146"><glossterm>primary administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>The person who is entrusted to create new <olink targetptr="glossary-54" remap="internal">rights profile</olink>s for the organization, and
to fix machine difficulties that are beyond the power of the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> and <olink targetptr="glossary-125" remap="internal">system administrator</olink> combined. This role
should be assumed rarely. After initial security configuration, more secure
sites can choose not to create this role, and not to assign any role the Primary
Administrator profile.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-99"><glossterm>privilege</glossterm><glossdef><para>Powers that are granted to a process that is executing a command.
The full set of privileges describes the full capabilities of the system,
from basic capabilities to administrative capabilities. Privileges that bypass <olink targetptr="glossary-113" remap="internal">security policy</olink>, such as setting the clock
on a system, can be granted by a site's <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security
administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-100"><glossterm>process</glossterm><glossdef><para>An action that executes a command on behalf of the user who
invokes the command. A process receives a number of <olink targetptr="glossary-112" remap="internal">security attribute</olink>s from the user, including
the user ID (UID), the group ID (GID), the supplementary group list, and the
user's audit ID (AUID).  Security attributes received by a process include
any <olink targetptr="glossary-99" remap="internal">privilege</olink>s that are available to
the command being executed and the <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity
label</olink> of the current workspace.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-102"><glossterm>profile shell</glossterm><glossdef><para>A special shell that recognizes <olink targetptr="glossary-99" remap="internal">privilege</olink>s. A profile shell typically limits users to fewer commands, but can
allow these commands to run with privilege. The profile shell is the default
shell of a <olink targetptr="glossary-131" remap="internal">trusted role</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-103"><glossterm>remote host</glossterm><glossdef><para>A different system than the local system. A remote host can
be an <olink targetptr="glossary-137" remap="internal">unlabeled host</olink> or a <olink targetptr="glossary-68" remap="internal">labeled host</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-54"><glossterm>rights profile</glossterm><glossdef><para>A bundling mechanism for commands and CDE actions and for
the <olink targetptr="glossary-112" remap="internal">security attribute</olink>s that are assigned
to these executables. Rights profiles allow Solaris administrators to
control who can execute which commands and to control the attributes these
commands have when they are executed. When a user logs in, all rights assigned
to that user are in effect, and the user has access to all the commands, CDE
actions, and <olink targetptr="glossary-9" remap="internal">authorization</olink>s assigned
in all of that user's rights profiles.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-104"><glossterm>role</glossterm><glossdef><para>A role is like a user, except that a role cannot log in. Typically,
a role is used to assign administrative capabilities. Roles are limited to
a particular set of commands and CDE actions. See <olink targetptr="glossary-5" remap="internal">administrative
role</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-111"><glossterm>security administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>In an organization where sensitive information must be protected,
the person or persons who define and enforce the site's <olink targetptr="glossary-113" remap="internal">security policy</olink>. These persons are cleared
to access all information that is being processed at the site. In software,
the Security Administrator <olink targetptr="glossary-5" remap="internal">administrative role</olink> is
assigned to one or more individuals who have the proper <olink targetptr="glossary-16" remap="internal">clearance</olink>. These administrators configure
the <olink targetptr="glossary-112" remap="internal">security attribute</olink>s of all users
and hosts so that the software enforces the site's security policy. In contrast,
see <olink targetptr="glossary-125" remap="internal">system administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-112"><glossterm>security attribute</glossterm><glossdef><para>An attribute that is used to enforce Trusted Extensions <olink targetptr="glossary-113" remap="internal">security policy</olink>. Various sets of security
attributes are assigned to <olink targetptr="glossary-100" remap="internal">process</olink>es,
users, zones, hosts, allocatable <olink targetptr="glossary-28" remap="internal">device</olink>s,
and other objects.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-24"><glossterm>security label set</glossterm><glossdef><para>Specifies a discrete set of security labels for a <olink targetptr="glossary-129" remap="internal">tnrhtp database</olink> entry. Hosts that are assigned
to a template with a security label set can send and receive packets that
match any one of the labels in the label set.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-113"><glossterm>security policy</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Trusted Extensions host, the set of <olink targetptr="glossary-26" remap="internal">DAC</olink>, <olink targetptr="glossary-74" remap="internal">MAC</olink>,
and labeling rules that define how information can be accessed.  At a customer
site, the set of rules that define the sensitivity of the information being
processed at that site and the measures that are used to protect the information
from unauthorized access.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-114"><glossterm>sensitivity label</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink> that
is assigned to an object or a process. The label is used to limit access according
to the security level of the data that is contained.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-148"><glossterm>separation of duty</glossterm><glossdef><para>The security policy that two administrators or roles be required
to create and authenticate a user. One administrator or role is responsible
for creating the user, the user's home directory, and other basic administration.
The other administrator or role is responsible for the user's security attributes,
such as the password and the label range.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-144"><glossterm>Solaris Management Console</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Java-based administrative GUI that contains <olink targetptr="glossary-145" remap="internal">toolbox</olink>es of administrative programs. In Trusted CDE,
this GUI can be launched from the Application Manager. Most system, network,
and user administration is done by using the Console toolboxes.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-124"><glossterm>system</glossterm><glossdef><para>Generic name for a computer. After installation, a system
on a network is often referred to as a host.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-123"><glossterm>system accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The set of all valid <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>s
that are created according to the rules that the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> defines in the <olink targetptr="glossary-69" remap="internal">label_encodings
file</olink>, plus the two administrative <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>s
that are used on every system that is configured with Trusted Extensions. The
administrative labels are <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> and <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-125"><glossterm>system administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>In Trusted Extensions, the <olink targetptr="glossary-131" remap="internal">trusted
role</olink> assigned to the user or users who are responsible for performing
standard system management tasks such as setting up the non-security-relevant
portions of user accounts. In contrast, see <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security
administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-128"><glossterm>tnrhdb database</glossterm><glossdef><para>The trusted network remote host database. This database assigns
a set of label characteristics to a remote host. The database is accessible
either as a file in <filename>/etc/security/tsol/tnrhdb</filename> or from
the LDAP server.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-129"><glossterm>tnrhtp database</glossterm><glossdef><para>The trusted network remote host template. This database defines
the set of label characteristics that a remote host can be assigned. The database
is accessible either as a file in <filename>/etc/security/tsol/tnrhtp</filename>,
 or from the LDAP server.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-145"><glossterm>toolbox</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of programs in the <olink targetptr="glossary-144" remap="internal">Solaris
Management Console</olink>. On a Trusted Extensions host, administrators use <literal>Policy=TSOL</literal> toolboxes. Each toolbox has programs that are usable
in the scope of the toolbox. For example, the Trusted Network Zones tool,
which handles the system's <filename>tnzonecfg</filename> database, exists
only in the <literal>Files</literal> toolbox, because its scope is always
local. The User Accounts program exists in all toolboxes. To create a local
user, the administrator uses the <literal>Files</literal> toolbox, and to
create a network user, the administrator uses the <literal>LDAP</literal> toolbox.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-159"><glossterm>trusted editor</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
the trusted editor is used to create and modify administrative files. The
file name cannot be changed by the editor. Also, use of the editor is audited
and shell escape commands are disabled. In Trusted CDE, the Admin Editor action
starts the trusted editor. In Trusted GNOME,
the <command>/usr/dt/bin/trusted_edit</command> command starts the trusted
editor.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-130"><glossterm>Trusted Network databases</glossterm><glossdef><para><filename>tnrhtp</filename>, the trusted network remote host
template and <filename>tnrhdb</filename>, the trusted network remote host
database together define the <olink targetptr="glossary-103" remap="internal">remote host</olink>s
that a Trusted Extensions system can communicate with.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-156"><glossterm>trusted path</glossterm><glossdef><para>On a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
the trusted path is a reliable, tamper-proof way to interact with the system.
The trusted path is used to ensure that administrative functions cannot be
compromised. User functions that must be protected, such as changing a password,
also use the trusted path. When the trusted path is active, the desktop displays
a tamper-proof indicator.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-157"><glossterm>unlabeled system</glossterm><glossdef><para>To a Solaris system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
an unlabeled system is a system that is not running a multilevel operating
system, such as Trusted Extensions or SELinux with MLS enabled. An unlabeled system
does not send labeled packets. If the communicating Trusted Extensions system
has assigned to the unlabeled system a single label, then network communication
between the Trusted Extensions system and the unlabeled system happens at that
label. An unlabeled system is also called a &ldquo;single-level system&rdquo;.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-131"><glossterm>trusted role</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="glossary-5" remap="internal">administrative role</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-133"><glossterm>trusted stripe</glossterm><glossdef><para>A region that cannot be spoofed. In Trusted CDE, the trusted stripe
is at the bottom of the screen, and in Trusted GNOME the
stripe is at the top. The stripe provides visual feedback about the state
of the window system: a trusted path indicator and window <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity label</olink>. When <olink targetptr="glossary-114" remap="internal">sensitivity label</olink>s are configured to not
be viewable for a user, the trusted stripe is reduced to an icon that displays
only the trusted path indicator.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-147"><glossterm>txzonemgr script</glossterm><glossdef><para>The <filename>/usr/sbin/txzonemgr</filename> script provides
a simple GUI for managing labeled zones. The script also provides menu items
for networking options, name services options, and for clienting the global
zone to an existing LDAP server. <filename>txzonemgr</filename> is run by
root in the global zone.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-137"><glossterm>unlabeled host</glossterm><glossdef><para>A networked system that sends unlabeled network packets, such
as a system that is running the Solaris OS.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-138"><glossterm>user accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The set of all possible labels at which a regular user can
work on the <olink targetptr="glossary-124" remap="internal">system</olink>. The site's <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> specifies the range
in the <olink targetptr="glossary-69" remap="internal">label_encodings file</olink> file. The
rules for well-formed <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>s that define
the <olink targetptr="glossary-123" remap="internal">system accreditation range</olink> are
additionally restricted by the values in the <literal>ACCREDITATION RANGE</literal> section
of the file: the upper bound, the lower bound, the combination constraints
and other restrictions.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-139"><glossterm>user clearance</glossterm><glossdef><para>The <olink targetptr="glossary-16" remap="internal">clearance</olink> assigned
by the <olink targetptr="glossary-111" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> that
sets the upper bound of the set of <olink targetptr="glossary-66" remap="internal">label</olink>s
at which a user can work at any time. The user can decide to accept the default,
or can further restrict that clearance during any particular login session.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary><?Pub *0000037312 0?>