<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub Inc?><chapter id="managemail-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="10"?><?Pub Tag
atict:user user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Multilevel Mail in Trusted Extensions (Overview)</title><indexterm><primary>administering</primary><secondary>mail</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>mail</primary><secondary>administering</secondary>
</indexterm><highlights><para>This chapter covers security and multilevel mailers on systems that
are configured with Solaris Trusted Extensions.</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="managemail-2" remap="internal">Multilevel Mail Service</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="managemail-12" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Mail Features</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="managemail-2"><title>Multilevel Mail Service</title><indexterm><primary>mail</primary><secondary>multilevel</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions provides multilevel mail for any mail application. When
regular users start their mailer, the application opens at the user's current
label. If users are operating in a multilevel system, they might want to link
or copy their mailer initialization files. For details, see <olink targetptr="manageusers-11" remap="internal">How to Configure Startup Files for Users in Trusted
Extensions</olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="managemail-12"><title>Trusted Extensions Mail Features</title><indexterm><primary>mail</primary><secondary>implementation in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, the System Administrator role sets up and administers
mail servers according to instructions in the Solaris <olink targetdoc="sysadv2" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Advanced Administration</citetitle></olink> and <olink targetdoc="sysadv3" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: IP Services</citetitle></olink>.
In addition, the security administrator determines how Trusted Extensions mail
features need to be configured.</para><itemizedlist><para>The following aspects of managing mail are specific to Trusted Extensions:</para><listitem><para>The <filename>.mailrc</filename> file is at a user's minimum
label.</para><para>Therefore, users who work at multiple labels do not have
a <filename>.mailrc</filename> file at the higher labels, unless they copy
or link the <filename>.mailrc</filename> file in their minimum-label directory
to each higher directory.</para><para>The Security Administrator role or the
individual user can add the <filename>.mailrc</filename> file to either <filename>.copy_files</filename> or <filename>.link_files</filename>. For a description
of these files, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="updatehome-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>updatehome</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page. For configuration suggestions, see <olink targetptr="manageusers-28" remap="internal">.copy_files and .link_files Files</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Your mail reader can run at every label on a system. Some
configuration is required to connect a mail client to the server.</para><para>For
example, to use Mozilla mail for multilevel mail requires that you configure
a Mozilla mail client at each label to specify the mail server. The mail server
could be the same or different for each label, but the server must be specified.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The Mailing Lists tool in the Solaris Management Console manages mail aliases.</para><para>Depending on the scope of the selected Solaris Management Console toolbox, you can update
the local <filename>/etc/aliases</filename> file or the LDAP entry on the Sun Java System Directory Server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions software checks host and user labels before sending or
forwarding mail.</para><listitem><para>The software checks that the mail is within the accreditation
range of the host. The checks are described in this list and in <olink targetptr="managetnet-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, Managing Networks in Trusted Extensions (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The software checks that the mail is between the account's
clearance and minimum label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Users can read email that is received within their accreditation
range. During a session, users can read mail only at their current label.</para><para>To contact regular user by email, an administrative role must send mail
from a workspace that is at a label that the user can read. The user's default
label is usually a good choice.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000004945 0?>