<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><chapter id="secreq-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="10"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Security Requirements on a Trusted Extensions System
(Overview)</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes configurable security features on a system that
is configured with Solaris Trusted Extensions.</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="secreq-2" remap="internal">Configurable Solaris Security
Features</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="commontasks-11" remap="internal">Security Requirements Enforcement</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="commontasks-7" remap="internal">Rules When Changing the Level
of Security for Data</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="commontasks-25" remap="internal">Customization of Solaris
Trusted Extensions (CDE)</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="secreq-2"><title>Configurable Solaris Security Features</title><para>Trusted Extensions uses the same security features that the Solaris OS provides,
and adds some features. For example, the Solaris OS provides <command>eeprom</command> protection,
password requirements and strong password algorithms, system protection by
locking out a user, and protection from keyboard shutdown.</para><para>Trusted Extensions differs from the Solaris OS in the actual procedures that
are used to modify these security defaults. In Trusted Extensions, you typically
administer systems by assuming a role. Local settings are modified by using
the <olink targetptr="glossary-159" remap="internal">trusted editor</olink>.
Changes that affect the network of users, roles, and hosts are made in the Solaris Management Console.</para><sect2 id="secreq-3"><title>Trusted Extensions Interfaces for Configuring Security
Features</title><para>Procedures are provided in this book where Trusted Extensions requires a
particular interface to modify security settings, and that interface is optional
in the Solaris OS. Where Trusted Extensions requires the use of the trusted editor
to edit local files, no separate procedures are provided in this book. For
example, the procedure <olink targetptr="commontasks-29" remap="internal">How to Prevent Account
Locking for Users</olink> describes how to update a user's account by using
the Solaris Management Console to prevent the account from being locked. However, the procedure
for setting a system-wide password lock policy is not provided in this book.
You follow the Solaris instructions, except that in Trusted Extensions,
you use the trusted editor to modify the system file.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-13"><title>Extension of Solaris Security Mechanisms
by Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>security mechanisms</primary><secondary>extensible</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>The following Solaris security mechanisms are extensible in Trusted Extensions as
they are in the Solaris OS:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Audit events and classes &ndash;</emphasis> Adding
audit events and audit classes is described in <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="audittask-1" remap="external">Chapter 30, <citetitle remap="chapter">Managing Solaris Auditing (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Rights profiles &ndash;</emphasis> Adding
rights profiles is described in <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="prbactm-1" remap="external">Part&nbsp;III, <citetitle remap="chapter">Roles, Rights Profiles, and Privileges,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Roles &ndash;</emphasis> Adding roles
is described in <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="prbactm-1" remap="external">Part&nbsp;III, <citetitle remap="chapter">Roles, Rights Profiles, and Privileges,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Authorizations &ndash;</emphasis> For
an example of adding a new authorization, see <olink targetptr="managedev-16" remap="internal">Customizing
Device Authorizations in Trusted Extensions (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>As in the Solaris OS, privileges cannot be extended.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="secreq-5"><title>Trusted Extensions Security Features</title><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions provides the following unique security features:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Labels &ndash;</emphasis> Subjects
and objects are labeled. Processes are labeled. Zones and the network are
labeled.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Device Allocation Manager &ndash;</emphasis> By
default, devices are protected by allocation requirements. The Device Allocation
Manager GUI is the interface for administrators and for regular users.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Change Password menu item</primary><secondary>description</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>passwords</primary><secondary>Change Password menu item</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>passwords</primary><secondary>changing user passwords</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>Change Password menu item</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Change Password menu item &ndash;</emphasis> The
Trusted Path menu enables you to change your user password, and the password
of the role that you have assumed.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="commontasks-11"><title>Security Requirements Enforcement</title><para><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>security training</secondary></indexterm>To ensure that the security of the system is not compromised,
administrators need to protect passwords, files, and audit data. Users need
to be trained to do their part. To be consistent with the requirements for
an evaluated configuration, follow the guidelines in this section.</para><sect2 id="commontasks-16"><title>Users and Security Requirements</title><indexterm><primary>security policy</primary><secondary>training users</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Each site's security administrator ensures that users are trained in
security procedures. The security administrator needs to communicate the following
rules to new employees and remind existing employees of these rules on a regular
basis:</para><listitem><para>Do not tell anyone your password.</para><para>Anyone who knows
your password can access the same information that you can without being identified
and therefore without being accountable.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Do not write your password down or include it in an email
message.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Choose passwords that are hard to guess.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Do not send your password to anyone by email.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Do not leave your computer unattended without locking the
screen or logging off.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Remember that administrators do not rely on email to send
instructions to users. Do not ever follow emailed instructions from an administrator
without first double-checking with the administrator.</para><para>Be aware
that sender information in email can be forged.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Because you are responsible for the access permissions on
files and directories that you create, make sure that the permissions on your
files and directories are set appropriately. Do not allow unauthorized users
to read a file, to change a file, to list the contents of a directory, or
to add to a directory.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Your site might want to provide additional suggestions.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-4"><title>Email Usage</title><para>It is an unsafe practice to use email to instruct users to take an action.</para><para>Tell users not to trust email with instructions that purport to come
from an administrator. Doing so prevents the possibility that spoofed email
messages could be used to fool users into changing a password to a certain
value or divulging the password, which could subsequently be used to log in
and compromise the system.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-2"><title>Password Enforcement</title><para>The System Administrator role must specify a unique user name and user
ID when creating a new account. When choosing the name and ID for a new account,
the administrator you must ensure that both the user name and associated ID
are not duplicated anywhere on the network and have not been previously used.</para><itemizedlist><para>The Security Administrator role is responsible for specifying the original
password for each account and for communicating the passwords to users of
new accounts. You must consider the following information when administering
passwords:</para><listitem><para>Make sure that the accounts for users who are able to assume
the Security Administrator role are configured so that the account cannot
be locked. This practice ensures that at least one account can always log
in and assume the Security Administrator role to reopen everyone's account
if all other accounts are locked.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Communicate the password to the user of a new account in such
a way that the password cannot be eavesdropped by anyone else.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Change an account's password if you have any suspicion that
the password has been discovered by someone who should not know it.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Never reuse user names or user IDs over the lifetime of the
system.</para><itemizedlist><para>Ensuring that user names and user IDs are not reused prevents possible
confusion about the following:</para><listitem><para>Which actions were performed by which user when audit records
are analyzed</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Which user owns which files when archived files are restored</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-3"><title>Information Protection</title><indexterm><primary>computer access</primary><secondary>administrator responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>You as an administrator are responsible for correctly setting up and
maintaining discretionary access control (DAC) and mandatory access control
(MAC) protections for security-critical files. Critical files include the
following:</para><listitem><para><filename>shadow</filename> <emphasis role="strong">file &ndash;</emphasis> Contains
encrypted passwords. See <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="shadow-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>shadow</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>prof_attr</filename> <emphasis role="strong">database &ndash;</emphasis> Contains definitions of rights profiles. See <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="prof-attr-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>prof_attr</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>exec_attr</filename> <emphasis role="strong">database &ndash;</emphasis> Contains commands and actions that are part of rights profiles.
See <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="exec-attr-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>exec_attr</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>user_attr</filename> <emphasis role="strong">file &ndash;</emphasis> Contains the rights profiles, privileges, and authorizations that
are assigned to local users. See <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="user-attr-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>user_attr</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Audit trail &ndash;</emphasis> Contains
the audit records that the auditing service has collected. See <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="audit.log-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>audit.log</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><caution><para>Because the protection mechanisms for LDAP entries are not
subject to the access control policy enforced by the Trusted Extensions software,
the default LDAP entries must not be extended, and their access rules must
not be modified.</para>
</caution>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-22"><title>Password Protection</title><para><indexterm><primary>passwords</primary><secondary>storage</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary sortas="ADMIN_HIL"><constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> label</primary><secondary>protecting administrative files</secondary></indexterm>In
local files, passwords are protected from viewing by DAC and from modifications
by both DAC and MAC. Passwords for local accounts are maintained in the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file, which is readable only by superuser. For more
information, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="shadow-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>shadow</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-5"><title>Group Administration</title><indexterm><primary>groups</primary><secondary>security requirements</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The System Administrator role needs to verify on the local system and
on the network that all groups have a unique group ID (GID).</para><itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>groups</primary><secondary>deletion precautions</secondary></indexterm>When a local group is deleted from the system, the System Administrator
role must ensure the following:</para><listitem><para>All objects with the GID of the deleted group must be deleted
or assigned to another group.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>security training</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>security precautions</secondary></indexterm>All users who have the deleted group as their primary group must
be reassigned to another primary group.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-6"><title>User Deletion Practices</title><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>deletion precautions</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>When an account is deleted from the system, the System Administrator
role and the Security Administrator role must take the following actions:</para><listitem><para>Delete the account's home directory.</para>
</listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><para>Delete any processes or jobs that are owned by the deleted account:</para><listitem><para>Delete any objects that are owned by the account,or assign
the ownership to another user.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Delete any <command>at</command> or <command>batch</command> jobs
that are scheduled on behalf of the user. For details, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="at-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>at</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> and <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="crontab-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>crontab</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Never reuse the user (account) name or user ID.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="commontasks-7"><title>Rules When Changing the Level of Security
for Data</title><indexterm><primary>cut and paste</primary><secondary>and labels</secondary>
</indexterm><para>By default, regular users can perform cut-and-paste, copy-and-paste,
and drag-and-drop operations on both files and selections. The source and
target must be at the same label.</para><para>To change the label of files, or the label of information within files
requires authorization. When users are authorized to change the security level
of data, the Selection Manager application mediates the transfer. The <filename>/usr/dt/config/sel_config</filename> file controls file relabeling actions, and the cutting and copying
of information to a different label. The <filename>/usr/dt/bin/sel_mgr</filename> application
controls drag-and-drop operations between windows. As the following tables
illustrate, the relabeling of a selection is more restrictive than the relabeling
of a file.</para><para>The following table summarizes the rules for file relabeling. The rules
cover cut-and-paste, copy-and-paste, and drag-and-drop operations.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1" id="commontasks-tbl-1"><title>Conditions
for Moving Files to a New Label</title><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><?PubTbl tgroup dispwid="6.98in"?><colspec colname="column1" colwidth="117.81*" colsep="1"/><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="65.77*"/><colspec colname="column3" colwidth="87.00*"/><colspec colname="column4" colwidth="125.42*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Transaction Description</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Label Relationship</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Owner Relationship</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Required Authorization</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry morerows="4" align="left" valign="top"><para>Copy and paste, cut and paste, or drag and drop of files between File
Managers</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same label</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>None</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Downgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.file.downgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Upgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.file.upgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Downgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Different UIDs</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.file.downgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Upgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Different UIDs</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.file.upgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>Different rules apply to selections within a window or file. Drag-and-drop
of <emphasis>selections</emphasis> always requires equality of labels and
ownership. Drag-and-drop between windows is mediated by the <filename>sel_mgr</filename> application,
not by the <filename>sel_config</filename> file.</para><para>The rules for changing the label of selections are summarized in the
following table.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1" id="commontasks-tbl-2"><title>Conditions
for Moving Selections to a New Label</title><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><?PubTbl tgroup dispwid="6.98in"?><colspec colname="column1" colwidth="96.13*" colsep="1"/><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="78.91*"/><colspec colname="column3" colwidth="106.95*"/><colspec colname="column4" colwidth="113.98*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Transaction Description</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Label Relationship</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Owner Relationship</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Required Authorization</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry morerows="4" align="left" valign="top"><para>Copy and paste, or cut and paste of selections between windows</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same label</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>None</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Downgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.win.downgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Upgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.win.upgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Downgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Different UIDs</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.win.downgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Upgrade</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Different UIDs</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para><constant>solaris.label.win.upgrade</constant></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Drag and drop of selections between windows</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same label</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>Same UID</para>
</entry><entry align="left" valign="top"><para>None applicable</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>Trusted Extensions provides a selection confirmer to mediate label changes.
This window appears when an authorized user attempts to change the label of
a file or selection. The user has 120 seconds to confirm the operation. To
change the security level of data without this window requires the <constant>solaris.label.win.noview</constant> authorization, in addition to the relabeling authorizations. The
following illustration shows a selection, <literal>zonename</literal>, in
the window.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="selmgr.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The illustration shows the Selection Confirmer.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><para>By default, the selection confirmer displays whenever data is being
transferred to a different label. If a selection requires several transfer
decisions, the automatic reply mechanism provides a way to reply once to the
several transfers. For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="sel-config-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sel_config</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page and the following
section.</para><sect2 id="commontasks-34"><title><filename>sel_config</filename> File</title><para><indexterm><primary><filename>sel_config</filename> file</primary><secondary>configuring selection transfer rules</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>/usr/dt/config/sel_config</filename> file</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/dt/config/sel_config</filename> file</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>cutting and pasting</primary><secondary>configuring rules for label changes</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary><filename>sel_config</filename> file</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>changing</primary><secondary>rules for label changes</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>downgrading labels</primary><secondary>configuring rules for selection confirmer</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>upgrading labels</primary><secondary>configuring rules for selection confirmer</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>configuring rules for label changes</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>downgrading and upgrading</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Selection Manager</primary><secondary>configuring rules for selection confirmer</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary><filename>/usr/dt/config/sel_config</filename></secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary><filename>/etc/dt/config/sel_config</filename></secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/dt/config/sel_config</filename> file</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>/usr/dt/config/sel_config</filename> file</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>sel_config</filename> file</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>system files</primary><secondary>Trusted Extensions <filename>sel_config</filename></secondary></indexterm>The  <filename>sel_config</filename> file
is checked to determine the behavior of the selection confirmer when an operation
would upgrade or downgrade a label.</para><itemizedlist><para>The <filename>sel_config</filename> file defines the following:</para><listitem><para>A list of selection types to which automatic replies are given</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether certain types of operations can be automatically confirmed</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether a selection confirmer dialog box is displayed</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>changing</primary><secondary>Selection Confirmer defaults</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>modifying</primary><secondary><filename>sel_config</filename> file</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Selection Confirmer</primary><secondary>changing defaults</secondary></indexterm>In Trusted CDE, the Security Administrator role can change the defaults
by using the Configure Selection Confirmation action in the Trusted_Extensions
folder. The new settings become effective at the next login. If you are in Solaris Trusted Extensions (JDS) when
modifying the file, do not use the CDE action. Copy the <filename>sel_config</filename> file
to the <filename>/etc/dt/config</filename> directory. Then, customize that
copy as you would customize any other CDE configuration file.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="commontasks-25"><title>Customization of Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE)</title><para>In Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE), users can add actions to the Front Panel and customize the
Workspace menu. Trusted Extensions software limits users' ability to add programs
and commands to CDE.</para><sect2 id="commontasks-14"><title>Front Panel Customization</title><para>Anyone can drag and drop a pre-existing action from the Application
Manager to the Front Panel, as long as the account performing the modification
has the action in its profile. Actions in the <filename class="directory">/usr/dt/</filename> or <filename class="directory">/etc/dt/</filename>  directories
can be added to the Front Panel, but applications in the  <filename class="directory">$HOME/.dt/appconfig</filename> directory cannot. While users
can use the Create Action action, they cannot write into any of the directories
where the system-wide actions are stored. Therefore, regular users cannot
create actions that are usable.</para><para>In Trusted Extensions, the actions' search path has been changed. Actions
in any individual's home directory are processed last instead of first. Therefore,
no one can customize existing actions.</para><para><indexterm><primary>Security Administrator role</primary><secondary>modifying window configuration files</secondary></indexterm>The Security Administrator
role is assigned the Admin Editor action, so can make any needed modifications
to the <filename>/usr/dt/appconfig/types/C/dtwm.fp</filename> file and the
other configuration files for the Front Panel subpanels.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="commontasks-10"><title>Workspace Menu Customization</title><para>The Workspace Menu is the menu that appears when you click mouse button
3 on the background of the workspace. Regular users can customize the menu,
and add items to the menu.</para><itemizedlist><para>The following conditions apply when a user is allowed to work at multiple
labels:</para><listitem><para>The user must have a home directory in the global zone.</para><para>To save the customizations, processes in the global zone must be able
to write to the user's home directory at the correct label. The zone path
to a user home directory that is writable by global zone processes is similar
to the following:</para><screen>/zone/<replaceable>zone-name</replaceable>/home/<replaceable>username</replaceable></screen>
</listitem><listitem><para>The user must use the Customize Menu and Add Item to Menu
options in a regular user workspace. The user can create a different customization
for each label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>When the user assumes a role, changes to the Workspace Menu
persist.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Changes that are made to the Workspace Menu are stored in
the user's home directory at the current label. The customized menu file is <filename class="directory">.dt/wsmenu</filename>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The user's rights profile must enable the user to run the
desired action.</para><para>Any action that is added to the Workspace Menu
must be handled by one of the user's rights profiles. Otherwise, the action
fails when invoked and an error message is displayed.</para><para>For example, anyone with the Run action can double-click the icon for
any executable and run it, even if the action or any commands that the action
invokes are not in one of the account's rights profiles. By default, roles
are not assigned the Run action. Therefore, any menu item that requires the
Run action fails when executed by a role.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000030006 0?>