<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><appendix id="txapp-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="10"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Quick Reference to Trusted Extensions Administration</title><indexterm><primary>administering</primary><secondary>quick reference for administrators</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Trusted Extensions</primary><secondary>quick reference to administration</secondary>
</indexterm><highlights><para>Solaris Trusted Extensions interfaces extend the Solaris OS. This appendix provides a quick
reference of the differences. For a detailed list of interfaces, including
library routines and system calls, see <olink targetptr="txmp-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;E, List of Trusted Extensions Man Pages</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="txapp-2"><title>Administrative Interfaces in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>differences</primary><secondary>administrative interfaces in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions provides interfaces for its software. The following interfaces
are available only when Trusted Extensions software is running:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term><command>txzonemgr</command> script</term><listitem><para>Provides a menu-based wizard for creating, installing, initializing,
and booting labeled zones. The title of the menu is Labeled Zone Manager.
This script also provides menu items for networking options, name services
options, and for clienting the global zone to an existing LDAP server.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Trusted CDE actions</term><listitem><para>In Trusted CDE, Workspace Menu &ndash;&gt; Application Manager &ndash;&gt;
Trusted_Extensions contains CDE actions that configure files, install and
boot zones, and simplify other Trusted Extensions tasks. For the tasks that these
actions perform, see <olink targetptr="txtool-3" remap="internal">Trusted CDE Actions</olink>. Trusted CDE online
help also describes these actions.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Admin Editor</term><listitem><para>This trusted editor is used to edit system files. In Trusted CDE,
Workspace Menu &ndash;&gt; Application Manager &ndash;&gt; Trusted_Extensions &ndash;&gt;
 Admin Editor invokes the Admin Editor. In Trusted GNOME,
the editor is invoked from the command line. You provide the file to be edited
as the argument, as in:</para><screen>/usr/dt/bin/trusted_edit <replaceable>filename</replaceable></screen>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Device Allocation Manager</term><listitem><para>In Trusted Extensions, this GUI is used to administer devices.
The Device Administration dialog box is used by administrators to configure
devices.</para><para>The Device Allocation Manager is used by roles and regular users to
allocate devices. The GUI is available from the Trusted Path menu.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Label Builder</term><listitem><para>This application is invoked when the user can choose a label
or a clearance. This application also appears when a role assigns labels or
label ranges to devices, zones, users, or roles.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Selection Manager</term><listitem><para>This application is invoked when an authorized user or authorized
role attempts to upgrade or downgrade information.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Trusted Path menu</term><listitem><para>This menu handles interactions with the trusted computing
base (TCB). For example, this menu has a Change Password menu item. In Trusted CDE,
you access the Trusted Path menu from the workspace switch area. In Trusted JDS,
you access the Trusted Path menu by clicking the trusted symbol at the left
of the trusted stripe.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Administrative commands</term><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions provides commands to obtain labels and perform
other tasks. For a list of the commands, see <olink targetptr="txtool-4" remap="internal">Command
Line Tools in Trusted Extensions</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1><sect1 id="txapp-3"><title>Solaris Interfaces Extended by Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>differences</primary><secondary>extending  Solaris interfaces</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions adds to existing Solaris configuration files, commands,
and GUIs:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Administrative commands</term><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions adds options to selected Solaris commands.
For a list, see <olink targetptr="txtool-tbl-5" remap="internal">Table&nbsp;8&ndash;5</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Configuration files</term><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions adds two privileges, <constant>net_mac_aware</constant> and <constant>net_mlp</constant>. For the use of <constant>net_mac_aware</constant>, see <olink targetptr="managefiles-31" remap="internal">Access to NFS Mounted Directories in Trusted Extensions</olink>.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds authorizations to the <filename>auth_attr</filename> database.
For a list, see <olink targetdoc="trsoltrans" targetptr="trans-28" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Additional Rights and Authorizations in Trusted Extensions</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Transition Guide</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds executables, including CDE actions, to the <filename>exec_attr</filename> database.</para><para>Trusted Extensions modifies existing rights profiles in the <filename>prof_attr</filename> database. It also adds profiles to the database.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds CDE actions to the executables that can be privileged
in the <filename>exec_attr</filename> database.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds fields to the <filename>policy.conf</filename> database.
For the fields, see <olink targetptr="manageusers-45" remap="internal">policy.conf File Defaults
in Trusted Extensions</olink>.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds audit tokens, audit events, audit classes, and audit
policy options. For a list, see <olink targetptr="audtask-25" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions
Audit Reference</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Solaris Management Console</term><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions adds a Security Templates tool to the Computers
and Networks tool set.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds a Trusted Network Zones tool to the Computers and
Networks tool set.</para><para>Trusted Extensions adds a Trusted Extensions Attributes tab to the Users
tool and the Administrative Roles tool.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Shared directories from zones</term><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions enables you to share directories from labeled
zones. The directories are shared at the label of the zone by creating an <filename>/etc/dfs/dfstab</filename> file from the global zone.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1><sect1 id="txapp-4"><title>Tighter Security Defaults in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>differences</primary><secondary>defaults in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions establishes tighter security defaults than the Solaris OS:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Auditing</term><listitem><para>By default, auditing is enabled.</para><para>An administrator can turn off auditing. However, auditing is typically
required at sites that install Trusted Extensions.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Devices</term><listitem><para>By default, device allocation is enabled.</para><para>By default, device allocation requires authorization. Therefore, by
default, regular users cannot use removable media.</para><para>An administrator can remove the authorization requirement. However,
device allocation is typically required at sites that install Trusted Extensions.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Printing</term><listitem><para>Regular users can print only to printers that include the
user's label in the printer's label range.</para><para>By default, printed output has trailer and banner pages. These pages,
and the body pages, include the label of the print job.</para><para>By default, users cannot print PostScript files.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Roles</term><listitem><para>Roles are available in the Solaris OS, but their use is optional.
In Trusted Extensions, roles are required for proper administration.</para><para>Making the <literal>root</literal> user a role is possible in the Solaris OS.
In Trusted Extensions, the <literal>root</literal> user is made a role to better
audit who is acting as superuser.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1><sect1 id="txapp-5"><title>Limited Options in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>differences</primary><secondary>limited options in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions narrows the range of Solaris configuration options:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Desktop</term><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions offers two desktops, the Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) and the Solaris Trusted Extensions (JDS).</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Naming service</term><listitem><para>The LDAP naming service is supported. All zones must be administered
from one naming service.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Zones</term><listitem><para>The global zone is an administrative zone. Only the <literal>root</literal> user or a role can enter the global zone. Therefore, administrative
interfaces that are available to regular Solaris users are not available
to regular Trusted Extensions users. For example, in Trusted Extensions, users cannot
bring up the Solaris Management Console.</para><para>Non-global zones are labeled zones. Users work in labeled zones.</para><para>All zones must be administered from one naming service.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1>
</appendix><?Pub *0000010117 0?>