<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><chapter id="txintro-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="10"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Trusted Extensions Administration
Concepts</title><indexterm><primary>actions</primary><seealso>individual actions by name</seealso>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>exporting</primary><see>sharing</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>choosing</primary><see>selecting</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>debugging</primary><see>troubleshooting</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>tools</primary><see>administrative tools</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labeled zones</primary><see>zones</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access</primary><see>computer access</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>managing</primary><see>administering</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>CDE actions</primary><see>actions</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>floppy disks</primary><see>diskettes</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>floppies</primary><see>diskettes</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>procedures</primary><see>tasks and task maps</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>administrative actions</primary><seealso>actions</seealso>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>controlling</primary><see>restricting</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>trailer pages</primary><see>banner pages</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>printer output</primary><see>printing</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><seealso>label ranges</seealso>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>translation</primary><see>localizing</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>accounts</primary><seealso>users</seealso>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>accounts</primary><see>roles</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>regular users</primary><see>users</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>profiles</primary><see>rights profiles</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>rights</primary><see>rights profiles</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>wildcard address</primary><see>fallback mechanism</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>OpenOffice</primary><see>StarOffice</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>viewing</primary><see>accessing</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>security templates</primary><see>remote host templates</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>internationalizing</primary><see>localizing</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>administrative roles</primary><see>roles</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>preventing</primary><see>protecting</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>network</primary><see>trusted network</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>programs</primary><see>applications</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>MLPs</primary><see>multilevel ports (MLPs)</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>MAC</primary><see>mandatory access control (MAC)</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>DAC</primary><see>discretionary access control (DAC)</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>security administrators</primary><see>Security Administrator role</see>
</indexterm><highlights><para>This chapter introduces you to administering a system that is configured
with <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Trusted Extensions software.</para><itemizedlist remap="jumplist"><listitem><para><olink targetptr="txintro-4" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Software and
the Solaris OS</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="txintro-3" remap="internal">Basic Concepts of Trusted Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="txintro-4"><title>Trusted Extensions Software and the Solaris OS</title><para><indexterm><primary>access policy</primary><secondary>Discretionary Access Control (DAC)</secondary></indexterm>Trusted Extensions software adds labels
to a system that is running the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS). Labels
implement <firstterm>mandatory access control</firstterm> (MAC). MAC, along
with discretionary access control (DAC), protects system subjects (processes)
and objects (data). Trusted Extensions software provides interfaces to handle
label configuration, label assignment, and label policy.</para><sect2 id="txintro-10"><title>Similarities Between Trusted Extensions and
the Solaris OS</title><indexterm><primary>similarities</primary><secondary>between Trusted Extensions and Solaris OS</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Trusted Extensions</primary><secondary>similarities with Solaris OS</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Solaris OS</primary><secondary>similarities with Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions software uses rights profiles, roles, auditing, privileges,
and other security features of the Solaris OS. You can use Solaris Secure
Shell (SSH), BART, the Solaris cryptographic framework, IPsec, and IPfilter
with Trusted Extensions.</para><listitem><para>As in the Solaris OS, users can be limited to using applications
that are necessary for performing their jobs. Other users can be authorized
to do more.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>As in the Solaris OS, capabilities that were formerly assigned
to superuser are assigned to separate, discrete &ldquo;roles.&rdquo;</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>As in the Solaris OS, privileges protect processes. Zones are
also used to separate processes.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>As in the Solaris OS, events on the system can be audited.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions uses the system configuration files of the Solaris OS,
such as <filename>policy.conf</filename> and <filename>exec_attr</filename>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="txintro-11"><title>Differences Between Trusted Extensions and the Solaris OS</title><indexterm><primary>differences</primary><secondary>between Trusted Extensions and Solaris OS</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Trusted Extensions</primary><secondary>differences from Solaris OS</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Solaris OS</primary><secondary>differences from Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access policy</primary><secondary>Discretionary Access Control (DAC)</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>access policy</primary><secondary>Mandatory Access Control (MAC)</secondary></indexterm>Trusted Extensions software extends the Solaris OS.
The following list provides an overview. For a quick reference, see <olink targetptr="txapp-1" remap="internal">Appendix&nbsp;D, Quick Reference to Trusted Extensions Administration</olink>.</para><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions controls access to data with special security
tags that are called <firstterm>labels</firstterm>. Labels provide <firstterm>mandatory
access control</firstterm> (MAC). MAC protection is in addition to <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> file permissions, or discretionary access
control (DAC). Labels are directly assigned to users, zones, devices, windows,
and network endpoints. Labels are implicitly assigned to processes, files,
and other system objects.</para><para>MAC cannot be overridden by regular
users. Trusted Extensions requires regular users to operate in labeled zones.
By default, no users or processes in labeled zones can override MAC.</para><para>As in the Solaris OS, the ability to override security policy can be assigned
to specific processes or users when MAC can be overridden. For example, users
can be authorized to change the label of a file. Such an action upgrades or
downgrades the sensitivity of the information in that file.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions adds to existing configuration files and commands.
For example, Trusted Extensions adds audit events, authorizations, privileges,
and rights profiles.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Some features that are optional on a Solaris system
are required on a Trusted Extensions system.  For example, zones and roles are
required on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Some features that are optional on a Solaris system
are recommended on a Trusted Extensions system. For example, in Trusted Extensions the <literal>root</literal> user should be turned into the <literal>root</literal> role.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions can change the default behavior of the Solaris OS.
For example, on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions, auditing
is enabled by default. In addition, device allocation is required.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions can narrow the options that are available in
the Solaris OS. For example, on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions,
the NIS+ naming service is not supported. Also, in Trusted Extensions, all zones
are labeled zones. Unlike the Solaris OS, labeled zones must use the same pool
of user IDs and group IDs. Additionally, in Trusted Extensions, labeled zones
can share one IP address.</para>
</listitem><listitem><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions provides trusted versions of two desktops. To work in
a labeled environment, desktop users of Trusted Extensions must use one of these
desktops:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) &ndash;</emphasis> Is the
trusted version of Common Desktop Environment (CDE). The name can be shortened
to Trusted CDE.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME) &ndash;</emphasis> Is the trusted version of the GNOME desktop. The name can be shortened
to Trusted GNOME.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions provides additional graphical user interfaces
(GUIs) and command line interfaces (CLIs). For example, Trusted Extensions provides
the Device Allocation Manager to administer devices. In addition, the <command>updatehome</command> command is used to place startup files in an regular user's home
directory at every label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions requires the use of particular GUIs for administration.
For example, on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions, the Solaris Management Console is
used to administer users, roles, and the network. Similarly, in Trusted CDE, the Admin Editor is used to edit system files.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions limits what users can see. For example, a device
that cannot be allocated by a user cannot be seen by that user.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Trusted Extensions limits users' desktop options. For example,
users are allowed a limited time of workstation inactivity before the screen
locks.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="txintro-22"><title>Multiheaded Systems and the Trusted Extensions Desktop</title><para><indexterm><primary>trusted stripe</primary><secondary>on multiheaded system</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>multiheaded system</primary><secondary>trusted stripe</secondary></indexterm>When the monitors of a multiheaded Trusted Extensions system
are configured horizontally, the trusted stripe stretches across the monitors.
When the monitors are configured vertically, the trusted stripe appears in
the lowest monitor.</para><para>When different workspaces are displayed on the monitors of a multiheaded
system, Trusted CDE and Trusted GNOME render the trusted
stripe differently.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>On a Trusted GNOME desktop, each
monitor displays a trusted stripe.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>On a Trusted CDE desktop, one trusted stripe appears on the primary
monitor.</para><caution><para>If a second trusted stripe appears on a Trusted CDE multiheaded
system, the stripe is not generated by the operating system. You might have
an unauthorized program on your system.</para><para>Contact your security
administrator immediately. To determine the correct trusted stripe, see <olink targetptr="commontasks-48" remap="internal">How to Regain Control of the Desktop's Current
Focus</olink>.</para>
</caution>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="txintro-3"><title>Basic Concepts of Trusted Extensions</title><para>Trusted Extensions software adds labels to a Solaris system. Labeled
desktops and trusted applications, such as the Label Builder and the Device
Allocation Manager, are also added. The concepts in this section are necessary
to understand Trusted Extensions, both for users and administrators. Users are
introduced to these concepts in the <olink targetdoc="trssug" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions User&rsquo;s Guide</citetitle></olink>.</para><sect2 id="txintro-12"><title>Trusted Extensions Protections</title><para>Trusted Extensions software enhances the protection of the Solaris OS. The Solaris OS protects
access to the system with user accounts that require passwords. You can require
that passwords be changed regularly, be of a certain length, and so on. Roles
require additional passwords to perform administrative tasks. Additional authentication
limits the damage that can be done by an intruder who guesses the root password,
because roles cannot be used as login accounts. Trusted Extensions software goes
further by restricting users and roles to an approved label range. This label
range limits the information that users and roles can access.</para><para>Trusted Extensions software displays the Trusted Path symbol, an unmistakable,
tamper-proof emblem that appears at the left of the trusted stripe. In Trusted CDE,
the stripe is at the bottom of the screen. In Trusted GNOME,
the stripe is at the top of the screen. The Trusted Path symbol indicates
to users when they are using security-related parts of the system. If this
symbol does not appear when the user is running a trusted application, that
version of the application should be checked immediately for authenticity.
If the trusted stripe does not appear, the desktop is not trustworthy. For
a sample desktop display, see <olink targetptr="txintro-fig-1" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;7&ndash;1</olink>.</para><figure id="txintro-fig-1"><title>Trusted Extensions Multilevel CDE Desktop</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="workspace.basic.eps" width="100"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows labels on windows and icons, the trusted
stripe with the trusted symbol and workspace label.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>Most security-related software, that is, the Trusted Computing Base
(TCB), runs in the global zone. Regular users cannot enter the global zone
or view its resources. Users are able to interact with TCB software, as in
when they change passwords. The Trusted Path symbol is displayed whenever
the user interacts with the TCB. </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="txintro-2"><title>Trusted Extensions and Access Control</title><para><indexterm><primary>mandatory access control (MAC)</primary><secondary>in Trusted Extensions</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>discretionary access control (DAC)</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>described</secondary></indexterm>Trusted Extensions software protects information and other resources
through both discretionary access control (DAC) and mandatory access control
(MAC). DAC is the traditional UNIX permission bits and access control lists
that are set at the discretion of the owner. MAC is a mechanism that the system
enforces automatically. MAC controls all transactions by checking the labels
of processes and data in the transaction.</para><para><indexterm><primary>authorizations</primary><secondary>granted</secondary></indexterm>A user's <firstterm>label</firstterm> represents the sensitivity
level at which the user is permitted to operate and chooses to operate. Typical
labels are <literal>Secret</literal>, or <literal>Public</literal>. The label
determines the information that the user is allowed to access. Both MAC and
DAC can be overridden by special permissions that are in the Solaris OS. <firstterm>Privileges</firstterm> are special permissions that can be granted to processes. <firstterm>Authorizations</firstterm> are special permissions that can be granted to
users and roles by an administrator.</para><para>As an administrator, you need to train users on the proper procedures
for securing their files and directories, according to your site's security
policy. Furthermore, you need to instruct any users who are allowed to upgrade
or downgrade labels as to when doing so is appropriate.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="txintro-14"><title>Roles and Trusted Extensions</title><para>On a system that is running Solaris software without Trusted Extensions,
roles are optional. On a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions, roles
are required. The system is administered by the System Administrator role
and the Security Administrator role. In some cases, the <literal>root</literal> role
is used.</para><para>As in the Solaris OS, rights profiles are the basis of a role's capabilities. Trusted Extensions provides
two rights profiles, Information Security and User Security. These two profiles
define the Security Administrator role.</para><para><indexterm><primary>trusted path attribute</primary><secondary>when available</secondary></indexterm>The programs that are available to a role
in Trusted Extensions have a special property, the <firstterm>trusted path attribute</firstterm>.
This attribute indicates that the program is part of the TCB. The trusted
path attribute is available when a program is launched from the global zone.</para><para>For information about roles, see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="prbactm-1" remap="external">Part&nbsp;III, <citetitle remap="chapter">Roles, Rights Profiles, and Privileges,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="txintro-15"><title>Labels in Trusted Extensions Software</title><para><indexterm><primary>clearances</primary><secondary>label overview</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>overview</secondary></indexterm>Labels and clearances are at the center of mandatory access control
(MAC) in Trusted Extensions. They determine which users can access which programs,
files, and directories. Labels and clearances consist of one <firstterm>classification</firstterm> component and zero or more <firstterm>compartment</firstterm> components.
The classification component indicates a hierarchical level of security such
as <literal>TOP SECRET</literal> or <literal>CONFIDENTIAL</literal>. The compartment
component represents a group of users who might need access to a common body
of information. Some typical types of compartments are projects, departments,
or physical locations. Labels are readable by authorized users, but internally,
labels are manipulated as numbers. The numbers and their readable versions
are defined in the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file.</para><para>Trusted Extensions mediates all attempted security-related transactions.
The software compares the labels of the accessing entity, typically a process,
and the entity being accessed, usually a filesystem object. The software then
permits or disallows the transaction depending on which label is <firstterm>dominant</firstterm>. Labels are also used to determine access to other system resources,
such as allocatable devices, networks, frame buffers, and other hosts.</para><sect3 id="txintro-5"><title>Dominance Relationships Between Labels</title><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>relationships</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>dominance</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>dominance of labels</primary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>One entity's label is said to <emphasis>dominate</emphasis> another
label if the following two conditions are met:</para><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>classification label component</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>classification component</secondary></indexterm>The classification component of the first
entity's label is equal to or higher than the second entity's classification.
The security administrator assigns numbers to classifications in the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file. The software compares these numbers to determine dominance.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>compartment label component</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>compartment component</secondary></indexterm>The set of compartments in the first entity includes all of the
second entity's compartments.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Two labels are said to be <emphasis>equal</emphasis> if they have the
same classification and the same set of compartments. If the labels are equal,
they dominate each other and access is permitted.</para><para>If one label has a higher classification or if it has the same classification
and its compartments are a superset of the second label's compartments, or
both, the first label is said to <emphasis>strictly dominate</emphasis> the
second label.</para><para>Two labels are said to be <emphasis>disjoint</emphasis> or <emphasis>noncomparable</emphasis> if neither label dominates the other label.</para><para>The following table presents examples of label comparisons for dominance.
In the example, <literal>NEED_TO_KNOW</literal> is a higher classification
than <literal>INTERNAL</literal>. There are three compartments: Eng, Mkt,
and Fin.</para><table frame="topbot" id="txintro-16"><title>Examples of Label Relationships</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="column1" colwidth="3*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="column2" colwidth="2*"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="column3" colwidth="3*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Label 1</para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Relationship</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Label 2</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>(strictly) dominates</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>INTERNAL Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>(strictly) dominates</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>(strictly) dominates</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>INTERNAL Eng</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>dominates (equals)</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Fin</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Fin</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left"><para><literal>NEED_TO_KNOW Eng Mkt</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>INTERNAL Eng Mkt Fin</literal></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><sect4 id="txintro-8"><title>Administrative Labels</title><para><indexterm><primary><constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> label</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>administrative labels</primary></indexterm>Trusted Extensions provides
two special administrative labels that are used as labels or clearances: <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> and <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>. These labels are
used to protect system resources and are intended for administrators rather
than regular users.</para><para><constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> is the highest label. <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> dominates
all other labels in the system and is used to protect system data, such as
administration databases or audit trails, from being read. You must be in
the global zone to read data that is labeled <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>.</para><para><indexterm><primary sortas="ADMIN_HIL"><constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> label</primary><secondary>lowest label</secondary></indexterm><constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> is
the lowest label. <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> is dominated by all other
labels in a system, including labels for regular users. Mandatory access control
does not permit users to write data to files with labels lower than the user's
label. Thus, a file at the label <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> can be read
by regular users, but cannot be modified. <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> is
typically used to protect public executables that are shared, such as files
in <filename class="directory">/usr/bin</filename>.</para>
</sect4>
</sect3><sect3 id="txintro-6"><title>Label Encodings File</title><indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/security/tsol/label_encodings</filename> file</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>label_encodings</filename> file</primary><secondary>contents</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>All label components for a system, that is, classifications, compartments,
and the associated rules, are stored in an <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> file,
the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file. This file is located in the <filename>/etc/security/tsol</filename> directory. The security administrator sets up
the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file for the site. A label encodings
file contains:</para><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>component definitions</primary><secondary><filename>label_encodings</filename> file</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Component
definitions</emphasis> &ndash; Definitions of classifications, compartments,
labels, and clearances, including rules for required combinations and constraints</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary><filename>label_encodings</filename> file</primary><secondary>source of accreditation ranges</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>accreditation ranges</primary><secondary><filename>label_encodings</filename> file</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Accreditation range definitions</emphasis> &ndash;
Specification of the clearances and minimum labels that define the sets of
available labels for the entire system and for regular users</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>printing</primary><secondary>and <filename>label_encodings</filename> file</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Printing specifications</emphasis> &ndash; Identification and handling information for print banners,
trailers, headers, footers, and other security features on printer output</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>customizing</primary><secondary><filename>label_encodings</filename> file</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Customizations</emphasis> &ndash;
Local definitions including label color codes, and other defaults</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="label-encodings-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>label_encodings</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page. Detailed information
can also be found in <olink targetdoc="trsollbladmin" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Label Administration</citetitle></olink> and <olink targetdoc="wslblencode" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Compartmented Mode Workstation Labeling: Encodings Format</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="txintro-7"><title>Label Ranges</title><para><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>well-formed</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>well-formed labels</primary></indexterm>A <firstterm>label range</firstterm> is the set of potentially usable labels at which users
can operate. Both users and resources both have label ranges. Resources that
can be protected by label ranges include such things as allocatable devices,
networks, interfaces, frame buffers,  and commands or actions. A label range
is defined by a clearance at the top of the range and a minimum label at the
bottom.</para><para>A range does not necessarily include all combinations of labels that
fall between a maximum and minimum label. Rules in the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file
can disqualify certain combinations. A label must be <emphasis>well-formed</emphasis>,
that is, permitted by all applicable rules in the label encodings file, in
order to be included in a range.</para><para>However, a clearance does not have to be well-formed. Suppose, for example,
that a <filename>label_encodings</filename> file prohibits any combination
of compartments <literal>Eng</literal>, <literal>Mkt</literal>, and <literal>Fin</literal> in
a label. <literal>INTERNAL Eng Mkt Fin</literal> would be a valid clearance
but not a valid label. As a clearance, this combination would let a user access
files that are labeled <literal>INTERNAL Eng</literal>, <literal>INTERNAL
Mkt</literal>, and <literal>INTERNAL Fin</literal>.</para><sect4 id="txintro-17"><title>Account Label Range</title><para>When you assign a clearance and a minimum label to a user, you define
the upper and lower boundaries of the <emphasis>account label range</emphasis> in
which that user is permitted to operate. The following equation describes
the account label range, using &le; to indicate &ldquo;dominated by or the
same as&rdquo;:</para><para>minimum label &le; permitted label &le; clearance</para><para>Thus, the user is permitted to operate at any label that is dominated
by the clearance as long as that label dominates the minimum label. When a
user's clearance or minimum label is not expressly set, the defaults that
are defined in the <filename>label_encodings</filename> file take effect.</para><para><indexterm><primary>single-label operation</primary></indexterm>Users
can be assigned a clearance and a minimum label that enable them to operate
at more than one label, or at a single label. When a user's clearance and
minimum label are equal, the user can operate at only one label.</para>
</sect4><sect4 id="txintro-18"><title>Session Range</title><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>labels of processes</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>session range</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>session range</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>of user processes</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>processes</primary><secondary>labels of user processes</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The <emphasis>session range</emphasis> is the set of labels that is
available to a user during a Trusted Extensions session. The session range must
be within the user's account label range and the label range set for the system.
At login, if the user selects single-label session mode, the session range
is limited to that label. If the user selects multilabel session mode, then
the label that the user selects becomes the session clearance. The session
clearance defines the upper boundary of the session range. The user's minimum
label defines the lower bound. The user begins the session in a workspace
at the minimum label. During the session, the user can switch to a workspace
at any label within the session range.</para>
</sect4>
</sect3><sect3 id="txintro-19"><title>What Labels Protect and Where Labels Appear</title><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>of processes</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>protecting</primary><secondary>information with labels</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>processes</primary><secondary>labels of</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Labels appear on the desktop and on output that is executed on the desktop,
such as printer output.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Applications &ndash;</emphasis> Applications
start processes. These processes run at the label of the workspace where the
application is started. An application in a labeled zone, as a file, is labeled
at the label of the zone.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Devices &ndash;</emphasis> Data flowing
through devices is controlled through device allocation and device label ranges.
To use a device, users must be within the label range of the device, and be
authorized to allocate the device.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">File system mount points &ndash;</emphasis> Every
mount point has a label. The label is viewable by using the <command>getlabel</command> command.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Network interfaces &ndash;</emphasis> IP
addresses (hosts) have templates that describe their label range. Unlabeled
hosts also have a default label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Printers and printing &ndash;</emphasis> Printers
have label ranges. Labels are printed on body pages. Labels, handling information,
and other security information is printed on the banner and trailer pages.
To configure printing in Trusted Extensions, see <olink targetptr="manageprint-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;21, Managing Labeled Printing (Tasks)</olink> and <olink targetdoc="trsollbladmin" targetptr="overview-337" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Labels on Printed Output</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Label Administration</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Processes &ndash;</emphasis> Processes
are labeled. Processes run at the label of the workspace where the process
originates. The label of a process is visible by using the <command>plabel</command> command.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Users &ndash;</emphasis> Users are
assigned a default label and a label range. The label of the user's workspace
indicates the label of the user's processes.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>workspaces</primary><secondary>colors indicating label of</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>colors</primary><secondary>indicating label of workspace</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Windows &ndash;</emphasis> Labels are visible at the top of
desktop windows. The label of the desktop is also indicated by color. The
color appears on the desktop switch and above window title bars.</para><para>When
a window is moved to a differently labeled workspace, the window maintains
its original label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Zones &ndash;</emphasis> Every zone
has a unique label. The files and directories that are owned by a zone are
at the zone's label. For more information, see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="getzonepath-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>getzonepath</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000036475 0?>