<preface id="fqnkw"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>The <citetitle>Solaris Express Developer Edition Release Notes</citetitle> contains installation and runtime
problem details. Also included are end-of-software support statements for
the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Operating System (Solaris OS).</para><note><para>This Solaris release supports systems that use the <trademark class="registered">SPARC</trademark> and x86 families of processor architectures: <trademark class="registered">UltraSPARC</trademark>, SPARC64, AMD64, Pentium, and Xeon
EM64T. The supported systems appear in the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware
Compatibility List</citetitle> at <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl" type="url">http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/hcl</ulink>. This document cites any
implementation differences between the platform types.</para><para>In
this document the term &ldquo;x86&rdquo; refers to 64-bit and 32-bit systems
manufactured using processors compatible with the AMD64 or Intel Xeon/Pentium
product families. For supported systems, see the <citetitle>Solaris 10 Hardware
Compatibility List</citetitle>.</para>
</note>
</highlights><sect1 id="fqnla"><title>Who Should Use This Book</title><para>These notes are for users and system administrators who install and
use the Solaris Operating System.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="fqnka"><title>Related Books</title><para>You might need to refer to the following manuals when you install Solaris
software:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><citetitle>Java Desktop System Release 3 Solaris 10 Collection</citetitle></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris 10 Start Here</citetitle> card</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris 10 Installation Guide: Basic</citetitle></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris 10 Installation Guide: Network-Based
Installations</citetitle></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris 10 Installation Guide: Solaris Live
Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris 10 Installation Guide: Advanced,
JumpStart, Solaris Flash Archives and RAID-1 Volumes</citetitle></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris 10 System Administrator Collection</citetitle></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>These collections of books are found in <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com" type="url"></ulink></para><para>For information on current CERT advisories, see the official CERT Web
site at <ulink url="http://www.cert.org" type="text">http://www.cert.org</ulink>.</para><para>For some hardware configurations, you might need supplemental hardware-specific
instructions for installing the Solaris Operating System. If your system requires hardware-specific
actions at certain points, the manufacturer of your hardware has provided
supplemental Solaris installation documentation. Refer to those materials,
such as <citetitle>Solaris Sun Hardware Platform Guide</citetitle>, for hardware-specific
installation instructions.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="fqnju"><title>Third-Party Web Site References</title><para>Third-party URLs are referenced in this document and provide additional,
related information.</para><note><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party Web
sites mentioned in this document. Sun does not endorse and is not responsible
or liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials that
are available on or through such sites or resources. Sun will not be responsible
or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused by or in connection
with the use of or reliance on any such content, goods, or services that are
available on or through such sites or resources.</para>
</note>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>