<preface xml:id="preface">
	<title>Preface</title>
	<para>The <citetitle>ZFS Administration Guide</citetitle> provides information about setting up and managing ZFS file systems.</para>
	<para>This guide contains information for both <trademark class="registered">SPARC</trademark> based and x86 based systems.</para>
	<note>
		<para>This illumos release supports systems that use the SPARC and x86 families of processor architectures:  <trademark class="registered">UltraSPARC</trademark>, SPARC64, AMD64, Pentium, and Xeon EM64T. The supported systems appear in the <link xl:href="https://illumos.org/hcl/">illumos Hardware Compatibility List</link>. This document cites any implementation differences between the platform types.</para>
		<para>In this document these x86 terms mean the following:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>&ldquo;x86&rdquo; refers to the larger family of 64-bit and 32-bit x86 compatible products.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>&ldquo;x64&rdquo; points out specific 64-bit information about AMD64 or EM64T systems.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>&ldquo;32-bit x86&rdquo; points out specific 32-bit information about x86 based systems.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>For supported systems, see the <citetitle>illumos Hardware Compatibility List</citetitle>.</para>
	</note>
	<sect1 xml:id="preface-9">
		<title xml:id="preface-2">Who Should Use This Book</title>
		<para>This guide is intended for anyone who is interested in setting up and
managing ZFS file systems. Experience using illumos or another <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> operating system
is recommended.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="preface-4">
	<title>How This Book Is Organized</title>
	<para>The following table describes the chapters in this book.</para>
	<informaltable frame="topbot">
		<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
			<colspec colwidth="29.96*"/>
			<colspec colwidth="70.04*"/>
			<thead>
				<row rowsep="1">
					<entry><para>Chapter</para></entry>
					<entry><para>Description</para></entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="zfsover-1" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Provides an overview of ZFS and its features and benefits. It also covers some basic concepts and terminology.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="setup-1" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Provides step-by-step instructions on setting up simple ZFS configurations with simple pools and file systems. This chapter also provides the hardware and software required to create ZFS file systems.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="gbcik" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Identifies important features that make ZFS significantly different from traditional file systems. Understanding these key differences will help reduce confusion when using traditional tools to interact with ZFS.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="gavwn" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Provides a detailed description of how to create and administer storage pools.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="gavwq" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Provides detailed information about managing ZFS file systems. Included are such concepts as hierarchical file system layout, property inheritance, and automatic mount point management and share interactions.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="snapshots" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Describes how to create and administer ZFS snapshots and clones.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="acls" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Describes how to use access control lists (ACLs) to protect your ZFS files by providing more granular permissions then the standard UNIX permissions.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="advanced" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Provides information on using ZFS volumes, using ZFS with zones, and alternate root pools.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry><para><xref linkend="gavwg" /></para></entry>
					<entry><para>Describes how to identify ZFS failure modes and how to recover from them. Steps for preventing failures are covered as well.</para></entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</informaltable>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="preface-5">
	<title>Related Books</title>
	<para>Related information about general Solaris system administration topics
		can be found in the following books:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris System Administration: Basic Administration</citetitle></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris System Administration: Advanced Administration</citetitle></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris System Administration: Devices and File Systems</citetitle></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris System Administration: Security Services</citetitle></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><citetitle>Solaris Volume Manager Administration Guide</citetitle></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>
