<glossary id="glossary-1"><title>Glossary</title><glossentry id="glossary-19ddd"><glossterm><filename>/etc</filename> directory</glossterm><glossdef><para>A directory that contains critical system configuration files
and maintenance commands.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-19sdfgs"><glossterm><filename>/etc/netboot</filename> directory</glossterm><glossdef><para>The directory on a WAN boot server that contains the client
configuration information and security data that are required for a WAN boot
installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-20sfghsgf"><glossterm><filename>/export</filename> file
system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file system on an OS server that is shared with other systems
on a network. For example, the <literal>/export</literal> file system can
contain the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system and swap space for diskless
clients and the home directories for users on the network. Diskless clients
rely on the <literal>/export</literal> file system on an OS server to boot
and run.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-45"><glossterm><filename>/opt</filename> file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file system that contains the mount points for third-party
and unbundled software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-68"><glossterm><filename>/usr</filename> file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file system on a standalone system or server that contains
many of the standard UNIX programs. Sharing the large <literal>/usr</literal> file
system with a server rather than maintaining a local copy minimizes the overall
disk space that is required to install and run the Solaris software on a system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-69"><glossterm><filename>/var</filename> file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file system or directory (on standalone systems) that contains
system files that are likely to change or grow over the life of the system.
These files include system logs, <literal>vi</literal> files, mail files,
and UUCP files.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-11"><glossterm>3DES</glossterm><glossdef><para>([Triple DES] Triple-Data Encryption Standard). A symmetric-key
encryption method that  provides a key length of 168 bits. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-12"><glossterm>AES</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Advanced Encryption Standard) A symmetric 128-bit block data
encryption technique. The  U.S. government adopted the Rijndael variant of
the algorithm as its encryption standard in  October 2000. AES replaces DES
encryption as the government standard.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-8"><glossterm>archive</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that contains a collection of files that were copied
from a master system. The file also contains identification information about
the archive, such as a name and the date that you created the archive. After
you install an archive on a system, the system contains the exact configuration
of the master system.</para><para>An archive could be a differential archive,
which is a Solaris Flash archive that contains only the differences between
two system images, an unchanged master image and an updated master image.
The differential archive contains files to be retained, modified, or deleted
from the clone system.  A differential update changes only the files specified
and is restricted to systems that contain software consistent with the unchanged
master image.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-10"><glossterm>arrow keys</glossterm><glossdef><para>One of the four directional keys on the numeric keypad.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-3"><glossterm>begin script</glossterm><glossdef><para>A user-defined Bourne shell script, specified within the <literal>rules</literal> file, that performs tasks before the Solaris software is installed
on the system. You can use begin scripts only with custom JumpStart installations.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-5boot"><glossterm>boot</glossterm><glossdef><para>To load the system software into memory and start it.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>boot archive</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: A boot archive
is a collection of critical files that is used to boot the Solaris OS. These
files are needed during system startup before the root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system is mounted. Two boot archives  are maintained on a system:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The boot archive that is used to boot the Solaris OS on a
system. This boot archive is sometimes called the primary  boot archive.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The boot archive that is used for recovery when the primary
boot  archive is damaged. This boot archive starts the system without mounting
the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system. On the GRUB menu, this boot
   archive is called failsafe. The archive's essential purpose  is to regenerate
the primary boot archive, which is usually used to boot the system.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="chapter-58"><glossterm>boot environment</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of mandatory file systems (disk slices and mount
points) that are critical to the operation of the Solaris OS. These disk slices
might be on the same disk or distributed across multiple disks. </para><para>The
active boot environment is the one that is  currently booted. Exactly one
active  boot environment can be booted. An inactive boot environment is not
currently booted, but can be in a state of waiting for activation on the next
reboot.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>boot loader</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: The boot loader
is the first software program that runs after you turn on a  system. This
program begins the booting process.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-bootlog"><glossterm><filename>bootlog-cgi</filename> program</glossterm><glossdef><para>The CGI program that enables a web server to collect and store
remote client-booting and installation console messages during a WAN boot
installation. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-4aa"><glossterm>boot server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A server system that provides client systems on the same network
subnet with the programs and information that they need to start. A boot server
is required to install over the network if the install server is on a different
subnet than the systems on which Solaris software is to be installed.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-13"><glossterm>certificate authority</glossterm><glossdef><para>(CA) A trusted third-party organization or company that issues
 digital certificates that are used to create digital signatures and public-private
key pairs. The CA  guarantees that the individual who is granted the unique
certificate is who she or he claims to be.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-14ww"><glossterm><filename>certstore</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that contains a digital certificate for a specific
client system. During  an SSL negotiation, the client might be asked to provide
the certificate file to the server.  The server uses this file to verify the
identity of the client.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry sortas="CGI" id="glossary-15gsd"><glossterm>CGI</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Common Gateway Interface) An interface by which external
programs communicate with the  HTTP server. Programs that are written to use
CGI are called CGI programs or CGI scripts.  CGI programs handle forms or
parse output the server does not normally handle or parse.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-17lkii"><glossterm>checksum</glossterm><glossdef><para>The result of adding a group of data items that are used for
checking the group. The data items can be either numerals or other character
strings that are treated as numerals during the checksum calculation. The
checksum value verifies that communication between two devices is successful.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-50jh"><glossterm>client</glossterm><glossdef><para>In the client-server model for communications, the client
is a process that remotely accesses resources of a compute server, such as
compute power and large memory capacity. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-90ff"><glossterm>clone system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system that you install by using a Solaris Flash archive.
The clone system has the same installation configuration as the master system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-60asd"><glossterm>cluster</glossterm><glossdef><para>A logical collection of packages (software modules). The Solaris
software is divided into <emphasis>software groups</emphasis>, which are each
composed of clusters and <emphasis>packages</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-9sadf"><glossterm>command line</glossterm><glossdef><para>A string of characters that begins with a command, often followed
by arguments, including options, file names, and other expressions, and terminated
by the end-of-line character.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-6zxcv"><glossterm>concatenation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A RAID-0 volume. If slices are concatenated, the data is written
to the first available slice until that slice is full. When that slice is
full, the data is written to the next slice, serially. A concatenation provides
no data redundancy unless it is contained in a mirror. See also RAID-0 volume.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7vcbn"><glossterm>Core Software Group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software group that contains the minimum software that is
required to boot and run the Solaris OS on a system. Core includes some networking
software and the drivers that are required to run the Common Desktop Environment
(CDE) desktop. Core does not include the CDE software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="chapter-620"><glossterm>critical file systems</glossterm><glossdef><para>File systems that are required by the Solaris OS. When you
use Solaris Live Upgrade, these file systems are separate mount points in
the <filename>vfstab</filename> file of the active and inactive boot environments.
Example file systems are <filename>root</filename> (/), <filename>/usr</filename>, <filename>/var</filename>, and <filename>/opt</filename>. These file systems are always
copied from the source to the inactive boot environment.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-8avn"><glossterm>custom JumpStart</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of installation in which the Solaris software is automatically
installed on a system that is based on a user-defined profile. You can create
customized profiles for different types of users and systems. A custom JumpStart
installation is a JumpStart installation you create.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-100vbn"><glossterm>custom probes file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file, which must be located in the same JumpStart directory
as the <filename>rules</filename> file, that is a Bourne shell script that
contains two types of functions: probe and comparison. Probe functions gather
the information you want or do the actual work and set a corresponding <envar>SI_</envar> environment variable you define. Probe functions become probe keywords.
Comparison functions call a corresponding probe function, compare the output
of the probe function, and return 0 if the keyword matches or 1 if the keyword
doesn't match. Comparison functions become rule keywords. See also <emphasis>rules
file</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-decr"><glossterm>decryption</glossterm><glossdef><para>The process of converting coded data to plain text. See also <olink targetptr="glossary-encr" remap="internal">encryption</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-9avcn"><glossterm>derived profile</glossterm><glossdef><para>A profile that is dynamically created by a begin script during
a custom JumpStart installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-16cvnb"><glossterm>DES</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Data Encryption Standard) A symmetric-key encryption method
that was developed in 1975 and  standardized by ANSI in 1981 as ANSI X.3.92.
DES uses a 56-bit key.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-10acvbn"><glossterm>Developer Solaris Software Group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software group that contains the End User Solaris Software
Group plus the libraries, include files, man pages, and programming tools
for developing software. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-71cvbn"><glossterm>DHCP</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) An application-layer
protocol. Enables individual computers, or clients, on a TCP/IP network to
extract an IP address and other network configuration information from a designated
and centrally maintained DHCP server or servers. This facility reduces the
overhead of maintaining and administering a large IP network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7778"><glossterm>differential archive</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Solaris Flash archive that contains only the differences
between two system images, an unchanged master image and an updated master
image. The differential archive contains files to be retained, modified, or
deleted from the clone system.  A differential update changes only the files
that are specified and is restricted to systems that contain software consistent
with the unchanged master image.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-17cvbn"><glossterm>digital certificate</glossterm><glossdef><para>A nontransferable, nonforgeable, digital file issued from
a third  party that both communicating parties already trust.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-18"><glossterm>disc</glossterm><glossdef><para>An optical disc, as opposed to a magnetic disk, which recognizes
the common spelling that is used in the compact disc (CD) market. For example,
a CD-ROM or DVD-ROM is an optical disc. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-120"><glossterm>disk</glossterm><glossdef><para>A round platter, or set of platters, of a magnetized medium
that is organized into concentric tracks and sectors for storing data such
as files. See also disc.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-11fgh"><glossterm>disk configuration file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that represents a structure of a disk (for example,
bytes/sector, flags, slices). Disk configuration files enable you to use the <literal>pfinstall</literal> command from a single system to test profiles on different&ndash;size
disks.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-12o"><glossterm>diskless client</glossterm><glossdef><para>A client on a network that relies on a server for all of its
disk storage.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-18dfg"><glossterm>document root directory</glossterm><glossdef><para>The root of a hierarchy on a web server machine that contains
the  files, images, and data you want to present to users who are accessing
the web server.  </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-13ert"><glossterm>domain</glossterm><glossdef><para>A part of the Internet naming hierarchy. A domain represents
a group of systems on a local network that share administrative files.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-14ert"><glossterm>domain name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The name that is assigned to a group of systems on a local
network that share administrative files. The domain name is required for the
Network Information Service (NIS) database to work properly. A domain name
consists of a sequence of component names that are separated by periods (for
example: <literal>tundra.mpk.ca.us</literal>). As you read a domain name from
left to right, the component names identify more general (and usually remote)
areas of administrative authority. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry sortas="encryption" id="glossary-encr"><glossterm>encryption</glossterm><glossdef><para>The process of protecting information from unauthorized use
by making the  information unintelligible. Encryption is based on a code,
called a key, which is used to  decrypt the information. See also <olink targetptr="glossary-decr" remap="internal">decryption</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-15fff"><glossterm>End User Solaris Software Group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software group that contains the Core Software Group plus
the recommended software for an end user, including the Common Desktop Environment
(CDE) and DeskSet software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-160fd"><glossterm>Entire Solaris Software Group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software group that contains the entire Solaris release.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-170ggg"><glossterm>Entire Solaris Software Group
Plus OEM Support</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software group that contains the entire Solaris release
plus additional hardware support for OEMs. This software group is recommended
when installing Solaris software on SPARC based servers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>failsafe boot archive</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: A boot archive
that is used for recovery when the primary boot  archive is damaged. This
boot archive starts the system without  mounting the root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system. This boot archive is called  failsafe on the GRUB menu. The archive's
essential purpose  is to regenerate the primary boot archive, which is usually
used  to boot the system. See <emphasis>boot archive</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="chapter-62asdgfad"><glossterm>fallback</glossterm><glossdef><para>A reversion to the environment that ran previously. Use fallback
when you are activating an environment and the boot environment that is designated
for booting fails or shows some undesirable behavior.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-21aadsf"><glossterm><literal>fdisk</literal> partition</glossterm><glossdef><para>A logical partition of a disk drive that is dedicated to a
particular operating system on x86 based systems. To install the Solaris software,
you must set up at least one Solaris <literal>fdisk</literal> partition on
an x86 based system. x86 based systems allow up to four different <literal>fdisk</literal> partitions
on a disk. These partitions can be used to hold individual operating systems.
Each operating system must be located on a unique <literal>fdisk</literal> partition.
A system can only have one Solaris <literal>fdisk</literal> partition per
disk.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-22asfd"><glossterm>file server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A server that provides the software and file storage for systems
on a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry sortas="file server" id="glossary-23asdf"><glossterm>file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>In the <trademark>SunOS</trademark> operating system, a tree-structured
network of files and directories that you can access.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-24asdf"><glossterm>finish script</glossterm><glossdef><para>A user-defined Bourne shell script, specified within the <literal>rules</literal> file, that performs tasks after the Solaris software is installed
on the system but before the system reboots. You use finish scripts with custom
JumpStart installations.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-30lk"><glossterm>format</glossterm><glossdef><para>To put data into a structure or divide a disk into sectors
for receiving data.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-110kl"><glossterm>function key</glossterm><glossdef><para>One of the 10 or more keyboard keys that are labeled F1, F2,
F3, and so on that are mapped to particular tasks.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>global zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>In Solaris Zones, the global zone is both the default zone
for the system and the zone used for system-wide administrative control. 
The global zone is the only zone from which a non-global zone can be configured,
installed, managed, or uninstalled.  Administration of the system infrastructure,
such as physical devices, routing, or dynamic reconfiguration (DR), is only
possible in the global zone.  Appropriately privileged processes running in
the global zone can access objects associated with other zones.  See also <emphasis>Solaris Zones</emphasis> and <emphasis>non-global zone</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>GRUB</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: GNU GRand Unified
Bootloader (GRUB) is an open source boot loader  with a simple menu interface.
 The menu displays a list of operating systems that are installed on a system.
GRUB enables you to easily boot these various operating systems,  such as
the Solaris OS, Linux, or Microsoft Windows.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>GRUB main menu</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: A boot menu that
lists the operating systems that are installed  on a system. From this menu,
you can easily boot an operating  system without modifying the BIOS or <literal>fdisk</literal> partition settings.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>GRUB edit menu</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: A boot menu that
is a submenu of the GRUB main menu. GRUB commands  are displayed on this menu.
These commands can be edited to change  boot behavior.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-130lk"><glossterm>hard link</glossterm><glossdef><para>A directory entry that references a file on disk. More than
one such directory entry can reference the same physical file.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-21kl"><glossterm>hash</glossterm><glossdef><para>A number that is produced by taking some input and generating
a number that is significantly shorter than the input.  The same output value
is always generated for identical inputs. Hash functions can be used in table
search algorithms, in error detection, and in tamper detection. When used
for tamper detection, hash functions are chosen such that it is difficult
to find two inputs that yield the same hash result. MD5 and SHA-1 are examples
of one-way hash functions.  For example, a message digest takes a variable-length
input such as a disk file and reduces it to a small value.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-20kl"><glossterm>hashing</glossterm><glossdef><para>The process of changing a string of characters into a value
or key that represents  the original string.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-22hj"><glossterm>HMAC</glossterm><glossdef><para>Keyed hashing method for message authentication. HMAC is used
with an iterative  cryptographic hash function, such as MD5 or SHA-1, in combination
with a secret shared key.  The cryptographic strength of HMAC depends on the
properties of the underlying hash  function. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-25hj"><glossterm>host name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The name by which a system is known to other systems on a
network. This name must be unique among all the systems within a particular
domain (usually, this means within any single organization). A host name can
be any combination of letters, numbers, and minus signs (<literal>-</literal>),
but it cannot begin or end with a minus sign.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-140gh"><glossterm>HTTP</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Hypertext Transfer Protocol) (n.) The Internet protocol that
fetches hypertext objects from remote hosts. This protocol is based on TCP/IP.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-23gh"><glossterm>HTTPS</glossterm><glossdef><para>A secure version of HTTP, implemented by using the Secure
Sockets Layer (SSL). </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7779"><glossterm>initial installation</glossterm><glossdef><para>An installation that overwrites the currently running software
or initializes a blank disk. </para><para>An initial installation of the Solaris
OS overwrites the system's disk or disks with the new version of the Solaris
OS. If your system is not running the Solaris OS, you must perform an initial
installation.  If  your system is running an upgradable version of the Solaris
OS, an  initial installation overwrites the disk and does not preserve the
OS  or local modifications.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-27er"><glossterm>install server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A server that provides the Solaris DVD or CD images from which
other systems on a network can install Solaris (also called a <emphasis>media
server</emphasis>). You can create an install server by copying the Solaris
DVD or CD images to the server's hard disk.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-29we"><glossterm>IP address</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Internet protocol address)  In TCP/IP, a unique 32-bit number
that identifies each host in a network. An IP address consists of four numbers
that are separated by periods (192.168.0.0, for example). Most often, each
part of the IP address is a number between 0 and 225. However, the first number
must be less than 224 and the last number cannot be 0.</para><para>IP addresses
are logically divided into two parts: the network (similar to a telephone
area code), and the local system on the network (similar to a phone number).
The numbers in a Class A IP address, for example, represent &ldquo;<literal>network.local.local.local</literal>&rdquo; and the numbers in a Class C IP address represent &ldquo;<literal>network.network.network.local</literal>.&rdquo;</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-72sa"><glossterm>IPv6</glossterm><glossdef><para>IPv6 is a version (version 6) of Internet Protocol (IP) that
is designed to be an evolutionary step from the current version, IPv4 (version
4). Deploying IPv6, by using defined transition mechanisms, does not disrupt
current operations. In addition, IPv6 provides a platform for new Internet
functionality. IPv6 is described in more detail in<olink targetdoc="sysadv3" targetptr="ipv6-overview-7" remap="external">Chapter 3, <citetitle remap="chapter">Planning an IPv6 Addressing Scheme (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: IP Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-16sd"><glossterm>job</glossterm><glossdef><para>A user-defined task to be completed by a computer system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-31js"><glossterm>JumpStart directory</glossterm><glossdef><para>When you use a profile diskette for custom JumpStart installations,
the JumpStart directory is the root directory on the diskette that contains
all the essential custom JumpStart files. When you use a profile server for
custom JumpStart installations, the JumpStart directory is a directory on
the server that contains all the essential custom JumpStart files.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-32asd"><glossterm>JumpStart installation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of installation in which the Solaris software is automatically
installed on a system by using the factory-installed JumpStart software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-32x"><glossterm>Kerberos</glossterm><glossdef><para>A network authentication protocol that uses strong, secret-key
cryptography to enable a client and server to identify themselves to each
other over an insecure network connection.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-24key"><glossterm>key</glossterm><glossdef><para>The code for encrypting or decrypting data. See also <olink targetptr="glossary-encr" remap="internal">encryption</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-25keystore"><glossterm><filename>keystore</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that contains keys shared by a client and server. During
a WAN boot  installation, the client system uses the keys to verify the integrity
of, or decrypt the  data and files transmitted from, the server.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-42lan"><glossterm>LAN</glossterm><glossdef><para>(local area network) A group of computer systems in close
proximity that can communicate by way of some connecting hardware and software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-32ldap"><glossterm>LDAP</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Lightweight Directory Access Protocol) A standard, extensible
directory access protocol that is used by LDAP naming service clients and
servers to communicate with each other.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-33locale"><glossterm>locale</glossterm><glossdef><para>A geographic or political region or community that shares
the same language, customs, or cultural conventions (English for the U.S.
is <literal>en_US</literal>, and English for the U.K. is <literal>en_UK</literal>).</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-210l"><glossterm>logical device</glossterm><glossdef><para>A group of physical slices on one or more disks that appear
to the system as a single device. A logical device is called a volume in Solaris
Volume Manager. A volume is functionally identical to a physical disk for
the purposes of an application or file system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7780"><glossterm>manifest section</glossterm><glossdef><para>A section of a Solaris Flash archive that is used to validate
a clone system. The manifest section lists the files on a system to be retained,
added to, or deleted from the clone system. This section is informational
only. The section lists the files in an internal format and cannot be used
for scripting.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-11a"><glossterm>master system</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system that you use to create a Solaris Flash archive.
The system configuration is saved in the archive.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-26"><glossterm>MD5</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Message Digest 5) An iterative cryptographic hash function
that is used for message authentication,  including digital signatures. The
function was developed in 1991 by Rivest.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-35"><glossterm>media server</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <emphasis>install server</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><filename>menu.lst</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para><emphasis role="strong">x86 only</emphasis>: A file that lists
all the operating systems that are installed on a  system.  The contents of
this file dictate the list of operating systems  that is displayed on the
GRUB menu.  From the GRUB menu, you can easily  boot an operating system without
modifying the BIOS or <literal>fdisk</literal> partition  settings.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-70"><glossterm>metadevice</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <emphasis>volume</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-2"><glossterm>miniroot</glossterm><glossdef><para>A minimal, bootable root (<filename>/</filename>) file system
that is included in Solaris  installation media. A miniroot consists of the
Solaris software  that is required to install and upgrade systems. On x86
based systems,  the miniroot is copied to the system to be used as the failsafe
boot archive. See <emphasis>failsafe boot archive</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-5"><glossterm>mirror</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <emphasis>RAID-1 volume</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-36"><glossterm>mount</glossterm><glossdef><para>The process of accessing a directory from a disk that is attached
to a machine that is making the mount request or a remote disk on a network.
To mount a file system, you need a mount point on the local system and the
name of the file system to be mounted (for example, <literal>/usr</literal>).</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-37"><glossterm>mount point</glossterm><glossdef><para>A workstation directory to which you mount a file system that
exists on a remote machine.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-38"><glossterm>name server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A server that provides a naming service to systems on a network. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-39"><glossterm>naming service</glossterm><glossdef><para>A distributed network database that contains key system information
about all the systems on a network so that the systems can communicate with
each other. With a naming service, the system information can be maintained,
managed, and accessed on a network-wide basis. Without a naming service, each
system has to maintain its own copy of the system information in the local <literal>/etc</literal> files. Sun supports the following naming services: LDAP, NIS,
and NIS+. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-41"><glossterm>networked systems</glossterm><glossdef><para>A group of systems (called hosts) that are connected through
hardware and software so that they can communicate and share information.
Referred to as a local area network (LAN). One or more servers are usually
needed when systems are networked.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-40"><glossterm>network installation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A way to install software over the network from a system with
a CD-ROM or DVD-ROM drive to a system without a CD-ROM or DVD-ROM drive. Network
installations require a <emphasis>name server</emphasis> and an <emphasis>install
server</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-42"><glossterm>NIS</glossterm><glossdef><para>The SunOS 4.0 (minimum) Network Information Service. A distributed
network database that contains key information about the systems and the users
on the network. The NIS database is stored on the master server and all the
slave servers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-43"><glossterm>NIS+</glossterm><glossdef><para>The SunOS 5.0 (minimum) Network Information Service. NIS+
replaces NIS, the SunOS 4.0 (minimum) Network Information Service. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>non-global zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>A virtualized operating system environment created within
 a single instance of the Solaris Operating System.  One or more  applications
can run in a non-global zone without interacting with the rest of the system.
Non-global zones are also called zones. See also <emphasis>Solaris Zones</emphasis> and <emphasis>global zone</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-44"><glossterm>nonnetworked systems</glossterm><glossdef><para>Systems that are not connected to a network or do not rely
on other systems.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-46"><glossterm>OS server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system that provides services to systems on a network. To
serve diskless clients, an OS server must have disk space set aside for each
diskless client's root (/) file system and swap space (<literal>/export/root</literal>, <literal>/export/swap</literal>). </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-12a"><glossterm>package</glossterm><glossdef><para>A collection of software that is grouped into a single entity
for modular installation. The Solaris software is divided into <emphasis>software
groups</emphasis>, which are each composed of <emphasis>clusters</emphasis> and
packages.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7781"><glossterm>panel</glossterm><glossdef><para>A container for organizing the contents of a window, a dialog
box, or applet. The panel might collect and confirm user input. Panels might
be used by wizards and follow an ordered sequence to fulfill a designated
task. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-48"><glossterm>patch analyzer</glossterm><glossdef><para>A script that you can run manually or as part of the Solaris
installation program. The patch analyzer performs an analysis on your system
to determine which (if any) patches will be removed by upgrading to a Solaris
update.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-13a"><glossterm>platform group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A vendor-defined grouping of hardware platforms for the purpose
of distributing specific software. Examples of valid platform groups are i86pc
and sun4u.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-49"><glossterm>platform name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The output of the <literal>uname -i</literal> command. For
example, the platform name for the Ultra 60 is SUNW,Ultra-60.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-14a"><glossterm>Power Management</glossterm><glossdef><para>Software that automatically saves the state of a system and
turns it off after it is idle for 30 minutes. When you install the Solaris
software on a system that complies with Version 2 of the U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency's Energy Star guidelines, the Power Management software
is installed by default. A <literal>sun4u</literal> SPARC based system is
an example of a system that has Power Management installed by default. After
a subsequent reboot, you are prompted to enable or disable the Power Management
software.</para><para>Energy Star guidelines require that systems or monitors
automatically enter a &ldquo;sleep state&rdquo; (consume 30 watts or less)
after the system or monitor becomes inactive.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>primary boot archive</glossterm><glossdef><para>A boot archive that is used to boot the Solaris OS on  a system.
This boot archive is sometimes called the primary boot archive. See <emphasis>boot
archive</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7z"><glossterm>probe keyword</glossterm><glossdef><para>A syntactical element that extracts attribute information
about a system when using the custom JumpStart method to install. A probe
keyword does not require you to set up a matching condition and run a profile
as required for a rule. See also <emphasis>rule</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-500"><glossterm>profile</glossterm><glossdef><para>A text file that defines how to install the Solaris software
when using the custom JumpStart method. For example, a profile defines which
software group to install. Every rule specifies a profile that defines how
a system is to be installed when the rule is matched. You usually create a
different profile for every rule. However, the same profile can be used in
more than one rule. See also <emphasis>rules file</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-51"><glossterm>profile diskette</glossterm><glossdef><para>A diskette that contains all the essential custom JumpStart
files in its root directory (JumpStart directory). </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-52"><glossterm>profile server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A server that contains all the essential custom JumpStart
files in a JumpStart directory.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-27"><glossterm>private key</glossterm><glossdef><para>The decryption key used in public-key encryption.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-28"><glossterm>public key</glossterm><glossdef><para>The encryption key used in public-key encryption.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-29"><glossterm>public-key cryptography</glossterm><glossdef><para>A cryptographic system that uses two keys: a public key known
to  everyone, and a private key known only to the recipient of the message.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-31"><glossterm>RAID-1 volume</glossterm><glossdef><para>A class of volume that replicates data by maintaining multiple
copies. A RAID-1 volume is composed of one or more RAID-0 volumes called <emphasis>submirrors</emphasis>.  A RAID-1 volume is sometimes called a <emphasis>mirror</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-4raid"><glossterm>RAID-0 volume</glossterm><glossdef><para>A class of volume that can be a stripe or a concatenation.
These components are also called submirrors. A stripe or concatenation is
the basic building block for mirrors.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-1215"><glossterm>Reduced Network Support Software
Group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software group that contains the minimum code that is required
to boot and run a Solaris system with limited network service support. The
Reduced Networking Software Group provides a multiuser text-based console
and system administration utilities. This software group also enables the
system to  recognize network interfaces, but does not activate network services.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-53"><glossterm>root</glossterm><glossdef><para>The top level of a hierarchy of items. Root is the one item
from  which all other items are descended.  See <emphasis>root directory</emphasis> or <emphasis>root</emphasis> (<filename>/</filename>) <emphasis>file system</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>root (<filename>/</filename>) file system</glossterm><glossdef><para>The top-level file system from which all other file systems
stem. The root (<filename>/</filename>) file system is the base on which all
other file systems are mounted, and is never unmounted. The root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system contains the directories and files critical for system operation,
such as the kernel, device drivers, and the programs that are used to start
(boot) a system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>root directory</glossterm><glossdef><para>The top-level directory from which all other directories stem.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-54"><glossterm>rule</glossterm><glossdef><para>A series of values that assigns one or more system attributes
to a profile. A rule is used in a custom JumpStart installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-55"><glossterm><filename>rules</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A text file that contains a rule for each group of systems
or single systems that you want to install automatically. Each rule distinguishes
a group of systems, based on one or more system attributes. The <filename>rules</filename> file
links each group to a profile, which is a text file that defines how the Solaris
software is to be installed on each system in the group. A <filename>rules</filename> file
is used in a custom JumpStart installation. See also <emphasis>profile</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-56"><glossterm><filename>rules.ok</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A generated version of the <literal>rules</literal> file.
The <filename>rules.ok</filename> file is required by the custom JumpStart
installation software to match a system to a profile. You <emphasis>must</emphasis> use
the <literal>check</literal> script to create the <literal>rules.ok</literal> file.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-30"><glossterm>Secure Sockets Layer</glossterm><glossdef><para>(SSL) A software library establishing a secure connection
between two  parties (client and server) used to implement HTTPS, the secure
version of HTTP.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-15a"><glossterm>server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A network device that manages resources and supplies services
to a client.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-31sha"><glossterm>SHA1</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Secure Hashing Algorithm) The algorithm that operates on
any input length less  than 2<superscript>64</superscript> to produce a message
digest.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-190"><glossterm>shareable file systems</glossterm><glossdef><para>File systems that are user-defined files such as <filename>/export/home</filename> and <filename>/swap</filename>. These file systems are shared
between the active and inactive boot environment when you use Solaris Live
Upgrade. Shareable file systems contain the same mount point in the <filename>vfstab</filename> file in both the active and inactive boot environments. Updating
shared files in the active boot environment also updates data in the inactive
boot environment. Shareable file systems are shared by default, but you can
specify a destination slice, and then the file systems are copied. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-57"><glossterm>slice</glossterm><glossdef><para>The unit into which the disk space is divided by the software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-600"><glossterm>software group</glossterm><glossdef><para>A logical grouping of the Solaris software (clusters and packages).
During a Solaris installation, you can install one of the following software
groups: Core, End User Solaris Software, Developer Solaris Software, or Entire
Solaris Software, and for SPARC systems only, Entire Solaris Software Group
Plus OEM Support.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-58"><glossterm>Solaris DVD or CD images</glossterm><glossdef><para>The Solaris software that is installed on a system, which
you can access on the Solaris DVDs or CDs or an install server's hard disk
to which you have copied the Solaris DVD or CD images.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-18a"><glossterm>Solaris Flash</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Solaris installation feature that enables you to create
an archive of the files on a system, called the <emphasis>master system</emphasis>.
You can then use the archive to install other systems, making the other systems
identical in their configuration to the master system. See also <emphasis>archive.</emphasis></para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-16a"><glossterm>Solaris installation program</glossterm><glossdef><para>A graphical user interface (GUI) or command-line interface
(CLI) installation program that uses wizard panels to guide you step-by-step
through installing the Solaris software and third-party software.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7782"><glossterm>Solaris Live Upgrade</glossterm><glossdef><para>An upgrade method that enables a duplicate boot environment
to be upgraded while the active boot environment is still running, thus eliminating
downtime of the production environment. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Solaris Zones</glossterm><glossdef><para>A software partitioning technology used to virtualize operating
system services and provide an isolated and secure environment for running
applications.  When you create a non-global zone, you produce an application
execution environment in which processes are isolated from all other zones.
 This isolation prevents processes that are running in a zone from monitoring
or affecting processes that are running in any other zones. See also <emphasis>global
zone</emphasis> and <emphasis>non-global zone</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-61"><glossterm>standalone</glossterm><glossdef><para>A computer that does not require support from any other machine.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-8sd"><glossterm>state database</glossterm><glossdef><para>A database that stores information about the state of your
Solaris Volume Manager configuration. The state database is a collection of
multiple, replicated database copies. Each copy is referred to as a <emphasis>state
database replica</emphasis>. The state database tracks the location and status
of all known state database replicas.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-9st"><glossterm>state database replica</glossterm><glossdef><para>A copy of a state database. The replica ensures that the data
in the database is valid.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7sub"><glossterm>submirror</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <emphasis>RAID-0 volume</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-62"><glossterm>subnet</glossterm><glossdef><para>A working scheme that divides a single logical network into
smaller physical networks to simplify routing.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-63"><glossterm>subnet mask</glossterm><glossdef><para>A bit mask that is used to select bits from an Internet address
for subnet addressing. The mask is 32 bits long and selects the network portion
of the Internet address and 1 or more bits of the local portion. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>superuser</glossterm><glossdef><para>A special user who has privileges to perform all administrative
tasks on the system. The superuser has  the ability to read and write to any
file, run all programs,  and send kill signals to any process.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-64"><glossterm>swap space</glossterm><glossdef><para>A slice or file that temporarily holds the contents of a memory
area till it can be reloaded in memory. Also called the <literal>/swap</literal> or <literal>swap</literal> file system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-17a"><glossterm><filename>sysidcfg</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file in which you specify a set of special system configuration
keywords that preconfigure a system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-32"><glossterm>system configuration file</glossterm><glossdef><para>(<filename>system.conf</filename>) A text file in which you
specify the locations of the <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file and  the custom
JumpStart files you want to use in a WAN boot installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-66"><glossterm>time zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>Any of the 24 longitudinal divisions of the earth's surface
for which a standard time is kept.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-33"><glossterm><filename>truststore</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that contains one or more digital certificates. During
a WAN boot  installation, the client system verifies the identity of the server
that is trying to  perform the installation by consulting the data in the <filename>truststore</filename> file.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-150"><glossterm>unmount</glossterm><glossdef><para>The process of removing access to a directory on a disk that
is attached to a machine or to a remote disk on a network. </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7783"><glossterm>update</glossterm><glossdef><para>An installation, or to perform an installation, on a system
that changes software that is of the same type. Unlike an upgrade, an update
might downgrade the system.  Unlike an initial installation, software of the
same type that is being installed must be present before an update can occur.
 </para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-7784"><glossterm>upgrade</glossterm><glossdef><para>An installation that merges files with existing files and
preserves modifications where possible. </para><para>An upgrade of the Solaris
OS merges the new version of the Solaris OS with the existing files on the
system's disk or disks. An upgrade saves as many modifications as possible
that you have made to the previous version of the Solaris OS.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-67"><glossterm>upgrade option</glossterm><glossdef><para>An option that is presented by the Solaris installation program . The upgrade
procedure merges the new version of Solaris with existing files on your disk
or disks. An upgrade also saves as many local modifications as possible since
the last time Solaris was installed.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-34"><glossterm>URL</glossterm><glossdef><para>(Uniform Resource Locator) The addressing system used by the
server and the client to  request documents. A URL is often called a location.
The format of a URL is  <replaceable>protocol://machine:port/document</replaceable>.</para><para>A sample URL is <literal>http://www.example.com/index.html</literal>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-400"><glossterm>utility</glossterm><glossdef><para>A standard program, usually furnished at no charge with the
purchase of a computer, that does the computer's housekeeping.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-80"><glossterm>volume</glossterm><glossdef><para>A group of physical slices or other volumes that appear to
the system as a single logical device. A volume is functionally identical
to a physical disk for the purposes of an application or file system. </para><para>In some command-line utilities, a volume is called a metadevice. Volume
is also called <emphasis>pseudo device</emphasis> or <emphasis>virtual device</emphasis> in
standard UNIX terms.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-700"><glossterm>removable
media services</glossterm><glossdef><para>A program that provides a mechanism to administer and obtain
access to the data on DVD-ROMs, CD-ROMs, and diskettes.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-36wan"><glossterm>WAN</glossterm><glossdef><para>(wide area network) A network that connects multiple local
area networks (LANs) or systems at different geographical sites by using telephone,
fiber-optic, or satellite links.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-37wbi"><glossterm>WAN boot installation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A type of installation that enables you to boot and install
software  over a wide area network (WAN) by using HTTP or HTTPS. The WAN boot
installation method  enables you to transmit an encrypted Solaris Flash archive
over a public network and perform  a custom JumpStart installation on a remote
client.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-38wbmini"><glossterm>WAN boot miniroot</glossterm><glossdef><para>A miniroot that has been modified to perform a WAN boot installation.
The WAN boot miniroot contains a subset of the software in the Solaris miniroot.
See also  <olink targetptr="glossary-2" remap="internal">miniroot</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-39wbs"><glossterm>WAN boot server</glossterm><glossdef><para>A web server that provides the configuration and security
files that are used during a WAN boot installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-35wanboot"><glossterm><filename>wanboot</filename> program</glossterm><glossdef><para>The second-level boot program that loads the WAN boot miniroot,
client configuration files, and installation files that are required to perform
a WAN boot  installation. For WAN boot installations, the <filename>wanboot</filename> binary
performs tasks similar to the  <filename>ufsboot</filename> or <filename>inetboot</filename> second-level boot programs.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-40wbcgi"><glossterm><filename>wanboot-cgi</filename> program</glossterm><glossdef><para>The CGI program that retrieves and transmits the data and
files that are used in a WAN boot installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossary-41wbconf"><glossterm><filename>wanboot.conf</filename> file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A text file in which you specify the configuration information
and  security settings that are required to perform a WAN boot installation.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>zone</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <emphasis>non-global zone</emphasis></para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary>