<chapter id="intro-1"><title>Where to Find Solaris Installation Planning
Information</title><highlights><para>This book contains two parts: the high-level planning of your installation
or upgrade and overviews of several technologies that relate to installation.
This chapter provides a roadmap through this book.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="intro"><title>Where to Find Planning and System Requirement Information</title><para>The <olink targetdoc="solinstallpbiu" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Planning for Installation and Upgrade</citetitle></olink> provides
system requirements and high-level planning information, such as planning
guidelines for file systems, and upgrade planning and much more. The following
list describes the chapters in the planning book and provides links to those
chapters.</para><informaltable frame="topbot" pgwide="100"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="61.61*"/><colspec colwidth="38.39*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Chapter Descriptions</para>
</entry><entry><para>Reference</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>This chapter describes new features in the Solaris installation programs.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gaufd" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2,
What's New in Solaris Installation</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter provides you with information about decisions you need
to make before you install or upgrade the Solaris OS. Examples are deciding
when to use a network installation image or DVD media and descriptions of
all the Solaris installation programs.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="planning-8" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3,
Solaris Installation and Upgrade (Roadmap)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter describes system requirements to install or upgrade to
the Solaris OS. General guidelines for planning the disk space and default
swap space allocation are also provided. Upgrade limitations are also described.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="diskspace-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4,
System Requirements, Guidelines, and Upgrade (Planning)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>This chapter contains checklists to help you gather all of the information
that you need to install or upgrade your system. This information is useful,
for example, if you are performing an interactive installation. You'll have
all the information in the checklist that you'll need to do an interactive
installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gatherinfo-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Gathering Information
Before Installation or Upgrade (Planning)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>These chapters provide overviews of several technologies that relate
to a Solaris OS installation or upgrade. Guidelines and requirements related
to these technologies are also included. These chapters include information
about GRUB based booting, Solaris Zones partitioning technology, and RAID-1
volumes that can be created at installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="epucs" remap="internal">Part&nbsp;II, Understanding
Installations That Relate to GRUB, Solaris Zones, and RAID-1 Volumes</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
</chapter>