<chapter id="planning-8"><title>Solaris Installation and Upgrade (Roadmap)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides you with information about decisions you need
to make before you install or upgrade the Solaris Operating System (Solaris
OS). This chapter contains the following sections:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planning-32" remap="internal">Task Map: Installing or Upgrading
the Solaris Software</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planning-5" remap="internal">Installing From the Network
or From DVD or CDs?</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planning-11" remap="internal">Initial Installation, or Upgrade?</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planning-222" remap="internal">Choosing a Solaris Installation
Method</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gdpgj" remap="internal">Planning Network Security</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="planning-84" remap="internal">Sun Java System Application
Server Platform Edition 9</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>This book uses the term <emphasis>slice</emphasis>, but some Solaris
documentation and programs might refer to a slice as a partition.</para><para>x86:
To avoid confusion, this book distinguishes between x86 <filename>fdisk</filename> 
partitions and the divisions within the Solaris <filename>fdisk</filename> partition.
The x86 <filename>fdisk</filename> divisions are called partitions. The divisions
within the Solaris <filename>fdisk</filename> partition are called slices.</para>
</note>
</highlights><sect1 id="planning-32"><title>Task Map: Installing or Upgrading the Solaris
Software</title><para>The following task map is an overview of the
steps necessary to install or upgrade the Solaris OS when using any installation
program. Use this task map to identify all of the decisions that you need
to make to complete the most efficient installation for your environment.</para><table frame="all" pgwide="1" id="planning-tbl-33"><title>Task Map: Installing
or Upgrading the Solaris Software</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="23.60*"/><colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.60*"/><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="27.80*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Choose initial installation or upgrade.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Decide if you want to perform an initial installation or an upgrade.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="planning-11" remap="internal">Initial Installation, or Upgrade?</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Choose an installation program.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The Solaris OS provides several programs for installation or upgrade.
Choose the installation method that is most appropriate for your environment.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="planning-222" remap="internal">Choosing a Solaris Installation Method</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Solaris interactive installation program) Choose a default or custom
installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Decide which type installation is suitable for your environment:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If you are using a graphical user interface (GUI) you can
choose a default or a custom installation:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>A default installation formats the hard disk and installs
a preselected set of software.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A custom installation enables you to modify the hard disk
layout and select the software that you want to install.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you use a text installer (non-graphical interface), you
can select the default values or edit the values to select the software you
want to install.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para>For information on the Solaris installation program's choices, see <olink targetptr="gatherinfo-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Gathering Information Before Installation
or Upgrade (Planning)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>For initial installations only, choose open network security or restricted
network security.</para>
</entry><entry><para>For an initial installation, determine whether to disable or constrain
network services to respond to local requests only during the installation.
The default is to select open network security during installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdpgj" remap="internal">Planning Network Security</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Review system requirements. Also, plan and allocate disk space and swap
space.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Determine if your system meets the minimum requirements to install or
upgrade. Allocate disk space on your system for the components of the Solaris
OS that you want to install. Determine the appropriate swap-space layout for
your system.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="diskspace-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, System Requirements,
Guidelines, and Upgrade (Planning)</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Choose to install a system from local media or from the network.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Decide on the most appropriate installation media for your environment.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="planning-5" remap="internal">Installing From the Network or From DVD
or CDs?</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Gather information about your system.</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For the Solaris installation program, complete the worksheet
to collect all of the information that you need to install or upgrade.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the custom JumpStart installation method, decide which
profile keywords to use in your profile. Then review the keyword descriptions
to find the information about your system that you need.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For the Solaris installation program, see either of the following
documents:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For an initial installation:</para><para><olink targetptr="gatherinfo-2" remap="internal">Checklist for Installation</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For an upgrade: <olink targetptr="gatherinfo-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5,
Gathering Information Before Installation or Upgrade (Planning)</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>For the custom JumpStart installation method, see <olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" targetptr="jumpstartreference-1" remap="external">Chapter 8, <citetitle remap="chapter">Custom JumpStart (Reference),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Optional) Set system parameters.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You can preconfigure system information to avoid being prompted for
the information during the installation or upgrade.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="preconsysid-15630" remap="external">Chapter 2, <citetitle remap="chapter">Preconfiguring System Configuration Information (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Optional) Prepare to install the Solaris software from the network.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you chose to install the Solaris software from the network, complete
the following tasks.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>(x86 based systems) Verify that your system supports PXE</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create an installation server</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a boot server (if necessary)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Configure a DHCP server (if necessary)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Set up systems to be installed from the network</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para>To install over a local area network, see <olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="netinstall-28995" remap="external">Chapter 6, <citetitle remap="chapter">Installing From the Network With CD Media (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>To install over a wide area network, see <olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="wanboottasks-1" remap="external">Chapter 11, <citetitle remap="chapter">Installing With WAN Boot (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>(Upgrade only) Perform tasks prior to upgrade.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Back up your system and determine if you can upgrade with disk space
reallocation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="emyaq" remap="internal">Upgrade Planning</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Perform an installation or upgrade.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the Solaris installation method that you chose to install or upgrade
the Solaris software.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The chapter or chapters that provide detailed instructions for the installation
programs.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Troubleshoot installation problems</para>
</entry><entry><para>Review the troubleshooting information when you encounter problems with
your installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" targetptr="troubleshooting-9" remap="external">Appendix A, <citetitle remap="appendix">Troubleshooting (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1><sect1 id="planning-5"><title>Installing From the Network or From DVD or CDs?</title><para>The Solaris software is distributed on DVD or CD media so that you can
install or upgrade systems that have access to a DVD-ROM or CD-ROM drive.</para><para>You can set up the systems to install from the network with remote DVD
or CD images. You might want to set up systems this way for the following
reasons:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If you have systems that do not have local DVD-ROM or CD-ROM
drives </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are installing several systems and do not want to insert
the discs into every local drive to install the Solaris software</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>You can use all of the Solaris installation methods to install a system
from the network. However, by installing systems from the network with the Solaris Flash installation
feature or with a custom JumpStart installation, you can centralize and automate
the installation process in a large enterprise. For more details about the
different installation methods, refer to <olink targetptr="planning-222" remap="internal">Choosing
a Solaris Installation Method</olink>.</para><para>Installing the Solaris software from the network requires initial setup.
For information about preparing to install from the network, choose one of
the following options. </para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><tbody><row><entry><para>For detailed instructions about preparing to install from a local area
network</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="netinstall-28995" remap="external">Chapter 6, <citetitle remap="chapter">Installing From the Network With CD Media (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>For instructions about preparing to install over a wide area network</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="wanboottasks-1" remap="external">Chapter 11, <citetitle remap="chapter">Installing With WAN Boot (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>For instructions about how to install x86 based clients over the network
by using PXE</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="bootdiskette-31" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Overview of Booting and Installing Over the Network With PXE</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="planning-11"><title>Initial Installation, or Upgrade?</title><para>You can choose to perform an initial installation or, if your system
is already running the Solaris OS, you can upgrade your system.</para><sect2 id="esbjr"><title>Initial Installation</title><para>An initial installation overwrites the system's disk with the new version
of the Solaris OS. If your system is not running the Solaris OS, you must
perform an initial installation.</para><para>If the system is already running the Solaris OS, you can choose to perform
an initial installation. If you want to preserve any local modifications,
before you install, you must back up the local modifications. After you complete
the installation, you can restore the local modifications.</para><para>You can use any of the Solaris installation methods to perform an initial
installation. For detailed information about the different Solaris installation
methods, refer to <olink targetptr="planning-222" remap="internal">Choosing a Solaris Installation
Method</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="esbjt"><title>Upgrade</title><para>You can upgrade the Solaris OS by using two upgrade methods: standard
and Solaris Live Upgrade. A standard upgrade maintains as many existing configuration
parameters as possible of the current Solaris OS. Solaris Live Upgrade creates
a copy of the current system. This copy can be upgraded with a standard upgrade.
The upgraded Solaris OS can then be switched to become the current system
by a simple reboot. If a failure occurs, you can switch back to the original
Solaris OS with a reboot. Solaris Live Upgrade enables you to keep your system
running while you upgrade and enables you to switch back and forth between
Solaris OS releases.</para><para>For more information about upgrading and the list of upgrade methods,
see <olink targetptr="emyaq" remap="internal">Upgrade Planning</olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="planning-222"><title>Choosing a Solaris Installation Method</title><para>The Solaris OS provides several programs for
installation or upgrade. Each installation technology offers different features
that are designed for specific installation requirements and environments.
Use the following table to help you decide which installation method to use.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="100" id="esimi"><title>Choosing Your Installation
Method</title><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="32.92*"/><colspec colwidth="27.46*"/><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="46.37*"/><colspec colwidth="25.25*"/><thead><row><entry rowsep="1"><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Installation Method</para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Reasons for Choosing This Program</para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1"><para>Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Install one system from CD-ROM or DVD-ROM media with an interactive
program.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Solaris installation program</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>This program divides tasks into panels, prompts you for information,
and offers default values.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>This program is not an efficient method when you have to install
or upgrade multiple systems. For batch installations of multiple systems,
use custom JumpStart or the Solaris Flash installation feature.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solarisinstall" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Basic Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Install one system over a local area network.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Solaris installation program over the network</para>
</entry><entry><para>This program enables you to set up an image of the software you want
to install on a server and install this image on a remote system. If you need
to install multiple systems, you can use the network installation image with
the custom JumpStart and Solaris Flash installation methods to efficiently
install or upgrade systems on your network.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="ejurp" remap="external">Part&nbsp;II, <citetitle remap="chapter">Installing Over a Local Area Network,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Automate the installation or upgrade of multiple systems based on profiles
you create.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Custom JumpStart</para>
</entry><entry><para>This program efficiently installs multiple systems. But if you only
have a few systems, the creation of a custom JumpStart environment might be
time consuming. For a few systems, use the Solaris interactive installation
program.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" targetptr="preparecustom-56440" remap="external">Chapter 3, <citetitle remap="chapter">Preparing Custom JumpStart Installations (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Replicate the same software and configuration on multiple systems.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Solaris Flash archives</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>This program saves installation time by installing all Solaris
packages at once on your system. Other programs install each individual Solaris
package and update the package map for each package.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Solaris Flash archives are large files and require a significant
amount of disk space. To manage different installation configurations or to
change your installation configuration, you might consider using the custom
JumpStart installation method. Alternatively, you can accomplish system-specific
customizations by using a JumpStart finish script or an embedded Solaris Flash postdeployment
script.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallflash" targetptr="flash-24" remap="external">Chapter 1, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Flash (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Install systems over a wide area network (WAN) or the Internet.</para>
</entry><entry><para>WAN boot</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you want to install a Solaris Flash archive over the network, this
program enables a secure installation.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="wanbootoverview-1" remap="external">Chapter 9, <citetitle remap="chapter">WAN Boot (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Upgrade a system while it is running.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Solaris Live Upgrade</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>This program enables you to upgrade or add patches to avoid
the system down time related to a standard upgrade</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>This program enables you to test an upgrade or new patches
without affecting the current OS</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" targetptr="luoverview-1" remap="external">Chapter 2, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Live Upgrade (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>After installing the Solaris OS, create an isolated application environment.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Solaris Zones partitioning technology</para>
</entry><entry><para>This program creates isolated non-global zones that provide a secure
application environment. This isolation prevents processes that are running
in one zone from monitoring or affecting processes that are running in any
other zones. </para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="sysadrm" targetptr="zones.intro-1" remap="external">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Introduction to Solaris Zones,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1><sect1 id="planning-84"><title>Sun Java System Application Server Platform
Edition 9</title><para>The Sun Java System Application Server Platform Edition 9 provides for
broad deployment of application services and web services. This software is
automatically installed with the Solaris OS. You can find documentation for
the server in the following areas:</para><informaltable frame="topbot" pgwide="100"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="22.42*"/><colspec colwidth="77.58*"/><thead><row><entry rowsep="1" valign="top"><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1" valign="top"><para>For More Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>For documentation about starting the server</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="sjsaseeqsg" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Sun Java System Application Server Platform Edition 9 Quick Start Guide</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>For the full Application Server documentation set</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/coll/1343.3" type="url">http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/coll/1343.3</ulink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>For the JavaTM EE 5 Tutorial</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="java.sun.com/javaee/5/docs/tutorial/doc/index.html" type="url">http://java.sun.com/javaee/5/docs/tutorial/doc/index.html</ulink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
</chapter>