<chapter id="gaufd"><title>What's New in Solaris Installation</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes new features in the Solaris installation
programs. To view features for all of the Solaris OS, see <olink targetdoc="solwhatsnew" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Developer Edition What&rsquo;s New</citetitle></olink>. This chapter describes the following
sections.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="gevkv"><title>What's New in the Solaris Express
Developer Edition</title><sect2 id="gfajo" arch="x86"><title>GRUB
Extended Support for Directly Loading and Booting the UNIX Kernel</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express Developer
Edition 5/07 release,</emphasis> changes have been made to GRUB that enable
the boot loader to directly load and boot the <literal>unix</literal> kernel.
The GRUB multiboot module is no longer used. This implementation integrates
the previous multiboot functionality directly into the platform-specific <literal>unix</literal> kernel module. These changes reduce the time, as well as memory
requirements, that are needed to boot the Solaris OS.</para><para>Two new keywords, <literal>kernel$</literal> and <literal>module$</literal>,
have been added to GRUB to assist in creating <filename>menu.lst</filename> entries
that work with either 32-bit or 64-bit systems. Another new keyword, <literal>$ISADIR</literal>, displays 32&ndash;bit and 64&ndash;bit information in the
boot command. In addition, the <command>bootadm</command> command that manages
the <filename>menu.lst</filename> file has been modified to create file entries
for the platform-specific <literal>unix</literal> module that is loaded by
GRUB. During an upgrade, the <command>bootadm</command> command converts any
existing multiboot <filename>menu.lst</filename> entries to <literal>unix</literal> entries.</para><note><para>These new keywords are used in normal installations. However,
the miniroot is 32-bit only. Therefore, failsafe installations do not use
the new keywords.</para>
</note><para>For overview and task-related information, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="grubtasks-1" remap="external">Chapter 11, <citetitle remap="chapter">Administering the GRUB Bootloader (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink>. See also <olink targetdoc="sysadv1" targetptr="hbx86boot-68676" remap="external">Chapter 12, <citetitle remap="chapter">Booting a Solaris System With GRUB (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink>.</para><para>For more information, see the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>boot</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>bootadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> man pages.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="geuqh"><title>The Solaris Express Developer Edition
Release</title><para><emphasis role="strong">The Solaris Express Developer Edition
5/07 (Developer) release</emphasis> includes new device drivers and additional
developer tools.  In addition, you can now upgrade
your Developer release. Additional developer
tools  include Sun Studio
12, NetBeans Visual Web Pack 5.5, and NetBeans Profiler 5.5.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express Developer Edition
2/07 release</emphasis>, a new installation provides a simple initial  installation
of the Solaris OS for your laptop. Combined with community and Sun support
and training services, the Developer release includes the tools,  technologies,
and platforms that enable developers to create custom Solaris, <trademark>Java</trademark>,
and Web 2.0 applications.</para><para>The Developer release installs a Solaris system that is  automatically
networked by using DHCP with DNS name resolution. IPv6 is also enabled. The
Solaris Developer release is an initial installation, not an upgrade.</para><para>The Developer release is the new default installation from the DVD.
In the initial installation screen, you now see the following choices with
the Developer release as the default.</para><screen>Solaris Express Developer Edition
Solaris Express
Solaris Express Serial Console ttya
Solaris Express Serial Console ttyb (for lx50,v60x and v65x)</screen><para>The &ldquo;Solaris Express&rdquo; and &ldquo;Solaris Express Serial
Console&rdquo; installations provide system administrators with the necessary
choices to set up servers and clients. Because of the configuration choices,
these installations require more time. These installation options do not include
the developer tools. If you choose the Solaris Express Developer Edition option and do
not have enough memory to run the graphical user interface (GUI), you must
select one the of the other &ldquo;Solaris Express&rdquo; installations on
the screen.</para><para>The Developer release includes the following developer tools, operating
system, and desktop:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><trademark>Sun</trademark> Studio 11 &ndash; C, C++, Fortran
compilers, IDE, and integrated tools</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><trademark>NetBeans</trademark> IDE 5.5 &ndash; An open-sourced
IDE for Java software  developers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>NetBeans IDE Enterprise Pack 5.5 &ndash; Added to the NetBeans
IDE, functionality to develop Java Platform, Enterprise Edition 5 based  applications</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Java Platform, Standard Edition 6 &ndash; The OpenJDK based
release of the Java platform JDK</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><trademark>StarOffice</trademark> 8 &ndash; The OpenOffice
based productivity suite,  including word processor, spreadsheet, and presentation
tools</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Open Source Tools &ndash; Over 150 open source applications,
including Perl, Python, and GCC</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Solaris Express operating system and desktop - Includes new
features from the Java Desktop System (JDS). JDS is a secure and comprehensive
enterprise desktop software solution that combines open-source innovation
from communities such as GNOME, and Firefox. The Desktop includes the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>GNOME 2.16 - The latest enhanced GNOME desktop</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Firefox 2.0 and Thunderbird 1.5 - Current release of Mozilla
browser and email service</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Orca - Screen reader and magnifier for the JDS/GNOME  desktop</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Java and GNOME bindings for the GNOME Platform libraries and
the Cairo 2D drawing engine - Enable GNOME and GTK+ applications to be written
in Java software</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>NetBeans plug-ins - Used in the NetBeans IDE to create  applications</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ekiga - An open-source desktop Voice over IP  (VoIP) and video-conferencing
application for the GNOME desktop</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Vino - Provides the ability to remotely administer a desktop
session</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para> To learn more about the JDS features, see <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/project/jds" type="text">Open Solaris</ulink> http://opensolaris.org/os/project/jds/.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>The Solaris Express
Developer Edition is currently only for x86 based systems. However, developers
on SPARC based systems can obtain  similar functionality by downloading Solaris Express Community Edition
and then installing Sun Studio and NetBeans IDE 5.5 with NetBeans Enterprise
Pack 5.5.</para><itemizedlist><para>Downloads are available at the following Web sites:</para><listitem><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/downloads" type="text_url">Solaris Express Community
Edition</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://developers.sun.com/sunstudio/downloads" type="text_url">Sun Studio 11</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.netbeans.info/downloads/index.php" type="text_url">NetBeans IDE 5.5</ulink> with NetBeans Enterprise Pack 5.5.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="gfagg"><title>Automated Network Configuration</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express
Developer Edition 5/07 release, </emphasis> the booting process runs the <command>nwamd</command> daemon. This daemon implements an alternate instance of the
SMF service <literal>svc:/network/physical</literal> which enables automated
network configuration with minimal intervention. The Open Solaris Network
Auto-Magic Phase 0 page and <command>nwamd</command> man page contain further
information, including instructions for turning off the NWAM daemon, if preferred.
For more information and a link to the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>nwamd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page, see <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/nwam/phase0/" type="text">http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/nwam/phase0/</ulink>.</para><note><itemizedlist><para>For the 5/07 developer release, the NWAM daemon is enabled by default
under the following circumstances:</para><listitem><para>You have selected the &ldquo;Solaris Express Developer Edition&rdquo;
choice on the installation screen.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>And, after having made this choice, you are performing an
initial installation.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>The NWAM daemon is not enabled under the following circumstances:</para><listitem><para>On the installation screen, you choose &ldquo;Solaris Express.&rdquo;</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Or, you choose to upgrade after any choice on the installation
screen.</para><para>In those cases, you must manually turn on the NWAM daemon.
See the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>nwamd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page for details.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="geupp"><title>Upgrading the Solaris OS When Non-Global Zones Are
Installed</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express Developer Edition
2/07 release</emphasis>, you can upgrade the Solaris OS when non-global
zones are installed.</para><note><para>The only limitation to upgrading involves a Solaris Flash 
archive. When you use a Solaris Flash archive to install,  an archive
that contains non-global zones is not properly installed on your system.</para>
</note><para>Changes to accommodate systems that have non-global zones installed
are summarized below.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For the Solaris interactive installation program, you can
upgrade or patch a system when non-global zones are installed. The time to upgrade or patch might be extensive, depending on the
number of non-global zones that are installed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For an automated JumpStart installation, you can upgrade or
patch with any keyword that applies to an upgrade or patching. The
time to upgrade or patch might be extensive, depending on the number of non-global
zones that are installed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para> For Solaris Live Upgrade, you can upgrade or patch a system
that contains non-global zones.  If you have a system that contains non-global
zones, Solaris Live Upgrade is the recommended upgrade program or program
to add patches.  Other upgrade programs might require extensive upgrade time,
because the time required to complete the upgrade increases linearly with
the number of installed non-global zones.  If you are patching a system with
Solaris Live Upgrade, you do not have  to take the system to single-user mode
and you can maximize  your system's uptime.</para><para>Solaris Live Upgrade
creates a copy of the OS on the inactive boot environment.  The inactive boot
environment can be upgraded or patched when non-global zones are installed.
 The inactive boot environment can then be booted to become the new boot environment.
 Changes to accommodate systems that have non-global zones installed are the
following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>A new package, <literal>SUNWlucfg</literal>, is required to
be installed with the  other Solaris Live Upgrade packages, <literal>SUNWlur</literal> and <literal>SUNWluu</literal>. This package is required for any system, not just a system
with non-global zones installed.</para><para>These three packages comprise
the software needed to upgrade by using Solaris Live Upgrade. These packages
include existing software, new features, and bug fixes. If you do not install
these  packages on your system before using Solaris Live Upgrade,  upgrading
to the target release fails.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Creating a new boot environment from the currently running
boot environment remains the same as in previous releases with one exception.
You can specify a destination disk slice for a shared file system within a
non-global zone.</para><para>The argument to the <option>m</option> option
has a new optional field, <replaceable>zonename</replaceable>.  This new field
enables creating the new boot environment and specifying zones that contain
separate file systems.  This argument places the zone's file system on a separate
slice in the new boot environment.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <command>lumount</command> command now provides non-global
zones with access to their corresponding file systems that exist on inactive
boot environments.  When the global zone administrator uses the <command>lumount</command> command
to mount an inactive boot environment, the boot environment is mounted for
non-global zones as well.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Comparing boot environments is enhanced. The <command>lucompare</command> command
now generates a comparison of boot environments that includes the contents
of any non-global zone.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Listing file systems with the <command>lufslist</command> command
is enhanced to display a list of file systems for both the global zone and
the non-global zones.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For step-by-step procedures for upgrading a system with non-global 
zones installed or for information on the Solaris Zones partitioning  technology,
see the following references.</para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For More Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Upgrading with Solaris Live Upgrade on a system with non-global zones</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" targetptr="gdzlc" remap="external">Chapter 9, <citetitle remap="chapter">Upgrading the Solaris OS on a System With Non-Global  Zones Installed,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Creating and using non-global zones</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="sysadrm" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Upgrading with JumpStart</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Upgrading with the Solaris installation interactive GUI</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solarisinstall" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Basic Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect2><sect2 id="geuub"><title>New <command>sysidkdb</command> Tool Prevents
Having to Configure Your Keyboard </title><para>SPARC: This
feature was introduced for SPARC based systems in the <emphasis role="strong">Solaris
Express 10/06 release</emphasis>.</para><para>x86: This feature was introduced
for x86 based systems in the <emphasis role="strong">Solaris Express Developer
Edition 2/07</emphasis>.</para><para>The <command>sysidkdb</command> tool
configures your USB language and its corresponding keyboard layout.</para><para>The following procedure occurs:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If the keyboard is self-identifying, the keyboard language
and layout automatically configures during installation. </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If the keyboard is not self-identifying, the <command>sysidkdb</command> tool
provides you, during the installation, a list of supported keyboard layouts
during installation, so that you can select a layout for keyboard configuration.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><emphasis role="strong">SPARC</emphasis>: Previously, the USB keyboard
assumed a self-identifying value of 1 during the installation. Therefore,
all of the keyboards that were not self-identifying always configured for
a U.S. English keyboard layout during installation.</para><note><para>PS/2 keyboards are not self-identifying. You are asked to select
the keyboard layout during the installation.</para>
</note><sect3 id="geviy"><title>Prevent Prompting When You Use the JumpStart Program</title><para>If the keyboard is not self-identifying and you want to prevent being
prompted during your JumpStart installation, select the keyboard language
in your <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file. For JumpStart installations, the
default is for the U.S. English language. To select another language and its
corresponding keyboard layout, set the keyboard keyword in your <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file.</para><itemizedlist><para>For more information, see one of the following:</para><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="preconsysid-55534" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Preconfiguring With the sysidcfg File</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="sysidtool-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidtool</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman" targetptr="sysidcfg-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidcfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2><sect2 id="gfakx"><title>New <command>sharemgr</command> Utility for File-Sharing</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express Developer
Edition 2/07 release,</emphasis> you can use the new <command>sharemgr</command> utility for file-sharing tasks during installations. This
new utility both simplifies and enhances the file-sharing process and related
tasks. You do not need to use the <command>share</command>, <command>shareall</command>,
or <command>unshare</command> utilities, although these utilities are still
available. Additionally, you do not need to edit the <filename>/etc/dfs/dfstab</filename> file.</para><para>The <command>sharemgr</command> utility introduces the concept of a
share group. Options for <command>sharemgr</command> are set to a share group,
not to a specific file or directory. A share group can be used by multiple
file-system types, such as NFS and ZFS. For example, the share group, <literal>my_group</literal>, could have one set of options for NFS and another set of options
for ZFS.</para><para>For more information, see the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>sharemgr</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page. See also, <olink targetdoc="sysadv4" targetptr="gcrvu" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">sharemgr Command</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Network Services</citetitle></olink>.</para><note><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express Developer
Edition 5/07 release,</emphasis> installation documentation
provides both options for file-sharing, using <command>sharemgr</command> or
using the <command>share</command> command.</para>
</note>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdlfa"><title>What's New in the Solaris Express
7/06 Release for Installation</title><sect2><title>Enhanced Security Using the Restricted Networking Profile</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting
with the Solaris Express 7/06</emphasis>, the generic installation has been
changed so that all network services, except Secure Shell,  are disabled or
restricted to respond to local requests only. This change minimizes the potential
vulnerabilities a remote attacker might try to exploit. In addition, the change
provides a base for customers to enable only the services they require.</para><para>For Solaris Express releases, the hardening changes are automatically applied
whenever a fresh install is performed. This effect is achieved by invoking
the <command>netservices</command> command from the SMF upgrade file found
in <filename>/var/svc/profile</filename>. Behavior is unchanged if the system
is upgraded.</para><para>All of the affected services are controlled by the
Service Management Framework (SMF). Any individual service can be enabled
by using the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>svsadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>svccfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> commands. The <citerefentry><refentrytitle>netservices</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> command can be used to switch the service startup behavior.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="geuou"><title>Installing Solaris Trusted Extensions</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express 7/06 release</emphasis>, Solaris Trusted Extensions provides multilevel security for the
Solaris OS. This feature enables you to control information in a flexible
but highly secure manner. You can now enforce strict access controls to your
data based on data sensitivity, not just data ownership.</para><para>An installation that accesses Solaris Trusted Extensions differs from
a standard installation. For a list of these installation differences and
further information about Solaris Trusted Extensions, see <olink targetdoc="trsolinstall" targetptr="startinst-4" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Installing or Upgrading the Solaris OS for Trusted Extensions</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Trusted Extensions Installation and Configuration</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="geupi"><title>Solaris Flash Can
Create an Archive That Includes Large Files</title><para>The <command>flarcreate</command> command
no longer has size limitations on individual files. You can create a Solaris Flash archive
that contains individual files over 4 Gbytes. The following two archive utilities
are available for use: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The portable archive interchange utility, <command>pax</command>,
is the default. The archive can be created without size limitations on individual
files.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <command>cpio</command> archive utility is invoked with <option>L cpio</option> option.  Individual files cannot be greater than 2 or 4 Gbytes.
 The size limitation depends  on the version of <command>cpio</command> used.
This option is useful for backward compatibility issues.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For more information, see <olink targetdoc="solinstallflash" targetptr="gbwbm" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Creating an Archive That Contains Large Files</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle></olink></para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gfats"><title>What's
New in the Solaris Express 5/06 Release
for Installation</title><sect2 id="geupg"><title>NFSv4 Domain Name Configurable During Installation</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the
Solaris Express 5/06 release</emphasis>,
the NFS version 4 domain can now be defined during the installation of the
Solaris OS. Previously, the NFS domain name was defined during the first system
reboot after installation.</para><para>This new feature affects installation as follows:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The <command>sysidtool</command> command includes an enhanced <command>sysidnfs4</command> program. The <command>sysidnfs4</command> program now
runs during the installation process to determine whether an NFSv4 domain
has been configured for the network.</para><para>For further information,
see the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="sysidtool-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidtool</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> and <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="sysidnfs4-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidnfs4</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man pages.</para><para>During an interactive installation, the user is provided with the default
NFSv4 domain name that is automatically derived from the OS. The user can
accept this default. Or, the user can specify a different NFSv4 domain.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>As part of a Solaris JumpStart installation, a new keyword
is available in the <filename>sysidcfg</filename> file. The user can now assign
a value for the NFSv4 domain by using the new keyword, <literal>nfs4_domain</literal>.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For further information about this new keyword, see the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="sysidnfs4-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysidnfs4</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.
This man page also provides an example of how to use this new keyword</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For further information about the NFSv4 domain name configuration,
 see the <olink targetdoc="sysadv4" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Network Services</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="s10206"><title>What's New in the Solaris Express
1/06 Release for Solaris Installation</title><para>This section describes the following new installation features in the
Solaris Express release.</para><sect2 id="fwfdg" arch="x86"><title>GRUB Based Booting</title><para><emphasis role="strong">Starting with the Solaris Express  release</emphasis>, the open source GNU GRand Unified Boot Loader (GRUB) has been
adopted in the Solaris OS for x86 based systems. GRUB is responsible for loading
 a boot archive into the system's memory. A boot archive is a collection of
critical files that is needed during system startup before the root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system is mounted. The boot archive is used to boot the Solaris OS.</para><para>The most notable change is the replacement of the Solaris Device Configuration Assistant with
the GRUB menu. The GRUB menu facilitates booting the different operating systems
that are installed on your system. The GRUB menu is displayed when you boot
an x86 based system. From the GRUB menu, you can select an OS instance to
install by using the arrow keys. If you do not make a selection, the default
OS instance is booted. </para><para>The GRUB based boot feature provides the following improvements:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Faster boot times</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Installation from USB CD or DVD drives</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ability to boot from USB storage devices</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Simplified DHCP setup for PXE boot (no vendor-specific options)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Elimination of all realmode drivers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ability to use Solaris Live Upgrade and the GRUB menu to quickly
activate and fall back to boot environments</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For more information about GRUB refer to the following sections.</para><informaltable frame="topbot" pgwide="1"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="30.14*"/><colspec colwidth="52.68*"/><colspec colwidth="67.17*"/><thead><row><entry rowsep="1"><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1" valign="top"><para>GRUB Task</para>
</entry><entry rowsep="1" valign="top"><para>For More Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry morerows="5"><para>Installation</para>
</entry><entry><para>Overview information about GRUB based booting</para>
</entry><entry><para>What's
New: <olink targetptr="gfajo" remap="internal">GRUB Extended Support for Directly Loading and
Booting the UNIX Kernel</olink></para><para><olink targetptr="fxivs" remap="internal">GRUB Based Booting (Overview)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Installation planning for GRUB based booting</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gavdl" remap="internal">GRUB Based Booting (Planning)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>How to boot and install over the network with the GRUB menu</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallnet" targetptr="eyaup" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Installing the System From the Network With a DVD Image</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Network-Based Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>How to boot and install with the GRUB menu and the Custom JumpStart
installation method</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" targetptr="customjump-3" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Performing a Custom JumpStart Installation</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>How to use the GRUB menu and Solaris Live Upgrade to activate and fall
back to boot environments </para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" targetptr="luupgrade-84" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Activating a Boot Environment</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" targetptr="luupgrade-85" remap="external">Chapter 6, <citetitle remap="chapter">Failure Recovery: Falling Back to the Original Boot Environment (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Locating the GRUB menu's <filename>menu.lst</filename> file</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" targetptr="gbdfr" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Locating the GRUB Menu&rsquo;s menu.lst File (Tasks)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>System Administration</para>
</entry><entry><para>How to perform system administration tasks with the GRUB menu</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="sysadv1" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Basic Administration</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="sagdfs" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Devices and File Systems</citetitle></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="bootadm-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>bootadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="installgrub-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>installgrub</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><note><para>GNU is a recursive acronym for &ldquo;GNU's Not UNIX.&rdquo; For
more information, go to <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org" type="url">http://www.gnu.org</ulink>.</para>
</note>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>