<chapter id="gdhbj"><title>Upgrading When Solaris Zones Are Installed
on a System (Planning)</title><highlights><para>This chapter provides an overview of  how Solaris Zones partitioning
technology relates to upgrading the Solaris OS when non-global zones are configured.</para><para>This chapter contains the following sections:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gavhc" remap="internal">Solaris Zones (Overview)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gdkbx" remap="internal">Upgrading With Non-Global Zones</olink>l</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="gcdfn" remap="internal">Disk Space Requirements for Non-Global
Zones</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="gavhc"><title>Solaris Zones (Overview)</title><para>The Solaris Zones partitioning technology is used to virtualize operating
system services and provide an isolated and secure environment for running
applications. A non-global zone is a virtualized operating system environment
created within a single instance of the Solaris OS. When you create a non-global
zone, you produce an application execution environment in which processes
are isolated from the rest of the system. This isolation prevents processes
that are running in one non-global zone from monitoring or affecting processes
that are running in other non-global zones. Even a process running with superuser
credentials cannot view or affect activity in other zones.  A non-global zone
also provides an abstract layer that separates applications from the physical
attributes of the machine on which they are deployed. Examples of these attributes
include physical device paths.</para><para>Every Solaris system contains a global zone. The global zone has a dual
function. The global zone is both the default zone for the system and the
zone used for system-wide administrative control. All processes run in the
global zone if no non-global zones are created by the global administrator.
 The global zone is the only zone from which a non-global zone can be configured,
installed, managed, or uninstalled. Only the global zone is bootable from
the system hardware. Administration of the system infrastructure, such as
physical devices, routing, or dynamic reconfiguration (DR), is only possible
in the global zone. Appropriately privileged processes running in the global
zone can access objects associated with the non-global zones. </para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For More Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>The following sections describe how you can upgrade a system that contains
non-global zones.</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetptr="gdkbx" remap="internal">Upgrading With Non-Global Zones</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>For complete information on creating and configuring non-global zones</para>
</entry><entry><para><olink targetdoc="sysadrm" targetptr="zones.intro-1" remap="external">Chapter 16, <citetitle remap="chapter">Introduction to Solaris Zones,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="gdkbx"><title>Upgrading With Non-Global Zones</title><para>After the
Solaris OS is installed, you can install and configure non-global zones. You
can upgrade the Solaris OS when non-global zones are installed. If you have
branded non-global zones installed, they are ignored during the upgrade process.
Changes to accommodate systems that have non-global zones installed are summarized
below.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For the Solaris interactive installation program, you can
upgrade or patch a system when non-global zones are installed.  The time to
upgrade or patch might be extensive, depending on the number of non-global
zones that are installed. For more information about installing with this
program, see <olink targetdoc="solarisinstall" targetptr="webstart-91" remap="external">Chapter 2, <citetitle remap="chapter">Installing With the Solaris Installation Program (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Basic Installations</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For an automated JumpStart installation, you can upgrade or
patch with any keyword that applies to an upgrade or patching. The time to
upgrade or patch might be extensive, depending on the number of non-global
zones that are installed. For more information about installing with this
program, see <olink targetdoc="solinstalladv" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Custom JumpStart and Advanced Installations</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para> For Solaris Live Upgrade, you can upgrade or patch a system
that contains non-global zones.  If you have a system that contains non-global
zones, Solaris Live Upgrade is the recommended upgrade program or program
to add patches.  Other upgrade programs might require extensive upgrade time,
because the time required to complete the upgrade increases linearly with
the number of installed non-global zones.  If you are patching a system with
Solaris Live Upgrade, you do not have  to take the system to single-user mode
and you can maximize  your system's uptime. Changes to accommodate systems
that have non-global zones installed are the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>A new package, <literal>SUNWlucfg</literal>, is required to
be installed with the  other Solaris Live Upgrade packages, <literal>SUNWlur</literal> and <literal>SUNWluu</literal>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Creating a new boot environment from the currently running
boot environment remains the same with one exception. You can specify a destination
slice for a shared file system within a non-global zone. This exception occurs
under the following circumstances:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If on the current boot environment the <command>zonecfg add
fs</command> command was used that created a separate file system for a non-global
zone</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If this separate file system resides on a shared file system,
such as <filename>/zone/root/export</filename></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>To prevent this separate file system from being shared in the new boot
environment, the <command>lucreate</command> command has changed to enable
specifying a destination slice for a separate file system for a non-global
zone. The argument to the <option>m</option> option has a new optional field, <replaceable>zonename</replaceable>. This new field places the non-global zone's separate
file system on a separate slice in the new boot environment. For more information
on setting up a non-global zone with a separate file system, see <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="zonecfg-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>zonecfg</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>.</para><note><para>By default, any file system other than the critical file systems
(root (<filename>/</filename>), <filename>/usr</filename>, and <filename>/opt</filename> file
systems) is shared between the current and new boot environments. Updating
shared files in the active boot environment also updates data in the inactive
boot environment. The <filename>/export</filename> file system is an example
of a shared file system. If you use the <option>m</option> option and the <replaceable>zonename</replaceable> option, the non-global zone's shared file system is
copied to a separate slice and data is not shared. This option prevents non-global
zone file systems that were created with the <command>zonecfg add fs</command> command
from being shared between the boot environments. </para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>Comparing boot environments is enhanced. The <command>lucompare</command> command
now generates a comparison of boot environments that includes the contents
of any non-global zone.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <command>lumount</command> command now provides non-global
zones with access to their corresponding separate file systems that exist
on inactive boot environments.  When the global zone administrator uses the <command>lumount</command> command to mount an inactive boot environment, the boot
environment is mounted for non-global zones as well.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Listing file systems with the <command>lufslist</command> command
is enhanced to display a list of file systems for both the global zone and
the non-global zones.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For step-by-step instructions on using Solaris Live Upgrade when non-global
zones are installed, see <olink targetdoc="solinstallupg" targetptr="gdzlc" remap="external">Chapter 9, <citetitle remap="chapter">Upgrading the Solaris OS on a System With Non-Global  Zones Installed,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide:  Solaris Live Upgrade and Upgrade Planning</citetitle></olink>.</para><table frame="topbot" id="gebmx"><title>Limitations When Upgrading With Non-Global
Zones</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="32.84*"/><colspec colwidth="67.16*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Program or Condition</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Solaris Flash archives</para>
</entry><entry><para>A Solaris Flash archive
cannot be properly created when a non-global zone is installed. The Solaris
Flash feature is not compatible  with Solaris Zones partitioning technology.
If you create a Solaris Flash archive, the resulting  archive is not installed
properly when the archive is deployed under these conditions:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The archive is created in a non-global zone.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The archive is created in a global zone that has non-global
zones installed.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For more information about using Solaris Flash archives, see <olink targetdoc="solinstallflash" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">Solaris Express Installation Guide: Solaris Flash Archives (Creation and Installation)</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Using a command that uses the <option>R</option> option or equivalent
must not be used in some situations.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Any command that accepts an alternate root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system by using the <option>R</option> option or equivalent must not
be used if the following are true:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The command is run in the global zone.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The alternative root (<filename>/</filename>) file system
refers to any path within a non-global zone.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>An example is the <option>R</option> <replaceable>root_path</replaceable> option
to the <command>pkgadd</command> utility run from the global zone with a path
to the root (<filename>/</filename>) file system in a non-global zone.</para><para>For a list of utilities that accept an alternate root (<filename>/</filename>)
file system and more information about zones, see <olink targetdoc="sysadrm" targetptr="z.admin.ov-46" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Restriction on Accessing A Non-Global Zone From the Global Zone</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>ZFS file systems and non-global zones</para>
</entry><entry><para> If a non-global zone is on a ZFS file system, the upgrade process does
not upgrade the non-global zone.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><sect2 id="gdhbs"><title>Backing Up Your System Before Performing
an Upgrade With Zones</title><para>You should back up the global and non-global zones on your Solaris system
before you perform the upgrade. For information about backing up a system
with zones installed, see <olink targetdoc="sysadrm" targetptr="z.admin.ov-1" remap="external">Chapter 26, <citetitle remap="chapter">Solaris Zones Administration (Overview),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="gcdfn"><title>Disk Space Requirements for Non-Global Zones</title><para>When installing the global zone, be sure to  reserve enough disk
space for all of the zones you might create. Each non-global zone might have
unique disk space requirements. </para><para>No limits are placed on how much disk space can be consumed by a zone.
 The global zone administrator is responsible for space restriction.  Even
a small uniprocessor system can support a number of zones running simultaneously.
 The characteristics of the packages installed in the global zone affect the
space requirements of the non-global zones that are created.  The number of
packages and space requirements are factors.</para><para>For complete planning requirements and recommendations, see <olink targetdoc="sysadrm" targetptr="z.conf.start-1" remap="external">Chapter 18, <citetitle remap="chapter">Planning and Configuring Non-Global Zones (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Solaris Containers-Resource Management and Solaris Zones</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>