<chapter id="chapter3-20"><title>Configuring the DHCP Service (Tasks)</title><highlights><para>When you configure the DHCP service on your network, you configure and
start the first DHCP server. Other DHCP servers can be added later and can access
the same data from a shared location if the data store supports shared data. This
chapter describes tasks that enable you to configure the DHCP server and place networks
and their associated IP addresses under DHCP management. This chapter also explains
how to unconfigure a DHCP server.</para><itemizedlist><para>Each task includes a procedure to help you perform the task in DHCP Manager
and a procedure for the equivalent task with the <literal>dhcpconfig</literal> utility.
This chapter contains the following information:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="chapter3-21" remap="internal">Configuring and Unconfiguring a DHCP
Server Using DHCP Manager</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="dhcp-config-13" remap="internal">Configuring and Unconfiguring a
DHCP Server Using dhcpconfig Commands</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>If you experience problems configuring the DHCP service, see <olink targetptr="dhcp-trouble-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;17, Troubleshooting DHCP (Reference)</olink>.</para><para>After you configure the DHCP service, see <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-9" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;15, Administering DHCP (Tasks)</olink> for information about managing the DHCP service.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="chapter3-21"><title>Configuring and Unconfiguring a DHCP Server Using DHCP
Manager</title><para>This section includes procedures to help you configure and unconfigure a DHCP
server with DHCP Manager. Note that you must be running an X Window system such as
CDE or GNOME to use DHCP Manager.</para><para>DHCP Manager can be run as superuser with the <command>/usr/sadm/admin/bin/dhcpmgr</command> command. See <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-1" remap="internal">About DHCP Manager</olink> for
general information about the utility. See <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-109" remap="internal">How to Start and Stop the DHCP Service (DHCP Manager)</olink> for more detailed information
about running DHCP Manager.</para><para>When you run DHCP Manager on a server that is not configured for DHCP, the following
screen is displayed. You can specify whether you want to configure a DHCP server or
a BOOTP relay agent.</para><figure id="dhcp-config-fig-82"><title>Choose Server Configuration Dialog Box in DHCP
Manager</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="dhcp-config-choice.tif"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Dialog box shows options Configure as DHCP server and Configure
as BOOTP relay. Shows OK, Cancel, and Help buttons.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><sect2 id="dhcp-config-65"><title>Configuring DHCP Servers</title><para>When you configure a
DHCP server, DHCP Manager starts the DHCP Configuration Wizard, which prompts you
for information that is needed to configure the server. The initial screen of the
wizard is shown in the following figure.</para><figure id="dhcp-config-fig-85"><title>DHCP Configuration Wizard's Initial Screen</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="dhcp-config-wiz.tif"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Dialog box shows storage choices, back and forward arrows, and
Cancel and Help buttons.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>When you finish answering the wizard prompts, DHCP Manager creates the items
that are listed in the following table.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1" id="dhcp-config-tbl-68"><title>Items Created During
DHCP Server Configuration</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="25.04*"/><colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="33.12*"/><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="40.83*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Item</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>Contents</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Service configuration file, <filename>/etc/inet/dhcpsvc.conf</filename></para>
</entry><entry><para>Records keywords and values for server configuration options.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Data store type and location, and options that are used with <literal>in.dhcpd</literal> to start the DHCP daemon when the system boots. Do not edit this file manually.
You must use <filename>dhcpmgr</filename> or <filename>dhcpconfig</filename> to modify
DHCP configuration information.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><filename>dhcptab</filename> table </para>
</entry><entry><para>DHCP Manager creates a <literal>dhcptab</literal> table if the table does not
already exist.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Macros and options with assigned values.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Locale macro (optional), which is named <literal>Locale</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>Contains the local time zone's offset in seconds from Universal time (UTC).</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>UTCoffst</literal> option with assigned number of seconds.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Server macro, which is named to match the server's node name</para>
</entry><entry><para>Contains options whose values are determined by input from the administrator
who configured the DHCP server. Options apply to all clients that use addresses owned
by the server.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The <literal>Locale</literal> macro, plus the following options: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literal>Timeserv</literal>, set to point to the server's primary
IP address.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>LeaseTim</literal>, set to the number of seconds for the
leases.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>LeaseNeg</literal>, if you selected negotiable leases.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>DNSdmain</literal> and <literal>DNSserv</literal>, if DNS
is configured.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>Hostname</literal>, which <emphasis>must not</emphasis> be
assigned a value. The presence of this option indicates that the host name must be
obtained from the name service.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Network address macro, whose name is the same as the network address of
client's network</para>
</entry><entry><para>Contains options whose values are determined by input from the administrator
who configured the DHCP server. Options apply to all clients that reside on the network
specified by the macro name.</para>
</entry><entry><para>The following options: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><literal>Subnet</literal>, set to the subnet mask for the local subnet</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>Router</literal>, set to the IP address of a router, or <literal>RDiscvyF</literal>, to cause the client to use router discovery</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>Broadcst</literal>, set to the broadcast IP address. This
option is present only if the network is not a Point-to-Point network.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>MTU</literal></para><para>, for the maximum transmission
unit</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>NISdmain</literal> and <literal>NISservs</literal>, if NIS
is configured</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>NIS+dom</literal> and <literal>NIS+serv</literal>, if NIS+
is configured</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Network table for the network</para>
</entry><entry><para>An empty table is created until you create IP addresses for the network.</para>
</entry><entry><para>No content until you add IP addresses.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2><task id="dhcp-config-96"><title>How to Configure a DHCP Server (DHCP Manager)</title><taskprerequisites><itemizedlist><para>Make sure that you have read <olink targetptr="chap2-26" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Planning for DHCP Service (Tasks)</olink> before you configure your DHCP server. In particular,
you should use the guidelines in <olink targetptr="chapter2-29" remap="internal">Making Decisions for
Your DHCP Server Configuration (Task Map)</olink> to help you perform the following
tasks:</para><listitem><para>Select the system that you want to use as a DHCP server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Make decisions about your data store, lease policy, and router information.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step id="chapter3-step-4"><para>Become superuser on the server system.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-150"><para>Start DHCP Manager.</para><screen>#<userinput>/usr/sadm/admin/bin/dhcpmgr &amp;</userinput></screen>
</step><step id="chapter3-step-5"><para>Choose the option Configure as DHCP Server.</para><para>The DHCP Configuration Wizard starts, to help you configure your server.</para>
</step><step id="chapter3-step-6"><para>Select options, or type requested information, based
on the decisions you made in the planning phase.</para><para>If you have difficulty,
click Help in the wizard window to open your web browser and display help for the
DHCP Configuration Wizard.</para>
</step><step id="chapter3-step-7"><para>Click Finish to complete the server configuration
when you have finished specifying the requested information.</para>
</step><step id="chapter3-step-8"><para>At the Start Address Wizard prompt, click Yes to
configure IP addresses for the server.</para><para>The Add Addresses to Network wizard
enables you to specify which addresses to place under the control of DHCP.</para>
</step><step id="chapter3-step-9"><para>Answer the prompts according to decisions you made
in the planning phase.</para><para>See <olink targetptr="chapter2-30" remap="internal">Making Decisions
for IP Address Management (Task Map)</olink> for more information. If you have difficulty,
click Help in the wizard window to open your web browser and display help for the
Add Addresses to Network wizard.</para>
</step><step id="chapter3-step-10"><para>Review your selections, and then click Finish to
add the IP addresses to the network table.</para><para>The network table is updated
with records for each address in the range you specified.</para>
</step>
</procedure><taskrelated role="see-also"><para>You can add more networks to the DHCP server with the Network Wizard, as explained
in <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-17" remap="internal">Adding DHCP Networks</olink>.</para>
</taskrelated>
</task><sect2 id="dhcp-config-66"><title>Configuring BOOTP Relay Agents</title><itemizedlist><para>When you configure a BOOTP relay
agent, DHCP Manager takes the following actions:</para><listitem><para>Prompts you for the IP address for one or more DHCP servers to which
requests should be relayed</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Stores settings needed for BOOTP relay service</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The following figure shows the screen displayed when you choose to configure
a BOOTP relay agent.</para><figure id="dhcp-config-fig-84"><title>Configure BOOTP Relay Dialog Box in DHCP Manager</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="dhcp-config-bootp.tif"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Dialog box shows input field labeled DHCP Servers, with an Add
button. Shows an empty list, with up and down arrows and Delete button.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2><task id="dhcp-config-97"><title>How to Configure a BOOTP Relay Agent (DHCP Manager)</title><taskprerequisites><para>Make sure that you have read <olink targetptr="chap2-26" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Planning for DHCP Service (Tasks)</olink> before you configure your BOOTP relay agent. In particular,
you should see <olink targetptr="chapter2-38" remap="internal">Selecting a Host to Run the DHCP Service</olink> for help in selecting the system to use.</para>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step id="dhcp-config-step-23"><para>Become superuser on the server system.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-70"><para>Start the DHCP Manager.</para><screen>#<userinput>/usr/sadm/admin/bin/dhcpmgr &amp;</userinput></screen><para>If the system has not been configured as a DHCP
server or BOOTP relay agent, the DHCP Configuration Wizard starts. If the system has
already been configured as a DHCP server, you must first unconfigure the server. See <olink targetptr="dhcp-config-11" remap="internal">Unconfiguring DHCP Servers and BOOTP Relay Agents</olink>.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-24"><para>Select Configure as BOOTP Relay.</para><para>The Configure BOOTP Relay dialog box opens.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-8"><para>Type the IP address or host name of one or more
DHCP servers, and click Add.</para><para>The specified DHCP servers must be configured
to handle BOOTP or DHCP requests received by this BOOTP relay agent.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-33"><para>Click OK to exit the dialog box.</para><para>Notice that DHCP Manager offers only the File menu to exit the application and the
Service menu to manage the server. The disabled menu options are useful only on a
DHCP server.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><sect2 id="dhcp-config-11"><title>Unconfiguring DHCP Servers and BOOTP Relay Agents</title><itemizedlist><para>When you unconfigure a DHCP server or a BOOTP relay agent, DHCP Manager
takes the following actions:</para><listitem><para>Stops the DHCP daemon (<literal>in.dhpcd</literal>) process</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Removes the <filename>/etc/inet/dhcpsvc.conf</filename> file, which
records information about daemon startup and the data store location</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The following figure shows the screen that is displayed when you choose to unconfigure
a DHCP server.</para><figure id="dhcp-config-fig-83"><title>Unconfigure Service Dialog Box in DHCP Manager</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="dhcp-unconfig.tif"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Dialog box shows choices for removing DHCP data. Shows OK, Cancel,
and Help buttons.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2><sect2 id="dhcp-config-11-1115"><title>DHCP Data on an Unconfigured Server</title><para>When
you unconfigure a DHCP server, you must decide what to do with the <filename>dhcptab</filename> table and the DHCP network tables. If the data is shared among servers,
you should not remove the <filename>dhcptab</filename> and DHCP network tables. If
the tables are removed, DHCP would become unusable across your network. Data can be
shared through NIS+ or on exported local file systems. The file <filename>/etc/inet/dhcpsvc.conf</filename> records the data store used and its location.</para><para>You can unconfigure a DHCP server but leave the data intact by not selecting
any of the options to remove data. If you unconfigure the server and leave the data
intact, you disable the DHCP server.</para><para>If you want another DHCP server to take ownership of the IP addresses, you must
move the DHCP data to the other DHCP server. You must move the data before you unconfigure
the current server. See <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-mv1211" remap="internal">Moving Configuration
Data Between DHCP Servers (Task Map)</olink> for more information.</para><para>If you are certain you want to remove the data, you can select an option to
remove the <literal>dhcptab</literal> and network tables. If you had generated client
names for the DHCP addresses, you can also elect to remove those entries from the
hosts table.  Client name entries can be removed from DNS, <systemitem>/etc/inet/hosts</systemitem>, or NIS+.</para><para>Before you unconfigure a BOOTP relay agent, be sure that no clients rely on
this agent to forward requests to a DHCP server.</para>
</sect2><task id="dhcp-config-98"><title>How to Unconfigure a DHCP Server or a BOOTP Relay
Agent (DHCP Manager)</title><procedure><step id="dhcp-config-step-29"><para>Become superuser.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-71"><para>Start DHCP Manager.</para><screen>#<userinput>/usr/sadm/admin/bin/dhcpmgr &amp;</userinput></screen>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-30"><para>From the Service menu, choose Unconfigure.</para><para>The Unconfigure Service dialog box is displayed. If the server is a BOOTP relay
agent, the dialog box enables you to confirm your intention to unconfigure the relay
agent. If the server is a DHCP server, you must decide what to do with the DHCP data
and make selections in the dialog box. See <olink targetptr="dhcp-config-fig-83" remap="internal">Figure 14&ndash;4</olink>.</para>
</step><step performance="optional" id="dhcp-config-step-10"><para>Select options to remove
data.</para><para>If the server uses shared data through NIS+ or in files shared through
NFS, do not select any options to remove the data. If the server does not use shared
data, select one option or both options to remove the data.</para><para>See <olink targetptr="dhcp-config-11-1115" remap="internal">DHCP Data on an Unconfigured Server</olink> for more
information about removing data.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-12"><para>Click OK to unconfigure the server.</para><para>The Unconfigure Service dialog box and DHCP Manager are closed.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="dhcp-config-13"><title>Configuring and Unconfiguring a DHCP Server Using <command>dhcpconfig</command> Commands</title><para>This section includes procedures to help you configure and unconfigure a DHCP
server or a BOOTP relay agent by using <literal>dhcpconfig</literal> with command-line
options.</para><task id="dhcp-config-14"><title>How to Configure a DHCP Server (<literal>dhcpconfig
-D</literal>)</title><taskprerequisites><itemizedlist><para>Make sure that you have read <olink targetptr="chap2-26" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;13, Planning for DHCP Service (Tasks)</olink> before you configure your DHCP server. In particular,
you should use the guidelines in <olink targetptr="chapter2-29" remap="internal">Making Decisions for
Your DHCP Server Configuration (Task Map)</olink> to help you perform the following
tasks:</para><listitem><para>Select the system that you want to use as a DHCP server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Make decisions about your data store, lease policy, and router information.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step><para>Log in to the system on which you want to configure the DHCP server.</para>
</step>&roleDHCPstep;<step id="dhcp-config-step-19"><para>Configure the DHCP server by typing a command
of the following format:</para><screen>#<userinput>/usr/sbin/dhcpconfig -D -r <replaceable>datastore</replaceable> -p <replaceable>location</replaceable></userinput></screen><para><replaceable>datastore</replaceable> is one of the following: <literal>SUNWfiles</literal>, <literal>SUNWbinfiles</literal>, or <literal>SUNWnisplus</literal>.</para><para><replaceable>location</replaceable> is the data-store-dependent location where
you want to store the DHCP data. For <literal>SUNWfiles</literal> and <literal>SUNWbinfiles</literal>, the location must be an absolute path name. For <literal>SUNWnisplus</literal>,
the location must be a fully specified NIS+ directory.</para><para>For example, you
might type a command similar to the following:</para><screen>dhcpconfig -D -r SUNWbinfiles -p /var/dhcp</screen><para>The <literal>dhcpconfig</literal> utility uses the host's system files and network
files to determine values used to configure the DHCP server. See the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dhcpconfig-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dhcpconfig</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page for information about additional
options to the <literal>dhcpconfig</literal> command that enable you to override the
default values.</para>
</step><step id="dhcp-config-step-20"><para>Add one or more networks to the DHCP service.</para><para>See <olink targetptr="dhcp-admin-127-1115" remap="internal">How to Add a DHCP Network (dhcpconfig)</olink> for the procedure to add a network.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="dhcp-config-21"><title>How to Configure a BOOTP Relay Agent (<literal>dhcpconfig
-R</literal> )</title><taskprerequisites><para>Select the system that you want to use as a BOOTP relay agent, using the requirements
listed in <olink targetptr="chapter2-38" remap="internal">Selecting a Host to Run the DHCP Service</olink>.</para>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step id="dhcp-config-step-23-1115"><para>Log in to the server that you want to configure
as a BOOTP relay agent.</para>
</step>&roleDHCPstep;<step id="dhcp-config-step-25"><para>Configure the BOOTP relay agent by typing a command
of the following format:</para><screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/dhcpconfig -R <replaceable>server-addresses</replaceable></userinput></screen><para>Specify one or more IP addresses of DHCP servers to which you want requests
to be forwarded. If you specify more than one address, separate the addresses with
commas.</para><para>For example, you might type a command similar to the following:</para><screen>/usr/sbin/dhcpconfig -R 192.168.1.18,192.168.42.132</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="dhcp-config-34"><title>How to Unconfigure a DHCP Server or a BOOTP Relay
Agent (<literal>dhcpconfig -U</literal>)</title><procedure><step><para>Log in to the DHCP server or the BOOTP relay agent system that you want
to unconfigure.</para>
</step>&roleDHCPstep;<step id="dhcp-config-step-37"><para>Unconfigure the DHCP server or the BOOTP relay
agent:</para><screen># <userinput>/usr/sbin/dhcpconfig -U</userinput></screen><para>If the server does not use shared data, you can also use the <option>x</option> option
to remove the <literal>dhcptab</literal> and network tables. If the server uses shared
data, do not use the <option>x</option> option. The <option>h</option> option can
be used to remove host names from the host table. See the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="dhcpconfig-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dhcpconfig</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page for more information about <literal>dhcpconfig</literal> options.</para><para>See <olink targetptr="dhcp-config-11-1115" remap="internal">DHCP Data on an Unconfigured Server</olink> for more information about removing data.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
</chapter>