<chapter id="ipplan-1"><title>Planning an IPv4 Addressing
Scheme (Tasks</title><highlights><para>This chapter describes the issues you must resolve in order to create
your network in an organized, cost-effective manner. After you resolve these
issues, you can devise a network plan as you configure and administer your
network in the future. </para><para>This chapter contains the following information:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipplan-2" remap="internal">Determining the Network Hardware</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipplan-34" remap="internal">Obtaining Your Network's IP Number</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipplan-4" remap="internal">Deciding on an IP Addressing Format
for Your Network</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipplan-26" remap="internal">Naming Entities on Your Network</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipplan-37" remap="internal">Planning for Routers on Your Network</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For tasks for configuring a network, refer to <olink targetptr="ipconfig-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;5, Configuring TCP/IP Network Services and IPv4 Addressing (Tasks)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="ipplan-3"><title>Network Planning (Task Map)</title><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50.00*"/><thead><row><entry><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry><para>For Information</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>1. Plan your hardware requirements and network topology</para>
</entry><entry><para>Determine the types of equipment that you need and the layout of this
equipment at your site.</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For general network topology questions, refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-2" remap="internal">Determining the Network Hardware</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For IPv6 topology planning, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-16" remap="internal">Preparing the Network Topology for IPv6 Support</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For information about a specific type of equipment, refer
to the equipment manufacturer's documentation.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>2. Obtain a registered IP address for your network</para>
</entry><entry><para>Your network must have a unique IP address if you plan to communicate
outside your local network, for example, over the Internet.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-34" remap="internal">Obtaining Your Network's IP Number</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>3. Devise an IP addressing scheme for your systems, based on your IPv4
network prefix or IPv6 site prefix.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Determine how addresses are to be deployed at your site.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-5" remap="internal">Designing an IPv4 Addressing Scheme</olink> or
refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-9" remap="internal">Preparing an IPv6 Addressing Plan</olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>4. Create a list that contains the IP addresses and host names of all
machines on your network. </para>
</entry><entry><para>Use the list to build network databases</para>
</entry><entry><para>Refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-29" remap="internal">Network Databases</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>5. Determine which name service to use on your network. </para>
</entry><entry><para>Decide whether to use NIS, LDAP, DNS, or the network databases in the
local <filename>/etc</filename> directory.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-28" remap="internal">Selecting a Name Service and Directory
Service</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>6. Establish administrative subdivisions, if appropriate for your network</para>
</entry><entry><para>Decide if your site requires that you divide your network into administrative
subdivisions</para>
</entry><entry><para>Refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-33" remap="internal">Administrative Subdivisions</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>7. Determine where to place routers in the network design.</para>
</entry><entry><para>If your network is large enough to require routers, create a network
topology that supports them.</para>
</entry><entry><para>Refer to <olink targetptr="ipplan-37" remap="internal">Planning for Routers on Your Network</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>8. If required, design a strategy for subnets.</para>
</entry><entry><para>You might need to create subnets for administering your IP address space
or to make more IP addresses available for users.</para>
</entry><entry><para>For IPv4 subnet planning, refer to <olink targetptr="ipconfig-31" remap="internal">What
Is Subnetting?</olink></para><para>For IPv6 subnet planning, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-22" remap="internal">Creating
a Numbering Scheme for Subnets</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipplan-2"><title>Determining the Network Hardware</title><para>When you design your network, you must decide what type of network
best meets the needs of your organization. Some of the planning decisions
you must make involve the following network hardware: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The network topology, the layout, and connections of the network
hardware</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The number of host systems your network can support</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The types of hosts that the network supports: standalone and
dataless</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The types of servers that you might need</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The type of network media to use: Ethernet, Token Ring, FDDI,
and so on </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether you need bridges or routers extend this media or connect
the local network to external networks</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether some systems need separately purchased interfaces
in addition to their built in interfaces</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Based on these factors, you can determine the size of your local area
network. </para><note><para>How you plan the network hardware is outside the scope of this
manual. For assistance, refer to the manuals that come with your hardware. </para>
</note>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipplan-4"><title>Deciding on an IP Addressing Format for Your Network</title><para>The number of systems that you expect to support affects how you
configure your network. Your organization might require a small network of
several dozen standalone systems that are located on one floor of a single
building. Alternatively, you might need to set up a network with more than
1,000 systems in several buildings. This setup can require you to further
divide your network into subdivisions that are called <emphasis>subnets</emphasis>. </para><para>When you plan your network addressing scheme, consider the following
factors:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The type of IP address that you want to use: IPv4 or IPv6</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The number of potential systems on your network</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The number of systems that are multihomed or routers, which
require an IP address for each interface</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether to use private addresses on your network</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Whether to have a DHCP server that manages pools of IPv4 addresses</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The worldwide growth of the Internet since 1990 has resulted in a shortage
of available IP addresses. To remedy this situation, the Internet Engineering
Task Force (IETF) has developed a number of IP addressing alternatives. Types
of IP addresses in use today include the following:</para><para>If your organization has been assigned more than one IP address
for your network or uses subnets, appoint a centralized authority within your
organization to assign network IP addresses. That authority should maintain
control of a pool of assigned network IP addresses, and assign network, subnet,
and host addresses as required. To prevent problems, ensure that duplicate
or random network numbers do not exist in your organization. </para><sect2 id="eyhxx"><title>IPv4 Addresses</title><para>These 32-bit addresses are the original IP addressing format that was
designed for TCP/IP. Originally, IP networks have three classes, A, B, and
C. The <emphasis>network number</emphasis> that is assigned to a network reflects
this class designation plus 8 or more bits to represent a host. Class-based
IPv4 addresses require you to configure a netmask for the network number.
Furthermore, to make more addresses available for systems on the local network,
these addresses were often divided into subnets. </para><para>Today, IP addresses are referred to as <emphasis>IPv4 addresses</emphasis>.
Although you can no longer obtain class-based IPv4 network numbers from an
ISP, many existing networks still have them. For more information about administering
IPv4 addresses, refer to <olink targetptr="exlxp" remap="internal">Designing Your IPv4 Addressing
Scheme</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="eyhxz"><title>IPv4 Addresses in CIDR Format</title><para>The IETF has developed Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) addresses
as a short to medium term fix for the shortage of IPv4 addresses. In addition,
CIDR format was designed as a remedy to the lack of capacity of the global
Internet routing tables. An IPv4 address with CIDR notation is 32 bits in
length and has the same dotted decimal format. However, CIDR adds a prefix
designation after the rightmost byte to define the network portion of the
IPv4 address. For more information, refer to <olink targetptr="exlvx" remap="internal">Designing
Your CIDR IPv4 Addressing Scheme</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="eyhyc"><title>DHCP Addresses</title><para>The Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) protocol enables a system
to receive configuration information from a DHCP server, including an IP address,
as part of the booting process. DHCP servers maintain pools of IP address
from  which to assign addresses to DHCP clients. A site that uses DHCP can
use a smaller pool of IP addresses than would be needed if all clients were
assigned a permanent IP address. You can set up the Solaris DHCP  service
to manage your site's IP addresses, or a portion of the addresses. For more
information, refer to <olink targetptr="dhcp-overview-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;12, About Solaris DHCP (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="eyhyd"><title>IPv6 Addresses</title><para>The IETF has deployed 128&ndash;bit IPv6 addresses as the long term
solution to the shortage of available IPv4 addresses. IPv6 addresses provide
greater address space than is available with IPv4. The Solaris OS supports
IPv4 and IPv6 addressing on the same host, through the use of dual-stack TCP/IP.
As with IPv4 addresses in CIDR format, IPv6 addresses have no notion of network
classes or netmasks. As in CIDR, IPv6 addresses use prefixes to designate
the portion of the address that defines the site's network. For an introduction
to IPv6, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-overview-10" remap="internal">IPv6 Addressing Overview</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="eyhyb"><title>Private Addresses and Documentation Prefixes</title><para>The IANA has reserved a block of IPv4 addresses and an IPv6 site prefix
for use on private networks. You can deploy these addresses on systems within
an enterprise network but be aware that packets with private addresses cannot
be routed across the Internet. For more information on private addresses,
refer to <olink targetptr="ewpop" remap="internal">Using Private IPv4 Addresses</olink>.</para><note><para>Private IPv4 addresses are also reserved for documentation purposes.
The examples in this book use private IPv4 addresses and the reserved IPv6
documentation prefix.</para>
</note>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipplan-34"><title>Obtaining Your Network's IP Number</title><para>An IPv4 network is defined by a combination of an IPv4 network number
plus a network mask, or <emphasis>netmask</emphasis>. An IPv6 network is defined
by its <emphasis>site prefix</emphasis>, and, if subnetted, its <emphasis>subnet
prefix</emphasis>.</para><para>Unless your network plans to be private in perpetuity, your local users
most likely need to communicate beyond the local network. Therefore, you must
obtain a registered IP number for your network from the appropriate organization
before your network can communicate externally. This address becomes the network
number for your IPv4 addressing scheme or the site prefix for your IPv6 addressing
scheme. </para><para>Internet Service Providers provide IP addresses for networks with pricing
that is based on different levels of service. Investigate with various ISPs
to determine which provides the best service for your network. ISP's typically
offer dynamically allocated addresses or static IP addresses to businesses.
Some ISPs offer both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses.</para><para>If your site is an ISP, you obtain IP address blocks for your customers
from the Internet Registry (IR) for your locale. The Internet Assigned Numbers
Authority (IANA) is ultimately responsible for delegating registered IP addresses
to IRs around the world. Each IR has registration information and templates
for the locale that the IR services. For information about the IANA and its
IRs, refer to the <ulink url="http://www.iana.org/ipaddress/ip-addresses.htm" type="text_url">IANA's IP Address Service page</ulink>.</para><note><para>Do not arbitrarily assign IP addresses to your network, even if
you are not currently attaching the network to external TCP/IP networks. Instead,
use private addresses as described in <olink targetptr="ewpop" remap="internal">Using Private
IPv4 Addresses</olink>.</para>
</note>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipplan-5"><title>Designing an IPv4 Addressing Scheme</title><note><para>For IPv6 address planning information, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-9" remap="internal">Preparing an IPv6 Addressing Plan</olink>.</para>
</note><para>This section gives an overview IPv4 addressing to aid you in designing
an IPv4 addressing plan. For information on IPv6 addresses, see <olink targetptr="ipv6-overview-10" remap="internal">IPv6 Addressing Overview</olink>. For information
on DHCP addresses, see <olink targetptr="dhcp-overview-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;12, About Solaris DHCP (Overview)</olink>.</para><para>Each IPv4-based network must have the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>A unique network number that is assigned by either an ISP,
an IR, or, for older networks, registered by the IANA. If you plan to use
private addresses, the network numbers you devise must be unique within your
organization.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Unique IPv4 addresses for the interfaces of every system on
the network.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A network mask.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The IPv4 address is a 32-bit number that uniquely identifies a
network interface on a system, as explained in <olink targetptr="ipplan-25" remap="internal">How
IP Addresses Apply to Network Interfaces</olink>. An IPv4 address is written
in decimal digits, divided into four 8-bit fields that are separated by periods.
Each 8-bit field represents a byte of the IPv4 address. This form of representing
the bytes of an IPv4 address is often referred to as the <emphasis>dotted-decimal
format</emphasis>. </para><para>The following figure shows the component parts of an IPv4 address, <literal>172.16.50.56</literal>.</para><figure id="eypfv"><title>IPv4 Address Format</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="trad-IPv4"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The figure divides the IPv4 address into two parts, network
part and network host, which are described in the next context.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><variablelist><varlistentry><term><literal>172.16</literal></term><listitem><para>Registered IPv4 network number. In class-based IPv4 notation,
this number also defines the IP network class, Class B in this example, that
would have been registered by the IANA. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><literal>50.56</literal></term><listitem><para>Host part of the IPv4 address. The host part uniquely identifies
an interface on a system on a network. Note that for each interface on a local
network, the network part of the address is the same, but the host part must
be different.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>If you plan to subnet a class-based IPv4 network, you need to define
a subnet mask, or <emphasis>netmask</emphasis>, as explained in <olink targetptr="ipconfig-30" remap="internal">netmasks Database</olink>.</para><para>The next example shows of the CIDR format address <literal>192.168.3.56/22</literal></para><figure id="eypku"><title>CIDR Format IPv4 Address</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="CIDR"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The figure shows the three parts of the CIDR address,
network part, host part, and network prefix, which are described in the next
context.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><variablelist><varlistentry><term><literal>192.168.3</literal></term><listitem><para>Network part, which consists of the IPv4 network number that
is received from an ISP or IR.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><literal>56</literal></term><listitem><para>Host part, which you assign to an interface on a system.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><literal>/22</literal></term><listitem><para>Network prefix, which defines how many bits of the address
comprise the network number. The network prefix also provides the subnet mask
for the IP address. Network prefixes are also assigned by the ISP or IR.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>A Solaris-based network can combine standard IPv4 addresses, CIDR format
IPv4 addresses, DHCP addresses, IPv6 addresses, and private IPv4 addresses.</para><sect2 id="exlxp"><title>Designing Your IPv4 Addressing Scheme</title><para>This section describes the classes into which standard IPv4 address
are organized. Though the IANA no longer gives out class-based network numbers,
these network numbers are still in use on many networks. You might need to
administer the address space for a site with class-based network numbers.
For a complete discussion of IPv4 network classes, refer to <olink targetptr="ipref-4" remap="internal">Network Classes</olink>.</para><para>The following table shows the division of the standard IPv4 address
into network and host address spaces. For each class, &ldquo;Range&rdquo;
specifies the range of decimal values for the first byte of the network number. &ldquo;Network
Address&rdquo; indicates the number of bytes of the IPv4 address that are
dedicated to the network part of the address. Each byte is represented by <replaceable>xxx</replaceable>. &ldquo;Host Address&rdquo; indicates the number of bytes
that are dedicated to the host part of the address. For example, in a class
A network address, the first byte is dedicated to the network, and the last
three bytes are dedicated to the host. The opposite designation is true for
a class C network.</para><table frame="topbot" id="exlxq"><title>Division of the IPv4 Classes</title><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="column1" colwidth="99*"/><colspec colname="column2" colwidth="99*"/><colspec colname="column3" colwidth="99*"/><colspec colname="column4" colwidth="99*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Class</para>
</entry><entry><para>Byte Range</para>
</entry><entry><para>Network Number</para>
</entry><entry><para>Host Address</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>A </para>
</entry><entry><para>0&ndash;127 </para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>xxx</replaceable> </para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>xxx</replaceable>.<replaceable>xxx</replaceable>.<replaceable>xxx</replaceable></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>B </para>
</entry><entry><para>128&ndash;191 </para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>xxx</replaceable>.<replaceable>xxx</replaceable> </para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>xxx</replaceable>.<replaceable>xxx</replaceable></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>C </para>
</entry><entry><para>192&ndash;223 </para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>xxx</replaceable>.<replaceable>xxx</replaceable>.<replaceable>xxx</replaceable> </para>
</entry><entry><para><replaceable>xx</replaceable><replaceable>x</replaceable><replaceable></replaceable></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>The numbers in the first byte of the IPv4 address define whether
the network is class A, B, or C. The remaining three bytes have a range from
0&ndash;255. The two numbers 0 and 255 are reserved. You can assign the numbers
1&ndash;254 to each byte, depending on the network class that was assigned
to your network by the IANA. </para><para>The following table shows which bytes of the IPv4 address are
assigned to you. The table also shows the range of numbers within each byte
that are available for you to assign to your hosts.</para><table frame="topbot" id="exlxs"><title>Range of Available IPv4 Classes</title><tgroup cols="5" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="column1" colwidth="2*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="column2" colwidth="2*"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="column3" colwidth="2*"/><colspec colnum="4" colname="column4" colwidth="2*"/><colspec colnum="5" colname="column5" colwidth="2*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Network Class</para>
</entry><entry><para>Byte 1 Range</para>
</entry><entry><para>Byte 2 Range</para>
</entry><entry><para>Byte 3 Range </para>
</entry><entry><para>Byte 4 Range</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>A </para>
</entry><entry><para>0&ndash;127</para>
</entry><entry><para>1&ndash;254</para>
</entry><entry><para>1&ndash;254 </para>
</entry><entry><para>1&ndash;254</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>B </para>
</entry><entry><para>128&ndash;191</para>
</entry><entry><para>Preassigned by IANA</para>
</entry><entry><para>1&ndash;254</para>
</entry><entry><para>1&ndash;254</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>C </para>
</entry><entry><para>192&ndash;223</para>
</entry><entry><para>Preassigned by IANA</para>
</entry><entry><para>Preassigned by IANA</para>
</entry><entry><para>1&ndash;254</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2><sect2 id="extaq"><title>IPv4 Subnet Number</title><para>Local networks with large numbers of hosts are sometimes divided
into subnets. If you divide your IPv4 network number into subnets, you need
to assign a network identifier to each subnet. You can maximize the efficiency
of the IPv4 address space by using some of the bits from the host part of
the IPv4 address as a network identifier. When used as a network identifier,
the specified part of the address becomes the subnet number. You create a
subnet number by using a netmask, which is a bitmask that selects the network
and subnet parts of an IPv4 address. Refer to <olink targetptr="ipconfig-32" remap="internal">Creating
the Network Mask for IPv4 Addresses</olink> for details. </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="exlvx"><title>Designing Your CIDR IPv4 Addressing Scheme</title><para>The network classes that originally constituted IPv4 are no longer in
use on the global Internet. Today, the IANA distributes classless CIDR format
addresses to its registries around the world. Any IPv4 address that you obtain
from an ISP is in CIDR format, as shown in <olink targetptr="eypku" remap="internal">Figure
2&ndash;2</olink>.</para><para>The network prefix of the CIDR address indicates how many IPv4
addresses are available for hosts on your network. Note that these host addresses
are assigned to interfaces on a host. If a host has more than one physical
interface, you need to assign a host address for every physical interface
that is in use. </para><para>The network prefix of a CIDR address also defines the length of the
subnet mask. Most Solaris 10 commands recognize the CIDR prefix designation
of a network's subnet mask. However, the Solaris installation program and <filename>/etc/netmask file</filename> require you to set the subnet mask by using dotted
decimal representation. In these two cases, use the dotted decimal representation
of the CIDR network prefix, as shown in the next table.</para><table frame="topbot" id="extkp"><title>CIDR Prefixes and Their Decimal Equivalent</title><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="35.65*"/><colspec colwidth="61.08*"/><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="59.47*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>CIDR Network Prefix</para>
</entry><entry><para>Available IP Addresses</para>
</entry><entry><para>Dotted Decimal Subnet Equivalent</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>/19</para>
</entry><entry><para>8,192 </para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.224.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/20</para>
</entry><entry><para>4,096 </para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.240.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/21</para>
</entry><entry><para>2,048</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.248.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/22</para>
</entry><entry><para>1024</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.252.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/23</para>
</entry><entry><para>512</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.254.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/24</para>
</entry><entry><para>256</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.255.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/25</para>
</entry><entry><para>128</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.255.128</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/26</para>
</entry><entry><para>64</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.255.192</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>/27</para>
</entry><entry><para>32</para>
</entry><entry><para>255.255.255.224</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>For more information on CIDR addresses, refer to the following sources:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>For technical details on CIDR, refer to <ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1519.txt?number=1519" type="text_url">RFC
1519, Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR):  an Address Assignment and Aggregation
Strategy</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>More general information about CIDR is available from Pacific
Bell Internet at <ulink url="http://public.pacbell.net/dedicated/cidr.html" type="text_url">Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) Overview</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Another CIDR overview can be found in the Wikipedia article,<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classless_inter-domain_routing" type="text_url">"Classless inter-domain routing"</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ewpop"><title>Using Private IPv4 Addresses</title><para>The IANA has reserved three blocks of IPv4 addresses for companies to
use on their private networks. These addresses are defined in <ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1918.txt?number=1918" type="text_url">RFC
1918, Address Allocation for Private Internets</ulink>. You can use these <emphasis>private addresses</emphasis>, also known as 1918 addresses, for systems on
local networks within a corporate intranet. However, private addresses are
not valid on the Internet. Do not use them on systems that must communicate
outside the local network.</para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="47.56*"/><colspec colwidth="52.44*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>IPv4 Address Range</para>
</entry><entry><para>netmask</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>10.0.0.0 - 10.255.255.255</para>
</entry><entry><para>10.0.0.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>172.16.0.0 - 172.31.255.255</para>
</entry><entry><para>172.16.0.0</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>192.168.0.0 - 192.168.255.255</para>
</entry><entry><para>192.168.0.0</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipplan-25"><title>How IP Addresses Apply to Network Interfaces</title><para>To connect to the network, a system must have at least one <emphasis>physical network interface</emphasis>. Each network interface must have its
own unique IP address. During Solaris installation, you must supply the IP
address for the first interface that the installation program finds. Usually
that interface has the name <replaceable>device-name</replaceable>0, for example <literal>eri0</literal> or <literal>hme0</literal>. This interface is considered the <emphasis>primary network interface</emphasis>.</para><para>If you add a second network interface to a host, that interface also
must have its own unique IP address. When you add the second network interface,
the host then becomes <emphasis>multihomed</emphasis>. By contrast, when you
add a second network interface to a host and enable IP forwarding, that host
becomes a router. See <olink targetptr="ipconfig-116" remap="internal">Configuring an IPv4
Router</olink> for an explanation. </para><para>Each network interface has a device name, a device driver, and an associated
device file in the <filename>/devices</filename> directory. The network interface
might have a device name such as <filename>eri</filename> or <filename>smc0</filename>,
which are device names for two commonly used Ethernet interfaces. </para><para>For information and tasks related to interfaces, refer to  <olink targetptr="fwawf" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;6, Administering
Network Interfaces (Tasks)</olink>.</para><note><para>This book assumes that your systems have Ethernet network interfaces.
If you plan to use different network media, refer to the manuals that come
with the network interface for configuration information. </para>
</note>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipplan-26"><title>Naming Entities on Your Network</title><para>After you receive your assigned network IP address and you have
given the IP addresses to your systems, the next task is to assign names to
the hosts. Then you must determine how to handle name services on your network.
You use these names initially when you set up your network and later when
you expand your network through routers, bridges, or PPP. </para><para>The TCP/IP protocols locate a system on a network by using its IP address.
However, if you use a recognizable name, then you can easily identify the
system. Therefore, the TCP/IP protocols (and the Solaris OS) require both
the IP address and the host name to uniquely identify a system. </para><para>From a TCP/IP perspective, a network is a set of named entities. A host
is an entity with a name. A router is an entity with a name. The network is
an entity with a name. A group or department in which the network is installed
can also be given a name, as can a division, a region, or a company. In theory,
the hierarchy of names that can be used to identify a network has virtually
no limit. The domain name identifies a <emphasis>domain</emphasis>.</para><sect2 id="ipplan-27"><title>Administering Host Names</title><para>Many sites let users pick host names for their machines. Servers
also require at least one host name, which is associated with the IP address
of its primary network interface. </para><para>As a system administrator, you must ensure that each host name in your
domain is unique. In other words, no two machines on your network can both
have the name &ldquo;fred.&rdquo; However, the machine &ldquo;fred&rdquo;
might have multiple IP addresses. </para><para>When planning your network, make a list of IP addresses and their associated
host names for easy access during the setup process. The list can help you
verify that all host names are unique.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipplan-28"><title>Selecting a Name Service and Directory Service</title><para>The Solaris OS enables you to use three types of name services:
local files, NIS, and DNS. Name services maintain critical information about
the machines on a network, such as the host names, IP addresses, Ethernet
addresses, and so forth. The Solaris OS also gives you the option of using
the LDAP directory service in addition to or instead of a name service. For
an introduction to name services on Solaris, refer to <olink targetdoc="sysadv5" targetptr="intro-1" remap="external">Part&nbsp;I, <citetitle remap="chapter">About Naming and Directory Services,</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Naming and Directory Services (DNS, NIS, and LDAP)</citetitle></olink>.</para><sect3 id="ipplan-29"><title>Network Databases</title><para>When you install the operating system, you supply the host name
and IP address of your server, clients, or standalone system as part of the
procedure. The Solaris installation program adds this information into the <filename>hosts</filename> . This database is part of a set of network
databases that contain information necessary for TCP/IP operation on your
network. The name service that you select for your network reads these databases. </para><para>The configuration of the network databases is critical. Therefore, you
need to decide which name service to use as part of the network planning process.
Moreover, the decision to use name services also affects whether you organize
your network into an administrative domain. <olink targetptr="ipconfig-42" remap="internal">Network
Databases and the nsswitch.conf File</olink> has detailed information on the
set of network databases.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipplan-30"><title>Using NIS or DNS as the Name Service</title><para>The NIS and DNS name services maintain network databases on several
servers on the network.  <olink targetdoc="sysadv5" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Naming and Directory Services (DNS, NIS, and LDAP)</citetitle></olink> describes
these name services and explains how to configure the databases. In addition,
the guide explain the &ldquo;namespace&rdquo; and &ldquo;administrative domain&rdquo;
concepts in detail. </para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipplan-31"><title>Using Local Files as the Name Service</title><para>If you do not implement NIS, LDAP, or DNS, the network uses <emphasis>local files</emphasis> to provide the name service. The term &ldquo;local
files&rdquo; refers to the series of files in the <filename>/etc</filename> directory
that the network databases use. The procedures in this book assume you are
using local files for your name service, unless otherwise indicated. </para><note><para>If you decide to use local files as the name service for your
network, you can set up another name service at a later date.</para>
</note>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipplan-32"><title>Domain Names</title><para>Many networks organize their hosts and routers into a hierarchy
of administrative domains. If you are using the NIS or DNS name service, you
must select a domain name for your organization that is unique worldwide.
To ensure that your domain name is unique, you should register the domain
name with the InterNIC. If you plan to use DNS, you also need to register
your domain name with the InterNIC. </para><para>The domain name structure is hierarchical. A new domain typically is
located below an existing, related domain. For example, the domain name for
a subsidiary company can be located below the domain of the parent company.
If the domain name has no other relationship, an organization can place its
domain name directly under one of the existing top-level domains. </para><para>The following are a few examples of top-level domains: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><filename>.com</filename> &ndash; Commercial companies (international
in scope)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>.edu</filename> &ndash; Educational institutions
(international in scope)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>.gov</filename> &ndash; U.S. government agencies</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><filename>.fr</filename> &ndash; France</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>You select the name that identifies your organization, with the provision
that the name must be unique. </para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipplan-33"><title>Administrative Subdivisions</title><para>The question of administrative subdivisions deals with matters
of size and control. The more hosts and servers that you have in a network,
the more complex your management task. You might want to handle such situations
by setting up additional administrative divisions. Add networks of a particular
class. Divide existing networks into subnets. The decision about setting up
administrative subdivisions for your network is determined by the following
factors: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">How large is the network?</emphasis></para><para>A single administrative division can handle a single network of several
hundred hosts, all in the same physical location and requiring the same administrative
services. However, sometimes you should establish several administrative subdivisions.
Subdivisions are particularly useful if you have a small network with subnets
and the network is scattered over an extensive geographical area.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Do users on the network have similar
needs?</emphasis></para><para>For example, you might have a network that is confined to a single
building and supports a relatively small number of machines. These machines
are divided among a number of subnetworks. Each subnetwork supports groups
of users with different needs. In this example, you might use an administrative
subdivision for each subnet.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>&ipplan-router;
</chapter>