<chapter id="ipqos-intro-1"><title>Introducing IPQoS (Overview)</title><highlights><para>IP Quality of Service (IPQoS) enables you to prioritize, control, and
gather accounting statistics. Using IPQoS, you can provide consistent levels
of service to users of your network. You can also manage traffic to avoid
network congestion.</para><para>The following is a list of topics in this chapter:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipqos-intro-52" remap="internal">IPQoS Basics</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipqos-intro-6" remap="internal">Providing Quality of Service
With IPQoS</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipqos-intro-90" remap="internal">Improving Network Efficiency
With IPQoS</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipqos-intro-11" remap="internal">Differentiated Services
Model</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipqos-intro-54" remap="internal">Traffic Forwarding on an
IPQoS-Enabled Network</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="ipqos-intro-52"><title>IPQoS Basics</title><para>IPQoS enables the Differentiated Services (Diffserv) architecture
that is defined by the Differentiated Services Working Group of the Internet
Engineering Task Force (IETF). In the Solaris OS, IPQoS is implemented at
the IP level of the TCP/IP protocol stack. </para><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-50"><title>What Are Differentiated Services?</title><para>By enabling IPQoS, you can provide different levels of network
service for selected customers and selected applications. The different levels
 of service  are collectively referred to as  <emphasis>differentiated services</emphasis>.
The differentiated services that you provide to customers can be based on
 a structure of service levels that your company offers to its customers.
You can also provide differentiated services based on the priorities that
are set for applications or users on your network.</para><para>Providing quality of service involves the following activities:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Delegating levels of service to different groups, such as
customers or departments in an enterprise</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Prioritizing network services that are given to particular
groups or applications</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Discovering and eliminating areas of network bottlenecks and
other forms of congestion</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Monitoring network performance and providing performance statistics</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Regulating bandwidth to and from network resources</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-12"><title>IPQoS Features</title><para>IPQoS has the following features:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><command>ipqosconf</command> Command-line tool for configuring
the QoS policy</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Classifier that selects actions, which are based on filters
that configure the QoS policy of your organization</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Metering module that measures network traffic, in compliance
with the Diffserv model</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Service differentiation that is based on the ability to mark
a packet's IP header with forwarding information</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Flow-accounting module that gathers statistics for traffic
flows </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Statistics gathering for traffic classes, through the UNIX&reg; <command>kstat</command> command</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Support for SPARC&reg; and x86 architecture</para><note><para>The x86 architecture does not support IPQoS on VLANs.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>Support for IPv4 and IPv6 addressing</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Interoperability with IP Security Architecture (IPsec)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Support for 802.1D user-priority markings for virtual local
area networks (VLANs)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-4"><title>Where to Get More Information About Quality-of-Service
Theory and Practice</title><para>You can find information on differentiated services and quality of service
from print and online sources.</para><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-5"><title>Books About Quality of Service</title><para>For more information on quality-of-service theory and practice, refer
to the following books:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Ferguson, Paul and Geoff Huston. <emphasis>Quality of Service</emphasis>.
John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 1998.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Kilkki, Kalevi. <emphasis>Differentiated Services for the
Internet</emphasis>. Macmillan Technical Publishing, 1999.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-60"><title>Requests for Comments (RFCs) About Quality
of Service</title><para>IPQoS conforms to the specifications that are described in the
following RFCs and the following Internet drafts:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2474.txt?number=2474" type="text_url">RFC 2474, Definition of the Differentiated Services Field
(DS Field) in the IPv4 and IPv6 Headers</ulink> &ndash; Describes an enhancement
to the type of service (ToS) field or DS fields of the IPv4 and IPv6 packet
headers to support differentiated services</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2475.txt?number=2475" type="text_url">RFC 2475, An Architecture for Differentiated Services</ulink> &ndash;
Provides a detailed description of the organization and modules of the Diffserv
architecture</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2597.txt?number=2597" type="text_url">RFC 2597, Assured Forwarding PHB Group</ulink> &ndash; Describes
how the assured forwarding (AF) per-hop behavior works.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2598.txt?number=2598" type="text_url">RFC 2598, An Expedited Forwarding PHB</ulink> &ndash; Describes
how the expedited forwarding (EF) per-hop behavior works</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Internet-Draft, <emphasis>An Informal Management Model for
Diffserv Routers</emphasis> &ndash; Presents a model for implementing the
Diffserv architecture on routers.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-7"><title>Web Sites With Quality-of-Service Information</title><para>The Differentiated Services Working Group of the IETF maintains a web
site with links to Diffserv Internet drafts at <filename>http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/diffserv-charter.html.</filename></para><para>Router manufacturers such as Cisco Systems and Juniper Networks provide
information on their corporate web sites that describes how Differentiated
Services are implemented in their products.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-8"><title>IPQoS Man Pages</title><para>IPQoS documentation includes the following man pages:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="ipqosconf-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipqosconf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> -
Describes the command for setting up the IPQoS configuration file</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="ipqos-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipqos</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash;
Describes the IPQoS implementation of the Diffserv architectural model</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="ipgpc-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipgpc</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash;
Describes the IPQoS implementation of a Diffserv classifier</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="tokenmt-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>tokenmt</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash;
Describes the IPQoS <command>tokenmt</command> meter </para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="tswtclmt-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>tswtclmt</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash; Describes the IPQoS <command>tswtclmt</command> meter</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="dscpmk-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dscpmk</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash;
Describes the DSCP marker module</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="dlcosmk-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>dlcosmk</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash;
Describes the IPQoS 802.1D user-priority marker module</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="flowacct-7ipp" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>flowacct</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7ipp</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink>&ndash; Describes the IPQoS flow-accounting module</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="acctadm-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>acctadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> &ndash;
Describes the command that configures the Solaris extended accounting facilities.
The <command>acctadm</command> command  includes IPQoS extensions.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipqos-intro-6"><title>Providing Quality of Service With IPQoS</title><para>IPQoS features enable Internet service providers (ISPs) and application
service providers (ASPs) to offer different levels of network service to customers.
These features enable individual companies and educational institutions to
prioritize services for internal organizations or for major applications.</para><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-15"><title>Implementing Service-Level Agreements</title><para>If your organization is an ISP or ASP, you can base your IPQoS configuration
on the <emphasis>service-level agreement</emphasis> (SLA) that your company
offers to its customers. In an SLA, a service provider guarantees to a customer
a certain level of network service that is based on a price structure. For
example, a premium-priced SLA might ensure that the customer receives highest
priority for all types of network traffic 24 hours per day. Conversely, a
medium-priced SLA might guarantee that the customer receives high priority
for email only during business hours. All other traffic would receive medium
priority  24 hours a day. </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-77"><title>Assuring Quality of Service for an Individual
Organization</title><para>If your organization is an enterprise or an institution, you can also
provide quality-of-service features for your network. You can guarantee that
traffic from a particular group or from a certain application is assured a
higher or lower degree of service. </para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-9"><title>Introducing the Quality-of-Service Policy</title><para>You implement quality of service by defining a <emphasis>quality-of-service
(QoS) policy</emphasis>. The QoS policy defines various network attributes,
such as customers' or applications' priorities, and actions for handling different
categories of traffic. You implement your organization's QoS policy in an
IPQoS configuration file. This file configures the IPQoS modules that reside
in the Solaris OS kernel. A host with an applied IPQoS policy is considered
an <emphasis>IPQoS-enabled system</emphasis>.</para><para>Your QoS policy typically defines the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Discrete groups of network traffic that are called <emphasis>classes
of service</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Metrics for regulating the amount of network traffic for each
class. These metrics govern the traffic-measuring process that is called <emphasis>metering</emphasis>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An action that an IPQoS system and a Diffserv router must
apply to a packet flow. This type of action is called a <emphasis>per-hop
behavior</emphasis> (PHB).</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Any statistics gathering that your organization requires for
a class of service. An example is traffic that is generated by a customer
or particular application.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>When packets pass to your network, the IPQoS-enabled system evaluates
the packet headers. The action that the IPQoS system takes is determined by
your QoS policy.</para><para>Tasks for designing the QoS policy are described in <olink targetptr="ipqos-config-planning-7" remap="internal">Planning the Quality-of-Service Policy</olink>. </para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipqos-intro-90"><title>Improving Network Efficiency With IPQoS</title><para>IPQoS contains features that can help you make network performance
more efficient as you implement quality of service. When computer networks
expand, the need also increases for managing network traffic that is generated
by increasing numbers of users and more powerful processors. Some symptoms
of an overused network include lost data and traffic congestion. Both symptoms
result in slow response times. </para><para>In the past, system administrators handled network traffic problems
by adding more bandwidth. Often, the level of traffic on the links varied
widely. With IPQoS, you can manage traffic on the existing network and help
assess where, and whether, expansion is necessary. </para><para>For example, for an enterprise or institution, you must maintain an
efficient network to avoid traffic bottlenecks. You must also ensure that
a group or application does not consume more than its allotted bandwidth.
For an ISP or ASP, you must manage network performance to ensure that customers
receive their paid-for level of network service.</para><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-25"><title>How Bandwidth Affects Network Traffic</title><para>You can use IPQoS to regulate network <emphasis>bandwidth</emphasis>,
the maximum amount of data that a fully used network link or device can transfer.
Your QoS policy should prioritize the use of bandwidth to provide quality
of service to customers or users. The IPQoS metering modules enable you to
measure and control bandwidth allocation among the various traffic classes
on an IPQoS-enabled host.</para><para>Before you can effectively manage traffic on your network, you must
answer these questions about bandwidth usage:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>What are the traffic problem areas for your local network?</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>What must you do to achieve optimum use of available bandwidth?</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>What are your site's critical applications, which must be
given highest priority?</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Which applications are sensitive to congestion?</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>What are your less critical applications, which can be given
a lower priority?</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-70"><title>Using Classes of Service to Prioritize Traffic</title><para>To implement quality of service, you analyze
network traffic to determine any broad groupings into which the traffic can
be divided. Then, you organize the various groupings into classes of service
with individual characteristics and individual priorities. These classes form
the basic categories on which you base the QoS policy for your organization.
The classes of service represent the traffic groups that you want to control.</para><para>For example, a provider might offer platinum, gold, silver, and
bronze levels of service, available at a sliding price structure. A platinum
SLA might guarantee top priority to incoming traffic that is destined for
a web site that the ISP hosts for the customer. Thus, incoming traffic to
the customer's web site could be one traffic class.</para><para>For an enterprise, you could create classes of service that are based
on department requirements. Or, you could create classes that are  based on
the preponderance of a particular application in the network traffic. Here
are a few examples of traffic classes for an enterprise:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Popular applications such as email and outgoing FTP to a particular
server, either of which could constitute a class. Because employees constantly
use these applications, your QoS policy might guarantee email and outgoing
FTP a small amount of bandwidth and a lower priority.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An order-entry database that needs to run 24 hours a day.
Depending on the importance of the database application to the enterprise,
you might give the database a large amount of bandwidth and a high priority.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A department that performs critical work or sensitive work,
such as the payroll department. The importance of the department to the organization
would determine the priority and amount of bandwidth you would give to such
a department.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Incoming calls to a company's external web site. You might give
this class a moderate amount of bandwidth that runs at low priority.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipqos-intro-11"><title>Differentiated Services Model</title><para>IPQoS includes the following modules, which are part of the <emphasis>Differentiated Services (Diffserv)</emphasis> architecture that is defined
in RFC 2475:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Classifier</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Meter</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Marker</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>IPQoS adds the following enhancements to the Diffserv model:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Flow-accounting module</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>802.1D datagram marker</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>This section introduces the Diffserv modules as they are used by IPQoS.
You need to know about these modules, their names, and their uses to set up
the QoS policy. For detailed information about each module, refer to <olink targetptr="ipqos-reference-2" remap="internal">IPQoS Architecture and the Diffserv Model</olink>. </para><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-17"><title>Classifier <literal>(ipgpc)</literal> Overview</title><para>In the Diffserv model, the <emphasis>classifier</emphasis> selects packets from a network traffic flow. A <emphasis>traffic
flow</emphasis> consists of a group of packets with identical information
in the following IP header fields:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Source address</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Destination address</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Source port</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Destination port</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Protocol number</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>In IPQoS, these fields are referred to as the <emphasis>5-tuple</emphasis>.</para><para>The IPQoS classifier module is named <command>ipgpc</command>. The <command>ipgpc</command> classifier arranges traffic flows into classes that are based
on characteristics you configure in the IPQoS configuration file.</para><para>For detailed information about <command>ipgpc</command>, refer to <olink targetptr="ipqos-reference-3" remap="internal">Classifier Module</olink>.</para><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-26"><title>IPQoS Classes</title><para>A <emphasis>class</emphasis> is a group of network flows that
share similar characteristics. For example, an ISP might define classes to
represent the different service levels that are offered to customers. An ASP
might define SLAs that give different levels of service to various applications.
For an ASP's QoS policy, a class might include outgoing FTP traffic that is
bound for a particular destination IP address. Outgoing traffic from a company's
external web site might also be defined as a class. </para><para>Grouping traffic into classes is a major part of planning your QoS policy.
When you create classes by using the <command>ipqosconf</command> utility,
you are actually configuring the <command>ipgpc</command> classifier.</para><para>For information on how to define classes, see <olink targetptr="ipqos-config-planning-14" remap="internal">How to Define the Classes for Your QoS
Policy</olink>.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-27"><title>IPQoS Filters</title><para><emphasis>Filters</emphasis> are sets of rules that contain parameters
called <emphasis>selectors</emphasis>. Each filter must point to a class.
IPQoS matches packets against the selectors of each filter to determine if
the packet belongs to the filter's class. You can filter on a packet by using
a variety of selectors, for example, the IPQoS 5-tuple and other common parameters:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Source address and destination addresses</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Source port and destination port </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Protocol numbers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>User IDs</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Project IDs</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Differentiated Services Codepoint (DSCP)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Interface index</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For example, a simple filter might include the destination port with
the value of 80. The <command>ipgpc</command> classifier then selects all
packets that are bound for destination port 80 (HTTP) and handles the packets
as directed in the QoS policy.</para><para>For information on creating filters, see <olink targetptr="ipqos-config-planning-42" remap="internal">How to Define Filters in the QoS Policy</olink>.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-19"><title>Meter <literal>(tokenmt</literal> and <literal>tswtclmt)</literal> Overview</title><para>In the Diffserv model, the <emphasis>meter</emphasis> tracks the
transmission rate of traffic flows on a per-class basis. The meter evaluates
 how much the actual rate of the flow conforms to the configured rates to
determine the appropriate outcome. Based on the traffic flow's outcome, the
meter selects a subsequent action. Subsequent actions might include sending
the packet to another action or returning the packet to the network without
further processing.</para><para>The IPQoS meters determine whether a network flow conforms to
the transmission rate that is defined for its class in the QoS policy. IPQoS
includes two metering modules:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><command>tokenmt</command> &ndash;
Uses a two-token bucket metering scheme</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>tswtclmt</command> &ndash; Uses a time-sliding window metering scheme</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Both metering modules recognize three outcomes: red, yellow, and
green. You define the actions to be taken for each outcome in the parameters <literal>red_action_name</literal>, <literal>yellow_action_name</literal>, and <literal>green_action_name</literal>.</para><para>In addition, you can configure <command>tokenmt</command> to be
color aware. A color-aware metering instance uses the packet's size, DSCP,
traffic rate, and configured parameters to determine the outcome.  The meter
uses the DSCP to map the packet's outcome to a green, yellow, or red.</para><para>For information on defining parameters for the IPQoS meters, refer to <olink targetptr="ipqos-config-planning-16" remap="internal">How to Plan Flow Control</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-20"><title>Marker (<literal>dscpmk</literal> and <literal>dlcosmk</literal>) Overview</title><para>In the Diffserv model, the <emphasis>marker</emphasis> marks a
packet with a value that reflects a forwarding behavior. <emphasis>Marking</emphasis> is
the process of placing a value in the packet's header to indicate how to forward
the packet to the network. IPQoS contains two marker modules:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><command>dscpmk</command> &ndash;
Marks the DS field in an IP packet header with a numeric value that is called
the <emphasis>Differentiated Services codepoint</emphasis>, or <emphasis>DSCP</emphasis>.
A Diffserv-aware router can then use the DS codepoint to apply the appropriate
forwarding behavior to the packet.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>dlcosmk</command> &ndash; Marks the virtual local area
network (VLAN) tag of an Ethernet frame header with a numeric value that is
called the <emphasis>user priority</emphasis>. The user priority indicates
the <emphasis>class of service (CoS)</emphasis>, which defines the appropriate
forwarding behavior to be applied to the datagram.</para><para><command>dlcosmk</command> is
an IPQoS addition that is not part of the Diffserv model, as designed by the
IETF.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information on implementing a marker strategy for the QoS policy,
see <olink targetptr="ipqos-config-planning-45" remap="internal">How to Plan Forwarding Behavior</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-505"><title>Flow Accounting (<literal>flowacct</literal>)
Overview</title><para>IPQoS adds the <command>flowacct</command> accounting module to
the Diffserv model. You can use <command>flowacct</command> to gather statistics
on traffic flows, and bill customers in agreement with their SLAs. Flow accounting
is also useful for capacity planning and system monitoring.</para><para>The <command>flowacct</command> module works with the <command>acctadm</command> command to create an accounting log file. A basic log includes
the IPQoS 5-tuple and two additional attributes, as shown in the following
list:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Source address</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Source port</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Destination address</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Destination port</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Protocol number</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Number of packets</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Number of bytes</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>You can also gather statistics on other attributes, as described in <olink targetptr="ipqos-accounting-2" remap="internal">Recording Information About Traffic Flows</olink>,
and in the <command>flowacct</command>(7ipp) and <command>acctadm</command>(1M)
man pages.</para><para>For information on planning a flow-accounting strategy, see <olink targetptr="ipqos-config-planning-18" remap="internal">How to Plan for Flow Accounting</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-120"><title>How Traffic Flows Through the IPQoS Modules</title><para>The next figure shows a path that incoming traffic might take
through some of the IPQoS modules.</para><figure id="ipqos-intro-fig-2"><title>Traffic Flow Through the IPQoS Implementation
of the Diffserv Model</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="diffserv-module"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The context follows the graphic, which is a flow diagram.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>This figure illustrates a common traffic flow sequence on an IPQoS-enabled
machine:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>The classifier selects from the packet stream all packets
that match the filtering criteria in the system's QoS policy.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The selected packets are then evaluated for the next action
to be taken.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The classifier sends to the marker any traffic that does not
require flow control.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Traffic to be flow-controlled is sent to the meter.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The meter enforces the configured rate. Then, the meter assigns
a traffic conformance value to the flow-controlled packets.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The flow-controlled packets are then evaluated to determine
if any packets require accounting.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The meter sends  to the marker any traffic that does not require
flow accounting.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The flow-accounting module gathers statistics on received
packets. The module then sends the packets to the marker.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The marker assigns a DS codepoint to the packet header. This
DSCP indicates the per-hop behavior that a Diffserv-aware system must apply
to the packet.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipqos-intro-54"><title>Traffic Forwarding on an IPQoS-Enabled Network</title><para>This section introduces the elements that are involved in forwarding
packets on an IPQoS-enabled network. An IPQoS-enabled system handles any packets
on the network stream with the system's IP address as the destination. The
IPQoS system then applies its QoS policy to the packet to establish differentiated
services.</para><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-99"><title>DS Codepoint</title><para>The DS codepoint (DSCP) defines in the packet header the action
that any Diffserv-aware system should take on a marked packet. The diffserv
architecture defines a set of DS codepoints for the IPQoS-enabled system and
diffserv router to use. The Diffserv architecture also defines a set of  actions
that are called <emphasis>forwarding behaviors</emphasis>, which correspond
to the DSCPs. The IPQoS-enabled system marks the precedence bits of the DS
field in the packet header with the DSCP. When a router receives a packet
with a DSCP value, the router applies the forwarding behavior that is associated
with that DSCP. The packet is then released onto the network. </para><note><para>The <command>dlcosmk</command> marker does not use the DSCP. Rather, <command>dlcosmk</command> marks Ethernet frame headers with a CoS value. If you plan
to configure IPQoS on a network that uses VLAN devices, refer to <olink targetptr="ipqos-reference-11" remap="internal">Marker Module</olink>.</para>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipqos-intro-10"><title>Per-Hop Behaviors</title><para>In Diffserv terminology, the forwarding behavior that is assigned
to a DSCP is called the <emphasis>per-hop behavior (PHB)</emphasis>. The PHB
defines the forwarding precedence that a marked packet receives in relation
to other traffic on the Diffserv-aware system. This precedence ultimately
determines whether the IPQoS-enabled system or Diffserv router forwards or
drops the marked packet. For a forwarded packet, each Diffserv router that
the packet encounters en route to its destination applies the same PHB. The
exception is if another Diffserv system changes the DSCP. For more information
on PHBs, refer to <olink targetptr="ipqos-reference-330" remap="internal">Using the dscpmk
Marker for Forwarding Packets</olink>.</para><para>The goal of a PHB is to provide a specified amount of network resources
to a class of traffic on the contiguous network. You can achieve this goal
in the QoS policy. Define DSCPs that indicate the precedence levels for traffic
classes when the traffic flows leave the IPQoS-enabled system. Precedences
can  range from high-precedence/low-drop probability to low-precedence/high-drop
probability. </para><para>For example, your QoS policy can assign to one class of traffic a DSCP
that guarantees a low-drop PHB. This traffic class then receives a low-drop
precedence PHB from any Diffserv-aware router, which guarantees bandwidth
to packets of this class. You can add to the QoS policy other DSCPs that assign
varying levels of precedence to other traffic classes. The lower-precedence
packets are given bandwidth by Diffserv systems in agreement with the priorities
that are indicated in the packets' DSCPs.</para><para>IPQoS supports two types of forwarding behaviors, which are defined
in the Diffserv architecture, expedited forwarding and assured forwarding. </para><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-100"><title>Expedited Forwarding</title><para>The <emphasis>expedited forwarding (EF)</emphasis> per-hop behavior
assures that any traffic class with EFs related DSCP is given highest priority.
 Traffic with an EF DSCP is not queued. EF provides low loss, latency, and
jitter. The recommended DSCP for EF is 101110. A packet that is marked with
101110 receives guaranteed low-drop precedence as the packet traverses Diffserv-aware
networks en route to its destination. Use the EF DSCP when assigning priority
to customers or applications with a premium SLA.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-110"><title>Assured Forwarding</title><para>The <emphasis>assured forwarding (AF)</emphasis> per-hop behavior
provides four different forwarding classes that you can assign to a packet.
Every forwarding class provides three drop precedences, as shown in <olink targetptr="ipqos-reference-tbl-16" remap="internal">Table 37&ndash;2</olink>. </para><para>The various AF codepoints provide the ability to assign different levels
of service to customers and applications. In the QoS policy,  you can prioritize
traffic and services  on your network when you plan the QoS policy. You can
then assign different AF levels to the prioritized traffic.</para>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipqos-intro-86"><title>Packet Forwarding in a Diffserv Environment</title><para>The following figure shows part of an intranet at a company with
a partially Diffserv-enabled environment. In this scenario, all hosts on networks <literal>10.10.0.0</literal> and <literal>10.14.0.0</literal> are IPQoS enabled, and
the local routers on both networks are Diffserv aware. However, the interim
networks are not configured for Diffserv.</para><figure id="ipqos-intro-fig-13"><title>Packet Forwarding Across Diffserv-Aware
Network Hops</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="diffserv-aware-intra.epsi"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The context follows the graphic, which is a flow diagram</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>The next steps trace the flow of the packet that is shown in this
figure. The steps begin with the progress of a packet that originates at host <literal>ipqos1</literal>. The steps then  continue through several hops to host <literal>ipqos2</literal>.</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>The user on <literal>ipqos1</literal> runs the <literal>ftp</literal> command
to access host <literal>ipqos2</literal>, which is three hops away.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>ipqos1</literal> applies its QoS policy to the resulting
packet flow. <literal>ipqos1</literal> then successfully classifies the <literal>ftp</literal> traffic.</para><para>The system administrator has created a
class for all outgoing <command>ftp</command> traffic that originates on the
local network 10.10.0.0. Traffic for the <literal>ftp</literal> class is assigned
the AF22 per-hop behavior: class two, medium-drop precedence. A traffic flow
rate of 2Mb/sec is configured for the <command>ftp</command> class.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>ipqos-1</literal> meters the <command>ftp</command> flow
to determine if the flow exceeds the committed rate of 2 Mbit/sec.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The marker on <literal>ipqos1</literal> marks the DS fields
in the outgoing <literal>ftp</literal> packets with the 010100 DSCP, corresponding
to the AF22 PHB.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The router <literal>diffrouter1</literal> receives the <literal>ftp</literal> packets. <literal>diffrouter1</literal> then checks the DSCP. If <literal>diffrouter1</literal> is congested,  packets that are marked with AF22 are
dropped.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>ftp</command> traffic is forwarded to the next hop
in agreement with the per-hop behavior that is configured for AF22 in <literal>diffrouter1</literal>'s files.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <command>ftp</command> traffic traverses network <literal>10.12.0.0</literal> to <literal>genrouter</literal>, which is not Diffserv aware. As
a result, the traffic receives &ldquo;best-effort&rdquo; forwarding behavior.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>genrouter</literal> passes the <command>ftp</command> traffic
to network <literal>10.13.0.0</literal>, where the traffic is received by <literal>diffrouter2</literal>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>diffrouter2</literal> is Diffserv aware. Therefore,
the router forwards the <command>ftp</command> packets to the network in agreement
with the PHB that is defined in the router policy for AF22 packets.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>ipqos2</literal> receives the <command>ftp</command> traffic. <literal>ipqos2</literal> then prompts the user on <literal>ipqos1</literal> for a
user name and password.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>