<chapter id="gegel"><title>Troubleshooting
Network Problems (Tasks)</title><highlights><para>This chapter contains solutions for common problems that might occur
on your network. The following topics are covered:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipconfig-138" remap="internal">General Network Troubleshooting
Tips</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-troubleshoot-2" remap="internal">Common Problems When
Deploying IPv6</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="ipconfig-138"><title>General Network Troubleshooting Tips</title><para>One of the first signs of trouble on a network is a loss of communications
by one or more hosts. If a host does not to come up at all the first time
that the host is added to the network, the problem might be in one of the
configuration files. The problem might also be a faulty network interface
card. If a single host suddenly develops a problem, the network interface
might be the cause. If the hosts on a network can communicate with each other
but not with other networks, the problem could lie with the router. Or, the
problem could be in another network. </para><para>You can use the <command>ifconfig</command> command to obtain
information on network interfaces. Use the <command>netstat</command> command
to display routing tables and protocol statistics. Third-party network diagnostic
programs provide a number of troubleshooting tools. Refer to third-party documentation
for information. </para><para>Less obvious are the causes of problems that degrade performance
on the network. For example, you can use tools such as <command>ping</command> to
quantify problems such as the loss of packets by a host. </para><sect2 id="ipconfig-139"><title>Running Basic Diagnostic Checks</title><para>If the network has problems, you can run a series of software
checks to diagnose and fix basic, software-related problems.</para>
</sect2><task id="ipv6-troubleshoot-10"><title>How to Perform Basic Network Software
Checking</title><procedure><step><para>On the local system, assume the Network Management role or become
superuser.</para><para>Roles contain authorizations and privileged commands.
For more information about roles, see <olink targetdoc="sysadv6" targetptr="rbactask-15" remap="external"><citetitle remap="section">Configuring RBAC (Task Map)</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</step><step id="ipv6-troubleshoot-step-12"><para>Use the <command>netstat</command> command to display network
information. </para><para>For syntax and information about the <command>netstat</command> command,
refer to <olink targetptr="ipconfig-142" remap="internal">Monitoring Network Status With the
netstat Command</olink> and the <olink targetdoc="refman1m" targetptr="netstat-1m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>netstat</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</step><step id="ipv6-troubleshoot-step-13"><para>Check the <filename>hosts</filename> database  to ensure that the entries are correct and current. </para><para>For information about the <filename>/etc/inet/hosts</filename> database,
refer to <olink targetptr="ipconfig-18" remap="internal">hosts Database</olink> and the <olink targetdoc="refman4" targetptr="hosts-4" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>hosts</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page. </para>
</step><step id="ipv6-troubleshoot-step-14"><para>If you are running the Reverse Address Resolution Protocol (RARP),
check the Ethernet addresses in the <filename>ethers</filename> database to
ensure that the entries are correct and current. </para>
</step><step id="ipv6-troubleshoot-step-15"><para>Try to connect to the local host
by using the <command>telnet</command> command.</para><para>For syntax and
information about <command>telnet</command>, refer to the <olink targetdoc="refman1" targetptr="telnet-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>telnet</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</step><step id="ipv6-troubleshoot-step-16"><para>Ensure that the network daemon <command>inetd</command> is running. </para><para># <userinput>ps -ef | grep inetd</userinput></para><para>The following
output verifies that the <command>inetd</command> daemon is running:</para><screen>root 57 1 0 Apr 04 ? 3:19 /usr/sbin/inetd -s</screen>
</step><step id="ipv6-troubleshoot-step-17"><para>If IPv6 is enabled on your network, verify that the IPv6 daemon <command>in.ndpd</command> is running:</para><screen># <userinput>ps -ef | grep in.ndpd</userinput></screen><para>The following output verifies that the <command>in.ndpd</command> daemon
is running:</para><screen>root 123  1 0  Oct 27 ?  0:03 /usr/lib/inet/in.ndpd</screen>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipv6-troubleshoot-2"><title>Common Problems When Deploying IPv6</title><para>This section describes issues and problems that you might encounter
while planning and deploying IPv6 at your site. For actual planning tasks,
refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;4, Planning an IPv6
Network (Tasks)</olink>.</para><sect2 id="ipv6-troubleshoot-3"><title>IPv4 Router Cannot Be Upgraded to IPv6</title><para>If your existing equipment cannot be upgraded, you might have to purchase
IPv6-ready equipment. Check the manufacturers' documentation for any equipment-specific
procedures you might have to perform to support IPv6.</para><para>Certain IPv4 routers cannot be upgraded for IPv6 support. If this situation
applies to your topology, physically wire an IPv6 router next to the IPv4
router. Then, you can tunnel from the IPv6 router over the IPv4 router. For
tasks for configuring tunnels, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-config-tasks-17" remap="internal">Tasks
for Configuring Tunnels for IPv6 Support (Task Map)</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-troubleshoot-6"><title>Problems After Upgrading Services to
IPv6</title><para>You might encounter the following situations when preparing services
for IPv6 support:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Certain applications, even after they are ported to IPv6,
do not turn on IPv6 support by default. You might have to configure these
applications to turn on IPv6.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A server that runs multiple services, some of which are IPv4
only, and others that are both IPv4 and IPv6, can experience problems. Some
clients might need to use both types of services, which leads to confusion
on the server side.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-troubleshoot-7"><title>Current ISP Does Not Support IPv6</title><para>If you want to deploy IPv6 but your current ISP does not offer IPv6
addressing, consider the following alternatives to changing ISPs:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Hire an ISP to provide a second line for IPv6 communications
from your site. This solution is expensive.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Get a <emphasis>virtual ISP</emphasis>. A virtual ISP provides
your site with IPv6 connectivity but no link. Instead, you create a tunnel
from your site, over your IPv4 ISP, to the virtual ISP.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Use a 6to4 tunnel over your ISP to other IPv6 sites. For an
address, use the registered IPv4 address of the 6to4 router as the public
topology part of the IPv6 address.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-ref-58"><title>Security Issues When Tunneling to a 6to4 Relay
Router</title><para>By nature, a tunnel between a 6to4 router and a 6to4 relay router
is insecure. Security problems, such as the following, are inherent in such
a tunnel:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Though 6to4 relay routers do encapsulate and decapsulate packets,
these routers do not check the data that is contained within the packets.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Address spoofing is a major issue on tunnels to a 6to4 relay
router. For incoming traffic, the 6to4 router is unable to match the IPv4
address of the relay router with the IPv6 address of the source. Therefore,
the address of the IPv6 host can easily be spoofed. The address of the 6to4
relay router can also be spoofed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>By default, no trust mechanism exists between 6to4 routers
and 6to4 relay routers. Thus, a 6to4 router cannot identify whether the 6to4
relay router is to be trusted, or even if it is a legitimate 6to4 relay router.
A trust relationship between the 6to4 site and the IPv6 destination must exist,
or both sites leave themselves open to possible attacks.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>These problems and other security issues that are inherent with 6to4
relay routers are explained in the Internet Draft, <citetitle>Security Considerations
for 6to4</citetitle>. Generally, you should consider enabling support for
6to4 relay routers for the following reasons only:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Your 6to4 site intends to communicate with a private, trusted
IPv6 network. For example, you might enable 6to4 relay router support on a
campus network that consists of isolated 6to4 sites and native IPv6 sites.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Your 6to4 site has a compelling business reason to communicate
with certain native IPv6 hosts.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You have implemented the checks and trust models that are
suggested in the Internet Draft, <citetitle>Security Considerations for 6to4</citetitle>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-ref-59"><title>Known Issues With a 6to4 Router</title><para>The following known bugs affect 6to4 configuration:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>4709338 &ndash; Need a RIPng implementation which recognizes
static routes</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>4152864 &ndash; Configuring two tunnels with the same tsrc/tdst
pair works</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect3 id="ipv6-ref-60"><title>Implementing Static Routes at the 6to4 Site
(Bug ID 4709338)</title><para>The following issue occurs on 6to4 sites with routers that are internal
to the 6to4 boundary router. When you configure the 6to4 pseudo-interface,
the static route <literal>2002::/16</literal> is automatically added to the
routing table on the 6to4 router. Bug 4709338 describes a limitation in the
Solaris RIPng routing protocol that prevents this static route from being
advertised to the 6to4 site. </para><para>Either of the following workarounds are available for Bug 4709338.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Add the <literal>2002::/16</literal>static route to the routing
tables of all intrasite routers within the 6to4 site.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Use a routing protocol other than RIPng on the 6to4 site's
internal router.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipv6-ref-61"><title>Configuring Tunnels with the Same Source Address
(Bug ID 4152864)</title><para>Bug ID 4152864 describes problems that occur when two tunnels are configured
with the same tunnel source address, which is a serious issue for 6to4 tunnels. </para><caution><para>Do not configure a 6to4 tunnel and an automatic tunnel (<command>atun</command>) with the same tunnel source address. For information about automatics
and the <command>atun</command> command, refer to the <olink targetdoc="refman7" targetptr="lc-tun-7m" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>tun</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7M</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man page.</para>
</caution>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>