<chapter id="ipv6-planning-1"><title>Planning an IPv6 Network (Tasks)</title><highlights><para>Deploying IPv6 on a new network or an existing network requires a major
planning effort. This chapter contains the planning tasks that are necessary
before you can configure IPv6 at your site. For existing networks, IPv6 deployment
should be phased in gradually. The topics in this chapter help you phase in
IPv6 onto an otherwise IPv4-only network. </para><para>The following topics are discussed in this chapter:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-2" remap="internal">IPv6 Planning (Task Maps)</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-5" remap="internal">IPv6 Network Topology Scenario</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-7" remap="internal">Preparing the Existing
Network to Support IPv6</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-9" remap="internal">Preparing an IPv6 Addressing
Plan</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For an introduction to IPv6 concepts, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-overview-7" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Planning an IPv6 Addressing Scheme (Overview)</olink>.
For detailed information, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-ref-76" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;11, IPv6 in Depth (Reference)</olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="ipv6-planning-2"><title>IPv6 Planning (Task Maps)</title><para>Complete the tasks in the next task map in sequential order to accomplish
the planning tasks necessary for IPv6 deployment.</para><informaltable frame="all" pgwide="100"><tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="25.95*"/><colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="36.51*"/><colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="36.55*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Task</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Description</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>For Instructions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>1. Prepare your hardware to support IPv6.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Ensure that your hardware can be upgraded to IPv6.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-16" remap="internal">Preparing the Network Topology for
IPv6 Support</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>2. Get an ISP that supports IPv6.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Ensure that your current ISP supports IPv6. Otherwise, find an ISP who
can support IPv6. You can use two ISPs, one ISP for IPv6 and one for ISP IPv4
communications.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>3. Ensure that your applications are IPv6 ready.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Verify that your applications can run in an IPv6 environment.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-18" remap="internal">How to Prepare Network Services
for IPv6 Support</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>4. Get a site prefix.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Obtain a 48-bit site prefix for your site from your ISP or from the
nearest RIR.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-10" remap="internal">Obtaining a Site Prefix</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>5. Create a subnet addressing plan.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>You need to plan the overall IPv6 network topology and addressing scheme
before you can configure IPv6 on the various nodes in your network.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-22" remap="internal">Creating a Numbering Scheme for
Subnets</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>6. Design a plan for tunnel usage.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Determine which routers should run tunnels to other subnets or external
networks.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-31" remap="internal">Planning for Tunnels in the Network
Topology</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>7. Create an addressing plan for entities on the network.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Your plan for addressing servers, routers, and hosts should be in place
before IPv6 configuration.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-11" remap="internal">Creating an IPv6 Addressing Plan
for Nodes</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>8. Develop an IPv6 security policy.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Investigate IP Filter, IP security architecture (IPsec), Internet Key
Exchange (IKE), and other Solaris security features as you develop an IPv6
security policy.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipsectm-1" remap="internal">Part&nbsp;III, IP Security</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>9. (Optional) Set up a DMZ.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>For security purposes, you need an addressing plan for the DMZ and its
entities before you configure IPv6.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-41" remap="internal">Security Considerations for the
IPv6 Implementation</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>10. Enable the nodes to support IPv6.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Configure IPv6 on all routers and hosts.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-config-tasks-2" remap="internal">IPv6 Router Configuration (Task
Map)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>11. Turn on network services.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Make sure that existing servers can support IPv6.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-admintasks-2" remap="internal">Major TCP/IP Administrative Tasks
(Task Map)</olink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>12. Update name servers for IPv6 support.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para>Make sure that DNS, NIS, and LDAP servers are updated with the new IPv6
addresses.</para>
</entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="1"><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-config-tasks-10" remap="internal">Configuring Name Service Support
for IPv6</olink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipv6-planning-5"><title>IPv6 Network Topology Scenario</title><para>The tasks throughout this chapter explain how to plan for IPv6 services
on a typical enterprise network. The following figure shows the network that
is referred to throughout the chapter. Your proposed IPv6 network might include
some or all of the network links that are illustrated in this figure.</para><figure id="ipv6-planning-fig-33"><title>IPv6 Network Topology Scenario</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="ent-nw-IPv6-dep" width="100"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The figure shows an IPv6 network. The next text describes
the figure's contents.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>The enterprise network scenario consists of five subnets with existing
IPv4 addresses. The links of the network correspond directly to the administrative
subnets. The four internal networks are shown with RFC 1918-style private
IPv4 addresses, which is a common solution for the lack of IPv4 addresses.
The addressing scheme of these internal networks follows:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Subnet 1 is the internal network backbone <literal>192.168.1</literal>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Subnet 2 is the internal network <literal>192.168.2</literal>,
with LDAP, <command>sendmail</command>, and DNS servers.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Subnet 3 is the internal network <literal>192.168.3</literal>,
with the enterprise's NFS servers.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Subnet 4 is the internal network <literal>192.168.4</literal>,
which contains hosts for the enterprise's employees.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The external, public network <literal>172.16.85</literal> functions
as the corporation's DMZ. This network contains web servers, anonymous FTP
servers, and other resources that the enterprise offers to the outside world.
Router 2 runs a firewall and separates public network <literal>172.16.85</literal> from
the internal backbone. On the other end of the DMZ, Router 1 runs a firewall
and serves as the enterprise's boundary server. </para><para>In <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-fig-33" remap="internal">Figure 4&ndash;1</olink>,
the public DMZ has the RFC 1918 private address <literal>172.16.85</literal>.
In the real world, the public DMZ must have a registered IPv4 address. Most
IPv4 sites use a combination of public addresses and RFC 1918 private addresses.
However, when you introduce IPv6, the concept of public addresses and private
addresses changes. Because IPv6 has a much larger address space, you use public
IPv6 addresses on both private networks and public networks.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipv6-planning-7"><title>Preparing the Existing Network to Support
IPv6</title><note><para>The Solaris dual protocol stack supports concurrent IPv4 and IPv6
operations. You can successfully run IPv4&ndash;related operations during
and after deployment of IPv6 on your network.</para>
</note><para>IPv6 introduces additional features to an existing network. Therefore,
when you first deploy IPv6, you must ensure that you do not disrupt any operations
that are working with IPv4. The subjects covered in this section describe
how to introduce IPv6 to an existing network in a step-by-step fashion.</para><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-16"><title>Preparing the Network Topology for IPv6
Support</title><para>The first step in IPv6 deployment is to assess which existing entities
on your network can support IPv6.  In most cases, the network topology-wires,
routers, and hosts-can remain unchanged as you implement IPv6. However, you
might have to prepare existing hardware and applications for IPv6 before actually
configuring IPv6 addresses on network interfaces.</para><para>Verify which hardware on your network can be upgraded to IPv6. For example,
check the manufacturers' documentation for IPv6 readiness regarding the following
classes of hardware:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Routers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Firewalls</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Servers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Switches</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>All procedures in the this Part assume that your equipment, particularly
routers, can be upgraded to IPv6.</para>
</note><para>Some router models cannot be upgraded to IPv6. For more information
and a workaround, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-troubleshoot-3" remap="internal">IPv4 Router
Cannot Be Upgraded to IPv6</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-17"><title>Preparing Network Services for IPv6 Support</title><para>The following typical IPv4 network services in the current Solaris release
are IPv6 ready:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><command>sendmail</command></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>NFS</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>HTTP (Apache 2.x or Orion)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>DNS</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>LDAP</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>The IMAP mail service is for IPv4 only.</para><para>Nodes that are configured for IPv6 can run IPv4 services. When you turn
on IPv6, not all services accept IPv6 connections. Services that have been
ported to IPv6 will accept a connection. Services that have not been ported
to IPv6 continue to work with the IPv4 half of the protocol stack.</para><para>Some issues can arise after you upgrade services to IPv6. For details,
see <olink targetptr="ipv6-troubleshoot-6" remap="internal">Problems After Upgrading Services
to IPv6</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-43"><title>Preparing Servers for IPv6 Support</title><para>Because servers are considered IPv6 hosts, by default their IPv6 addresses
are automatically configured by the Neighbor Discovery protocol. However,
many servers have multiple network interface cards (NICs) that you might want
to swap out for maintenance or replacement. When you replace one NIC, Neighbor
Discovery automatically generates a new interface ID for that NIC. This behavior
might not be acceptable for a particular server.</para><para>Therefore, consider manually configuring the interface ID portion of
the IPv6 addresses for each interface of the server. For instructions, refer
to <olink targetptr="ipv6-config-tasks-70" remap="internal">How to Configure a User-Specified
IPv6 Token</olink>. Later, when you need to replace an existing NIC, the already
configured IPv6 address is applied to the replacement NIC.</para>
</sect2><task id="ipv6-planning-18"><title>How to Prepare Network Services for IPv6
Support</title><procedure><step><para>Update the following network services to support IPv6:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mail servers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>NIS servers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>NFS</para><note><para>LDAP supports IPv6 without requiring IPv6-specific configuration
tasks.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para>Verify that your firewall hardware is IPv6 ready.</para><para>Refer
to the appropriate firewall-related documentation for instructions.</para>
</step><step><para>Verify that other services on your network have been ported to
IPv6.</para><para>For more information,  refer to marketing collateral and
associated documentation for the software.</para>
</step><step id="ipv6-planning-step-30"><para>If your site deploys the following
services, make sure that you have taken the appropriate measures for these
services:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Firewalls</para><para>Consider strengthening the policies
that are in place for IPv4 to support IPv6. For more security considerations,
see <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-41" remap="internal">Security Considerations for the IPv6
Implementation</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Mail</para><para>In the MX records for DNS, consider adding
the IPv6 address of your mail server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>DNS</para><para>For DNS-specific considerations, see <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-35" remap="internal">How to Prepare DNS for IPv6 Support</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>IPQoS</para><para>Use the same Diffserv policies on a host that were used for IPv4.
For more information, see <olink targetptr="ipqos-reference-3" remap="internal">Classifier
Module</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para>Audit any network services that are offered by a node prior to
converting that node to IPv6.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="ipv6-planning-35"><title>How to Prepare DNS for IPv6 Support</title><tasksummary><para>The current Solaris release supports DNS resolution on both the client
side and the server side. Do the following to prepare DNS services for IPv6.</para><para>For more information that is related to DNS support for IPv6, refer
to <olink targetdoc="sysadv5" remap="external"><citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Naming and Directory Services (DNS, NIS, and LDAP)</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Ensure that the DNS server that performs recursive name resolution
is dual-stacked (IPv4 and IPv6) or for IPv4 only.</para>
</step><step id="ipv6-planning-step-37"><para>On the DNS server, populate the DNS
database with relevant IPv6 database AAAA records in the forward zone. </para><note><para>Servers that run multiple critical services require special attention.
Ensure that the network is working properly. Also ensure that all critical
services are ported to IPv6. Then, add the server's IPv6 address to the DNS
database.</para>
</note>
</step><step id="ipv6-planning-step-39"><para>Add the associated PTR records for
the AAAA records into the reverse zone.</para>
</step><step id="ipv6-planning-step-38"><para>Add either IPv4 only data, or both
IPv6 and IPv4 data into the NS record that describes zones.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-31"><title>Planning for Tunnels in the Network Topology</title><para>The IPv6 implementation supports a number of tunnel configurations to
serve as transition mechanisms as your network migrates to a mix of IPv4 and
IPv6. Tunnels enable isolated IPv6 networks to communicate. Because most of
the Internet runs IPv4, IPv6 packets from your site need to travel across
the Internet through tunnels to destination IPv6 networks.</para><para>Here are some major scenarios for using tunnels in the IPv6 network
topology:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The ISP from which you purchase IPv6 service allows you to
create a tunnel from your site's boundary router to the ISP network. <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-fig-33" remap="internal">Figure 4&ndash;1</olink> shows such a tunnel.
In such a case, you would run a manual, IPv6 over IPv4 tunnel.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You manage a large, distributed network with IPv4 connectivity.
To connect the distributed sites that use IPv6, you can run an automatic 6to4
tunnel from the edge router of each subnet.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Sometimes, a router in your infrastructure cannot be upgraded
to IPv6. In this case, you can create a manual tunnel over the IPv4 router,
with two IPv6 routers as endpoints. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For procedures for configuring tunnels, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-config-tasks-17" remap="internal">Tasks for Configuring Tunnels for IPv6 Support
(Task Map)</olink>. For conceptual information regarding tunnels, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-ref-47" remap="internal">IPv6 Tunnels</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-41"><title>Security Considerations for
the IPv6 Implementation</title><para>When you introduce IPv6 into an existing network, you must take care
not to compromise the security of the site. Be aware of the following security
issues as you phase in your IPv6 implementation:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The same amount of filtering is required for both IPv6 packets
and IPv4 packets.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>IPv6 packets are often tunneled through a firewall. Therefore,
you should implement either of the following scenarios:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Have the firewall do content inspection inside the tunnel.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Put an IPv6 firewall with similar rules at the opposite tunnel
endpoint.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Some transition mechanisms exist that use IPv6 over UDP over
IPv4 tunnels. These mechanisms might prove dangerous by short-circuiting the
firewall.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>IPv6 nodes are globally reachable from outside the enterprise
network. If your security policy prohibits public access, you must establish
stricter rules for the firewall. For example, consider configuring a stateful
firewall.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>This book includes security features that can be used within an IPv6
implementation.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The  IP security architecture (IPsec) feature enables you
to provide cryptographic protection for IPv6 packets. For more information,
refer to <olink targetptr="ipsec-ov-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;19, IP Security Architecture (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The Internet Key Exchange (IKE) feature enables you to use
public key authentication for IPv6 packets. For more information, refer to <olink targetptr="ike-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;22, Internet Key Exchange (Overview)</olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ipv6-planning-9"><title>Preparing an IPv6 Addressing Plan</title><para>A major part of the transition from IPv4 to IPv6 includes the development
of an addressing plan. This task involves the following preparations:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-10" remap="internal">Obtaining a Site Prefix</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-21" remap="internal">Creating the IPv6 Numbering
Scheme</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-10"><title>Obtaining a Site Prefix</title><para>Before you configure IPv6, you must obtain a site prefix. The site prefix
is used to derive IPv6 addresses for all the nodes in your IPv6 implementation.
For an introduction to site prefixes, refer to <olink targetptr="ipv6-overview-170" remap="internal">Prefixes in IPv6</olink>.</para><para>Any ISP that supports IPv6 can provide your organization with a 48-bit
IPv6 site prefix. If your current ISP only supports IPv4, you can use another
ISP for IPv6 support while retaining your current ISP for IPv4 support. In
such an instance, you can use one of several workarounds. For more information,
see <olink targetptr="ipv6-troubleshoot-7" remap="internal">Current ISP Does Not Support IPv6</olink>.</para><para>If your organization is an ISP, then you obtain site prefixes for your
customers from the appropriate Internet registry. For more information, see
the <ulink url="http://www.iana.org" type="text_url">Internet Assigned Numbers
Authority (IANA)</ulink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ipv6-planning-21"><title>Creating the IPv6 Numbering Scheme</title><para>Unless your proposed IPv6 network is entirely new, use your existing
IPv4 topology as the basis for the IPv6 numbering scheme. </para><sect3 id="ipv6-planning-22"><title>Creating a Numbering Scheme for Subnets</title><para>Begin your numbering scheme by mapping your existing IPv4 subnets into
equivalent IPv6 subnets. For example, consider the subnets illustrated in <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-fig-33" remap="internal">Figure 4&ndash;1</olink>. Subnets 1&ndash;4
use the RFC 1918 IPv4 private address designation for the first 16 bits of
their addresses, in addition to the digits 1&ndash;4 to indicate the subnet.
For illustrative purposes, assume that the IPv6 prefix <literal>2001:db8:3c4d/48</literal> has
been assigned to the site. The following table shows how the private IPv4
prefixes map into IPv6 prefixes.</para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>IPv4 Subnet Prefix</para>
</entry><entry><para>Equivalent IPv6 Subnet Prefix </para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><literal>192.168.1.0/24</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>2001:db8:fd3c4d:1::/64</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>192.168.2.0/24</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>2001:db8:3c4d:2::/64</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>192.168.3.0/24</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>2001:db8:3c4d:3::/64</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><literal>192.168.4.0/24</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>2001:db8:3c4d:4::/64</literal></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect3><sect3 id="ipv6-planning-11"><title>Creating an IPv6 Addressing Plan for Nodes</title><para>For most hosts, stateless autoconfiguration of IPv6 addresses for their
interfaces is an appropriate, time saving strategy. When the host receives
the site prefix from the nearest router, Neighbor Discovery automatically
generates IPv6 addresses for each interface on the host.</para><para>Servers need to have stable IPv6 addresses. If you do not manually configure
a server's IPv6 addresses, a new IPv6 address is autoconfigured whenever a
NIC card is replaced on the server. Keep the following tips in mind when you
create addresses for servers:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Give servers meaningful and stable interface IDs. One strategy
is to use a sequential numbering scheme for interface IDs. For example, the
internal interface of the LDAP server in <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-fig-33" remap="internal">Figure 4&ndash;1</olink> might become <literal>2001:db8:3c4d:2::2</literal>. </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Alternatively, if you do not regularly renumber your IPv4
network, consider using the existing IPv4 addresses of the routers and servers
as their interface IDs. In <olink targetptr="ipv6-planning-fig-33" remap="internal">Figure
4&ndash;1</olink>, suppose Router 1's interface to the DMZ has the IPv4 address <literal>123.456.789.111</literal>. You can convert the IPv4 address to hexadecimal
and use the result as the interface ID. The new interface ID would be <literal>::7bc8:156F.</literal></para><para>Only use this approach if you own the registered IPv4
address, rather than having obtained the address from an ISP. If you use an
IPv4 address that was given to you by an ISP, you create a dependency that
would create problems if you change ISPs.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Due to the limited number of IPv4 addresses, in the past a network designer
had to consider where to use global, registered addresses and private, RFC
1918 addresses. However, the notion of global and private IPv4 addresses does
not apply to IPv6 addresses. You can use global unicast addresses, which include
the site prefix, on all links of the network, including the public DMZ.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>