<preface id="preface-1"><title>Preface</title><highlights><para>Welcome to System Administration Guide: IP Services for the Solaris Express, Developer Edition 2/07. This
book  is
part of a nine-volume set that covers a significant part of the <trademark>Solaris</trademark> system administration information. This book assumes that you
have already installed the Solaris operating system (Solaris OS). You should
be ready to configure your network or ready to configure any networking software
that is required on your network. The Solaris OS  is part of the Solaris product family,
which also includes the Solaris Common Desktop Environment (CDE). Solaris
OS is compliant with AT&amp;T's System V, Release 4 operating system.</para>&platformnote;
</highlights><sect1 id="preface-9"><title id="preface-2">Who Should Use This Book</title><para>This book is intended for anyone responsible for administering systems
that run the Solaris OS release, which are configured in a network. To use
this book, you should have at least two years of <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> system administration experience. Attending UNIX system administration
training courses might be helpful.</para>
</sect1>&sagset;<sect1 id="preface-14"><title>Related Books</title><itemizedlist><para>The following trade books are referred to in this book.</para><listitem><para>Stevens, W. Richard. <citetitle>TCP/IP Illustrated, Volume
1, The Protocols</citetitle>. Addison Wesley, 1994.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Hunt Craig.<citetitle>TCP/IP Network Administration, 3rd Edition</citetitle>.
O'Reilly, 2002.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Perkins, Charles E. <citetitle>Mobile IP Design Principles
and Practices</citetitle>. Massachusetts, 1998, Addison-Wesley Publishing
Company.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Solomon, James D. <citetitle>Mobile IP: The Internet Unplugged</citetitle>.
New Jersey, 1998, Prentice-Hall, Inc. </para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ferguson, Paul and Geoff Huston. <citetitle>Quality of Service</citetitle>.
John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 1998.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Kilkki, Kalevi. <citetitle>Differentiated Services for the
Internet</citetitle>. Macmillan Technical Publishing, 1999.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="preface-22"><title>Related Third-Party Web Site References</title><para>Third party URLs are referenced in this document and provide additional,
related information.</para><note><para>Sun is not responsible for the availability of third-party Web
sites mentioned in this document. Sun does not endorse and is not responsible
or liable for any content, advertising, products, or other materials that
are available on or through such sites or resources. Sun will not be responsible
or liable for any actual or alleged damage or loss caused by or in connection
with the use of or reliance on any such content, goods, or services that are
available on or through such sites or resources.</para>
</note><para>Solaris IP Filter is derived from open source IP Filter software. To
view license terms, attribution, and copyright statements for IP Filter, the
default path is <filename>/usr/lib/ipf/IPFILTER.LICENCE</filename>. If Solaris
OS has been installed anywhere other than the default, modify the given path
to access the file at the installed location.</para>
</sect1>&sundocs;&typeconv;
</preface>