<!-- 
The contents of this Documentation are subject to the Public Documentation
License Version 1.01 (the "License"); you may only use this Documentation if
you comply with the terms of this License. A copy of the License is
available at http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/documentation/license.
-->

<chapter id="index"><title>Exploring OpenSolaris</title><highlights><para>The guide provides an introduction to the <trademark>OpenSolaris</trademark> operating system, as well as instructions for installing the current OpenSolaris
release on your system.</para><itemizedlist><para>If you are a new OpenSolaris user, review the following information:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="overview" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="explore" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>If you are already familiar with the OpenSolaris releases, you can go
to <olink targetptr="cdinstall" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="whatisosol"><title>What is OpenSolaris?</title><para>OpenSolaris has several meanings, depending on the context in which
it is used.</para><itemizedlist><para>For example, OpenSolaris is:</para><listitem><para>An operating system code base originally based on Sun's proprietary <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Operating System.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An open source development project.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A free binary distribution of the OpenSolaris software that
is available for redistribution under the terms of the Common Development
and Distribution License (CDDL).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>This guide is intended to help you install and set up the free binary
distribution of the OpenSolaris software and make your initial experience
with it a successful one.</para><para>For more information, see <olink targetptr="links1" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="whyuseosol"><title>Why Use OpenSolaris?</title><para>OpenSolaris includes, among other things, the GNOME desktop, GNU tools,
and a network-based software management system. OpenSolaris also includes
state-of-the art technology: the ZFS file system, Dynamic Tracing (DTrace)
framework, containers and zones for running applications in protected environments,
and advanced network virtualization capabilities.</para><para>Those who love technology, simply for technology's sake, will enjoy
the many features that OpenSolaris has to offer. However, from a practical
standpoint, these features are meant to simplify, improve, and streamline
your application development and system management.</para><itemizedlist><para>Some examples include:</para><listitem><para>Using Time Slider to easily browse and recover files from
ZFS backup snapshots, without the assistance of a system administrator. (ZFS
is the default file system type in the OpenSolaris release.)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Speeding up your application development and debugging your
system by using DTrace, a tracing infrastructure that provides visibility
into system performance. By using built-in measurement points in the operating
system, DTrace can display detailed performance characteristics about the
operating system or user programs that are running on the OpenSolaris release.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Organizing and isolating workloads by using containers and
zones.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Leveraging ZFS for unprecedented scalability, reliability,
and management simplicity.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Using sophisticated network virtualization capabilities to
maximize resource control, network performance and utilization, utility computing,
and server consolidation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Managing system services through the Service Management Facility
(SMF), a Windows-like service management capability that supports managing
service dependencies, service startup order, and service failures.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>All of these capabilities are available through a simple installation.
OpenSolaris can be easily upgraded through a networked package repository.
 You can also explore OpenSolaris on a Live CD, without actually installing
it on your system. Or, you can run OpenSolaris in a virtual machine, for example
VirtualBox.</para><para>For more information, see <olink targetptr="links1" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="overview"><title>Exploring the OpenSolaris Software</title><para>Each OpenSolaris release is a free binary distribution that can be redistributed.</para><itemizedlist><para>The OpenSolaris distribution enables you to do the following:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Explore an OpenSolaris environment
on a Live CD.</emphasis></para><para>Each OpenSolaris release provides a Live
CD for x86 platforms. This Live CD includes a basic, core OpenSolaris operating
system, and the GNOME desktop environment. You can explore the OpenSolaris
operating system from this Live CD without actually installing it on your
system.</para><note><para>A minimum of 512 Mbytes of memory is required to run the Live
CD and the GUI installer.</para>
</note><para>See <olink type="auto-generated" targetptr="explore" remap="internal">Explore the OpenSolaris
Live CD</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Install the OpenSolaris operating
system on your system.</emphasis> </para><para>You can install the current
OpenSolaris release on your system from the OpenSolaris Live CD. Or, you can
download a bootable image of the OpenSolaris operating system and run it in
a virtual machine on your system. An image is a collection of software in
a package that comprises an entire operating system in one file. An image
is bootable and usable for installations.</para><para>See <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/roadmap.html" type="text">Installation
Roadmap</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Add and update software on your system.</emphasis></para><para>After the OpenSolaris operating system is running on your system,
additional software packages, including developer tools, can be downloaded
to your system by using the Image Packaging System (IPS). IPS accesses software
packages from network repositories and installs them.</para><para>The Image Packaging System offers both the Package Manager GUI and command-line
utilities, such as the <command>pkg</command> command, to install and manage
the software packages on your installed system. The Package Manager is a graphical
user interface (GUI) for IPS that enables you to easily install, update, and
manage software packages.</para><para>For both the Live CD and an installed OpenSolaris system, Package Manager
can be started from the desktop's Main Menubar by selecting System &gt; Administration
&gt; Package Manager. On an installed OpenSolaris system, you can also start
the application by clicking the Package Manager icon that is located on the
desktop.</para><itemizedlist><para>Use Package Manager or the IPS command-line utilities to:</para><listitem><para>Add new packages to your system from network repositories.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Update the existing packages individually on your system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Update all of the packages on your system at once.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Select a build version with components for managing or creating
your own custom OpenSolaris image.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For information about using the Image Packaging System and Package Manager,
see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/new-user.html" type="text">Getting Additional Software</ulink>. See, also the <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/sc/src/pkg/gate/src/man/pkg.1.txt" type="text">pkg(1)</ulink> man page.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Upgrade your OpenSolaris operating
system.</emphasis></para><para>To upgrade an existing OpenSolaris release
to the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/upgrade.html" type="text">Upgrading
to the Next OpenSolaris Release</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Create and manage multiple boot environments
on your system.</emphasis></para><para>A boot environment is a bootable instance
of an OpenSolaris operating system image, plus any other application software
packages installed into that image. You can maintain multiple boot environments
on your system, and each boot environment could have different software versions
installed.</para><para>With multiple boot environments, the process of updating software becomes
a low risk operation, because you can create backup boot environments before
making any software updates to your system.  If necessary, you have the option
of booting a backup boot environment.</para><para>See <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/bootenv.html" type="text">Managing
Multiple Boot Environments on Your System</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Set up a customized application development
environment on your system.</emphasis></para><para>The OpenSolaris software
offers complete support for developing and deploying applications. Tools that
are required for application development are available for download and installation
through Package Manager. You can easily download and install tools, such as
Sun Studio compilers, debuggers, performance analyzers, <trademark>NetBeans</trademark>,  source code management, and the <command>make</command> utility.</para><para>You can also download and install Web Stack development tools, such
as Apache web server, Hypertext Preprocessor (PHP), Lighttpd web server, and
the Squid caching proxy.</para><para>See <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/appdev.html" type="text">Setting
Up Your Application Development Environment</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Install custom OpenSolaris images
on multiple client systems.</emphasis> </para><para>System administrators
can use the automated installer tool that is available with OpenSolaris releases
to provide simplified setup and configuration for multiple installations of
the OpenSolaris operating system.</para><para>The automated installer enables system administrators to create an installation
service that provides blueprints for specific x86 based, and starting with
OpenSolaris 2009.06 release, SPARC based installations. This installation
service includes a web server, which stores a list of manifest files with
installation specifications that have been made available by the administrator.</para><para>To locate an installation blueprint that matches the client's system
specifications, clients can contact the web server and review the available
services by using associated manifest files. When a matching blueprint or
manifest file is found, the service installs the client with the OpenSolaris
release, according to the specifications that are in the manifest file.</para><para>See the <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/AIinstall/" type="text">Automated Installer
Guide</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Build a custom, OpenSolaris image
that can be redistributed.</emphasis></para><para>System administrators and
operating system developers can use the distribution constructor tool that
is available with OpenSolaris releases to build preconfigured, bootable OpenSolaris
images. This tool takes an XML manifest file as input, and then builds an
ISO image based on the parameters that are specified in the manifest file.
Or, a USB image can be created, based on a generated ISO image. These images
can then be distributed to contacts and customers.</para><para>An ISO image or a USB image is a collection of software that comprises
an entire operating system in a single file. These images are bootable and
are usable for installations, for creating a bootable CD or DVD, and for other
purposes. An ISO image can be made available for distribution from the Internet.
A USB image can be copied to a USB flash drive.</para><para>See <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/DistroConst/index.html" type="text">Distribution Constructor Guide</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For additional resources, see <olink targetptr="links1" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="explore"><title>Exploring the OpenSolaris Live CD</title><para>Each OpenSolaris release provides a Live CD for x86 platforms.</para><para>The Live CD boots to a minimal OpenSolaris operating system, with a
GNOME desktop environment. The desktop includes the Firefox Web Browser, Thunderbird
Mail/Calendar, and other core applications.</para><para>The network auto&hyphen;magic (NWAM) daemon, <command>nwamd</command>, and the GNOME network-manager applet are enabled to automatically manage
your network interfaces.</para><para>For a general description of the purpose and function of the Live CD,
see <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Live_CD" type="text">What Is
a Live CD?</ulink></para><itemizedlist><para>To explore OpenSolaris on the Live CD, without affecting the existing
operating system that is installed on your system, follow these guidelines:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">If you have an OpenSolaris Live CD,
insert the OpenSolaris Live CD into your system and reboot.</emphasis></para><note><para>This procedure assumes that the CD drive is booted before the
hard drive in the BIOS boot order. However, if this is not the case, enter
the system BIOS by typing the appropriate keystroke combination for your system
type, then change the boot order.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">If you do not have an OpenSolaris
Live CD, you can download an ISO image of the current OpenSolaris Live CD.</emphasis></para><para>You can then burn this image to a CD and boot to it. Or, you
can save the image on your system and then run it in a virtual machine. See <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/virtualization.html" type="text">Virtualization Options</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="livecd"><title>Live CD Options</title><itemizedlist><para>The following are the OpenSolaris Live CD options:</para><listitem><para>You can choose another language for the OpenSolaris Live CD.
OpenSolaris has language support for more than 40 languages. Input and output
support for these additional languages can be activated on the Live CD in
the following ways:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Log out of the Live CD desktop.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Use the Option button on the login screen to choose a language.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Log in to the Live CD.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you need to use OpenSolaris accessibility features, use
the Magnifer and Screen Reader boot options.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are prompted to log in to the Live CD, both the user
name and password are <userinput>jack</userinput>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The root login is not enabled on either the Live CD or on
an installed system. The root password for the Live CD is <userinput>opensolaris</userinput>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can install the OpenSolaris release from the Live CD onto
your system, which is described in <olink targetptr="cdinstall" remap="internal"></olink>.</para><note><para>If you proceed to install the OpenSolaris release, you will create
a new user during the installation. After the installation, log in as that
user, and then become superuser to configure the system.</para><para>Because
the root user is a role, you must assume this role by using the <command>su</command> command. Or, you can use the <command>pfexec sh</command> command to run
commands in a privileged shell.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="cdinstall"><title>Installing from the Live CD</title><para>The OpenSolaris Live CD includes an installer that enables you to install
the OpenSolaris operating system on your x86 based system. </para><para>To start the installer, select the Installer icon on the Live CD desktop.</para><itemizedlist><para>Using the installer tool on the OpenSolaris Live CD, you have these
installation choices:</para><listitem><para>Install OpenSolaris as the only operating system on your system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Install OpenSolaris on a partition that is separate from your
existing operating system.</para><note><para>Be aware that the installation overwrites all software and data
on the selected partition.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>Install OpenSolaris inside a virtual machine.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For complete installation instructions, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2009.06/getstart/roadmap.html" type="text">Installation
Roadmap</ulink>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="links1"><title>Related Information</title><para>For more information, see the following additional resources:</para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="36.64*"/><colspec colwidth="63.36*"/><thead><row><entry><para>For More Information</para>
</entry><entry><para>Where To Go</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>To find out more about new OpenSolaris features.</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.com/learn/" type="url"></ulink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>To download OpenSolaris.</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.com/get/" type="url"></ulink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>To find out more about using OpenSolaris.</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.com/use/" type="url"></ulink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>To find out more about joining the OpenSolaris community and participating
in the development of OpenSolaris and other related projects.</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org" type="url"></ulink></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>To find out more about using accessibility features on the Live CD.</para>
</entry><entry><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/project/indiana/status/accessibility/AccessibleLiveCD" type="url"></ulink></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><?SolBook prefpagebreak?>
</chapter><chapter id="prepare"><title>Preparing to Install OpenSolaris</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>Review the following installation options and requirements for the OpenSolaris
2009.06 release.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="roadmap"><title>Installation Roadmap</title><para>You have a number of options for installing the current OpenSolaris
release from the OpenSolaris Live CD to your system.</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Choose one of the following options:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>To install the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release from the Live CD
onto your system, continue to Steps 2 and 3.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you do not have the OpenSolaris 2009.06 Live CD, go to
the <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.com/get/" type="url"></ulink> site
and select a link to download the image for the current OpenSolaris release
to your system. Once you have downloaded the image, choose one of the following
options:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Burn this image to a CD and continue to Steps 2 and 3.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Save the image on your system and mount it in a virtual machine
as described in <olink targetptr="virtualbox" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>To install or mount the OpenSolaris release from the Live
CD into a virtual machine, see <olink targetptr="virtualization" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you already have an OpenSolaris release installed on your
system, and you want to upgrade to the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release, do not
use these installation instructions. Instead, go to <olink targetptr="upgrade" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Check the requirements and limitations for running the installer
on your x86 based system:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Verify that your x86 based system meets the <olink targetptr="sysreq" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Review the <olink targetptr="limits" remap="internal">Installer Restrictions</olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Verify that you have installed all necessary device drivers
by using the Device Driver Utility 1.1. See <olink targetptr="devdriver" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Choose one of the following alternatives for installing from
the Live CD on your system:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If the OpenSolaris operating system will be the only operating
system installed on your x86 based system, see instructions for <olink targetptr="sliminstall" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you will be setting up a multiboot environment, review
the specifications in <olink targetptr="prepmulti" remap="internal"></olink>.</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Back up your system. This step is strongly recommended when
repartitioning your system. See the backup instructions in step one for <olink targetptr="partition" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Continue with the steps for <olink targetptr="partition" remap="internal"></olink>. If you already have a Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition
on your system, the installation overwrites this partition.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>After you have partitioned your system, see the instructions
to <olink targetptr="sliminstall" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</orderedlist><para>For installation issues, see <olink targetptr="troubleshooting" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="limits"><title>Installation Restrictions</title><itemizedlist><para>Installing the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release has the following restrictions:</para><listitem><para>At this time, the OpenSolaris 2009.06 installer on the Live
CD is for 32-bit or 64-bit x86 platforms only. If you want to install the
OpenSolaris 2009. 06 release to SPARC systems, use the automated installer
tool.</para><para>See the <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/dev/AIinstall/" type="text">Automated Installer
Guide</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The installer cannot upgrade an existing operating system.
The installer can perform an initial installation into a Solaris partition
or use an entire disk. The installation overwrites all the software and data
on the selected target.</para><para>However, you can upgrade all installed
packages on your installed system by using the Image Packaging System. See <olink targetptr="upgrade" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The entire content of a preexisting Solaris partition is overwritten
during the installation. Existing file systems cannot be preserved.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The OpenSolaris operating system installs a ZFS root file
system, not a UFS root file system, on the disk selected during installation.
The ZFS pool installed initially consists of the entire Solaris fdisk partition
on the selected disk. After the initial installation is complete, you can
add additional disks to this pool to create a mirrored pool configuration.
For further information, see <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/community/zfs/docs" type="text">ZFS Documentation</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A maximum of 2 Tbytes on a disk or on a partition is usable
for installing the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release, even if the disk or partition
is larger than 2 Tbytes.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="sysreq"><title>System Requirements</title><para>Review the following system requirements for installing the OpenSolaris
2009.06 release to your system.</para><informaltable frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="15.21*"/><colspec colwidth="84.79*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Requirement</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Memory</para>
</entry><entry><para>The minimum requirement is 512 MB.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Disk space</para>
</entry><entry><para>Recommended size is at least 9 GB. A minimum of 3.2 GB is required.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Multiboot capability</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you are installing OpenSolaris on a system that will have more than
one operating system, use the <command>fdisk</command> command or a third-party
partitioning tool to create a new partition or to make adjustments to preexisting
partitions. See <olink targetptr="partition" remap="internal"></olink>.</para><para>For multibooting information about specific operating systems, see <olink targetptr="prepmulti" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1><sect1 id="virtualization"><title>Virtualization Options</title><itemizedlist><listitem><para>To mount or install the OpenSolaris ISO image as a &ldquo;guest&rdquo;
in a VirtualBox, see <olink targetptr="virtualbox" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are installing on a system that is running the Mac
OS X, and you have installed Parallels on that system, see <olink targetptr="parallels" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are using VMware with Windows, see the following resources:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.deviantptr.net/blog/opensolaris/20081027/" type="text">Test-driving OpenSolaris
2008.11 (B99) With VMware Workstation 6</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.genunix.org/wiki/index.php/Getting_Started_with_OpenSolaris_using_VMWare" type="text">Getting Started With OpenSolaris Using VMWare</ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>To install an OpenSolaris &ldquo;guest&rdquo; on a hypervisor,
based on the Xen open source project, see the following resources:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><ulink url="http://blogs.sun.com/mrj/" type="text">Installing
OpenSolaris on Xen</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/xen/docs/" type="text">OpenSolaris xVM Documentation</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://blogs.sun.com/levon/entry/opensolaris_2008_11_as_a" type="text">OpenSolaris
2008.11 as a Para-Virtual Xen Guest</ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="devdriver"><title>Managing Device Drivers on Your System</title><para>Use the Device Driver Utility to identify a known Sun or third-party
driver for a device that you need on your system. Open the utility by selecting
the Device Driver Utility on the OpenSolaris desktop for either the Live CD
or an installed system.</para><itemizedlist><para>Use the Device Driver Utility to perform the following functions:</para><listitem><para>Get information about devices installed on your native system,
and check whether their corresponding device drivers exist.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Search the IPS repositories for your system devices that do
not have corresponding drivers attached.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Download and install device drivers from the IPS repositories
for devices on your system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Get the details of the third-party drivers that exist for
your system devices, and install them manually from the corresponding third-party
web site.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Submit system configurations to the OpenSolaris Operating
System Hardware Compatibility List (HCL).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>You must have an Internet connection to use all the functionality
of the Device Driver Utility.</para>
</note><para>For more information, see the online help in the utility tool menu.
If you have any questions, send an email to <literal>driver-utility-feedback@sun.com</literal>.</para><para>For additional driver resources, see <olink targetptr="adddriver" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="prepmulti"><title>Preparing for a Multiboot Environment</title><para>If you are installing an OpenSolaris release as part of a multiboot
environment, review the following multibooting specifications for various
operating systems.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1" id="gfpmb"><title>Multiboot Environments</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="27.14*"/><colspec colwidth="72.86*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Existing OS</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Microsoft Windows</para>
</entry><entry><para> If you have Windows installed, and you set up enough space to install
the OpenSolaris operating system, the installation should be straightforward.
All versions of the OpenSolaris release for the x86 platform use the GRUB
bootloader. These OpenSolaris releases recognize Windows and ensure that the
Windows partitions remain unchanged by default. When the OpenSolaris installation
is finished, the GRUB menu gives you the option to boot either Windows or
OpenSolaris.</para><para>If you are using VMware, see <ulink url="http://www.deviantptr.net/blog/opensolaris/20081027/" type="text">Test-driving OpenSolaris
2008.11 (B99) With VMware Workstation 6</ulink>. See also <ulink url="http://www.genunix.org/wiki/index.php/Getting_Started_with_OpenSolaris_using_VMWare" type="text">Getting Started With OpenSolaris Using VMWare</ulink>.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Linux, or Windows and Linux</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you have either Linux or Windows installed on your system, and you
boot through GRUB, before installing OpenSolaris, save a copy of the <filename>menu.lst</filename> file that shows the Linux and Windows boot entry information.
You will need to manually update the <filename>menu.lst</filename> file to
replace this information after the system boots. See the <command>grub(5)</command> man page.</para><note><para>If you are installing OpenSolaris on a multiboot system that also
contains the Linux operating system, the Solaris partition must precede the
Linux swap partition.</para>
</note>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Solaris 10 OS</para>
</entry><entry><para>The installer <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be used to multiboot the OpenSolaris
operating system. However, the installer can be used to replace instances
of the Solaris 10 1/06 and later OSes, and instances of Solaris Express, in
an existing multiboot Solaris system.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Extended Partitions</para>
</entry><entry><para>If you have another operating system on an extended partition, the existing
extended partition is not changed and is not lost during an OpenSolaris release
installation.  Existing extended partitions are not visible  during the OpenSolaris
release installation, but the primary <literal>fdisk</literal> partition in
which the extended partition resides is visible.  No data in these partitions
is lost due to the installation. The operating system on an extended partition
is not displayed on the GRUB menu. For information about updating the GRUB
menu, see <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2379/grubtasks-1?a=view" type="text">x86: Administering
the GRUB Bootloader</ulink>. See also <filename>menu.lst</filename> file specifics
at <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2379/hbx86boot-68676?a=view" type="text">x86:
Booting a Solaris System with GRUB</ulink>.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1><sect1 id="partition"><title>Partitioning a Multiboot System</title><para>The OpenSolaris installer uses the open source GRUB bootloader, which
supports installing multiple operating systems on one drive.  Prior to installing,
you need to create a partition for installing the OpenSolaris software. After
partitioning and installing the operating systems, one of the operating systems
can be deployed by choosing between the different operating systems at boot
time.</para><task id="gexqs"><title>How to Partition a System</title><procedure><step><para>Back up your system!</para><para><emphasis role="strong">Backing
up your system is strongly recommended</emphasis> before repartitioning your
hard drive. See the <ulink url="http://frsun.downloads.edgesuite.net/sun/07C00892/media/demos/OpenSolarisDualBoot-Step1-Backup.html" type="text">Backing Up the Disk Media Content</ulink> demo. The G4U open source tool
was designed to back up x86 based operating systems. This demo provides sample
step-by-step instructions for using the G4U open source tool to back up a
system that has Windows XP installed on it.</para>
</step><step><para>Create a partition on your hard drive for installing the OpenSolaris
operating system.</para><para>If you are installing OpenSolaris on a system
that will have more than one operating system, use the <command>fdisk</command> command or a third-party partitioning tool to create a new partition or
to make adjustments to preexisting partitions. Choose one of the following
options:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>Use the <command>fdisk</command> command to create or modify a
Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition.</para><para>For instructions,
see <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2723/disksxadd-19036?a=view" type="text">x86:
How to Create a Solaris fdisk Partition</ulink>. See, also, the <command>fdisk(1M)</command> man page.</para>
</step><step><para>Use commercial products or open-source tools to partition your
hard drive.</para><para>GParted is an open-source tool for disk partitioning.
The ISO image for the GParted tool can be downloaded from the <ulink url="http://gparted.sourceforge.net/download.php" type="text">GParted</ulink> web site.
Use this download to burn a CD that includes the GParted tool.</para><para>See the <ulink url="http://frsun.downloads.edgesuite.net/sun/07C00892/media/demos/OpenSolarisDualBoot-Step2-Partition.html" type="text">dual-boot partitioning</ulink> video. This video provides sample step-by-step
instructions that explain how to shrink a Windows XP system in order to make
room for a Linux swap partition.</para><para>Linux-swap is the same partition ID that Solaris uses. During the installation,
in the disk partitioning step, you can change this Linux-swap partition to
a Solaris partition.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Use the installer to install the OpenSolaris operating system
to the Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition as described in the next
section.</para>
</step>
</procedure><taskrelated role="see-also"><para>The demos that are referenced in this section show you how to partition
a system that has Windows XP installed on it. See <ulink url="http://frsun.downloads.edgesuite.net/sun/07C00892/media/demos/OpenSolarisDualBoot-Step1-Backup.html" type="text">Backing Up the Disk Media Content</ulink> and <ulink url="http://frsun.downloads.edgesuite.net/sun/07C00892/media/demos/OpenSolarisDualBoot-Step2-Partition.html" type="text">dual-boot partitioning</ulink>.</para><itemizedlist><para>Additional sample instructions are posted in the OpenSolaris community
for the following dual-boot procedures:</para><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.genunix.org/wiki/index.php/OpenSolaris_Dual_Boot" type="text">OpenSolaris
with MacOS on MacBook Pro</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/documentation/reviews/Dual_Boot_Install_Doc_Plan/Dual-Booting-OpenSolaris-with-Ubuntu-Linux" type="text">OpenSolaris and Ubuntu Linux Dual-Boot Installation Instructions</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/documentation/reviews/Dual_Boot_Install_Doc_Plan/Dual-Booting-OpenSolaris-with-Vista" type="text">OpenSolaris and Microsoft Vista Dual-Boot Installation Instructions</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://salmanjamali.blogspot.com/2008/04/recovering-opensolarissolairslinux.html" type="text">Recovering OpenSolaris/Solaris/Linux After Windows Installation</ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</taskrelated>
</task>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="install"><title>Installing OpenSolaris</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><itemizedlist><para>Select an installation procedure from one of the following options:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="sliminstall" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="virtualbox" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="parallels" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="sliminstall"><title>Installing OpenSolaris 2009.06 From the Live
CD</title><para>You can install the OpenSolaris to your hard driver. An existing Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition is overwritten during the initial installation.</para><task id="gfstb"><title>How to Install OpenSolaris 2009.06 from the Live CD</title><taskprerequisites><para>Before installing the OpenSolaris operating system, review the system
requirements and limitations described in the preceding sections of this document.</para><note><para>Before you install the OpenSolaris operating system on a system
that is running the Linux operating system, save a copy of the <filename>menu.lst</filename> file. The contents of the GRUB <filename>menu.lst</filename> file determine
what is displayed in the GRUB menu when you boot the system. You will need
to update the GRUB menu after the installation. For further information, see <filename>menu.lst</filename> file specifics at <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2379/hbx86boot-68676?a=view" type="text">x86:
Booting a Solaris System with GRUB</ulink>.</para>
</note><itemizedlist><para>The following are the default settings that are used by the OpenSolaris
installer:</para><listitem><para>The installation uses an existing partition or a new created
Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition to create a ZFS storage pool. If
a second disk is available, you can add a second disk to the ZFS pool to create
a mirrored configuration.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>This release installs an OpenSolaris system that is automatically
networked by using DHCP with DNS name resolution.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <command>nwamd</command> daemon is enabled by default. <command>nwamd</command> introduces an alternate instance of the network or physical
SMF service that enables automated network configuration.</para><para>For
further information, see the <literal>nwamd</literal>(1M) man page. The <citerefentry><refentrytitle>nwamd</refentrytitle></citerefentry>(1M) man page provides
instructions about how to disable or enable the network/physical:<command>nwam</command> instance.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>IPv6 is disabled.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The DNS domain and server IP addresses are retrieved from
the DHCP server.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The NFSv4 domain is dynamically derived.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Kerberos is disabled.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step><para>To start the installer from the Live CD desktop, select the Install
OpenSolaris icon on the Live CD desktop.</para><note><para>If you are prompted to log in to the Live CD, both the user name
and password are <userinput>jack</userinput>. The root password is <userinput>opensolaris</userinput>.</para>
</note><para>A text prompt enables you to select an installer language before the
installer begins. The default language is English.</para><para>The installer begins.</para>
</step><step><para>Complete any additional selections in the preliminary installation
panels.</para><itemizedlist><para>Note the following important considerations:</para><listitem><para>The installation overwrites the whole disk layout if one of
the following is true:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The disk table cannot be read.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The disk was not previously partitioned.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>If an existing Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition
is on a multiboot system, and the user makes no modifications to the existing
partitions, the installation overwrites the Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition only. Other existing partitions are not changed.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para>In the Disk panel, select disk and partition location for the
OpenSolaris operating system.</para><substeps><step><para>In the top portion of the Disk panel, select the disk where the
OpenSolaris operating system will be installed.</para><para>The top portion
of this panel displays the internal disks, external disks, and solid-state
drives that are available on the system. This panel also displays the size
of each disk in gigabytes.</para><note><para>To be recognized by the installer, the disks and solid-state drives
must be plugged in before the installer begins.</para>
</note><para>The recommended size and minimum size for the OpenSolaris operating
system installation are displayed. Disks that are too small for a successful
installation are labeled as such. The recommended size is at least 9 Gbytes.</para><note><para>A maximum of 2 Tbytes on a disk or on a partition is usable for
installing the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release, even if the disk or partition
is larger than 2 Tbytes.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>In the bottom portion of the Disk panel, click either Use the
whole disk or Partition the disk.</para><para>The bottom portion of this panel
displays the existing disk partitioning.</para><caution><para>If the existing partition table cannot be read, a warning is
displayed, and the panel displays proposed partitioning. In this case, all
data on the disk is destroyed.</para>
</caution><stepalternatives><step><para>If you choose to partition the disk, review the following partitioning
guidelines, then revise the partitioning panel settings as needed.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Only one Solaris partition is allowed. If an existing Solaris
partition is available, that Solaris partition will be the target for the
installation. Or, if you do not have an existing Solaris partition, you can
change any existing partition to a Solaris partition.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can resize existing partitions, delete partitions, and
create new partitions in this panel. For this option, one existing Solaris
partition must be available as the target for the installation.</para><caution><para>The partitions are displayed in physically sequential order
as they are laid out on the disk. Resizing a Solaris partition destroys the
data on that partition and all physically subsequent partitions. Existing
data is not moved to conform to a new partition layout. However, resizing
the last partition or appending a new partition does not affect the data that
already exists in other partitions. Non-Solaris partitions cannot be resized.</para>
</caution><caution><para>To make additional space available, you can change an existing
partition to Unused. However, if you change an existing partition to Unused,
all subsequent non-Solaris partitions are also changed to Unused.</para>
</caution><caution><para>New partitions can only use the available space that follows
the last defined partition. The installer cannot utilize unallocated chunks
of space between existing defined partitions. Use the <command>fdisk(1M)</command> command to create new partitions that use the free space between exiting
partitions.</para>
</caution>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you used a third-party partitioning tool such as GParted,
then the Disk panel displays a partition named Linux-swap on which you can
install the OpenSolaris operating system.</para><note><para>In this panel, use the drop-down list for the Linux-swap partition
name to change the partition name to Solaris.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>Manual control of the OpenSolaris file system layout is not supported.
During the installation, the Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition is
reformatted with a default ZFS file system layout. All existing file systems
on the Solaris partition are destroyed.</para><para>The installation uses
a Solaris <command>fdisk</command> partition to create a ZFS storage pool.</para><para>If a second disk is available, you can, after the installed system has
been booted, add a second disk to the ZFS pool to create a mirrored configuration.
To create a mirrored configuration, use the ZFS <command>attach</command> command
to add a second disk to the storage pool. For example:</para><screen># <command>zpool attach rpool c0t2d0s0 c0t4d0s0</command></screen><para>The following example illustrates a ZFS file system setup with a redundant
configuration:</para><screen># zpool status
  pool: rpool
 state: ONLINE
 scrub: none requested
config:

NAME          STATE     READ WRITE CKSUM
rpool         ONLINE       0     0     0
mirror        ONLINE       0     0     0
c0t2d0s0      ONLINE       0     0     0
c0t4d0s0      ONLINE       0     0     0

errors: No known data errors </screen>
</note>
</step><step><para>In the same panel, you can choose instead to install the OpenSolaris
operating system on the whole disk.</para><caution><para>This option erases the existing disk. The entire disk is overwritten
with the new OpenSolaris operating system.</para>
</caution>
</step>
</stepalternatives><para>When you have revised the partitioning as needed, click Next.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step><step><para>Complete time zone, date, and time settings.</para><para>The next
panel enables you to type the correct time zone, date, and time for the system
to be installed.  Select a time zone or location where the computer is typically
used. The top half of the panel displays a world map with major cities marked.
The bottom half of the panel provides drop-down selections. You can choose
the time zone either from the map or from the drop-down list.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>If you select the time zone from the map, click on a city or click
anywhere on the map.</para><para>If you click on the map, but not on a city,
the map automatically magnifies that area. You can click on a location within
that magnified area. You can drag the cursor to move the magnified area to
a different location on the map.  When you select a site on the map, the drop-down
selections automatically populate with the time zone, date, and current time
for that map selection. You can right-click to deselect magnification.</para>
</step><step><para>Instead of using the map, you can make your selections in the
drop-down fields.</para><para>Select your region, then select Location. Finally,
select time zone.  The options for each drop-down field are determined by
the selection made in the prior drop-down field.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives><note><para>You can edit the default date and time that is provided.</para>
</note><para>When the settings are correct, click Next.</para>
</step><step><para>Select language and locale, then click Next.</para><para>The next
panel enables you to select a language and locale. These selections determine
the language support, the default date and time, and other data formats for
the installed system.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>You can accept the default language selection or change the
selection.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A language selection is required. You can select &ldquo;no
default language support.&rdquo;</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The language chosen automatically determines the available
locales in the drop-down list. Only one locale can be selected.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>Any time that you log in to the installed system, you can change
either the locale for that particular session or the default locale by using
the Options button in the Login dialog box.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>Complete the user settings and click Next.</para><itemizedlist><para>Review the following guidelines:</para><listitem><para>Root login is not enabled either on the Live CD or on the
installed system. You must log in as the user that you create in this panel.
After you log in, you can then become root to configure the system.</para><note><para>If you do not create a user account in this panel, root is set
up as a normal account on the installed system, instead of as a role. This
is the only situation where you can log in to the installed system as root.</para>
</note><para>For further information, see <olink targetptr="login" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Both the root password and user account are optional. However,
for better security, complete these fields.</para><para>If the root password
is not defined, a reminder is displayed when you click Next. If you do not
want to define a root password, you can proceed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A user account requires only a Login name for the account
to be valid. For better security, however, do complete all fields.</para><para>If the user account information is not valid, a reminder is displayed when
you click Next. If you do not want to define a user account, you can proceed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Type a computer name or accept the default. The computer name
field cannot be blank.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For further information, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/dev/getstart/setusers.html" type="text">Setting
Up Users</ulink>.</para>
</step><step><para>In the Install panel, review and confirm installation specifications.</para><caution><para>The installation begins when you click Install. Do not interrupt
an installation in progress.</para>
</caution><para>During the installation, a progress bar is displayed.</para><para>The final panel displays completion messages. You can review the installation
log in this panel. You can either quit or reboot from this panel.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>After a successful installation, to start the installed system,
select Reboot. The reboot process might take a few minutes.</para><note><para>Eject the Live CD as the next boot begins. Or, select the &ldquo;Boot
from Hard Disk&rdquo; option in the GRUB menu.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>To exit, select Quit and shut down your system.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure><taskrelated role="additional-action"><para>After you have installed the OpenSolaris software, if you have another
operating system on your system, you might need to manually update the GRUB
menu. The GRUB menu displays a list of operating systems that can be booted.
Solaris and Windows operating systems are displayed automatically in the GRUB
menu. The contents of the GRUB <filename>menu.lst</filename> file determine
what is displayed in the GRUB menu when you boot the system. If you have installed
an additional OpenSolaris release, or the Linux operating system, you will
need to edit the GRUB <filename>menu.lst</filename> file to manually
add these entries. For more information, see <ulink url="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/819-2379/hbx86boot-68676?a=view" type="text">x86:
Booting a Solaris System with GRUB</ulink>.</para><para>If you are unable to log in to your installed system, or if you want
to customize the roles that were set up during the installation, see <olink targetptr="login" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</taskrelated>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="virtualbox"><title>Running OpenSolaris in VirtualBox</title><para>The <trademark>VirtualBox</trademark> software runs as an application
in your operating system, providing an environment called a <emphasis>virtual
machine</emphasis>, which enables you to install other operating systems as &ldquo;guests&rdquo;
inside the virtual machine.</para><para>The VirtualBox software supports the following host operating systems.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1"><title>VirtualBox Hosts</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Host Operating Systems</para>
</entry><entry><para>Supported Versions</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Windows</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Windows XP &ndash; All service packs</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Windows Server 2003</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Windows Vista &ndash; 32-bit and 64-bit</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Linux on 32-bit and 64-bit systems</para>
</entry><entry><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Debian GNU/Linux 3.1 at minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Fedora Core 4 at minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Gentoo Linux</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 3 at minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>SuSE Linux 9 at minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>OpenSuSE 10.1 at minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Ubuntu 5.10 at minimum</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Mandriva 2007.1 and 2008.0</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Apple Mac OS X (Intel)</para>
</entry><entry><para>All</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><task id="setvb"><title>How to Set Up OpenSolaris in a VirtualBox</title><tasksummary><para>Before running OpenSolaris inside your existing operating system, you
must first install the VirtualBox application. After VirtualBox is successfully
installed on your computer, you can run the OpenSolaris ISO image or the Live
CD as a virtual guest &ldquo;in the box.&rdquo; You do not need to burn a
DVD.</para><note><para>A minimum of 10 GB of disk space or virtual disk space is recommended
in order to install the VirtualBox and to install the OpenSolaris release
inside the VirtualBox.</para>
</note><para>To set up and run OpenSolaris inside VirtualBox, use the following procedure:</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Download the VirtualBox application for your operating system
from the <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/download/" type="text">Sun Download
Center</ulink>.</para><para>Save the application to your desktop or local
disk.</para>
</step><step><para>Download an OpenSolaris ISO image from <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.com/get/" type="url"></ulink> or order a free Live CD.</para><para>For convenience, save the file to the same location where you placed
your VirtualBox files.</para><note><para>The ISO image requires about 685 Mbytes on your hard drive. The
download can take several minutes.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>Install VirtualBox, following the specific instructions for your &ldquo;host&rdquo;
operating system:</para><stepalternatives><step><para><olink targetptr="installmac" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</step><step><para><olink targetptr="installlinux" remap="internal"></olink></para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Configure VirtualBox, per instructions at <olink targetptr="configure" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>Start OpenSolaris, per the instructions at <olink targetptr="start" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="installmac"><title>How to Install VirtualBox on a Windows or Macintosh
(Intel) System</title><procedure><step><para>Navigate to the downloaded VirtualBox installation files or folder.</para><para>For Macintosh, this is a <filename>.dmg</filename> image file.</para>
</step><step><para>To start the installation, double-click the VirtualBox installation
file and click Next or Continue.</para>
</step><step><para>Accept the license agreement and click Next or Continue</para>
</step><step><para>Choose a location for the VirtualBox software, accepting the default
location or modifying the location.</para><note><para>You need 10 Gbytes or more disk space to install both VirtualBox
and the OpenSolaris image.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>Click the Install button.</para><para>If requested, enter your
user password.</para>
</step><step><para>When the completion message is displayed, click Close or Finish.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="installlinux"><title>How to Install VirtualBox on a Linux System</title><tasksummary><note><para>Download the latest version of VirtualBox as described previously,
even if your Linux distribution comes with a VirtualBox version preinstalled.
The preinstalled VirtualBox software is usually the Open Source Edition (OSE),
which might not be suitable for running the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release.</para>
</note>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Open a terminal window and become the root user.</para>
</step><step><para>Navigate to the downloaded VirtualBox installation file.</para>
</step><step><para>Depending on your Linux distribution, start the installation process
by using one of the following commands:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>On rpm-based systems, such as Fedora, SuSE, or Red Hat, type the
following:</para><screen><command>rpm -ihv <replaceable>filename</replaceable></command></screen><para>Replace <replaceable>filename</replaceable> with the name of the downloaded
installation file.</para>
</step><step><para>On deb-based systems, like Debian, or Ubuntu, type the following:</para><screen><command>dpkg -i <replaceable>filename</replaceable></command></screen><para>Replace <replaceable>filename</replaceable> with the name of the downloaded
installation file.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives><note><para>You might need to install additional packages to fulfill dependencies.</para>
</note><para>The installer searches for a precompiled kernel module. If no kernel
module is available that is precompiled for your system, the installer attempts
to compile and install a kernel module.</para><note><para>You need to have basic build utilities, such as <filename>gcc</filename>, <filename>make</filename>, <filename>binutils</filename>, and <filename>kernel header</filename>, installed for the installer to be able to build
the kernel module. Usually, these utilities are part of the standard installation
of your Linux system. If these utilities are not present, the installer will
be unable to build the kernel module. In this case, install the build utilities
and manually start the kernel module compilation later by running <command>/etc/init.d vboxdrv setup</command> as  root user.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>Add the current user to the vboxusers group.</para><substeps><step><para>In a terminal window, type:</para><screen><command>sudo usermod -G vboxusers -a <replaceable>username</replaceable></command></screen><para>Replace <replaceable>username</replaceable> with the name of the current
user.</para>
</step><step><para>Log out and log in again to apply the changes.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step><step><para>Open a terminal window, type <userinput>VirtualBox</userinput>, and press Enter to start the VirtualBox.</para>
</step><step><para>Accept the license agreement.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="configure"><title>How to Configure VirtualBox for Use With OpenSolaris</title><taskprerequisites><para>If you have the OpenSolaris Live CD, boot to your host operating system,
then insert the Live CD. Then, open the VirtualBox application.</para>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step><para>Start VirtualBox by using one of the following steps:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>On Windows, click the Start button, and select VirtualBox from
the list of programs.</para>
</step><step><para>On Linux, open a terminal window, type <userinput>VirtualBox</userinput>, and press Enter.</para>
</step><step><para>On Mac OS X, open Applications in the Finder and double-click
VirtualBox.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>On the first start of VirtualBox, type your registration information
and click Confirm.</para><para>The main VirtualBox window appears.</para>
</step><step><para>Click the New icon on the left side of the GUI, and click Next
in the pop-up window.</para>
</step><step><para>Type a name for your virtual machine, and from the drop-down list,
select OpenSolaris as the operating system. Click Next.</para>
</step><step><para>Select the amount of RAM to allocate to the OpenSolaris installation
inside VirtualBox. Click Next.</para><note><para>512 Mbytes is the recommended minimum size. If you have 2 Gbytes
or more of memory on your system, you should choose 1 Gbyte for optimum performance.
See substep C of the next step.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>Add a Virtual Disk Image (vdi) by selecting a name or adding a
new name to the list. For the initial installation, follow these substeps:</para><substeps><step><para>Select New and click Next.</para>
</step><step><para>Accept the default Dynamically Expanding Image and click Next.</para>
</step><step><para>Accept the default name, or type a path and name, and allocate
space for the image.</para>
</step><step><para>When you've completed the settings, click Next.</para>
</step><step><para>Click Finish to create the disk image.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step><step><para>When the initial Virtual Disk Manager GUI appears with your new
vdi file selected, click Next.</para>
</step><step><para>In the Summary screen, click Finish.</para><para>The main VirtualBox
window appears. Your virtual OpenSolaris machine is displayed in the left
panel, and is ready to use as a virtual machine.</para>
</step><step><para>Click the CD/DVD-ROM link on the right-hand side, in the Details
tab.</para>
</step><step><para>Check Mount CD/DVD Drive and select one of the following:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>If you are using the OpenSolaris Live CD, select Host CD/DVD
Drive and close the Settings screen. Skip step 11.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are using a downloaded OpenSolaris ISO image, select
ISO Image File and go to step 11.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para>In the drop-down list, select the downloaded OpenSolaris ISO image.
If the ISO image is not in the list, add the image as follows:</para><substeps><step><para>Click the Select icon in the right of the drop-down list.</para>
</step><step><para>Click the CD/DVD Images tab.</para>
</step><step><para>Click the Add icon.</para>
</step><step><para>Navigate to the downloaded OpenSolaris ISO image file and click
Open.</para>
</step><step><para>Click Select and close the Settings screen.</para>
</step><step><para>Close the Settings screen.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="start"><title>How to Start OpenSolaris 2009.06 Using VirtualBox</title><procedure><step><para>Start VirtualBox by using one of the following options:</para><stepalternatives><step><para>On Windows, click the Start button and select VirtualBox from
the list of programs.</para>
</step><step><para>On Linux, select VirtualBox from the System Tools menu (GNOME
desktop) or from the System menu (KDE desktop).</para>
</step><step><para>On Mac OS X, open Applications in the Finder and double-click
VirtualBox.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Double-click your virtual machine icon or select it and click
Start.</para><note><para>Unless you have the ISO on a CD, click the CD/DVD-ROM link and
verify that the OpenSolaris ISO image file is selected.</para>
</note><para>The GRUB boot menu with three options is displayed. Then a SunOS Release
message is displayed. Finally, a list of languages appears.</para>
</step><step><para>When the list of keyboard layouts appears, press Enter to accept
the English default. Or, type the number for your keyboard layout and press
Enter.</para><note><para>When you click inside the VirtualBox window with your virtual
machine running, the mouse cursor is trapped inside the virtual desktop. Use
the Host Key to release the mouse cursor again. The Host Key is indicated
at the lower right corner of the VirtualBox window. By default, the Host Key
is the right Ctrl key on Windows and Linux, and the left Cmd key on Mac OS
X.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>When the list of desktop languages appears, press Enter to accept
the English default, or type the number to select another language and then
press Enter.</para><para>The application takes one or two minutes to load.</para><para>When the desktop screen appears, you are &ldquo;in the box,&rdquo; running
the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release.</para><note><para>You should install OpenSolaris to your virtual hard drive in order
to be able to install programs and save configurations.</para>
</note>
</step><step><para>To install OpenSolaris 2009.06 on your virtual hard disk, click
the Install OpenSolaris icon on the OpenSolaris desktop.</para><para>For installation
instructions, see <olink targetptr="sliminstall" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><?SolBook prefpagebreak?><sect1 id="parallels"><title>Running OpenSolaris in Parallels</title><para>If you are installing on a system and are running the Mac OS X and have
installed Parallels, use the following procedure to install an OpenSolaris
operating system.</para><task id="gfuvx"><title>How to Install When Using Parallels</title><taskprerequisites><para>See &ldquo;Solaris Network Driver Installation&rdquo; instructions in
the <ulink url="http://www.parallels.com/files/upload/Parallels_Desktop_for_Mac_User_Guide.pdf" type="text">Parallels Desktop for Mac User Guide</ulink>.</para>
</taskprerequisites><procedure><step><para>During the Parallels pseudo environment setup, set the networking
choice to Ethernet bridge.</para>
</step><step><para>Using Parallels, boot the Live CD.</para>
</step><step><para>Continue the installation of the OpenSolaris operating system.</para><para>For installation instructions, see <olink targetptr="sliminstall" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</step><step><para>After installation of the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release, install
the network driver.</para><para>For a sample installation that includes instructions
for installing the network driver, see <ulink remap="" url="http://blogs.sun.com/lr/entry/opensolaris_in_parallels_vm_on" type="text">OpenSolaris
in Parallels VM on Mac OS X</ulink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1><sect1 id="links2"><title>Related Links</title><itemizedlist><para>The following resources provide supplemental information about how to
use OpenSolaris in a VirtualBox environment.</para><listitem><para><ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/Appliance/Sun+xVM+VirtualBox+Best+Practices" type="text">Sun xVM VirtualBox Best Practices</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.genunix.org/wiki/index.php/OpenSolaris_Virtual_Box" type="text">OpenSolaris
VirtualBox on MacOS</ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>See the following blog for specific instructions for setting up OpenSolaris
in a VirtualBox on Ubuntu.</para><listitem><para><ulink url="http://amitksaha.blogspot.com/2008/03/innotek-virtual-box-on-ubuntu-704.html" type="text">Install VirtualBox on Ubuntu</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://amitksaha.blogspot.com/2008/03/getting-started-with-indiana-on-ubuntu.html" type="text">Getting Started With OpenSolaris on Ubunto and VirtualBox</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://amitksaha.blogspot.com/2008/03/installing-indiana-on-ubuntu-704-using.html" type="text">Installing OpenSolaris on Ubuntu using VirtualBox</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>For information about ZFS in the OpenSolaris environment,
see the <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/community/zfs/docs" type="text">ZFS Documentation Hub</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="verify"><title>Verifying and Finalizing Your Installed
System</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>Use the following information to check the set up on your installed
OpenSolaris system.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="netaccess"><title>Verifying Network Access</title><para>For information on this topic, see <ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisinfo/Administering+Your+Automatic+Network+Connection" type="text">Administering Your Automatic Network Connection</ulink>.</para><para>See, also, &ldquo;Networks and NWAM&rdquo; topics in the <ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisInfo/OpenSolaris+System+Administration+Topics+List" type="text">OpenSolaris System Administration Topics List</ulink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="netconnect"><title>Modifying Network Connectivity Using the NWAM
GUI</title><para>For information on this topic, see <ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisInfo/How+to+Modify+the+Automatic+Network+Configuration" type="text">How to Manually Modify the Automatic Network Configuration</ulink>.</para><para>See, also, &ldquo;Networks by Hand&rdquo; topics in the <ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisInfo/OpenSolaris+System+Administration+Topics+List" type="text">OpenSolaris System Administration Topics List</ulink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="new-user"><title>Getting Additional Software</title><para>After an initial installation of OpenSolaris operating system, you will
find that many of the software applications that you use on a regular basis
are not immediately available to you. These software applications are available
as packages in a repository for downloading and installing over the internet.
A repository is a source for packages.</para><para>The Image Packaging System enables users to connect to the repository
and download and install packages.</para><para>OpenSolaris uses IPS for its packaging system. Besides installing packages
from a repository, users can create and publish their own IPS packages, set
up an OpenSolaris repository, mirror an existing repository, and publish existing
packages to a repository.</para><para>Once you have installed packages, IPS enables you to search, update,
and manage packages on your system.</para><para>With IPS , you can upgrade your system to a newer build of OpenSolaris,
install and update your software to the latest available versions in a repository,
and retrieve packages from mirror repositories. </para><para>If the system on which IPS is installed is on the network, IPS can automatically
access the OpenSolaris repository. Your IPS client can access the packages
from <ulink url="http://pkg.opensolaris.org" type="url"></ulink>. </para><sect2 id="ghpfd"><title>OpenSolaris Repositories</title><para>The following repositories are available for the OpenSolaris release:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><ulink url="http://pkg.opensolaris.org" type="url"></ulink> &ndash; Users can access this repository to download and install software
that is specifically built to run on OpenSolaris 2009.06.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>See the table and information in <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/IMGPACKAGSYS/ssttii.html" type="url"></ulink> for a list of repositories that contain security fixes, access to
encumbered packages and third-party non-redistributable packages. Access to
these repositories may require a key and a certificate.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="pkg_mgr"><title>The Package Manager</title><para>The Package Manager application is a GUI for the IPS software. The Package Manager enables
you to search, install, and remove packages; add, and modify repositories;
and create and remove boot environments.</para><para>You can start the <application>Package Manager</application> in the following ways:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term><emphasis role="strong">Desktop Menu:</emphasis></term><listitem><para>Select System &gt; Administration &gt; Package Manager. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry><varlistentry><term><emphasis role="strong">Command line:</emphasis></term><listitem><para>Execute the following command at the prompt:</para><screen>$ <userinput>gksu packagemanager &amp;</userinput></screen>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist><para>The Package Manager documentation is available from the Help menu. To learn
how to use the Package Manager, select About &gt; Help.</para><para>View the <ulink url="http://webcast-west.sun.com/interactive/09B01790/index.html" type="text">screencast</ulink> <literal>(http://webcast-west.sun.com/<?SolBook preflinebreak?>&gt;interactive/09B01790/index.html)</literal> to learn how to use the Package Manager.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="adddriver"><title>Finding Missing Device Drivers</title><para>To locate additional Sun and third-party drivers and devices OpenSolaris,
see the following resources:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Wireless drivers: <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/laptop/wireless/" type="url"></ulink></para><para>Select the driver name to get a list of devices supported by the driver
and to get download, installation, and configuration instructions.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>OpenSolaris Device Drivers Community: <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/device_drivers/" type="url"></ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Open Source Software Sites on the Solaris Community: <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/software/solaris/community_resources.jsp" type="url"></ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Third Party Products &amp; Solutions: <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/io_technologies/" type="url"></ulink></para><para>Select the
technology on the left side of the page, such as Ethernet or USB.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Hardware Drivers on the Sun Download Center: <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/download/" type="url"></ulink></para><para>Select the tab View
by Category. Select the Hardware Drivers category.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1><sect1 id="links3"><title>Related Links</title><para>See <ulink url="http://www.genunix.org/wiki/index.php/Osoladmin:_Topics" type="text">OpenSolaris
System Administration</ulink> for additional instructions for setting up an
installed system, including:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Set up audio and video</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Set up printing</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Using basic commands</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Introduction to file systems</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Troubleshooting</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>To explore OpenOffice word processing and spreadsheet capabilities,
see <ulink url="http://documentation.openoffice.org/manuals/oooauthors2/0100GS-GettingStarted.pdf" type="text">Getting Started With OpenOffice.org 2.x</ulink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="roles"><title>Understanding Users and Roles</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>The OpenSolaris release includes user accounts and RBAC roles as described
in the following section.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="setusers"><title>Setting Up Users</title><para>When you install the OpenSolaris release to your system, you are prompted
to create a user account and a root password for your system.</para><itemizedlist><para>Review the following login, user account, and root specifications.</para><listitem><para>Root login is not enabled either on the Live CD or on the
installed system. You must log in as the user that you created during the
installation. After you log in, you can then become root to configure the
system. Because root is a role, open a terminal window and use the <command>su</command> command to assume the role, or the <command>pfexec sh</command> command to run commands in a privileged shell.</para><note><para>If you try to log in to the installed system as root, an error
message displays. Click OK and log in as the local user that you created during
the installation.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>Root is a role per Role-Based Access Control (RBAC) specifications.
However, if you do not create a user account during the installation, root
is set up as a normal account on the installed system, instead of as a role.
This is the only situation where you can log in to the installed system as
root without manually changing the role assignment for root.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>After you install the OpenSolaris release, if you wish to
manually change the installed system to permit root logins, remove root as
an assigned role for users. Then, type the following at the command line:</para><screen># <command>rolemod <option>K</option> type=normal root</command></screen><para>This command converts root to a normal account.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you forget the local user name or password that you entered
during the installation, you must boot the system into Maintenance Mode as
described in <olink targetptr="fixlogin" remap="internal"></olink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For additional instructions, see the following resources.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1"><title>RBAC Documentation</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Resource</para>
</entry><entry><para>Topic</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><command>rbac(5)</command> man page</para>
</entry><entry><para>Instructions for Role-Based Access Control</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/SYSADV6/prbac-1.html" type="text">RBAC: An Alternative
to the Superuser Model</ulink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Introduction to roles in the OpenSolaris environment</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/SYSADV6/rbactask-1.html#rbactask-14" type="text">Using RBAC (Task Map)</ulink></para>
</entry><entry><para>Instructions about using existing roles or customizing roles</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1><sect1 id="pfexec"><title>Executing Privileged Commands</title><para>The OpenSolaris operating system exploys the <command>pfexec</command> utility to execute commands with predefined attributes that the system administer
specifies in user profiles. The system administrator assigns privileges to
groups of users in a user profile. These privileges can restrict or permit
file access for the group, restrict or permit the group's ability to perform
various tasks, and so on.</para><para>See the <command>pfexec</command> man page for complete information
about using this utility.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="syssrv"><title>Managing System Services</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>The OpenSolaris operating system includes services such as delivering
email, responding to FTP requests, or permitting remote command execution.
The Service Management Facility (SMF) simplifies management of these system
services.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="syssrv2"><title>Managing Services on Your System</title><para>For information about managing the services on your system, see the &ldquo;Service
Management Facility&rdquo; topics on <ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisInfo/OPenSolaris+System+Administration+Topics+List" type="text"></ulink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="appdev"><title>Setting Up Your Application Development
Environment</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>The OpenSolaris 2009.06 release offers complete support for developing
and deploying applications for the web. The applications needed for development
of web applications are available as packages in the <filename>pkg.opensolaris.org </filename> repository. </para>
</highlights><sect1 id="setup_dev_env"><title>Installing Developer Tools</title><para>To learn how to download and install applications such as Sun Studio
compilers, NetBeans, and get the tools required to set up a Web Stack Development
environment, see the <ulink url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisInfo/OpenSolaris+2008.11+Development+Environment+Guide" type="text"><citetitle>Setting up Your OpenSolaris Development Environment</citetitle></ulink> <literal>(http://wikis.sun.com/display/OpenSolarisInfo/<?SolBook preflinebreak?>&gt;OpenSolaris+2008.11+Development+Environment+Guide)</literal>.</para><itemizedlist><para>Additional resource include the following:</para><listitem><para><ulink remap="" url="http://wikis.sun.com/display/WebStack/Web+Stack+Getting+Started+Guide" type="text">Web Stack Getting Started Guide for OpenSolaris 2008.11</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/MTPODG/groups-1.html" type="text">OpenSolaris
2008.11 Memory Thread Placement and Optimization Developer's Guide</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/NETPROTO" type="text">OpenSolaris 2008.11
Programming Interface Guide</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink remap="" url="http://docs.sun.com/source/820-3999" type="text">Getting Started With Sun Studio
Software</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink remap="" url="http://www.netbeans.org/kb/60/java/javase-intro.html" type="text">Introduction to
Developing General Java Applications</ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Develop a simple device driver with <ulink remap="" url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/DRIVERTUT/drivertutp.html" type="text">Device
Driver Tutorial</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Dtrace is a dynamic tracing facility that can display relevant
information about kernel or user processes. See <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/DYNMCTRCGGD" type="text">OpenSolaris
2008.11 Dynamic Tracing Guide</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="keepupdate"><title>Keeping Your System Updated</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>After you have installed the OpenSolaris release, you can add, remove,
and update packages on the system as described in the following sections.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="updatesw"><title>Updating Software on Your System</title><para>In the OpenSolaris releases, you upgrade an entire image or boot environment
by using the <command>pkg image-update</command> command to update all the
packages in that image that have available updates.</para><note><para>To upgrade from the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release to the OpenSolaris
2009.06 release, you must use a particular procedure, which is described at <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/indiana/resources/relnotes/200805/image-update/" type="text">Updating Your System to OpenSolaris Development Builds</ulink>.</para>
</note><itemizedlist><para>Use one of the following methods to upgrade an image or boot environment:</para><listitem><para>You can use the Package Manager GUI to update all installed
the packages in your image to the latest available version for each package.
You accomplish this task by selecting the Update All option in the GUI.</para><para>For information, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/IMGPACKAGESYS/pkg_mgr.html" type="text">The Package Manager</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The OpenSolaris operating system includes an Update Manager
tool on the desktop that notifies users when updates are available for the
packages that are installed on their system. You can use this tool to update
all the packages in your image.</para><para>To manually start the Update Manager,
from the Main Menubar, select System &gt; Administration &gt; Update Manager.</para><para>For information, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/IMGPACKAGESYS/update_mgr.html" type="text">The Update Manager</ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Alternately, you can use the <command>pkg image-update</command> command to perform that same task.</para><screen><literal>pkg image-update [-nv]</literal></screen><para>The <command>pkg image-update</command> command updates all packages
installed on your image that have available updates. Use the <literal>-n</literal> option to perform a test run of the updates. With the <literal>-n</literal> option, the command executes, but makes no persistent changes to the image.
 Or, you can use the <literal>-v</literal> option. With the <literal>-v</literal> option, the update is performed with progress messages displayed during
the operation.</para><note><para>The <command>pkg image-update</command> command does not support
zones in boot environments prior to the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release. Delete
these zones before you upgrade your image to the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release.
If you are using the OpenSolaris developmental builds, the <command>pkg image-update</command> command has no support for zones prior to build 98.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Using either the Package Manager or the <command>pkg image-update</command> command, the process of updating all the packages automatically creates
a clone: a new, bootable environment (BE). The process of updating all the
packages applies the changes to the clone instead of to the original boot
environment. After the successful completion of the changes to the clone and
reboot of the system, the new clone is provided as the default, active boot
environment in the GRUB menu. The original boot environment remains on the
GRUB menu as an alternate selection.</para><para>A clone of the boot environment includes everything hierarchically under
the main root dataset of the original boot environment.  Shared file systems
are not under the root dataset and are not cloned. Instead, the boot environment
accesses the original shared file systems.</para><note><para>The <command>pkg image-update</command> process does not upgrade
zones. If you have included zones in your OpenSolaris environment, the <command>pkg image-update</command> process clones these existing zones into the new
boot environment, but these zones are not upgraded. You must manually upgrade
each of these zones.</para>
</note><para>After upgrading an image or boot environment, you can use the <command>beadm list</command> command to see a list of the boot environments on the
system, including the new boot environment that was created by the <command>pkg image-update</command> command. See the following example.</para><screen>os# pkg image-update
A clone of opensolaris exists and has been updated and activated. 
On next boot the Boot Environment opensolaris-1 will be mounted on '/'. 
Reboot when ready to switch to this updated BE.

os# beadm list

BE            Active Active on Mountpoint Space
Name                 reboot               Used
----          ------ --------- ---------- -----
opensolaris   yes    no        legacy     57.5K
opensolaris-1 no     yes       -          2.59G </screen><para>In this example, the initial boot environment created by the installer
is named &ldquo;opensolaris.&rdquo; The boot environment created by the <command>pkg image-update</command> command is automatically named &ldquo;opensolaris-1.&rdquo;</para><para>After rebooting to the changed boot environment, any inactive boot environment
can be destroyed to save space by running the <command>beadm destroy</command> command.  For instructions, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/dev/snapupgrade/snap3.html" type="text">Managing
Boot Environments.</ulink>.</para><para>For further information about the <command>pkg</command> command, see
the <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/IMGPACKAGESYS/new-user.html" type="text">OpenSolaris 2009.06 Image Packaging System Guide</ulink> or the <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/sc/src/pkg/gate/src/man/pkg.1.txt" type="text">pkg(1)</ulink> man page.</para><sect2><title>Updating Specific Packages</title><para>As an alternative to upgrading an entire image or boot environment,
you can update specific installed packages or package groups in the image
or in the active boot environment by using either the Package Manager GUI
or the <command>pkg install</command> command. Either method automatically
checks for newer versions of specific packages or package groups, and installs
them if they are available. Any dependent packages are also automatically
updated.</para><para>For further information about updating specific packages, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/IMGPACKAGESYS/pkg_mgr.html" type="text">The Package Manager</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/2008.11/IMGPACKAGESYS/new-user.html" type="text">OpenSolaris 2009.06 Image Packaging System Guide</ulink>, or the <ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/sc/src/pkg/gate/src/man/pkg.1.txt" type="text">pkg(1)</ulink> man page.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="bootenv"><title>Managing Multiple Boot Environments on Your System</title><para>A boot environment is a bootable instance of an OpenSolaris operating
system image plus any other application software packages installed into that
image. You can maintain multiple boot environments on your system, and each
boot environment could have different software versions installed.</para><para>Upon the initial installation of OpenSolaris onto your system, a boot
environment is created.  Use the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>beadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> utility to administer additional
boot environments on your system.</para><sect2><title>Why Use Multiple Boot Environments?</title><para>With multiple boot environments, the process of updating software becomes
a low risk operation because you can create backup boot environments before
making any software updates to your system.  If needed, you have the option
of booting a backup boot environment.</para><itemizedlist><para>Here are some specific examples where having more than one OpenSolaris
boot environment, and managing them with the <command>beadm</command> utility,
is useful:</para><listitem><para>When you use either the Package Manager tool or the <command>pkg image-update</command> command to update all the packages in your active
OpenSolaris boot environment, this process automatically creates a clone of
that boot environment. The packages are updated in the clone rather than in
the original boot environment. After successfully completing the updates,
the new clone is activated. Then, the clone will become the new default boot
environment on the next reboot. The original boot environment remains on the
GRUB menu as an alternate selection.</para><para>For more information, see <olink targetptr="upgrade" remap="internal"></olink>.</para><para>You can use the <command>beadm list</command> command to see a list
of all the boot environments on the system, including the backup boot environment
that still has its original, unchanged software. If you are not satisfied
with the updates made to the environment, you can use the <command>beadm activate</command> command to specify that the backup will become the default boot environment
on the next reboot.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>If you are modifying a boot environment, you can take a snapshot
of that environment at any stage during modifications by using the <command>beadm create</command> command. A snapshot is a read-only image of a dataset
or boot environment at a given point in time.</para><para>You can create custom
names for each snapshot that identify when or why the snapshot was created.
For example, if you are doing monthly upgrades to your boot environment, you
can capture snapshots for each monthly upgrade. You can use the <command>beadm
list <option>s</option></command> command to view the available snapshots
for a boot environment.</para><para>A snapshot is not bootable. But, you can create a boot environment,
based on that snapshot, by using the <option>e</option> option for the <command>beadm create</command> command. Then you can use the <command>beadm activate</command>command to specify that this boot environment will become the default boot
environment on the next reboot.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can maintain more than one boot environment on your system,
and perform various upgrades on each of them as needed. For example, you can
clone a boot environment by using the <command>beadm create</command> command.
A clone is a bootable copy of a boot environment. Then, you can install, test,
and update different software packages on the original boot environment and
on its clone.</para><para>Although only one boot environment can be active
at a time, you can mount an inactive boot environment by using the <command>beadm mount</command> command. Then you can use the <command>pkg image-update</command> command with the <option>R</option> option to update all the packages in
that inactive, mounted environment. Or, use the <command>pkg install <replaceable>packagename</replaceable></command> with the <option>R</option> option to
update specific packages on that environment.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2><title>How to Manage Boot Environments</title><para>You can manage the boot environments on your system either by using
the <command>beadm</command> command or by using the Package Manager.</para><para>The Package Manager is a GUI that enables you to install, update, and
manage packages on your installed system. If you use the Package Manager to
update all the packages on your system, a clone of the active boot environment
is created. This clone enables you to, if necessary, boot into the boot environment
state that existed before the update process was started.</para><itemizedlist><para>In addition, <emphasis role="strong">starting with the OpenSolaris 2009.06
release</emphasis>, you can use the Package Manager to manage your boot environments
as follows:</para><listitem><para>You can delete old and unused boot environments, in order
to make the disk space available.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can change the default boot environment on your system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can activate a boot environment.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>For instructions, see the online help that is available in the Package
Manager.</para><para>The Package Manager is available on the Main Menubar of the desktop,
for both the OpenSolaris Live CD and the installed OpenSolaris 2009.06 system.
From the Main Menubar, select System &gt; Administration &gt; Package Manager. Or,
select the Get Software icon on the desktop.</para><para>The Package Manager, however, does not provide the full range of options
for managing your boot environments that is available by using the <command>beadm</command> command as described in the following sections.</para><para>For complete instructions about managing boot environments, see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/dev/snapupgrade/snap3.html" type="text">Managing Boot Environments.</ulink>. Or, see the <olink targetptr="beadm" remap="internal"></olink>. </para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="upgrade"><title>Upgrading to the Next OpenSolaris Release</title><para>To upgrade from the OpenSolaris 2008.11 release to the OpenSolaris 2009.06
release, you must use a particular procedure, which is described at <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/project/indiana/resources/relnotes/200811/image-update/" type="text">Updating Your System to OpenSolaris Development Builds</ulink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="troubleshooting"><title>Appendix A: Troubleshooting</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Review the OpenSolaris Release Notes for the current release,
per link at <ulink url="http://www.opensolaris.com/use/" type="url"></ulink>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Email troubleshooting questions to <literal>indiana-discuss@opensolaris.org</literal>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Review the troubleshooting information below.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="login"><title>Troubleshooting Login and Root Specifications</title><task id="fixlogin"><title>How to Troubleshoot Your OpenSolaris Login</title><tasksummary><para>If you are unable to log in to your installed system, use the following
procedure.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>Boot the system in single user mode.</para><para>For instructions,
see <ulink url="http://dlc.sun.com/osol/docs/content/SYSADV1/hbx86boot-68676.html#fvzqr" type="text">x86: How to Boot a System to Run Level S (Single-User Level)</ulink> with
two changes specific to the OpenSolaris 2009.06 release.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>In the instructions at this URL, use the <literal>kernel$</literal> line option in the instructions instead of <literal>kernel</literal> line
option.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Before you are prompted to enter the root password using these
instructions, you will need to enter an account name. The account name can
be root, or any other privileged account, such as &ldquo;jack&rdquo; on the
Live CD, or an account that you created during the installation.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para><emphasis>Optional:</emphasis> To view the existing users and
roles, type:</para><screen>-bash-3.2# <command> cat</command> <filename>/etc/user_attr</filename></screen>
</step><step><para><emphasis>Optional:</emphasis> To delete a user, type:</para><screen>-bash-3.2# <command>userdel <replaceable>username</replaceable></command></screen>
</step><step><para>Create the user name that you want.</para><screen>-bash-3.2# <command>useradd <replaceable>username</replaceable></command></screen>
</step><step><para>Assign a password for the user name.</para><screen>-bash-3.2# <command>passwd <replaceable>username</replaceable></command></screen><para>You will be prompted to type the password twice.</para>
</step><step><para>Assign the root role to that user.</para><screen>-bash-3.2# <command>usermod <option>R</option> root <replaceable>username</replaceable></command></screen>
</step><step><para>Type Exit to return to the installed system.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="nwamd"><title>Appendix B: <literal>nwamd(1M)</literal> Man Page</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><para>In this OpenSolaris release, the <command>nwamd</command> daemon is
enabled by default. <command>nwamd</command> introduces an alternate instance
of the network or physical SMF service that enables automated network configuration.</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="nwam"><title>Appendix: <literal>nwamd(1M)</literal> Man Page</title><para><emphasis role="strong">NAME:</emphasis> <command>nwamd</command> -
network auto-magic daemon</para><para><emphasis role="strong">SYNOPSIS:</emphasis> <filename>/lib/inet/nwamd</filename></para><para><emphasis role="strong">DESCRIPTION:</emphasis> <command>nwamd</command> is a system daemon to manage network interfaces.  This daemon is started
automatically and should not be invoked directly. It does not constitute a
programming interface.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">OPERATION:</emphasis> Whether this daemon is
enabled or not depends on your installation medium. To check, enter the following
at the command line: </para><screen>% <command>svcs svc:/network/physical</command></screen><para> The two instances will be listed: one as disabled, the other as online.
If the <command>nwam</command> instance is online then this daemon will be
running. The two instances correspond to the two modes of network configuration:
the default instance is for manual mode, while the <command>nwam</command> instance is for the automatic mode.</para><para> To go from manual mode to automatic mode:</para><screen>% <command>svcadm disable svc:/network/physical:default</command>
% <command>svcadm enable svc:/network/physical:nwam</command></screen><para> To go from automatic mode to manual mode:</para><screen>% <command>svcadm disable svc:/network/physical:nwam</command>
% <command>svcadm enable svc:/network/physical:default</command></screen><para>CAUTION: When switching modes like this, all network interfaces will
be brought down then back up, thus if a different IP address is configured
in this process, existing applications and sessions may be disrupted.</para><note><para> In automatic mode, there is a limitation that only one link is
active at a time. This mode is thus not recommended for machines which use
more than one link at once. For machines with wired and wireless links, wired
is preferred by default, although this can be adjusted by altering the order
of the lines in the plain text file <filename>/etc/nwam/llp</filename>. Note,
however, that this interface is Volatile and may change in a future release.</para>
</note><para><emphasis role="strong">PROFILES:</emphasis> Note that all interfaces
listed in this section are Volatile and may change in a future release. They
are documented here so that those wishing to experiment with this may do so.
 Profiles are a mechanism for making multiple related changes to the system
configuration after IP service is available. </para><para> There is not direct support for them yet, but a &ldquo;roll your own&rdquo;
mechanism is provided for now. Once an interface is brought up and an IP address
is configured for it, the daemon looks for<filename> /etc/nwam/ulp/check-conditions</filename>; if it exists and is executable, it is run. This is expected to print a
single line of output, which is the name of the profile which the user wishes
to be activated based on the current conditions. If such a line is read successfully
(<filename>foo</filename> in this example), then <filename>/etc/nwam/ulp/foo/bringup</filename> is executed. Likewise, when the interface gets torn down for whatever reason, <filename>/etc/nwam/ulp/foo/teardown</filename> is executed. The <command>bringup</command> and <command>teardown</command> scripts are invoked via <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pfexec</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> with default basic privileges. Samples for each of these scripts can be
found at:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/project/nwam/prototype/check-conditions" type="url"></ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/project/nwam/prototype/bringup" type="url"></ulink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ulink url="http://opensolaris.org/os/project/nwam/prototype/teardown" type="url"></ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><emphasis role="strong">WIRELESS:</emphasis> When no wired link is available,
a scan for wireless LANs will be done, and the resulting list offered via
a GUI pop-up to prompt the console user to select his/her preference. If a
successful connection is made, the WLAN in question will be stored in the
plain text file <filename>/etc/nwam/known_wifi_nets</filename> and subsequently
the daemon may connect to any WLAN in that list without prompting again. Should
a user wish to revoke his/her preference for a WLAN in that list, editing
the file and deleting the line with the entry should suffice. Note, however,
that this interface is Volatile and may change in a future release.</para><para><emphasis role="strong">ATTRIBUTE:</emphasis> See <citerefentry><refentrytitle>attributes</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry> for descriptions of the following attributes:</para><informaltable frame="all"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1"><colspec colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/><thead><row><entry valign="top"><para>ATTRIBUTE TYPE</para>
</entry><entry valign="top"><para>ATTRIBUTE VALUE</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para>Availability</para>
</entry><entry><para>SUNWcsr</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Interface Stability</para>
</entry><entry><para>Volatile</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable><para><emphasis role="strong">SEE ALSO: </emphasis> <citerefentry><refentrytitle>svcs</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>svcadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>attributes</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></para><para><emphasis role="strong">NOTES:</emphasis> The networking service is
managed by the service management facility, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>, under the service identifier:</para><screen>  svc:/network/physical</screen><para>Administrative actions on this service, such as enabling, disabling,
or requesting restart, can be performed using <citerefentry><refentrytitle>svcadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry>. The service's
status can be queried using the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>svcs</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> command.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="beadm"><title>Appendix C: <command>beadm</command> Command
Reference</title><highlights><caution><para><emphasis role="strong">This document is in development for
an upcoming release.</emphasis></para>
</caution><itemizedlist><para>The new <command>beadm</command> utility enables you to perform the
following tasks:</para><listitem><para>Create a new boot environment based on the active boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a new boot environment based on an inactive boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a snapshot of an existing boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a new boot environment based on an existing snapshot</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Create a new boot environment and add a custom title to the
GRUB menu.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Activate an existing, inactive boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Mount a boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Unmount a boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Destroy a boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Destroy a snapshot of a boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Rename an existing, inactive boot environment</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Display information about your boot environment snapshots
and datasets</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="beadmcomref"><title><command>beadm</command> Command
Reference</title><para>The <command>beadm</command> command, <filename>/usr/sbin/beadm</filename>, enables users to manage their boot environments. The following table summarizes
the subcommands and options for the <command>beadm</command> utility.</para><table frame="topbot" pgwide="1" id="gikqv"><title><command>beadm</command> Command</title><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="21.13*"/><colspec colwidth="78.87*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry><para>Subcommands</para>
</entry><entry><para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry><para><command>beadm</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Displays command usage.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm activate</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Makes <literal>beName</literal> the active boot environment on next
reboot.</para><para>Syntax: <command>beadm activate beName</command></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm create</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Creates a new boot environment name, beName. Unless the <option>e</option> option is provided, the new boot environment is created as a clone of the
currently running boot environment.</para><para>Syntax: <command>beadm create [-a] [-d description] [-e non-activeBeName
| beName@snapshot] [-o property=value] beName</command></para><itemizedlist><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-a</literal> &ndash; Activate the
newly created boot environment upon creation. The default is to not activate
the newly created boot environment.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>-d description</literal> &ndash; Use this description
as the title in the GRUB menu that describes this new boot environment. If
this option is not used, beName is used for the title.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-e non-activeBeName</literal> &ndash;
Create a new boot environment from an existing, inactive boot environment.
The default is to create the boot environment from the active boot environment.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-e beName@snapshot</literal> &ndash;
Create a new boot environment from an existing snapshot of the boot environment
named beName.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-o property=value</literal> &ndash;
Create the datasets for new boot environment with specific ZFS properties.
Multiple <literal>-o</literal> options can be specified. See <command>zfs(1M)</command> for more information on the <option>o</option> option.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>beName</literal> &ndash; Name of
the boot environment to create.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>beName@snapshot</literal> &ndash;
Name of an existing snapshot of the boot environment named beName.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm create beName@snapshot</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Creates a snapshot of the existing boot environment named beName.</para><para>Syntax: <command>beadm create beName@snapshot</command></para><para><literal>beName@snapshot</literal> &ndash; The snapshot name must use
the format, <command>beName@snapshotdescription</command>, where <command>beName</command> is the name of an existing boot environment that you want
to make a snapshot from. Enter a custom <command>snapshotdescription</command> to identify the date or purpose of the snapshot.</para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm destroy</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Destroys the boot environment named <command>beName</command> or destroys
an existing snapshot, <command>beName@snapshot</command>, of a boot environment.
Prompts for confirmation before destroying the boot environment.</para><para>Syntax: <command>beadm destroy [-fF] beName | beName@snapshot</command></para><itemizedlist><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-f</literal> &ndash; Forces destruction
of the boot environment even if it is mounted.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-F</literal> &ndash; Forces destruction
of the boot environment without prompting for confirmation.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm list</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Lists information about the existing boot environment, which is <command>beName</command>, or lists information for all boot environments if <command>beName</command> is not provided. The default is to list boot environments
without any additional information.</para><para>Syntax: <literal>beadm list [-a | [-ds] [-H] [beName]</literal></para><itemizedlist><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-a</literal> &ndash; Lists all available
information about the boot environment.  This information includes subordinate
datasets and snapshots.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-d</literal> &ndash; Lists information
about all subordinate datasets hat belong to the boot environment.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-s</literal> &ndash; Lists information
about the snapshots of the boot environment.</para>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>-H</literal> &ndash; Prevents listing
header information. Each field in the output is separated by a semicolon.</para><para>The example is displayed without a header:</para><screen>BE2:no:yes:mounted:/pool1/BE/BE2:6.2G;;;</screen><itemizedlist><para>Without header information, the display information is identified by
the following delimiters:</para><listitem><para><literal>;</literal> &ndash; Delimits boot environments, datasets,
zones, and snapshots.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>:</literal> &ndash; Delimits attributes for boot
environments, datasets, zones, and snapshots.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>,</literal> &ndash; Delimits multiple datasets, zones,
and snapshots.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Multiple boot environments are delimited with a return, a
blank line.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><note><para>The <option>p</option> option can be combined with the other options.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem override="none"><para><literal>beName</literal> &ndash; If <command>beName</command> is not provided, the command results display information
for all boot environments. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm mount</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Mounts a boot environment named <command>beName</command> at mount point.
The mount point must be an already existing, empty directory.</para><para>Syntax: <command>beadm mount beName mountpoint</command></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm rename</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Renames the boot environment named <command>beName</command> to <command>newBeName</command>.</para><para>Syntax: <literal>beadm rename beName newBeName</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para><command>beadm unmount</command></para>
</entry><entry><para>Unmounts the boot environment named <command>beName</command>.</para><para>Syntax: <command>beadm unmount [-f] beName</command></para><para><literal>-f</literal> &ndash; Forcefully unmounts the boot environment
even if it is currently busy.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>For detailed instructions about the <command>beadm</command> utility,
see the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>beadm</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1M</manvolnum></citerefentry> man page.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter><chapter id="ipscli"><title>Appendix D: Using IPS Commands</title><highlights><para>tbd</para>
</highlights><sect1 id="ipscli2"><title>IPS</title><para>TBD</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>