<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()chapter(3)?><chapter id="ugelem-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Elements of Trusted Extensions (Reference)</title><highlights><itemizedlist><para>This chapter explains the key elements of Solaris Trusted Extensions. This chapter covers
the following topics:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugelem-10" remap="internal">Visible Features of Trusted Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugtour-4" remap="internal">Files and Applications in Trusted
Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugelem-40" remap="internal">Password Security in the Solaris
OS</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugelem-42" remap="internal">Front Panel Security (Trusted
CDE)</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="ugelem-10"><title>Visible Features of Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>Trusted Extensions</primary><secondary>visible features</secondary>
</indexterm><para>After you have successfully completed the login process, as explained
in <olink targetptr="uglog-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;2, Logging In to Trusted Extensions
(Tasks)</olink>, you can work within Trusted Extensions. Your work is subject
to security restrictions. Restrictions that are specific to Trusted Extensions include
the label range of the system, your clearance, and your choice of a single-level
or multilevel session. As the following figure illustrates, four features
distinguish a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions from a Solaris system.</para><figure id="ugelem-fig-1"><title>Multilevel Trusted CDE Desktop</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="workspace.basic.eps" width="100"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows labels on windows and icons, the trusted
stripe with the trusted symbol and workspace label.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Label displays &ndash;</emphasis> All
windows, workspaces, files, and applications have a label. The desktop provides
stripes and other indicators for viewing an entity's label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>trusted stripe</primary><secondary>location in CDE</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted stripe</primary><secondary>location in Trusted GNOME</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>visibility</primary><secondary>trusted stripe</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Trusted stripe &ndash;</emphasis> This stripe is a special graphical
security mechanism. In Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE), the trusted stripe is always displayed at
the bottom of the screen. In Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME),
the stripe is displayed at the top of the screen.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Limited access to applications from
the workspace &ndash;</emphasis> The workspace provides access only to those
applications that are permitted in your user account.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Trusted Path menu</primary><secondary>location</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>finding</primary><secondary>Trusted Path menu</secondary></indexterm><emphasis role="strong">Trusted Path menu &ndash;</emphasis> In Trusted CDE, the switch area in the Front Panel provides access
to the Trusted Path menu, which is used to perform security-related tasks.
In Trusted GNOME, the trusted symbol provides
access to the menu.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="ugelem-26"><title>Labels on Trusted Extensions Desktops</title><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary> displayed in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>As discussed in <olink targetptr="ugintro-32" remap="internal">Mandatory Access Control</olink>,
all applications and files in Trusted Extensions have labels. Trusted Extensions displays
labels in the following locations:</para><listitem><para>Window label stripes above the window title bar</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Window icon label stripes under the minimized window</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Window label indicator in the trusted stripe</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Query window label indicator from the Trusted Path menu that
displays the label of the window or icon that is specified by the pointer
location</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><olink targetptr="ugelem-fig-1" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;4&ndash;1</olink> shows
how labels display on a system that is configured to display labels. The system
is using Trusted CDE as its desktop. A site can also be configured to hide labels.
Even if your administrator has configured the system to hide labels, labeling
is still in effect. The Query Window Label menu item can be used to display
the label of a window. For an illustration, see <olink targetptr="ugelem-fig-7" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;3&ndash;4</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-20"><title>Trusted Stripe</title><para><indexterm><primary>trusted stripe</primary><secondary>described </secondary></indexterm>In Trusted CDE, the trusted stripe appears in a reserved area at the
bottom of the screen in all Trusted Extensions sessions. In Trusted GNOME,
the trusted stripe appears at the top of the screen.</para><para>The purpose of the trusted stripe is to give you a visual confirmation
that you are in a legitimate Trusted Extensions session. The stripe indicates
when you are interacting with the trusted computing base (TCB). The stripe
also displays the labels of your current workspace and current window. The
trusted stripe cannot be moved or obscured by other windows or dialog boxes. </para><itemizedlist><para>In Trusted CDE, the trusted stripe has two elements:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">The trusted symbol &ndash;</emphasis> Displays
when the screen focus is security-related.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">The window label &ndash;</emphasis> Optional.
Displays the label of the active window.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><itemizedlist><para>In Trusted GNOME, the trusted stripe has
two additional elements:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">The current user name or role name &ndash;</emphasis> At the right of the trusted symbol, displays the name of the owner
of new processes in the workspace.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Labeled windows &ndash;</emphasis> Displays
the labels of all windows in the workspace.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><figure id="ugtour-35"><title><literal>PUBLIC</literal> Window Label in the
Trusted Stripe</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="win.label.public.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows the trusted stripe without the trusted symbol
and with a workspace label of PUBLIC.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><sect3 id="ugelem-8"><title>Trusted Symbol</title><para><indexterm><primary>trusted symbol</primary><secondary>described</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted computing base (TCB)</primary><secondary>symbol of interacting with</secondary></indexterm>Whenever you
access any portion of the TCB, the trusted symbol appears at the left of the
trusted stripe area. If your configuration suppresses labels, then the trusted
 symbol appears with the trusted stripe. In Trusted CDE, the symbol appears to
the left of the Front Panel. In Trusted GNOME,
the symbol appears at the left of the trusted stripe.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="shield.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Illustration shows the trusted symbol.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><para>The trusted symbol is not displayed when the pointer is focused in a
window or area of the screen that does not affect security. The trusted symbol
cannot be forged. If you see the symbol, you can be sure that you are safely
interacting with the TCB.</para><caution><para><indexterm><primary>no trusted indicator</primary><secondary>troubleshooting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>troubleshooting</primary><secondary>missing trusted indicator</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted indicator</primary><secondary>missing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Security Administrator role</primary><secondary>contacting about missing trusted indicator</secondary></indexterm>If the trusted stripe is missing from your workspace, contact
the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>. The problem
with your system could be serious.</para><para>The trusted stripe should not
appear during login, or when you lock your screen. If the trusted stripe shows,
contact the administrator immediately.</para>
</caution>
</sect3><sect3 id="ugelem-9"><title>Window Label Indicator</title><para><indexterm><primary>Window Label indicator</primary></indexterm>The <emphasis>Window Label</emphasis> indicator displays the label of the active window.
In a multilevel session, the indicator can help identify windows with different
labels in the same workspace. The indicator can also show that you are interacting
with the TCB. For example, when you change your password, the Trusted Path
indicator displays in the trusted stripe.</para><figure id="ugtour-fig-9"><title><literal>Trusted Path</literal> Indicator
in the Trusted Stripe</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="win.trusted.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows the trusted stripe without the trusted symbol
and with a label of Trusted Path.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugtour-4"><title>Files and Applications in Trusted Extensions</title><para>All applications in Trusted Extensions have a level of sensitivity that
is indicated by their label. Applications are <emphasis>subjects</emphasis> in
any data transactions. Subjects must dominate the <emphasis>objects</emphasis> that
the subjects try to access. Objects can be files and sometimes other processes
can be objects. The label information for an application is displayed in the
window label stripe. The label is visible when a window is open and when a
window is minimized. An application's label also appears in the trusted stripe
when the pointer is in the application's window.</para><para>In Trusted Extensions, files are objects in data transactions. Files can
be accessed only by applications whose labels dominate the files' labels.
A file can be viewed from windows that have the same label as the file.</para><para>Some applications use initialization files to configure the environment
for the user. Two special files in your home directory help you access initialization
files at every label. These files enable an application at one label to use
an initialization file that originates in a directory at a different label.
The two special files are <filename>.copy_files</filename> and <filename>.link_files</filename>.</para><sect2 id="ugfile-2"><title><filename>.copy_files</filename> File</title><indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary><filename>$HOME/.copy_files</filename></secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>.copy_files</filename> file</primary><secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The <filename>.copy_files</filename> file stores file names to be copied
when you first change to a workspace with a higher label. <filename>.copy_files</filename> is
stored in your home directory at your minimum label. This file is useful when
you have an application that always writes to a file in your home directory
with a specific name. <filename>.copy_files</filename> enables you to specify
that the application update the file at every label.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugfile-5"><title><filename>.link_files</filename> File</title><indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary><filename>$HOME/.link_files</filename></secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary><filename>.link_files</filename> file</primary><secondary>described</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The <filename>.link_files</filename> file stores file names to be linked
when you first change to a workspace with a higher label. <filename>.link_files</filename> is
stored in your home directory at your minimum label. This file is  useful
when a specific file needs to be available at multiple labels, but the content
must be identical at every label.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugelem-40"><title>Password Security in the Solaris OS</title><indexterm><primary>passwords</primary><secondary>user responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>user responsibilities</primary><secondary>password security</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>responsibilities</primary><secondary>users for password security</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary><tertiary>password security</tertiary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Users who change passwords on a frequent basis shorten the window of
opportunity for intruders to use illegally obtained passwords. Therefore,
your site's security policy can require you to change your password regularly.
The Solaris OS can set content requirements for passwords and enforce password
resetting requirements.  The following are possible resetting requirements:</para><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Minimum number of days between changes &ndash;</emphasis> Prevents you or anyone else from changing your password for a
set number of days.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Maximum number of days between changes &ndash;</emphasis> Requires you to change your password after a set number of days.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Maximum number of inactive days &ndash;</emphasis> Locks
your account after the set number of days of inactivity if the password has
not been changed.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Expiration date &ndash;</emphasis> Requires
you to change your password by a specific date.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>If your administrator has implemented one of the preceding options,
you are sent an email message that warns you to change your password prior
to the cutoff date.</para><itemizedlist><para>Passwords can have content criteria. At minimum, passwords in the Solaris OS must
meet the following criteria:</para><listitem><para>The password must be at least eight characters long.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The password must contain at least two alphabetic characters
and at least one numeric character or one special character.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The new password must differ from your previous password.
You cannot use a reverse or circular shift of the previous password. For this
comparison, uppercase letters and lowercase letters are considered to be equal.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The new password must have at least three characters that
are different from the old password. For this comparison, uppercase letters
and lowercase letters are considered to be equal.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The password must be difficult to guess. Do not use a common
word or a proper name. Programs and individuals who try to break into an account
can use lists to try to guess users' passwords.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>You can change your password by using the Change Password menu item
from the Trusted Path menu. For the steps, see <olink targetptr="ugelem-16" remap="internal">Performing
Trusted Actions</olink>.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugelem-42"><title>Front Panel Security (Trusted CDE)</title><para><indexterm><primary>Front Panel</primary><secondary>description of trusted applications on</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>CDE</primary><secondary>trusted applications on Front Panel</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted applications</primary><secondary>on Front Panel</secondary></indexterm>The Front Panel in Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) is very similar to the Front Panel
that is used in the standard CDE. The Trusted Extensions Front Panel restricts
access to only those applications, files, and utilities that you are allowed
to use. By clicking mouse button 3 anywhere in the workspace switch area,
the <olink targetptr="uggloss-61" remap="internal">Trusted Path menu</olink> is displayed.</para><para>Before you can access a device through the Removable Media Manager,
that device must be allocated by using the Device Allocation Manager. The
Device Allocation Manager is accessed from the Tools subpanel, which is above
the Style Manager icon in the Front Panel.</para><tip><para><indexterm><primary>troubleshooting</primary><secondary>minimized Front Panel</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Front Panel</primary><secondary>restoring when minimized</secondary></indexterm>If you minimize
the Front Panel, you can restore the panel by clicking anywhere in the trusted
stripe.</para>
</tip><para>In Trusted Extensions, Install Icon drop sites are limited to the applications
and files that you are permitted to use at the label of the current workspace.</para><para>For more information about the standard CDE, see the <citetitle>Common
Desktop Environment User's Guide</citetitle>.</para><sect2 id="ugelem-12"><title>Workspace Switch Area</title><indexterm><primary>workspace switch area</primary><secondary>in Trusted Extensions CDE</secondary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, the workspace buttons not only define separate workspaces,
but they also require you to work at particular labels. When you begin a multilevel
session, each workspace is set to the lowest label that you can use. If your
administrator has color-coded the labels at your site, the workspace buttons
display the color of the label. The Trusted Path menu is available from the
workspace switch area.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-32"><title>Trusted Path Menu</title><indexterm><primary>Trusted Path menu</primary><secondary>described </secondary>
</indexterm><para>The Trusted Path menu contains menu items that affect security, as the
following figure shows.</para><figure id="ugelem-fig-3"><title>Trusted Path Menu &ndash; Basic</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="tpmenu.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows the basic Trusted Path menu.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>For example, you change your password or allocate devices with this
menu. For details, see <olink targetptr="ugelem-16" remap="internal">Performing Trusted Actions</olink>.</para><para>In Trusted CDE, the Trusted Path menu has a second version. The Workspace <replaceable>Name</replaceable> version includes additional workspace options. The selections
that appear in your menu depend on how the administrator configured your account.</para><figure id="ugtour-fig-20"><title>Trusted Path Menu &ndash; Workspace <replaceable>Name</replaceable> Version</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="wsmenu.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows the Trusted Path menu that is accessed from
a workspace switch in Trusted CDE.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-13"><title>Clock Security</title><indexterm><primary>clock security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, only an administrator can change the date and time
that is set for your workstation.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-14"><title>Calendar Security</title><indexterm><primary>calendar security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>The calendar shows the appointments for you at the label of your current
workspace only. To view appointments at a different label, you need to open
the calendar at that label.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-15"><title>File Manager Security</title><indexterm><primary>File Manager</primary><secondary>security in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, the File Manager displays files at the label of the
current workspace. To view files at more than one label at a time, you run
the File Manager from workspaces at different labels. You then use the Occupy
Workspace command to display the different File Manager windows in the same
workspace.</para><para>The File Manager enables you to change a file or folder's basic permissions
and access control list (ACL). If you are authorized, you can also move or
link files between File Managers at different labels. For details about File
Manager use, see <olink targetptr="txwork-4" remap="internal">How to View Your Files in a Labeled
Workspace</olink> and <olink targetptr="ugelem-16" remap="internal">Performing Trusted Actions</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-17"><title>Text Editor Security</title><indexterm><primary>Text Editor security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>A text editor can be used to edit files at the label of the current
workspace only. If you are authorized, you can copy information between text
editors at different labels.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-18"><title>Personal Applications Subpanel</title><para>The default applications in the Personal Applications subpanel operate
similarly to the standard CDE environment. The Terminal icon opens the default
shell that is assigned to you by your administrator. To access a web server,
the label of your browser must be the same as the label of the web server.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-19"><title>Mailer Security</title><indexterm><primary>mail security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, all mail messages are labeled.   When you send a
message, it is sent at the label of your mail application. Only hosts and
users that are cleared for that label receive the message. Only users who
are working at that label can view the message.</para><para>If you need to use the vacation message option in your mail application,
you must explicitly enable vacation message replies for each label at which
you typically receive mail. Check with your security administrator for your
site's security policy on vacation messages.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-21"><title>Printer Security</title><indexterm><primary>Printer tool security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>The Print Manager in the Personal Printers subpanel displays icons for
all printers that are accredited up to your clearance. However, you can use
only those printers that are accredited to print documents at the label of
the current workspace.</para><itemizedlist><para>A typical print job in Trusted Extensions includes labels and extra pages,
as follows:</para><listitem><para>A banner page at the beginning of the print job identifies
the print job, handling instructions, and labels that are appropriate to the
site.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Body pages are labeled at the header and the footer.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A trailer page at the end of the print job signals the end
of the job.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>printing</primary><secondary>typical labeled banner page</secondary></indexterm>A typical banner page appears in the following
figure. The words <literal>JOB START</literal> indicate the banner page.</para><figure id="ugelem-fig-9"><title>Typical Banner Page of a Labeled Print Job</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="TypicalPrintBanr.eps"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Illustration shows job number and handling instructions
on a typical print banner page.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>For the exact security information regarding printing at your site,
see your administrator.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-23"><title>Style Manager Security</title><indexterm><primary>Style Manager</primary><secondary>limitations in Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE)</secondary>
</indexterm><para>With three exceptions, the Style Manager operates in the same manner
as on a Solaris system.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The Style Manager cannot be run from the Application Manager
when Trusted Extensions is configured because the Style Manager requires the 
trusted path. Run the Style Manager from the Front Panel and the Workspace
menu, where the Style Manager has the trusted path.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The Screen Saver and Screen Lock options are limited. Your
administrator specifies the maximum amount of time that your system can be
idle prior to being locked. You can reduce the idle time. You cannot increase
the idle time beyond the maximum. You can still choose a pattern for when
the screen is locked. See your administrator if you are not familiar with
the policy at your site.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The Startup control sets your startup session settings according
to the label or clearance that you specify at login. Thus, you can save a
different workspace configuration for each label in your account label range.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-24"><title>Application Manager Security</title><indexterm><primary>Application Manager security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>The Application Manager provides access to only those applications and
utilities that your administrator has assigned to you. In a role, you have
access to a different set of applications and capabilities. Remember that
the ability of a function to operate on a file depends on the label of the
current workspace.</para><para>Similarly, although you can add applications to the Personal Application
subpanel by dropping icons onto the Install Icon drop site, you can only run
an application if your administrator has assigned the application to you.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugelem-25"><title>Trash Can Security</title><indexterm><primary>Trash Can security in Trusted Extensions</primary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, the trash can stores files to be deleted by label.
Although you can drop files at any label in the trash can, the trash can displays
files at the current label only. You must delete sensitive information as
soon as the information is in the trash can.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugelem-28"><title>Workspace Security (Trusted GNOME)</title><indexterm><primary>Trusted GNOME</primary><secondary>workspace security</secondary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, Trusted GNOME provides
equivalent security to Trusted CDE, but the look and feel is different. As in Trusted CDE,
desktop applications are label-aware. Applications run at the label of the
current workspace, and display information only at the label of the process
that opened the application.</para><itemizedlist><para>The location of security features differs in Trusted GNOME from
their location in Trusted CDE. The behavior can also be different.</para><listitem><para>In Trusted GNOME, the Trusted
Path menu is available from the trusted stripe.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The label name of a window in the task list on the panel appears
in a tooltip when the mouse hovers over the window. Similarly, the label name
of a workspace in the switch area appears in the tooltip.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>To change a role, you click the user or role name in the trusted
stripe and choose the role.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>To add a workspace at a particular label, you select an existing
workspace and change its label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The desktop can be configured so that each workspace reflects
the color of the label at which you are working in that workspace.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000028683 0?>