<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()chapter(4)?><glossary id="uggloss-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Glossary</title><glossentry id="uggloss-29"><glossterm>access control list (ACL)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. An ACL extends <olink targetptr="uggloss-52" remap="internal">discretionary
access control (DAC)</olink> to use a list of permission specifications (ACL
entries) that apply to specific users and specific groups. An ACL allows finer-grained
control than the control that standard UNIX <olink targetptr="uggloss-22" remap="internal">permissions</olink> provides.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-54"><glossterm>access permission</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of most computer systems. Access permission
gives the user the right to read, write, execute, or view the name of a file
or directory. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-52" remap="internal">discretionary access
control (DAC)</olink> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-48" remap="internal">mandatory access control
(MAC)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-66"><glossterm>account label range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The set of <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink>s that
are assigned by the security administrator to a user or <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> for working on a system that is configured
with Trusted Extensions. A label range is defined at the upper end by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-89" remap="internal">user clearance</olink> and at the lower end by the
user's <olink targetptr="uggloss-51" remap="internal">minimum label</olink>. The set is limited
to <olink targetptr="uggloss-87" remap="internal">well-formed label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-75"><glossterm>accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>A set of labels that are approved for a class of users or
resources. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-79" remap="internal">system accreditation range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-85" remap="internal">user accreditation range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings file</olink>, and <olink targetptr="uggloss-77" remap="internal">network accreditation range</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-86"><glossterm>action</glossterm><glossdef><para>An application that can be accessed from the CDE (Common Desktop
Environment) graphical user interface. An action is represented by an icon.
The action consists of one or more commands and optional user prompts. In Trusted Extensions,
an action is only available to a user if the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security
administrator</olink> has included the action in a <olink targetptr="uggloss-78" remap="internal">rights profile</olink> that is assigned to the user's account. Similarly,
certain functions of the action might be available only if the security administrator
has assigned the appropriate <olink targetptr="uggloss-32" remap="internal">authorization</olink>s
and <olink targetptr="uggloss-97" remap="internal">privilege</olink>s in that rights profile.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-62"><glossterm>administrative labels</glossterm><glossdef><para>Two special labels intended for administrative files only: <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> and <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>. <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> is
the lowest label in the system with no compartments. This label is strictly
dominated by all labels in the system. Information at <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> can
be read by all but can only be written by a user in a <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> who is working at the <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant> label. <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> is the highest label in the system with all compartments.
This label strictly dominates all labels in the system. Information at <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> can only be read by users in roles that operate at <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant>. Administrative labels are used as <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> or <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> for roles and
systems. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-74" remap="internal">dominating label</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-60"><glossterm>allocatable device</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. An allocatable device can be used by one user
at a time, and is capable of importing or exporting data from the system.
The <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> determines
which users are authorized to access which allocatable devices. Allocatable
devices include tape drives, floppy drives, audio devices, and CD-ROM devices.
See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-71" remap="internal">device allocation</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-68"><glossterm>audit ID (AUID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. An audit ID represents the login user. the AUID
is unchanged after the user assumes a role, so is used to identify the user
for <olink targetptr="uggloss-81" remap="internal">auditing</olink> purposes. The audit ID
always represents the user for auditing even when the user acquires <olink targetptr="uggloss-76" remap="internal">effective UIDs/GIDs</olink>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-83" remap="internal">user ID (UID)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-81"><glossterm>auditing</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. Auditing is a process for capturing user activity
and other events on the system, then storing this information in a set of
files that is called an <emphasis>audit trail</emphasis>. Auditing produces
system activity reports to fulfill site security policy.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-32"><glossterm>authorization</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. An authorization grants permission to a user to
perform an action that is otherwise prohibited by security policy. The <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> assigns authorizations
to <olink targetptr="uggloss-78" remap="internal">rights profile</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.
Rights profiles are then assigned to user or <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> accounts.
Some commands and actions do not function fully unless the user has the necessary
authorizations. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-97" remap="internal">privilege</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-47"><glossterm>classification</glossterm><glossdef><para>A component of a <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink> or
a <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink>. A classification indicates
a hierarchical level of security, for example, <literal>TOP SECRET</literal> or <literal>UNCLASSIFIED</literal>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-96"><glossterm>clearance</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> that defines
the upper boundary of a <olink targetptr="uggloss-67" remap="internal">label range</olink>.
A clearance has two components: a <olink targetptr="uggloss-47" remap="internal">classification</olink> and
zero or more <olink targetptr="uggloss-53" remap="internal">compartment</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.
A clearance does not need to be a <olink targetptr="uggloss-87" remap="internal">well-formed
label</olink>. A clearance defines a theoretical boundary, not necessarily
an actual label. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-89" remap="internal">user clearance</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-38" remap="internal">session clearance</olink>, and <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-5"><glossterm>Common Desktop Environment (CDE)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A graphical desktop that includes a session manager, a window
manager, and various desktop tools. Trusted Extensions adds trusted applications
to the desktop, such as the <olink targetptr="uggloss-28" remap="internal">label builder</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-24" remap="internal">Device Allocation Manager</olink>, and <olink targetptr="uggloss-44" remap="internal">Selection Manager</olink>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-100" remap="internal">Trusted GNOME</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-53"><glossterm>compartment</glossterm><glossdef><para>A nonhierarchical component of a <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> that is used with the <olink targetptr="uggloss-47" remap="internal">classification</olink> component
to form a <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink> or a <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink>. A compartment represents a group of
users with a potential need to access this information, such as an engineering
department or a multidisciplinary project team.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-6"><glossterm>compartmented mode workstation (CMW)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A computing system that fulfills the government requirements
for a trusted workstation as stated in <citetitle>Security Requirements for
System High and Compartmented Mode Workstations</citetitle>, DIA document
number DDS-2600-5502-87. Specifically, it defines a trusted, X Window System-based
operating system for UNIX workstations.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-7"><glossterm>covert channel</glossterm><glossdef><para>A communication channel that is not normally intended for
data communication. A covert channel allows a process to transfer information
indirectly in a manner that violates the intent of the security policy.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-9"><glossterm>deallocated device</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A deallocated device is no longer allocated to
a user for exclusive use. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-71" remap="internal">device allocation</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-10"><glossterm>device</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-60" remap="internal">allocatable device</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-71"><glossterm>device allocation</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. Device allocation is a mechanism for protecting
the information on an <olink targetptr="uggloss-60" remap="internal">allocatable device</olink> from
access by anyone except the user who allocates the device. When the device
is deallocated, device clean scripts are run to clean information from the
device before the device can be accessed again by another user. In Trusted Extensions,
device allocation is handled by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-24" remap="internal">Device Allocation
Manager</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-24"><glossterm>Device Allocation Manager</glossterm><glossdef><para>A trusted application of Trusted Extensions. This GUI is used
to configure devices, and to allocate and deallocate devices. Device configuration
includes adding authorization requirements to a device.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-52"><glossterm>discretionary access control (DAC)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An access control mechanism that allows the owner of a file
or directory to grant or deny access to other users. The owner assigns read,
write, and execute <olink targetptr="uggloss-22" remap="internal">permissions</olink> to the
owner, the user group to which the owner belongs, and a category called other,
which refers to all other unspecified users. The owner can also specify an <olink targetptr="uggloss-29" remap="internal">access control list (ACL)</olink>. An ACL lets the
owner assign permissions specifically to additional users and additional groups.
Contrast with <olink targetptr="uggloss-48" remap="internal">mandatory access control (MAC)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-11"><glossterm>disjoint label</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-74" remap="internal">dominating label</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-74"><glossterm>dominating label</glossterm><glossdef><para>In a comparison of two labels, the label whose <olink targetptr="uggloss-47" remap="internal">classification</olink> component is higher than or
equal to the second label's classification and whose <olink targetptr="uggloss-53" remap="internal">compartment</olink> components include all of the second
label's compartment components. If the components are the same, the labels
are said to dominate each other and are <emphasis>equal</emphasis>. If one
label dominates the other and the labels are not equal, the first label is
said to <emphasis>strictly dominate</emphasis> the other. Two labels are <emphasis>disjoint</emphasis> if they are not equal and neither label is dominant.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-12"><glossterm>downgraded label</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> of an object
that has been changed to a value that does not dominate the previous value
of the label.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-76"><glossterm>effective UIDs/GIDs</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. Effective IDs override a real ID when necessary
to run a particular program or an option of a program. The <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> assigns an effective
UID to a command or action in a <olink targetptr="uggloss-78" remap="internal">rights profile</olink> when
that command or action must be run by a specific user, most often when the
command must be run as root. Effective group IDs are used in the same fashion.
Note that the use of the <command>setuid</command> command as in conventional
UNIX systems might not work due to the need for privileges.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-56"><glossterm>evaluatable configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>A computer system that meets a set standard of government
security requirements. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-98" remap="internal">extended configuration</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-98"><glossterm>extended configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>A computer system that is no longer an <olink targetptr="uggloss-56" remap="internal">evaluatable configuration</olink> due to modifications
that have broken security policy.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-13"><glossterm>fallback mechanism</glossterm><glossdef><para>A shortcut method for specifying IP addresses in the <filename>tnrhtp</filename> database. For IPv4 addresses, the fallback mechanism recognizes <literal>0</literal> as a wildcard for a subnet.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-14"><glossterm>gateway</glossterm><glossdef><para>A host that has more than one network interface. Such a host
can be  used to connect two or more networks. When the gateway is a Trusted Extensions host,
 the gateway can restrict traffic to a particular label.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-99"><glossterm>group ID (GID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A GID is an integer that identifies a group of
users who have common <olink targetptr="uggloss-54" remap="internal">access permission</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-52" remap="internal">discretionary access
control (DAC)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-50"><glossterm>host</glossterm><glossdef><para>A computer attached to a network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-15"><glossterm>host template</glossterm><glossdef><para>A record in the <filename>tnrhtp</filename> database that
defines the <olink targetptr="uggloss-42" remap="internal">security attribute</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> of
a class of hosts that can access the Trusted Extensions network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-16"><glossterm>host type</glossterm><glossdef><para>A classification of a <olink targetptr="uggloss-50" remap="internal">host</olink>.
The  classification is used for network communications. The definitions of
host types are  stored in the <filename>tnrhtp</filename> database. The host
type determines whether the CIPSO network protocol is used to communicate
with other hosts on the network. <emphasis>Network protocol</emphasis> refers
to the rules for packaging communication information.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-100"><glossterm>Trusted GNOME</glossterm><glossdef><para>A graphical desktop that includes a session manager, a window
manager, and various desktop tools. Trusted GNOME is
a fully accessible desktop.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-95"><glossterm>label</glossterm><glossdef><para>Also referred to as a sensitivity label. A label indicates
the security level of an entity. An entity is a file, directory, process,
device, or network interface. The label of an entity is used to determine
whether access should be permitted in a particular transaction. Labels have
two components: a <olink targetptr="uggloss-47" remap="internal">classification</olink> that
indicates the hierarchical level of security, and zero or more <olink targetptr="uggloss-53" remap="internal">compartment</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> for defining
who can access the entity at a given classification. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-28"><glossterm>label builder</glossterm><glossdef><para>A trusted application of Trusted Extensions. This GUI enables
users to choose a session clearance or a session label. The <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink> or <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> must
be within the <olink targetptr="uggloss-66" remap="internal">account label range</olink> that
the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> has assigned
to the user.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-84"><glossterm>label encodings file</glossterm><glossdef><para>A file that is managed by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security
administrator</olink>. The encodings file contains the definitions for all
valid <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. The file also
defines the <olink targetptr="uggloss-79" remap="internal">system accreditation range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-85" remap="internal">user accreditation range</olink>, and defines the security
information  on printouts at the site.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-67"><glossterm>label range</glossterm><glossdef><para>Any set of <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> that are bounded on the upper end by a <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink> or maximum label, on the lower end by a minimum label, and
that consist of <olink targetptr="uggloss-87" remap="internal">well-formed label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. Label ranges are used to enforce <olink targetptr="uggloss-48" remap="internal">mandatory
access control (MAC)</olink>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label
encodings file</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-66" remap="internal">account label range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-75" remap="internal">accreditation range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-77" remap="internal">network accreditation range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-73" remap="internal">session
range</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-79" remap="internal">system accreditation range</olink>,
and <olink targetptr="uggloss-85" remap="internal">user accreditation range</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-19"><glossterm>label view</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature that displays the <olink targetptr="uggloss-62" remap="internal">administrative labels</olink> or substitutes unclassified
placeholders for the administrative labels. For example, if  security policy
forbids exposing the labels <constant>ADMIN_HIGH</constant> and <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>, the labels <constant>RESTRICTED</constant> and <constant>PUBLIC</constant> can
be substituted.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-88"><glossterm>labeled workspace</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE) or a Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME) workspace.
A labeled workspace labels every activity that is launched from the workspace
with the <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> of the workspace. When
users move a window into a workspace of a different label, the moved window
 retains its original label.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-20"><glossterm>least privilege</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-57" remap="internal">principle of least privilege</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-48"><glossterm>mandatory access control (MAC)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A system-enforced access control mechanism that uses <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> to enforce security
policy. A clearance or a label is a security level. MAC associates the programs
that a user runs with the security level  at which the user chooses to work
in the session. MAC then permits access to information, programs, and devices
at the same or lower level only. MAC also prevents users from writing to files
at lower levels. MAC cannot be overridden without special <olink targetptr="uggloss-32" remap="internal">authorization</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> or <olink targetptr="uggloss-97" remap="internal">privilege</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. Contrast with <olink targetptr="uggloss-52" remap="internal">discretionary access control (DAC)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-51"><glossterm>minimum label</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> that is assigned
to a user as the lower bound of the set of labels at which that user can work.
When a user first begins a Trusted Extensions session, the minimum label is the
 user's default label. At login, the user can choose a different label for
the initial label.</para><para>Also, the lowest label that is permitted to
any non-administrative user. The minimum label is assigned by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> and defines the bottom
of the <olink targetptr="uggloss-85" remap="internal">user accreditation range</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-77"><glossterm>network accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The set of <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> within which Trusted Extensions hosts are permitted to communicate
on a network. The set can be a list of four discrete labels.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-17"><glossterm>object</glossterm><glossdef><para>A passive entity that contains or receives data, such as a
data file, directory, printer, or other device. An object is acted upon by <olink targetptr="uggloss-93" remap="internal">subject</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. In some cases,
a <olink targetptr="uggloss-18" remap="internal">process</olink> can be an object, such as
when you send a signal to a process.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-33"><glossterm>operator</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> that can be assigned
to the user or users who are responsible for backing up systems.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-23"><glossterm>ordinary user</glossterm><glossdef><para>A user who holds no special <olink targetptr="uggloss-32" remap="internal">authorization</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> that allow exceptions from the standard security
policies of the system. Typically, an ordinary user cannot assume an administrative <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-22"><glossterm>permissions</glossterm><glossdef><para>A set of codes that indicate which users are allowed to read,
write, or execute the file or directory (folder). Users are classified as
owner, group (the owner's group), and other (everyone else). Read permission
(indicated by <emphasis>r</emphasis>) lets the user read the contents of a
file or, if a directory, list the files in the folder. Write permission (<emphasis>w</emphasis>) lets the user make changes to a file or, if a folder, add or
delete files. Execute permission (<emphasis>e</emphasis>) lets the user run
the file if the file is executable. If the file is a directory, execute permission
lets the user read or search the files in the directory. Also referred to
as UNIX permissions or permission bits.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-57"><glossterm>principle of least privilege</glossterm><glossdef><para>The security principle that restricts users to only those
functions that are necessary to perform their jobs. The principle is applied
in Trusted Extensions by making privileges available to programs on an as-needed
basis. Privileges are available on an as-needed basis for specific purposes
only.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-97"><glossterm>privilege</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A privilege is a permission that is granted to
a program by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>.
A privilege can be required to override some aspect of security policy. See
also <olink targetptr="uggloss-32" remap="internal">authorization</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-25"><glossterm>privileged process</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A privileged <olink targetptr="uggloss-18" remap="internal">process</olink> runs
with assigned  has <olink targetptr="uggloss-97" remap="internal">privilege</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-18"><glossterm>process</glossterm><glossdef><para>A running program. Trusted Extensions processes have Solaris <olink targetptr="uggloss-42" remap="internal">security attribute</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>, such
as <olink targetptr="uggloss-83" remap="internal">user ID (UID)</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-99" remap="internal">group ID (GID)</olink>, the user's <olink targetptr="uggloss-68" remap="internal">audit ID (AUID)</olink>, and <olink targetptr="uggloss-97" remap="internal">privilege</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. Trusted Extensions adds a <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> to every process.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-26"><glossterm>profile</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-78" remap="internal">rights profile</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-27"><glossterm>profile shell</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A version of the Bourne shell that enables a user
to run programs with <olink targetptr="uggloss-42" remap="internal">security attribute</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-162"><glossterm>reading down</glossterm><glossdef><para>The ability of a <olink targetptr="uggloss-93" remap="internal">subject</olink> to
view an <olink targetptr="uggloss-17" remap="internal">object</olink> whose <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> the subject dominates. Security policy
generally allows reading down. For example, a text editor program that runs
at <literal>Secret</literal> can read <literal>Unclassified</literal> data.
See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-48" remap="internal">mandatory access control (MAC)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-78"><glossterm>rights profile</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A rights profile enables a site's <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> to bundle commands and
CDE actions with <olink targetptr="uggloss-42" remap="internal">security attribute</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. Attributes such as user <olink targetptr="uggloss-32" remap="internal">authorization</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-97" remap="internal">privilege</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> enable the commands and actions to succeed. A rights profile
generally contains related tasks. A profile can be assigned to users and to <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-70"><glossterm>role</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A role is a special account that gives the user
who assumes the role access to certain applications with the <olink targetptr="uggloss-42" remap="internal">security attribute</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> that
are necessary for performing the specific tasks.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-82"><glossterm>security administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>On system that is configured with Trusted Extensions, the <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> that is assigned to the user or users
who are responsible for defining and for enforcing security policy. The security
administrator can work at any label in the <olink targetptr="uggloss-79" remap="internal">system
accreditation range</olink>, and potentially has access to all information
at the site. The security administrator configures the <olink targetptr="uggloss-42" remap="internal">security attribute</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> for
all users and equipment. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings
file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-42"><glossterm>security attribute</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A property of an entity, such as a process, zone,
user, or device, that is related to security. Security attributes include
identification values such as <olink targetptr="uggloss-83" remap="internal">user ID (UID)</olink> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-99" remap="internal">group ID (GID)</olink>. Attributes that are specific
to Trusted Extensions include <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-67" remap="internal">label range</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>. Note that
only certain security attributes apply to a particular type of entity.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-30"><glossterm>security policy</glossterm><glossdef><para><indexterm><primary>security policy</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>The set of DAC, MAC, and label rules that define how information
can be accessed and by whom. At a customer site, the set of rules that defines
the sensitivity of the information that is processed at that site. Policy
includes the measures that are used to protect the information from unauthorized
access.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-44"><glossterm>Selection Manager</glossterm><glossdef><para>A trusted application of Trusted Extensions. This GUI appears
when authorized users attempt to upgrade information or downgrade information.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-94"><glossterm>sensitivity label</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-65"><glossterm>session</glossterm><glossdef><para>The time between logging in to a Trusted Extensions host and logging
out from the host. The <olink targetptr="uggloss-80" remap="internal">trusted stripe</olink> appears
in all Trusted Extensions sessions to confirm that users are not being <olink targetptr="uggloss-92" remap="internal">spoof</olink>ed by a counterfeit system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-38"><glossterm>session clearance</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink> set at login
that defines the upper boundary of <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis> for a Trusted Extensions <olink targetptr="uggloss-65" remap="internal">session</olink>.
If the user is permitted to set the session clearance, the user can specify
any value within the user's <olink targetptr="uggloss-66" remap="internal">account label range</olink>.
If the user's account is configured for forced single-level sessions, the
session clearance is set to the default value specified by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-73"><glossterm>session range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The set of labels that are available to a user during a Trusted Extensions session.
The session range is bounded at the upper boundary by the user's <olink targetptr="uggloss-38" remap="internal">session clearance</olink> and at the lower end by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-51" remap="internal">minimum label</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-31"><glossterm>single-label configuration</glossterm><glossdef><para>A user account that has been configured for operation at a
single <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> only. Also called a single-level
configuration.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-92"><glossterm>spoof</glossterm><glossdef><para><indexterm><primary>spoofing</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>To counterfeit a software program in order to illegally get access
to information on a system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-59"><glossterm>strict dominance</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-74" remap="internal">dominating label</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-93"><glossterm>subject</glossterm><glossdef><para>An active entity, usually a <olink targetptr="uggloss-18" remap="internal">process</olink> that runs on behalf of a user or <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink>.
A subject causes information to flow among <olink targetptr="uggloss-17" remap="internal">object</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>, or changes the system state.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-79"><glossterm>system accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The set of all valid labels for a site. The set includes the <olink targetptr="uggloss-62" remap="internal">administrative labels</olink> that are available to
the site's <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-161" remap="internal">system administrator</olink>. The system accreditation
range is defined in the <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-161"><glossterm>system administrator</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. The System Administrator <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> can be assigned to the user or users who
are responsible for performing standard system management tasks such as setting
up the non-security-relevant portions of user accounts. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-34"><glossterm>trusted application</glossterm><glossdef><para>An application that has been granted one or more privileges.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-40"><glossterm>trusted computing base (TCB)</glossterm><glossdef><para>The part of a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions that
affects security. The TCB includes software, hardware, firmware, documentation,
and administrative procedures. Utility programs and application programs that
can access security-related files are all part of the trusted computing base.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-35"><glossterm>trusted facilities management</glossterm><glossdef><para>All activities associated with system administration in a
conventional UNIX system, plus all of the administrative activities that are
necessary to maintain the security of a distributed system and the data that
the system contains.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-36"><glossterm>trusted path</glossterm><glossdef><para>Refers to the mechanism for accessing actions and commands
that are permitted to interact with the <olink targetptr="uggloss-40" remap="internal">trusted
computing base (TCB)</olink>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-61" remap="internal">Trusted
Path menu</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-91" remap="internal">trusted symbol</olink>, and <olink targetptr="uggloss-80" remap="internal">trusted stripe</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-61"><glossterm>Trusted Path menu</glossterm><glossdef><para>A menu of Trusted Extensions operations that is displayed by holding
down mouse button 3 over the switch area of the Front Panel. The menu selections
fall into three categories: workspace-oriented selections, <olink targetptr="uggloss-70" remap="internal">role</olink> assumption selections, and security-related
tasks.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-80"><glossterm>trusted stripe</glossterm><glossdef><para>A screen-wide rectangular graphic in a reserved area of the
screen. The trusted stripe appears in all Trusted Extensions sessions  to confirm
valid Trusted Extensions <olink targetptr="uggloss-65" remap="internal">session</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.
Depending on a site's configuration, the trusted stripe has one or two components:
(1) a mandatory <olink targetptr="uggloss-91" remap="internal">trusted symbol</olink> to indicate
interaction with the <olink targetptr="uggloss-40" remap="internal">trusted computing base
(TCB)</olink>, and (2) an optional <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> to
indicate the label of the current window or workspace.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-91"><glossterm>trusted symbol</glossterm><glossdef><para>The symbol that appears at the left of the <olink targetptr="uggloss-80" remap="internal">trusted stripe</olink> area. The symbol is displayed
whenever the user accesses any portion of the <olink targetptr="uggloss-40" remap="internal">trusted
computing base (TCB)</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-37"><glossterm>upgraded label</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> of an object
that has been changed to a value that dominates the previous value of the
label.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-85"><glossterm>user accreditation range</glossterm><glossdef><para>The largest set of labels that the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> can potentially assign to a user at a specific
site. The user accreditation range excludes the <olink targetptr="uggloss-62" remap="internal">administrative
labels</olink> and any label combinations that are available to administrators
only. The user accreditation range is defined in the <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-89"><glossterm>user clearance</glossterm><glossdef><para>A clearance that is assigned by the <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>. A user clearance defines the upper boundary
of a user's <olink targetptr="uggloss-66" remap="internal">account label range</olink>. The
user's clearance determines the highest label at which the user is permitted
to work. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-96" remap="internal">clearance</olink> and <olink targetptr="uggloss-38" remap="internal">session clearance</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-83"><glossterm>user ID (UID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A security feature of the Solaris OS. A UID identifies a user for the purposes of <olink targetptr="uggloss-52" remap="internal">discretionary access control (DAC)</olink>, <olink targetptr="uggloss-48" remap="internal">mandatory access control (MAC)</olink>, and <olink targetptr="uggloss-81" remap="internal">auditing</olink>. See also <olink targetptr="uggloss-54" remap="internal">access
permission</olink><emphasis>s</emphasis>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-87"><glossterm>well-formed label</glossterm><glossdef><para>A <olink targetptr="uggloss-95" remap="internal">label</olink> that can be
included in a range, because the label is permitted by all applicable rules
in the <olink targetptr="uggloss-84" remap="internal">label encodings file</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="uggloss-39"><glossterm>workspace</glossterm><glossdef><para>See <olink targetptr="uggloss-88" remap="internal">labeled workspace</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary><?Pub *0000039285 0?>