<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()?><chapter id="ugintro-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Introduction to Solaris Trusted Extensions Software</title><highlights><itemizedlist><para>This chapter introduces you to the labels and other security features
that <trademark>Solaris</trademark> Trusted Extensions software adds to the Solaris Operating System (Solaris OS).</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugintro-10" remap="internal">What Is Trusted Extensions Software?</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugintro-12" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Protects
Against Intruders</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugintro-14" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Provides
Discretionary and Mandatory Access Control</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugintro-16" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Separates
Information by Label</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="ugintro-18" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Enables Secure
Administration</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="ugintro-10"><title>What Is Trusted Extensions Software?</title><indexterm><primary>procedures</primary><see>users</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>tasks</primary><see>users</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>information</primary><see>data</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>profiles</primary><see>rights profiles</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary><command>pfsh</command> command</primary><see>profile shell</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>admin role</primary><see>System Administrator role</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>secadmin role</primary><see>Security Administrator role</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>oper role</primary><see>Operator role</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>sensitivity labels</primary><see>labels</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><seealso>clearances</seealso>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>policy</primary><see>security policy</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>peripheral devices</primary><see>devices</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE)</primary><see>CDE</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>containers</primary><see>zones</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>login process</primary><see>logging in</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>using a device</primary><see>allocating a device</see>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Trusted Extensions</primary><secondary>overview</secondary>
</indexterm><para>As the following logo indicates, the Trusted Extensions software package
is added to the Solaris OS.</para><figure><title>Trusted Extensions Logo in CDE</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="txDtlogo.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The title describes the graphic.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para><indexterm><primary>security policy</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>security practices</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>Trusted Extensions provides special security features for your system.
These features enable an organization to define and implement a security policy
on a Solaris system. A <emphasis>security policy</emphasis> is the set
of rules and practices that help protect information and other resources,
such as computer hardware, at your site. Typically, security rules handle
such issues as who has access to which information or who is allowed to write
data to removable media. <emphasis>Security practices</emphasis> are recommended
procedures for performing tasks.</para><para>The following sections describe some major security features that Trusted Extensions provides.
The text indicates which security features are configurable.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugintro-12"><title>Trusted Extensions Protects Against Intruders</title><para>Trusted Extensions software adds features to the Solaris OS that protect against
intruders. Trusted Extensions also relies on some Solaris features, such
as password protection. Trusted Extensions adds a password change GUI for roles.
Auditing is enabled by default.</para><sect2 id="ugintro-15"><title>Access to the Trusted Computing Base
Is Limited</title><para><indexterm><primary>trusted computing base (TCB)</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>The term <firstterm>trusted computing base</firstterm> (<emphasis>TCB</emphasis>) refers to the part of the Trusted Extensions software that handles
events that are relevant to security. The TCB includes software, hardware,
firmware, documentation, and administrative procedures. Utilities and application
programs that can access security-related files are all part of the TCB. Your
administrator sets limits on all potential interactions that you can have
with the TCB. Such interactions include programs that you need to perform
your job, files that you are allowed to access, and utilities that can affect
security.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-3"><title>Mandatory Access Control Protects Information</title><para>If an intruder manages to successfully log in to the system, further
obstacles prevent access to information. Files and other resources are protected
by access control. As in the Solaris OS, access control can be set by the owner
of the information. In Trusted Extensions, access is also controlled by the system.
For details, see <olink targetptr="ugintro-14" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Provides
Discretionary and Mandatory Access Control</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-7"><title>Peripheral Devices Are Protected</title><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>protecting</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>authorizations</primary><secondary>for allocating devices</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>In Trusted Extensions, administrators control access to local peripheral
devices such as tape drives, CD-ROM drives, printers, and microphones. Access
can be granted on a user-by-user basis. The software restricts access to peripheral
devices as follows:</para><listitem><para>By default, devices must be allocated for use.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You must be authorized to access devices that control removable
media.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Remote users cannot use local devices such as microphones
or CD-ROM drives. Only local users can allocate a device.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-5"><title>Programs That Spoof Users Are Prevented</title><para><indexterm><primary>spoofing</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted symbol</primary><secondary>tamper-proof icon</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted computing base (TCB)</primary><secondary>symbol of interacting with</secondary></indexterm>To &ldquo;spoof&rdquo;
means to imitate. Intruders sometimes spoof login or other legitimate programs
to intercept passwords or other sensitive data. Trusted Extensions protects you
from hostile spoofing programs by displaying the following <firstterm>trusted
 symbol</firstterm>, a clearly recognizable, tamper-proof icon at the bottom
of the screen.</para><figure id="ugintro-fig-6"><title>Trusted Symbol</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="shield.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Illustration shows the Trusted Symbol.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>This symbol is displayed whenever you interact with the trusted computing
base (TCB). The presence of the symbol ensures the safety of performing security-related
transactions. No visible symbol indicates a potential security breach. The
following figure shows the trusted symbol.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugintro-14"><title>Trusted Extensions Provides Discretionary and Mandatory
Access Control</title><para>Trusted Extensions controls which users can access which information by
providing both discretionary and mandatory access control.</para><sect2 id="ugintro-8"><title>Discretionary Access Control</title><indexterm><primary>discretionary access control (DAC)</primary><secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>protecting files</primary><secondary>DAC</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>at discretion of file owner</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access control lists (ACLs)</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access control</primary><secondary>permission bits</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access control</primary><secondary>access control lists (ACLs)</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>access control</primary><secondary>discretionary access control (DAC)</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Discretionary access control (DAC) is a software mechanism for controlling
user access to files and directories. DAC leaves setting protections for files
and directories to the owner's discretion. The two forms of DAC are <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> permission bits and access control lists
(ACLs).</para><para>Permission bits let the owner set read, write, and execute protection
by owner, group, and other users. In traditional UNIX systems, the superuser
or <literal>root</literal> user can override DAC protection. With Trusted Extensions software,
the ability to override DAC is permitted for administrators and authorized
users only. ACLs provide a finer granularity of access control. ACLs enable
owners to specify separate permissions for specific users and specific groups.
For more information, see <olink targetdoc="group-sa" targetptr="secfile-1" remap="external">Chapter 7, <citetitle remap="chapter">Controlling Access to Files (Tasks),</citetitle> in <citetitle remap="book">System Administration Guide: Security Services</citetitle></olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-32"><title>Mandatory Access Control</title><indexterm><primary>access control</primary><secondary>mandatory access control (MAC)</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>mandatory access control (MAC)</primary><secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>protecting files</primary><secondary>MAC</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>data</primary><secondary>protecting with MAC</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Mandatory access control (MAC) is a system-enforced access control mechanism
that is based on label relationships. The system associates a sensitivity
label with all processes that are created to execute programs. MAC policy
uses this label in access control decisions. In general, processes cannot
store information or communicate with other processes, unless the label of
the destination is equal to the label of the process. MAC policy permits processes
to read data from objects at the same label or from objects at a lower label.
However, the administrator can create a labeled environment in which few lower-level
objects or no lower-level objects are available.</para><para>By default, MAC policy is invisible to you. Regular users cannot see
objects unless they have MAC access to those objects. In all cases, users
cannot take any action that is contrary to MAC policy.</para><sect3 id="ugintro-9"><title>Sensitivity Labels and Clearances</title><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>components</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>classification component of label</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>A label has the following two components:</para><listitem><para>Classification, also referred to as a <emphasis>level</emphasis></para><para>This component indicates a hierarchical level of security. When applied
to people, the classification represents a measure of trust. When applied
to data, a classification is the degree of protection that is required.</para><para>In the U.S. Government, the classifications are <literal>TOP SECRET</literal>, <literal>SECRET</literal>, <literal>CONFIDENTIAL</literal>, and <literal>UNCLASSIFIED</literal>.
Industry classifications are not as standardized. Unique classifications can
be established by a company. For an example, see <olink targetptr="ugintro-fig-10" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;1&ndash;3</olink>. The terms on the
left are classifications. The terms on the right are compartments.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>compartment component of label</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>Compartments, also referred to as <emphasis>categories</emphasis></para><para>A compartment represents a grouping, such
as a work group, department, project, or topic. A classification does not
have to have a compartment. In <olink targetptr="ugintro-fig-10" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;1&ndash;3</olink>, the <literal>Confidential</literal> classification has three exclusive
compartments. <literal>Public</literal> and <literal>Max Label</literal> have
no compartments. As the figure shows, five labels are defined by this organization.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><indexterm><primary>types of labels</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>types</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>sensitivity labels</primary><secondary>label type</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>clearances</primary><secondary>label type</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>user clearances</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>sample industry labels</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>label ranges</primary><secondary>described</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>ranges</secondary></indexterm>Trusted Extensions maintains two types
of labels: <firstterm>sensitivity labels</firstterm> and <firstterm>clearances</firstterm>.
A user can be cleared to work at one or more sensitivity labels. A special
label, known as the <firstterm>user clearance</firstterm>, determines the
highest label at which a user is permitted to work. In addition, each user
has a minimum sensitivity label. This label is used by default during login
to a multilevel desktop session. After login, the user can choose to work
at other labels within this range. A user could be assigned <literal>Public</literal> as
the minimum sensitivity label and <literal>Confidential: Need to Know</literal> as
the clearance. At first login, the desktop workspaces are at the label <literal>Public</literal>. During the session, the user can create workspaces at <literal>Confidential:
Internal Use Only</literal> and <literal>Confidential: Need to Know</literal>.</para><figure id="ugintro-fig-10"><title>Typical Industry Sensitivity Labels</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="industry.labels.UG.eps"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Diagram shows typical labels and clearances as defined
by industry.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para><indexterm><primary>subject</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>object</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>All subjects and objects have labels on a system that is configured
with Trusted Extensions. A <emphasis>subject</emphasis> is an active entity, usually
a process. The process causes information to flow among objects or changes
the system state. An <emphasis>object</emphasis> is a passive entity that
contains or receives data, such as a data file, directory, printer, or other
device. In some cases, a process can be an object, such as when you use the <command>kill</command> command on a process.</para><para><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>displayed on desktop</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>trusted stripe</primary><secondary>location in CDE</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>visibility</primary><secondary>trusted stripe</secondary></indexterm>Labels can be displayed in
window title bars and in the <firstterm>trusted stripe</firstterm>, which
is a special stripe on the screen. Labels can be hidden. Label visibility
depends on how the administrator  configured the system. <olink targetptr="ugintro-fig-12" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;1&ndash;4</olink> shows a typical multilevel Trusted Extensions session
on a system that is configured to display labels.  The labels and trusted
stripe are indicated.</para><figure id="ugintro-fig-12"><title>Typical Trusted CDE Session</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="workspace.basic.eps" width="100"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Screen shows labels on windows and icons, the trusted
stripe with the trusted symbol and work space label, and the Trusted Path
menu.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect3><sect3 id="ugintro-25"><title>Containers and Labels</title><indexterm><primary>zones</primary><secondary>labeled</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>labeled zones</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions uses containers for labeling. Containers are also called <emphasis>zones</emphasis>. The <emphasis>global zone</emphasis> is an administrative
zone, and is not available to users. Non-global zones are called <emphasis>labeled
zones</emphasis>. Labeled zones are used by users. The global zone shares
some system files with users. When these files are visible in a labeled zone,
the label of these files is <constant>ADMIN_LOW</constant>.</para><para>Network communication is restricted by label. By default, zones cannot
communicate with each other because their labels are different. Therefore,
one zone cannot write into another zone.</para><para><indexterm><primary>home directories</primary><secondary>visible from higher-level zone</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>zones</primary><secondary>home directory visibility</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>visibility</primary><secondary>reading lower-level home directories</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>accessing</primary><secondary>lower-level home directories</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>directories</primary><secondary>visibility of home directories</secondary></indexterm>However,
the administrator can configure specific zones to be able to read specific
directories from other zones. The other zones could be on the same host, or
on a remote system. For example, a user's home directory in a lower-level
zone can be mounted by using the automount service. The pathname convention
for such lower-level home mounts includes the zone name, as follows:</para><screen>/zone/<replaceable>name-of-lower-level-zone</replaceable>/home/<replaceable>username</replaceable></screen><para>The following terminal window illustrates lower-level home directory
visibility. A user whose login label is <literal>Confidential: Internal Use
Only</literal> can view the contents of the <literal>Public</literal> zone
when the automount service is configured to make lower-level zones readable.
The <filename>textfileInfo.txt</filename> file has two versions. The <literal>Public</literal> zone version contains information that can be shared with the public.
The <literal>Confidential: Internal Use Only</literal> version contains information
that can be shared within the company only.</para><figure id="ugintro-26"><title>Viewing Public Information From a Higher-Label
Zone</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="dir.struct.internaltopublic.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Illustration shows that the contents of the Public zone
is visible from the Internal Use Only zone.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect3><sect3 id="ugintro-13"><title>Labels and Transactions</title><indexterm><primary>dominance between labels</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>dominance</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>relationships</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions software manages all attempted security-related transactions.
The software compares the subject's label with the object's label, then allows
or disallows the transaction depending on which label is <emphasis>dominant</emphasis>.
An entity's label is said to <emphasis>dominate</emphasis> another entity's
label if the following two conditions are met:</para><listitem><para>The classification component of the first entity's label is
equal to the object's classification or is higher than the object's classification.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>All compartments in the second entity's labels are included
in the first entity's label.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>Two labels are said to be <emphasis>equal</emphasis> if the labels have
the same classification and the same set of compartments. If the labels are
equal, the labels dominate each other. Therefore, access is permitted.</para><para>If one of the following conditions is met, then the first label is said
to <emphasis>strictly dominate</emphasis> the second label.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The first label has a higher classification than a second
label</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The first label's classification is equal to a second label's
classification, the first label includes the second label's compartments,
and the first label has additional compartments</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para>A label that strictly dominates a second label is permitted access to
the second label.</para><para>Two labels are said to be <emphasis>disjoint</emphasis> if neither label
dominates the other label. Access is not permitted between disjoint labels.</para><para><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>sample government labels</secondary></indexterm>For example, consider the following figure.</para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="TS.AB.Label.UG.eps"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Illustration shows a Top Secret classification with two
possible compartments, A and B.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject><itemizedlist><para>Four labels can be created from these components:</para><listitem><para><literal>TOP SECRET</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>TOP SECRET A</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>TOP SECRET B</literal></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal> dominates itself and strictly dominates
the other labels. <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> dominates itself and strictly
dominates <literal>TOP SECRET</literal>. <literal>TOP SECRET B</literal> dominates
itself and strictly dominates <literal>TOP SECRET</literal>. <literal>TOP
SECRET A</literal> and <literal>TOP SECRET B</literal> are disjoint.</para><para><indexterm><primary>read access</primary><secondary>in labeled environment</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>accessing</primary><secondary>for read only</secondary></indexterm>In a read transaction, the subject's label must dominate the object's
label. This rule ensures that the subject's level of trust meets the requirements
for access to the object. That is, the subject's label includes all compartments
that are allowed access to the object. <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> can
read <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> and <literal>TOP SECRET</literal> data.
Similarly, <literal>TOP SECRET B</literal> can read <literal>TOP SECRET B</literal> and <literal>TOP SECRET</literal> data. <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> cannot read <literal>TOP
SECRET B</literal> data. Nor can <literal>TOP SECRET B</literal> read  <literal>TOP
SECRET A</literal> data. <literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal> can read the data
at all labels.</para><para><indexterm><primary>write access</primary><secondary>in labeled environment</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>accessing</primary><secondary>for writing</secondary></indexterm>In a write transaction, that is, when a subject
creates or modifies an object, the resulting object's labeled zone must equal
the subject's labeled zone. Write transactions are not allowed from one zone
to a different zone.</para><para><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>sample label relationships</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>accessing</primary><secondary>for reading and writing</secondary></indexterm>In practice, subjects and objects in read
and write transactions usually have the same label and strict dominance does
not have to be considered. For example, a <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> subject
can create or modify a <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> object. In Trusted Extensions,
the <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal> object is in a zone that is labeled <literal>TOP SECRET A</literal>.</para><para>The following table illustrates dominance relationships among U.S. Government
labels and among a set of industry labels.</para><table frame="topbot" id="ugintro-tbl-14"><title>Examples of Label Relationships
in Trusted Extensions</title><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="colspec0" colwidth="1.84*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="column1" colwidth="3.14*"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="column2" colwidth="3.62*"/><colspec colnum="4" colname="column3" colwidth="2.41*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Label 1</para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Relationship</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Label 2</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry morerows="1"><para>U.S. Government Labels</para>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>(strictly) dominates</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>SECRET A</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><?PubTbl row rht="0.52in"?><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>(strictly) dominates</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>SECRET A B</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>(strictly) dominates</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET A</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>dominates (equals)</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET C</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>SECRET C</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry>
</entry><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>TOP SECRET AB</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>SECRET A B C</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry><para>Industry Labels</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Restricted</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>dominates</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Need to Know</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Restricted</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>dominates</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Internal Use Only</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Restricted</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>dominates</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Public</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Need to Know</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>dominates</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Internal Use Only</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Need to Know</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>dominates</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Public</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Confidential: Internal</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>dominates</para>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Public</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry>
</entry><entry><para><literal>Sandbox</literal></para>
</entry><entry><para>is disjoint with</para>
</entry><entry><para>All other labels</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>changing label on information</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>downgrading information</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>upgrading information</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>copy-and-paste</primary><secondary>effect on labels</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>drag-and-drop</primary><secondary>effect on labels</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>authorizations</primary><secondary>changing labels</secondary></indexterm>When you transfer information
between files with different labels, Trusted Extensions displays a confirmation
dialog box if you are authorized to change the label of the file. If you are
not authorized to do so, Trusted Extensions disallows the transaction. The security
administrator can authorize you to upgrade or downgrade information. For more
information, see <olink targetptr="ugelem-16" remap="internal">Performing Trusted Actions</olink>.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-21"><title>User Responsibilities for Protecting
Data</title><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary><tertiary>protecting data</tertiary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>responsibilities</primary><secondary>users to protect data</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>user responsibilities</primary><secondary>protecting data</secondary>
</indexterm><para><indexterm><primary>protecting files</primary><secondary>user responsibilities</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>user responsibilities</secondary></indexterm>As a user, you are responsible for
setting the permissions to protect your files and directories. Actions that
you can perform to set permissions use a mechanism called discretionary access
control (DAC). You can check the permissions on your files and directories
by using the <command>ls -l</command> command or by using the File Manager,
as described in <olink targetptr="ugtour-1" remap="internal">Chapter&nbsp;3, Working in Trusted
Extensions (Tasks)</olink>.</para><para>Mandatory access control (MAC) is enforced automatically by the system.
If you are authorized to upgrade or downgrade labeled information, you have
a critical responsibility to ensure that the need for changing the level of
information is legitimate.</para><para><indexterm><primary>email instructions</primary><secondary>user responsibilities</secondary></indexterm>Another aspect of protecting data involves email.
Never follow instructions that you receive in email from an administrator.
For example, if you followed emailed instructions to change your password
to a particular value, you would enable the sender to log in to your account.
In limited cases, you might verify the instructions independently before following
the instructions.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugintro-16"><title>Trusted Extensions Separates Information by Label</title><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>means of protecting data</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>protecting files</primary><secondary>by label</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions separates information at different labels by the following
means:</para><listitem><para>Users can select single-level or multilevel sessions.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The desktops provide workspaces that are labeled.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Files are stored in separate zones according to label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>MAC is enforced for all transactions, including email.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Data on objects is erased prior to object reuse.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="ugintro-19"><title>Single-Level or Multilevel Sessions</title><indexterm><primary>clearances</primary><secondary>setting at login</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>setting clearance at login</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>sessions</primary><secondary>single-level or multilevel</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>single-level sessions</primary><secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>multilevel sessions</primary><secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>session clearances</primary><secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>sessions</primary><secondary>choosing clearance</secondary>
</indexterm><para>When you first log in to a Trusted Extensions session, you specify whether
to operate at a single label or at multiple labels. You then set your <firstterm>session clearance</firstterm> or <firstterm>session label</firstterm>. This
setting is the security level at which you intend to operate.</para><para>In a single-label session, you can access only those objects that are
equal to your session label or are dominated by the label.</para><para>In a multilevel session, you can access information at labels that are
equal to or lower than your session clearance. You can specify different labels
for different workspaces. You can also have different workspaces at the same
label.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="uglog-13"><title>Session Selection Example</title><indexterm><primary>sessions</primary><secondary>effect of selecting level</secondary>
</indexterm><para><olink targetptr="uglog-4" remap="internal">Table&nbsp;1&ndash;2</olink> provides an
example that shows the difference between a single-level and a multilevel
session. This example contrasts a user who chooses to operate in a single-level
session at <literal>CONFIDENTIAL: NEED TO KNOW</literal> (<literal>CNF: NTK</literal>)
with a user who chooses a multilevel session, also at <literal>CNF: NTK</literal>.</para><para>The three columns on the left show each user's session selections at
login. Note that users set <emphasis>session labels</emphasis> for single-level
sessions and <emphasis>session clearances</emphasis> for multilevel sessions.
The system displays the correct <olink targetptr="uggloss-28" remap="internal">label builder</olink> according
to your selection. To view a label builder for a multilevel session, see <olink targetptr="uglog-fig-5" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;2&ndash;2</olink>.</para><para>The two columns on the right show the label values that are available
in the session. The Initial Workspace label column represents the label when
the user first accesses the system. The Available Labels column lists the
labels that the user is permitted to switch to during the session.</para><table frame="topbot" id="uglog-4"><title>Effect of Initial Label Selection
on Available Session Labels</title><tgroup cols="5" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="column1" colwidth="1.76*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="column2" colwidth="1.39*"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="column3" colwidth="1.82*"/><colspec colnum="4" colname="column4" colwidth="2.10*"/><colspec colnum="5" colname="column5" colwidth="2.98*"/><thead><row rowsep="1"><entry colname="column1" namest="column1" nameend="column3" colsep="1" align="center" valign="bottom"><para>User Selections</para>
</entry><entry colname="column4" namest="column4" nameend="column5" align="center" valign="bottom"><para>Session Label Values</para>
</entry>
</row><row rowsep="1"><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Session Type</para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Session Label</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" colsep="1" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Session Clearance</para>
</entry><entry colname="column4" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Initial Workspace Label</para>
</entry><entry colname="column5" align="left" valign="bottom"><para>Available Labels</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead><tbody><row><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para> single-level</para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>CNF: NTK</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" colsep="1" align="left" valign="top"><para>-</para>
</entry><entry colname="column4" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>CNF: NTK</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column5" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>CNF: NTK</literal></para>
</entry>
</row><row><entry colname="column1" align="left" valign="top"><para> multilevel</para>
</entry><entry colname="column2" align="left" valign="top"><para>-</para>
</entry><entry colname="column3" colsep="1" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>CNF: NTK</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column4" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>Public</literal></para>
</entry><entry colname="column5" align="left" valign="top"><para><literal>Public</literal></para><para><literal>CNF: Internal Use Only</literal></para><para><literal>CNF: NTK</literal></para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><para>As the first row of the table shows, the user has selected a single-level
session with a session label of <literal>CNF: NTK</literal>. The user has
an initial workspace label of <literal>CNF: NTK</literal>, which is also the
only label at which the user can operate.</para><para>As the second row of the table shows, the user has selected a multilevel
session with a session clearance of <literal>CNF: NTK</literal>. The user's
initial workspace label is set to <literal>Public</literal>, because <literal>Public</literal> is the lowest possible label in the user's account label range.
The user can switch to any label between <literal>Public</literal> and <literal>CNF:
NTK</literal>. <literal>Public</literal> is the minimum label, and <literal>CNF:
NTK</literal> is the session clearance.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-17"><title>Labeled Workspaces</title><indexterm><primary>workspaces</primary><secondary>labeled</secondary>
</indexterm><para><indexterm><primary>workspace switch area</primary><secondary>illustration</secondary></indexterm>In Solaris Trusted Extensions (CDE), or Trusted CDE, the workspaces in Trusted Extensions are accessed
through buttons in the center of the Front Panel, as in the Solaris OS. However,
with Trusted Extensions, you can devote a workspace entirely to a single label.
This setup is very convenient when you are in a multilevel session, and you
do not want to confuse information at different labels. The following illustration
shows the workspace switch area with four switches. Each switch opens a workspace
at a different label. You can also assign several workspaces to the same label.</para><figure id="ugintro-fig-11"><title>Workspace Switch Area</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="FPanel4.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>The illustration shows the Workspace Switch area on the
Front Panel with four labeled switches.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><para>In Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME),
or Trusted GNOME, the workspaces are accessed through buttons at the right of
the bottom panel. As in Trusted CDE, you can assign a workspace to a single label.
You can also assign the same label to several workspaces.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-23"><title>Enforcing MAC for Email Transactions</title><indexterm><primary>mandatory access control (MAC)</primary><secondary>enforced for email</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>email</primary><secondary>label enforcement</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions enforces MAC for email. You can send and read email at
your current label. You can receive email at a label within your account range.
In a multilevel session, you can switch to a workspace at a different label
to read email at that label. You use the same mail reader and the same login.
The system permits you to read mail at your current label only.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-24"><title>Erasing Data on Objects Prior to Object
Reuse</title><indexterm><primary>users</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary><tertiary>clearing devices</tertiary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>responsibilities</primary><secondary>users to clear media</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>object</primary><secondary>reuse</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>devices</primary><secondary>clearing prior to reuse</secondary>
</indexterm><para>Trusted Extensions prevents inadvertent exposure of sensitive information
by automatically erasing old information from user-accessible objects prior
to reuse. For example, memory and disk space are cleared before being used
again. Failure to erase sensitive data prior to reuse of the object risks
the exposure of data to inappropriate users. Through device deallocation, Trusted Extensions clears
all user-accessible objects prior to allocating the drives to processes. Note,
however, that you must clear all removable storage media, such as DVDs and
JAZ drives, before allowing another user access to the drive.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="ugintro-18"><title>Trusted Extensions Enables Secure Administration</title><indexterm><primary>roles</primary><secondary>special user account</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>system administration</primary><secondary>on Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>In contrast to traditional UNIX systems, superuser (the <literal>root</literal> user)
is not used to administer Trusted Extensions. Rather, administrative roles with
discrete capabilities administer the system. In this way, no single user can
compromise a system's security. A <firstterm>role</firstterm> is a special
user account that provides access to certain applications with the rights
that are necessary for performing the specific tasks. Rights include authorizations,
privileges, and effective UIDs/GIDs.</para><itemizedlist><para>The following security practices are enforced on a system that is configured
with Trusted Extensions:</para><listitem><para>You are granted access to applications and authorizations
on a need-to-use basis.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>You can perform functions that override security policy only
if you are granted special authorizations or special privileges by administrators.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>System administration duties are divided among multiple roles.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist><sect2 id="ugintro-38"><title>Accessing Applications in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>trusted applications</primary><secondary>by using rights profiles</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>rights profiles</primary><secondary>defined</secondary>
</indexterm><para>In Trusted Extensions, you can access only those programs that you need
to do your job. As in the Solaris OS, an administrator provides access by assigning
one or more rights profiles to your account. A <firstterm>rights profile</firstterm> is
a special package of programs and security attributes. These security attributes
enable successful use of the program that is in the rights profile.</para><para>The Solaris OS provides security attributes such as <firstterm>privileges</firstterm> and <firstterm>authorizations</firstterm>. Trusted Extensions provides labels. Any of these attributes,
if missing, can prevent use of the program or parts of the program. For example,
a rights profile might include an authorization that enables you to read a
database. A rights profile with particular security attributes might be required
for you to modify the database or read information that is classified as <literal>Confidential</literal>.</para><para>The use of rights profiles that contain programs with associated security
attributes helps prevent users from misusing programs and from damaging data
on the system. If you need to perform tasks that override the security policy,
the administrator can assign to you a rights profile that contains the necessary
security attributes. If you are prevented from running a certain task, check
with your administrator. You might be missing required security attributes.</para><para><indexterm><primary>profile shell</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm>In addition, the administrator might assign you a profile shell
as your login shell. A <emphasis>profile shell</emphasis> is a special version
of the Bourne shell that provides access to a particular set of applications
and capabilities. Profile shells are a feature of the Solaris OS. For details,
see the <olink targetdoc="group-refman" targetptr="pfsh-1" remap="external"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>pfsh</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></olink> man
page.</para><note><para><indexterm><primary><literal>Not in Profile</literal> error message</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary><literal>Not Found</literal> error message</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>troubleshooting</primary><secondary>command line error messages</secondary></indexterm>If you try to run a program and
receive a <literal>Not Found</literal> error message or if you try to run
a command and receive a <literal>Not in Profile</literal> error message, you
might not be permitted to use this program. Check with your security administrator.</para>
</note>
</sect2><sect2 id="ugintro-22"><title>Administration by Role in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>responsibilities</primary><secondary>of administrators</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>roles</primary><secondary>responsibilities of</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>roles</primary><secondary>common roles</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Security Administrator role</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>System Administrator role</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>Operator role</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>root role</primary><secondary>responsibilities</secondary>
</indexterm><itemizedlist><para>Trusted Extensions software uses roles for administration. Make sure that
you know who is performing which set of duties at your site. The following
are common roles:</para><listitem><para>root role &ndash; Is used primarily to prevent direct login
by superuser.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Primary Administrator role &ndash; Performs any tasks that
require privileges beyond the capabilities of other roles.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Security Administrator role &ndash; Performs security-relevant
tasks, such as setting passwords, authorizing device allocation, assigning
rights profiles, and evaluating software programs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>System Administrator role &ndash; Performs standard system
management tasks, such as setting up home directories, restoring backups,
and installing software programs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Operator role &ndash; Performs system backups, manages printers,
and mounts removable media.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000048944 0?>