<?Pub UDT _bookmark _target?><?Pub EntList bsol dash hellip gt lt minus?><?Pub CX solbook(book(title()bookinfo()chapter()?><chapter id="uglog-1"><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="off" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sharonr" fullname="Sharon Veach"?><title>Logging In to Trusted Extensions (Tasks)</title><highlights><itemizedlist><para>This chapter describes the two desktops and the login process on a system
that is configured with Solaris Trusted Extensions. This chapter covers the following topics:</para><listitem><para><olink targetptr="uglog-15" remap="internal">Desktops and Login in Trusted
Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="uglog-10" remap="internal">Trusted Extensions Login Process</olink></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><olink targetptr="uglog-18" remap="internal">Logging In to Trusted Extensions</olink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</highlights><sect1 id="uglog-15"><title>Desktops and Login in Trusted Extensions</title><indexterm><primary>visibility</primary><secondary>labels after login</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>desktops</primary><secondary>in Trusted Extensions</secondary>
</indexterm><para>The desktop that you use in Trusted Extensions is protected. Labels provide
a visible indication of protection. Applications, data, and your communications
are labeled. The desktop is a trusted version of the GNOME desktop.
The menu item is Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME).</para><para><indexterm><primary>unlabeled screens</primary><secondary>login screen</secondary></indexterm>The login screen is not labeled. The login process requires you
to establish a label for your session. Once you have chosen a label, the desktop,
its windows, and all applications are labeled. In addition, applications that
affect security are visibly protected by a trusted path indicator.</para>
</sect1><sect1 id="uglog-10"><title>Trusted Extensions Login Process</title><para><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>five steps of</secondary></indexterm>The login process on a system that is configured with Trusted Extensions is
similar to the login process for the Solaris OS. However, in Trusted Extensions,
you examine several screens for security-relevant information before the desktop
session can be started. The process is described in more detail in the sections
that follow. Here is a brief overview.</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Desktop choice &ndash; As in the Solaris OS, you choose which
desktop to use. In Trusted Extensions, you must choose the Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME) desktop.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Identification &ndash; As in the Solaris OS, you type your username
in the Username field.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Authentication &ndash; As in the Solaris OS, you type your password
in the Password field.</para><para>Successful completion of identification
and authentication confirms your right to use the system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Message checking and session type selection &ndash; You examine
the information in the Last Login dialog box. This dialog box displays the
time you last logged in, any messages from the administrator, and the security
attributes of your session. If you are permitted to operate at more than one
label, you can specify the type of session, single-level or multilevel.</para><note><para>If your account restricts you to operate at one label, you cannot
specify the type of session. This restriction is called a <emphasis>single-level</emphasis> or <emphasis>single-label</emphasis> configuration. For an example, see <olink targetptr="uglog-13" remap="internal">Session Selection Example</olink>.</para>
</note>
</listitem><listitem><para>Label selection &ndash; In the <olink targetptr="uggloss-28" remap="internal">label
builder</olink>, you choose the highest security level at which you intend
to work while in your session.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist><note><para>By default, remote login is not supported for regular users in Trusted Extensions.
If remote login is supported by your site, check with your administrator for
the procedure.</para>
</note><sect2 id="uglog-16"><title>Desktop Choice Before Login</title><para><indexterm><primary>choosing</primary><secondary>a desktop</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>choosing a desktop</secondary></indexterm>When a Solaris workstation is not in
a work session, it displays the login screen. The Trusted Extensions login screen
is similar to the Solaris login screen. As in the Solaris login
screen, you can choose a desktop from the Options menu.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="uglog-2"><title>Identification and Authentication During Login</title><para>Identification and authentication during login are handled by the Solaris OS.
The login screen initially contains the Username prompt. This part of the
login process is referred to as <emphasis>identification</emphasis>.</para><para>After you have entered the username, the password prompt is displayed.
This part of the process is referred to as <emphasis>authentication</emphasis>.
The password authenticates that you are indeed the user who is authorized
to use that username.</para><para>A <emphasis>password</emphasis> is a private combination of keystrokes
that validates your identity to the system. Your password is stored in an
encrypted form and is not accessible by other users on the system. It is your
responsibility to protect your password so that other users cannot use it
to gain unauthorized access. Never write down your password or disclose it
to anyone else because a person with your password has access to all your
data without being identifiable or accountable. Your initial password is supplied
by your <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink>.</para>
</sect2><sect2 id="uglog-11"><title>Review Security Attributes During Login</title><para><indexterm><primary>reviewing security settings</primary><secondary>Last Login dialog box</secondary></indexterm>The review of security attributes
is handled by Trusted Extensions, not by the Solaris OS. Before login is complete, Trusted Extensions displays
the Last Login dialog box. This dialog box provides status information for
you to review. You can review past information, such as when the system was
last used by you. You can also review the security attributes that are in
effect for the upcoming session. If your account is configured to operate
at more than one label, you can select a single-level or a multilevel session.</para><para>You then view your single label, or choose a label and clearance from
the label builder.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1><sect1 id="uglog-18"><title>Logging In to Trusted Extensions</title><para>The following tasks step you through logging in to Trusted Extensions. You
review and specify security information before reaching the desktop.</para><task id="uglog-20"><title>Choose a Trusted Desktop</title><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>choosing a desktop</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>choosing</primary><secondary>a desktop</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>single-level login</primary><secondary>Trusted GNOME</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>using trusted desktop</primary><secondary>single-level or multilevel</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>multilevel login</primary><secondary>Trusted GNOME</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step id="uglog-step-desktop"><para>On the login screen, choose a desktop
from the Options --&gt; Sessions menu.</para><para>For Trusted GNOME, choose Solaris Trusted Extensions (GNOME).</para>
</step><step><para>Continue with <olink targetptr="uglog-proc-3" remap="internal">Identify and Authenticate
Yourself to the System</olink>.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="uglog-proc-3"><title>Identify and Authenticate Yourself to the System</title><procedure><step id="uglog-step-1"><para>In the Username field of the login screen, type
your username.</para><para>Be sure to type your username exactly as your administrator
assigned it to you. Pay attention to spelling and capitalization.</para>
</step><step><para>If you made an error, restart.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>To retype your username, click Start Over.</para>
</step><step><para>To restart the windowing system completely, click Reset Login
from the Options menu.</para><para>Go to <olink targetptr="uglog-20" remap="internal">Choose
a Trusted Desktop</olink> after your restart.</para>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Confirm your entry.</para><para>Press Return to confirm your username.</para><caution><para>You should <emphasis>never</emphasis> see the trusted stripe
when the login screen appears. If you ever see the trusted stripe while attempting
to log in or unlock the screen, do not type your password. There is a possibility
that you are being spoofed. A <emphasis>spoof</emphasis> is when an intruder's
program is masquerading as a login program to capture passwords. Contact your <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security administrator</olink> immediately.</para>
</caution>
</step><step><para>Type your password in the password entry field, and press Return.</para><para>For security purposes, the characters do not display in the field. The
system compares the login name and password against a list of authorized users.</para>
</step>
</procedure><taskrelated role="troubleshooting"><para><indexterm><primary>troubleshooting</primary><secondary>password failure</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>troubleshooting</secondary></indexterm>If the password that you provided is incorrect, a dialog box appears
with the message:</para><para><literal>Login incorrect; please try again.</literal></para><para>Click OK to dismiss the error dialog box. Then, type the correct password.</para>
</taskrelated>
</task><task id="uglog-proc-14"><title>Check Messages and Select Session Type</title><indexterm><primary>reviewing security settings</primary><secondary>procedure during login</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>reviewing security settings</secondary>
</indexterm><tasksummary><para>If you do not restrict yourself to a single label, you can view data
at different labels. The range in which you can operate is bounded at the
upper end by the session clearance and at the lower end by the minimum label
that your administrator assigned to you.</para>
</tasksummary><procedure><step><para>In the Last Login dialog box, check that the time of your last
session is accurate.</para><para>Always check that nothing is suspicious about
the last login, such as an unusual time of day. If you have reason to believe
that the time is not accurate, contact your <olink targetptr="uggloss-82" remap="internal">security
administrator</olink>.</para><figure id="uglog-fig-2"><title>Last Login Dialog Box</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="last.login.eps"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Window shows date and time of the user's last login,
Message of the Day, and session attributes. Shows a single-label session button.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</step><step><para>Check for any messages from the administrator.</para><para>The
Message of the Day field can contain warnings about scheduled maintenance
or security problems. Always review the information in this field.</para>
</step><step><para>Examine the security attributes of your session.</para><para>As <olink targetptr="uglog-fig-2" remap="internal">Figure&nbsp;2&ndash;1</olink> shows, the Last Login
dialog box indicates any roles that you can assume, your minimum label, and
other security characteristics.</para>
</step><step performance="optional" id="uglog-step-2"><para><indexterm><primary>choosing</primary><secondary>label or clearance during login</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>choosing a label or clearance</secondary></indexterm>If you are permitted to log in to a multilevel session, decide
if you want a single-label session.</para><para>Click the Restrict Session
to a Single Label button to log in to a single-label session.</para><para>You are presented with a label builder. If you are logging in at a single
label, the label builder describes your session label. In a multilabel system,
the label builder enables you to choose your session clearance.</para>
</step><step><para>Confirm your label choice.</para><figure id="uglog-fig-5"><title>Label Builder</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata entityref="labelbldr.tiff"/>
</imageobject><textobject><simpara>Label Builder dialog box shows Task identifier, selected
clearance. Shows update field, and classification and compartments to create
new clearance.</simpara>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure><stepalternatives><step><para>Accept the default, unless you have a reason not to.</para>
</step><step><para><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>setting at login</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>setting session labels</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>sessions</primary><secondary>setting level</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>clearances</primary><secondary>setting session </secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>setting session labels</secondary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>clearances</primary><secondary>setting at login</secondary></indexterm>For a multilevel session,
select a clearance.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Deselect the current clearance, and click a classification
and a sensitivity label.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Or, in the Clearance field, type a clearance.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Or, in the Update With field, type a label.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step><step><para>For a single-level session, select a label.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Deselect the current label, and click a different classification.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Or, in the Update With field, type a label.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step><step><para>Click OK.</para><para>The trusted desktop  appears.</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</task><task id="uglog-14"><title>Troubleshoot Login Problems</title><indexterm><primary>failsafe login</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>failsafe</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>logging in</primary><secondary>troubleshooting</secondary>
</indexterm><indexterm><primary>troubleshooting</primary><secondary>login</secondary>
</indexterm><procedure><step><para>If your username or password is not recognized, check with the
administrator.</para>
</step><step><para><indexterm><primary>label ranges</primary><secondary>troubleshooting a workstation with a restricted range</secondary></indexterm>If your label
range is not permitted on your workstation, check with the administrator.</para><para>Workstations can be restricted to a limited range of session clearances
and labels. For example, a workstation in a lobby might be limited to <literal>PUBLIC</literal> labels only. If the label or session clearance that you specify
is not accepted, check with an administrator to determine if the workstation
is restricted.</para>
</step><step><para><indexterm><primary>initialization files</primary><secondary>troubleshooting when customized</secondary></indexterm>If you have customized your shell initialization
files and cannot log in, you have the following two options.</para><stepalternatives><step><para>Contact your <olink targetptr="uggloss-161" remap="internal">system administrator</olink> to
correct the situation.</para>
</step><step><para>If you can become <literal>root</literal>, log in to a failsafe
session.</para><para>In a standard login, the shell initialization files are
sourced at startup to provide a customized environment. In a failsafe login,
the default values are applied to your system and no shell initialization
files are sourced.</para><para>In Trusted Extensions, failsafe login is protected. Only superuser can access
failsafe login.</para><substeps><step><para>As in the Solaris OS, choose Options &ndash;&gt; Failsafe Session on
the login screen.</para>
</step><step><para>When prompted, provide your username and password.</para>
</step><step><para>When prompted for an additional password, provide the password
for <literal>root</literal>.</para>
</step>
</substeps>
</step>
</stepalternatives>
</step>
</procedure>
</task>
</sect1>
</chapter><?Pub *0000018748 0?>