<glossary id="glossary"><title>Glossary</title><para>The following terms are used throughout this book.</para><glossentry id="glossaryacl"><glossterm>access control list (ACL)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A list associated with a file that contains information about which users or groups have permission to access or modify the file.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryad"><glossterm>Active Directory (AD)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Windows naming service that runs on a domain controller to protect network objects from unauthorized access. This service also replicates objects across a network so that data is not lost if one domain controller fails.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryautohomeshare"><glossterm>autohome share</glossterm><glossdef><para>A transient share of a user's home directory that is created when the user logs in and is removed when the user logs out.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarysmbclient"><glossterm>CIFS client</glossterm><glossdef><para>Software that enables a system to access CIFS shares from a <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarysmbserver" remap="internal">CIFS server</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarysmbserver"><glossterm>CIFS server</glossterm><glossdef><para>Software that enables a system to make CIFS shares available to <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarysmbclient" remap="internal">CIFS clients</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarycifs"><glossterm>Common Internet File System (CIFS)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A protocol that follows the client-server model to share files and services over the network, and which is based on the <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarysmb" remap="internal">Server Message Block (SMB)</olink> protocol.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarydiagonalmapping"><glossterm>diagonal mapping</glossterm><glossdef><para>A rule that maps between a Windows group and a Solaris user and between a Solaris group and a Windows user. These mappings are needed when Windows uses a group identity as a file owner, or a user identity as a file group.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarydirbasedmapping"><glossterm>directory-based mappings</glossterm><glossdef><para>A way to use name mapping information that is stored in user or group objects in the Active Directory (AD), in the native LDAP directory service, or both to map users and groups.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarydns"><glossterm>Domain Name System (DNS)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A service that provides the naming policy and mechanisms for mapping domain and machine names to addresses outside of the enterprise, such as those on the Internet. DNS is the network information service used by the Internet.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarydynamicdns"><glossterm>Dynamic DNS (DDNS)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A service that is provided with <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossaryad" remap="internal">AD</olink> that enables a client to dynamically update its entries in the DNS database.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryephemeralid"><glossterm>ephemeral ID</glossterm><glossdef><para>A dynamic UID or GID mapping for an <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarysid" remap="internal">SID</olink> that is not already mapped by name.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryforest"><glossterm>forest</glossterm><glossdef><para>A forest can have one or more <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarytree" remap="internal">trees</olink> that do not form a contiguous namespace.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryforesttreemodel"><glossterm>forest-and-tree model</glossterm><glossdef><para>A logical structure that enables you to interconnect two or more Windows domains by bringing them into bidirectional, chained trust relationships. See also <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarytree" remap="internal"><emphasis>tree</emphasis></olink> and <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossaryforest" remap="internal"><emphasis>forest</emphasis></olink>.</para><para>Each tree in this model has a unique name, while a forest does not need to be named. The trees in a forest form a hierarchy for the purposes of the trust relationships. In this model, a single tree can constitute a forest. Each tree within a forest can be independent of the others.</para><para>You might use this model to run multiple environments under separate DNS namespaces.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarygid"><glossterm>group identifier (GID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An unsigned 32-bit identifier that is associated with a Solaris group.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryidmapping"><glossterm>identity mapping</glossterm><glossdef><para>A process that enables Windows clients to transparently access CIFS shares and remote services from the Solaris <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarysmbserver" remap="internal">CIFS server</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryldap"><glossterm>Lightweight Data Access Protocol (LDAP)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A standard, extensible directory access protocol that enables clients and servers that use LDAP naming services to communicate with each other.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarymountpoint"><glossterm>mount point</glossterm><glossdef><para>A directory to which you mount a file system or a share that exists on a remote system.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarynamebasedmapping"><glossterm>name-based mappings</glossterm><glossdef><para>A way to associate Windows users and groups with equivalent Solaris users and groups by name rather than by identifier. A name-based mapping can consist of <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarydirbasedmapping" remap="internal">directory-based mappings</olink> and <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossaryrulebasedmapping" remap="internal">rule-based mappings</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarynetbiosname"><glossterm>NetBIOS name</glossterm><glossdef><para>The name of a host or workgroup used by NetBIOS.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarynetbiosscope"><glossterm>NetBIOS scope</glossterm><glossdef><para>A valid domain name as defined by <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarydns" remap="internal">DNS</olink>. You use a NetBIOS scope identifier to identify logical NetBIOS networks that are on the same physical network. When you specify a NetBIOS scope identifier, the server will only be able to communicate with other systems that have the same scope defined. The value is a text string that represents a domain name and is limited to 16 characters. By default, no value is set.</para><para>You might specify a NetBIOS scope if you want to divide a large Windows workgroup into smaller groups. If you use a scope, the scope ID must follow NetBIOS name conventions or domain name conventions. The ID is limited to 16 characters.</para><para>Most environments do not require the use of the NetBIOS scope feature. If you must use this feature, ensure that you track the scope identifier assigned to each node.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarynis"><glossterm>Network Information Service (NIS) database</glossterm><glossdef><para>A distributed database that contains key information about the systems and the users on the network. The NIS database is stored on the master server and all the replica or slave servers.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryntp"><glossterm>Network Time Protocol (NTP)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A protocol that enables a client to automatically synchronize its system clock with a time server. The clock is synchronized each time the client is booted and any time it contacts the time server.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarypersistentpassword"><glossterm>persistent password</glossterm><glossdef><para>A stored password that enables a Solaris CIFS client to mount CIFS shares without having to authenticate each mount action. This password remains in storage until removed by the <command>smbutil logout</command> or <command>smbutil logoutall</command> command.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryrid"><glossterm>relative identifier (RID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A 32-bit identifier similar to a Solaris <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossaryuid" remap="internal">user identifier (UID)</olink> or <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarygid" remap="internal">group identifier (GID)</olink> that identifies a user, group, system, or domain.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryrulebasedmapping"><glossterm>rule-based mappings</glossterm><glossdef><para>A way to use rules to associate Windows users and groups with equivalent Solaris users and groups by name rather than by identifier.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarysamba"><glossterm>Samba</glossterm><glossdef><para>An open source service that enables UNIX servers to provide CIFS/SMB file-sharing and printing services to CIFS clients.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarysam"><glossterm>Security Accounts Manager (SAM) database</glossterm><glossdef><para>A database in which Windows users and groups are defined. The SAM database is managed on a <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarywindowsdomaincontroller" remap="internal">Windows domain controller</olink>.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarysid"><glossterm>security identifier (SID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A variable length structure that uniquely identifies a user or group both within the local domain and across all possible Windows domains.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryshare"><glossterm>share</glossterm><glossdef><para>A local resource on a server that is accessible to clients on the network. On a Solaris <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarysmbserver" remap="internal">CIFS server</olink>, a share is typically a directory. Each share is identified by a name on the network. To clients on the network, the share does not expose the local directory path directly above the root of the share.</para><para>Most shares have a type of <literal>disk</literal> because the shares are directories. A share of type <literal>pipe</literal> represents a device, such as an IPC share or a printer.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarysmb"><glossterm>Server Message Block (SMB)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A protocol that enables clients to access files and to request services of a server on the network.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarytree"><glossterm>tree</glossterm><glossdef><para>A named collection of domains that share the same network configuration, schema, and global catalog.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossaryuid"><glossterm>user identifier (UID)</glossterm><glossdef><para>An unsigned 32-bit identifier that is associated with a Solaris user.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarywindowsdomain"><glossterm>Windows domain</glossterm><glossdef><para>A centrally administered group of computers and accounts that share a common security and administration policy and database. Computer, user, and group accounts are centrally managed by using servers known as <olink type="custom-text" targetptr="glossarywindowsdomaincontroller" remap="internal">domain controllers</olink>. In order to participate in a Windows domain, a computer must join the domain and become a domain member.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarywindowsdomaincontroller"><glossterm>Windows domain controller</glossterm><glossdef><para>A Windows system that is used to provide authentication services for its Windows domain.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarywins"><glossterm>Windows Internet Naming Service (WINS)</glossterm><glossdef><para>A service that resolves NetBIOS names to IP addresses.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry><glossentry id="glossarywindowsworkgroup"><glossterm>Windows workgroup</glossterm><glossdef><para>A group of standalone computers that are independently administered. Each computer has independent, local user and group accounts, and security and policy database. In a Windows workgroup, computers cooperate through the use of a common workgroup name but this is a peer-to-peer model with no formal membership mechanism.</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary>